<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Chris Krycho - 2016-review</title><link href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/feeds/2016-review.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://www.chriskrycho.com/</id><updated>2016-12-27T16:00:00-05:00</updated><entry><title>2016 in Review, Part 1 of 6</title><link href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2016/2016-review-1.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-12-27T16:00:00-05:00</published><author><name>Chris Krycho</name></author><id>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2016-12-27:2016/2016-review-1.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;2016 was a long, difficult, strange, sometimes wonderful and sometimes dreadful year for me. It was one of the most professionally and scholastically enjoyable and rewarding years of my life, and also one of the most exhausting. As I often do at years-end, I am taking stock publicly of what went well, what went poorly, and what I might do different in a variety of categories—here, mostly in terms of my public-facing endeavors. This year’s summing-up post will also (for, I think, the first time) include some numbers! But first, a few comments on the big picture.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the end of 2015, I &lt;a href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2015/thoughts-on-2015-and-2016.html"&gt;offered a similar set of reflections&lt;/a&gt;. At the end of it, I laid out some plans for 2016:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am going to set a single goal in each of five major categories in my life:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;spiritual:&lt;/strong&gt; everything in my walk with God, including my own personal devotions, my involvement in the life of the church, and my “ministry” actions in general&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;family:&lt;/strong&gt; both quantity and quality time spent with my wife and my quickly-growing-up little girls&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;personal:&lt;/strong&gt; podcasting, blogging, and writing for &lt;a href="http://mereorthodoxy.com/author/chris-krycho/"&gt;other outlets&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;professional:&lt;/strong&gt; working in my new job and as a consultant, and carrying on toward the conclusion of my M. Div.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;health/fitness:&lt;/strong&gt; continuing to stay healthy, including eating well and continuing to stay fit by running and doing triathlon work&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Early in the year, I made the habit of writing these out formally on a day-by-day basis—and I did this off and on. If you were to look at my little (Moleskine-branded and delightful-to-me) daily planner, you’d see streaks of weeks where I noted specific tasks and whether I hit them or not, punctuated by weeks and months where I did nothing of the sort. I have always found it difficult to stick with these kinds of things, in part because I usually have a pretty good idea what I need to do on any given day without writing it down somewhere. (I use &lt;a href="https://www.omnigroup.com/omnifocus/" title="OmniFocus"&gt;other tools&lt;/a&gt; for tracking mid- and long-term deadlines for school.) In July, I started mashing this idea up with &lt;a href="http://bulletjournal.com" title="Bullet Journal site"&gt;bullet journaling&lt;/a&gt;, and I found that I (a) really like the system and (b) also didn’t stick with it consistently. A lot of that came down to the fact that I got thrown off—horribly—by getting a mild-but-still-utterly-debilitating case of walking pneumonia in July. (On which, more in a moment.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So much for last year’s ideas about &lt;em&gt;how&lt;/em&gt; I was going to hit those goals. How did I actually do at addressing them? The answer is: &lt;em&gt;okay&lt;/em&gt;. 2016 was not an amazing year. It was not a terrible year. But it had as many downs as ups.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My own walk with God remains &lt;em&gt;steady&lt;/em&gt;. Nothing amazing to report here, but I’m more than okay with that. I will perhaps say more on this in another post, but the older I get the more convinced I am that emotional highs are a trap. Sentiment and true religion are &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; the same thing; and Scripture calls us to &lt;em&gt;faithfulness&lt;/em&gt;, not &lt;em&gt;spiritual feelings&lt;/em&gt;. As such, in a year with this many bumps, I am glad to say that I had no horrible falls, and I read my Bible nearly every day and prayed every single day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our family learned some Bible verses, and started working on the Heidelberg Catechism. We shared the gospel with people as we were able, and met faithfully with our church. We were not extraordinary, and we were far from flawless, but I think we did &lt;em&gt;well&lt;/em&gt;. I hope and pray in God’s grace we are able to continue in faithfully doing well in the years to come. Certainly if there is one thing I hope to do more of in 2017 it is spend time with my girls. I am not a huge “kid person,” but these years are precious and go by quickly; far better to spend more time with them and have a podcast episode or a writing project go out later (or not at all) than to miss these little years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;i class='editorial'&gt;I originally drafted a single, mammoth post reflecting on this whole year—but at 5,000 words, that seemed like a bit much. As such, I’ve broken it into a series of posts, to be published daily through the start of the new year. Hopefully they’re a bit more digestible that way! Today you get something like a double feature, with the first set of non-general reflections included as well.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Part 1: Or: a ridiculous year summarized!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2016/2016-review-2.html"&gt;Part 2: So. many. words. I had no idea how many words.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2016/2016-review-3.html"&gt;Part 3: Podcasting: Winning Slowly, New Rustacean, and more!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2016/2016-review-4.html"&gt;Part 4: Writing software for Olo and for open source.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2016/2016-review-5.html"&gt;Part 5: Getting things done in 2016 and beyond.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2017/2016-review-6.html"&gt;Part 6: Plans for 2017!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;section id="fitness" class="level2"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;1. Fitness&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Wait, hold on,&lt;/em&gt; you say. &lt;em&gt;Go back. How did you get walking pneumonia?&lt;/em&gt; This is a fun story, and it’s a huge part of what made the other parts of the latter half of 2016 go the way they did.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I went for what I expected to be a 15–16 mile long run as part of training for the half-marathon I signed up for this year. The previous week &lt;a href="http://runwith.chriskrycho.com/runs/12/" title="Run summary on runwith.chriskrycho.com"&gt;I’d done a 14-mile run&lt;/a&gt;, so 15–16 would have been no problem. I was feeling &lt;em&gt;awesome&lt;/em&gt; on the run, so decided to extend it to 17. This was right at the edge of what makes good sense for a week-over-week increase in mileage; you generally want to stick with ~10% increases and max out at 20%; but 17 is right at that limit relative to 14. So I turned right to cut through another nearby town instead of left to head directly home when I was at roughly the 11-mile mark.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then, where I &lt;em&gt;did&lt;/em&gt; cut back toward home, I took a wrong turn out of a five-way intersection. (You can see on the north end of the map, in Youngsville, &lt;a href="https://www.strava.com/activities/644619792" title="Run overview on Strava"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;). I realized this half a mile on, but figured there would be a spot to cut over. There is not. So I got back to where I had taken the wrong turn, filled up my water bottle and hit the bathroom, and made my way home. But at this point, I was already at ~15 miles, and ~4 miles from home. As I got back into our town, I decided: why not just go ahead and extend out to 20 miles?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And the truth is, that extra three quarters of a mile probably didn’t matter a bit. 19.25 vs. 20 miles? Same difference in its effect on my immune system, which is to say: it completely crashed it. A 42% week over week increase in mileage is no joke. The little cold I picked up from my 2-year-old daughter turned into borderline bronchitis. Yay.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What with a busy spring preceding—I had no idea how much busier I would be taking 2 classes and working 30 hours a week than I had been taking 3 classes and working 20 hours a week—I didn’t manage a triathlon. I had contented myself with the thought that I’d likely set another PR in my half marathon, but after weeks of recovery from walking pneumonia, that thought fell apart as well. I lost about a minute per mile in my pace, and my mileage was shot as well. I never got it back—not least because of a writing project which went south on me. I ended up being sick off and on all fall, and I’m only now getting my feet back under me. Sad to say, one of those times I got sick was the week of the half marathon I signed up for, and I’d been getting loud, clear signals from my body on previous runs that I was pushing too hard. So no race &lt;em&gt;at all&lt;/em&gt; this year. But better that than pushing and injuring myself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here’s hoping 2017 is &lt;em&gt;much&lt;/em&gt; better in that regard! I plan to do a sprint-length triathlon and a full marathon. Why? Well, it seems like the thing to do the year I turn thirty and graduate seminary.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</summary><category term="writing"></category><category term="podcasting"></category><category term="software development"></category><category term="family"></category><category term="productivity"></category><category term="fitness"></category></entry></feed>