<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Chris Krycho - 2016-in-review</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/</link><description></description><lastBuildDate>Wed, 28 Dec 2016 07:00:00 -0500</lastBuildDate><item><title>2016 in Review, Part 2 of 6</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2016/2016-review-2.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;i class='editorial'&gt;I originally drafted a single, mammoth post reflecting on this whole year—but at more than 6,000 words, that seemed like a bit much. As such, I’ve broken it into a series of posts, to be published daily through the start of the new year. Hopefully they’re a bit more digestible that way!&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2016/2016-review-intro.html"&gt;Introduction, or: a ridiculous year summarized&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2016/2016-review-1.html"&gt;Part 1: Running headfirst into a wall of pneumonia.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2016/2016-review-2.html"&gt;Part 2: So. many. words. I had no idea how many words.&lt;/a&gt; (this post)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Part 3: Podcasting: Winning Slowly, New Rustacean, and more!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Part 4: Writing software for Olo and for open source.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Part 5: Getting things done in 2016 and beyond.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Part 6: Plans for 2017!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of my goals for 2016 was to continue writing not only on this blog but in other outlets. I did a &lt;em&gt;lot&lt;/em&gt; of writing this year, but relatively little of it is published. But here’s a look at some of the numbers! Note that “This site” excludes republication of school papers, and that I don’t have an exact count for the school papers because I’ve already discarded a few of the shorter pieces, but their average length is well-known to me. More on the unpublished &lt;em&gt;Rust vs. Swift&lt;/em&gt; project below.&lt;a href="#fn1" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref1"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr class="header"&gt;
&lt;th style="text-align: center;"&gt;Category&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th style="text-align: center;"&gt;Words&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr class="odd"&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/m-div/"&gt;School&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: center;"&gt;~130,500&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class="even"&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;a href="https://mereorthodoxy.com/author/chris-krycho/"&gt;Mere Orthodoxy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: center;"&gt;~6000&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class="odd"&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: center;"&gt;This site&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: center;"&gt;~63,000&lt;a href="#fn2" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref2"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class="even"&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Rust vs. Swift&lt;/em&gt; project&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: center;"&gt;~9350&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class="odd"&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Total&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;~207,850&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of the writing for school, only a small fraction of it is &lt;a href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/m-div/"&gt;published here&lt;/a&gt;, unlike previous years. Roughly 75,000 words of that content is research notes I put together for an independent study I did—which was deeply profitable for me in terms of thinking through hermeneutical and theological systems, and which will hopefully be helpful for the professor for whom I prepared them, but which are not at all publishable. Another 10,000 of those words fit in a category charitably describable as “busy-work” and publishing them is &lt;em&gt;possible&lt;/em&gt; but would have no &lt;em&gt;value&lt;/em&gt;. The school-writing also includes the notes and manuscripts for my sermon-delivery class. You can find those sermons &lt;a href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/sermons/"&gt;on this site&lt;/a&gt; as well well, with audio, video, and the manuscripts available—but the notes are not worth publishing, as they’re entirely internal. Still: they’re words, I wrote them, and there are a lot of them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the plus side, I wrote one of the papers I’m proudest of from my entire seminary career in the spring: &lt;a href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2016/realism-and-antirealism.html"&gt;Realism and Antirealism—A key debate in the philosophy of science (with interesting implications for young-earth creationism)&lt;/a&gt;. I’m happy with it not least because I wrote it in a very compressed fashion because of some family health issues that hit at the end of that semester, and it still turned out extremely well because I had &lt;em&gt;planned&lt;/em&gt; it meticulously. Despite having only a single draft with one typo-level revision pass, it’s easily the best paper I’ve ever written. It turns out that doing a really careful outline helps when you’re working at this scale. I’ve not normally been a fan of outlining (and I’ve not normally found it helpful when I’ve tried it), but for any longer, more sustained argument, it’s absolutely necessary.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of the content on this site (excluding republication of school papers), an astounding ~14,000 of those words are in my “microblog” content. It’s amazing how much those little posts add up. That said, I’m surprised to see that I’ve put out as many &lt;em&gt;other&lt;/em&gt; words as I have this year on this site, and the total there is rather staggering. Writing on this site includes everything from &lt;a href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2016/ask.html" title="Ask: a short story"&gt;fiction&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2016/to-paint-god-as-a-man.html" title="To paint God as a man: an Advent poem"&gt;poetry&lt;/a&gt; to &lt;a href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2016/a-simple-childrens-catechism.html"&gt;a simple children’s catechism&lt;/a&gt; to &lt;a href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2016/what-is-functional-programming.html"&gt;an introduction to functional programming&lt;/a&gt;. I’m exceptionally pleased in retrospect to see how this came out, and I look forward to writing on equally varied terms in the year ahead.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some 13,000 of the words I wrote for this site were in my &lt;a href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/rust-and-swift.html"&gt;Rust and Swift&lt;/a&gt; series, a project I’ve enjoyed enormously since starting it in 2015 and would like to get back to in 2017. It went on hold because I was offered, and accepted, a contract to write a 30–40 page report for O’Reilly comparing the two languages, which was intended to come out this fall. Unfortunately, somewhere along the way some wires got crossed and my pitch and what they wanted didn’t end up being the same. Once that became clear (at the beginning of October), they opted to drop the project. This was a huge disappointment to me: it was a small hit financially, but a big one time-wise, as I sunk a &lt;em&gt;lot&lt;/em&gt; of hours into it in what was an already-very-busy fall; the project was over ¾ done when it was dropped.&lt;a href="#fn3" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref3"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A few big lessons I learned from this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol type="1"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Don’t overcommit. Even if the project had gone through without issue, it would have been more on my plate than I could reasonably handle. The fact that it was canceled after having done a lot of the work meant it was also &lt;em&gt;financially&lt;/em&gt; frustrating, but I had overcommitted regardless. Won’t do that again.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Be &lt;em&gt;even more&lt;/em&gt; clear up-front about the terms and goals of a project. I don’t know how we ended up with the crossed wires we did, but it was extremely frustrating.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;If you can get an advance, get an advance. Just saying.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In general, I’m quite pleased with the &lt;em&gt;volume&lt;/em&gt; of my output in 2016 (who wouldn’t be, right?). I’d definitely like a lot more of that to be public-facing in 2017, even if it’s lower in overall volume. I hope to take the material from that &lt;em&gt;Rust vs. Swift&lt;/em&gt; project, expand it slightly, and self-publish it. I also hope to put together at least one substantive essay for Mere Orthodoxy next year. And of course there will probably be thousands of words in this space, too—inevitably more than I even realize.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section class="footnotes"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn1"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Note as well that this excludes all the &lt;a href="https://github.com/chriskrycho/newrustacean.com/tree/589cd13225cde91f92bfca93f6679f2395d78886/docs"&gt;podcast scripts&lt;/a&gt; I wrote this year! Those would add well over 10,000 more words to this count.&lt;a href="#fnref1"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn2"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Yes, that number includes these posts!&lt;a href="#fnref2"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn3"&gt;&lt;p&gt;They wanted an analysis of when you’d choose each language; I pitched a comparison along similar lines to my blog series, looking at the language design choices as a view into software engineering tradeoffs. When the mismatch became clear, I pointed out that “when to choose Rust vs. Swift” is, generally speaking, a roughly two-sentence answer: “Choose Rust for cross-platform, high-performance/low-level code. Choose Swift if you’re writing apps on an Apple platform.” This was not, apparently, obvious to everyone else involved. In the words of the internet: &lt;span style="whitespace: nowrap"&gt;¯\_(ツ)_/¯&lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="#fnref3"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 28 Dec 2016 07:00:00 -0500</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2016-12-28:2016/2016-review-2.html</guid><category>writing</category><category>podcasting</category><category>software development</category><category>family</category><category>productivity</category><category>fitness</category><category>2016-in-review</category></item><item><title>2016 in Review, Part 1 of 6</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2016/2016-review-1.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;i class='editorial'&gt;I originally drafted a single, mammoth post reflecting on this whole year—but at more than 6,000 words, that seemed like a bit much. As such, I’ve broken it into a series of posts, to be published daily through the start of the new year. Hopefully they’re a bit more digestible that way!&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2016/2016-review-intro.html"&gt;Introduction, or: a ridiculous year summarized&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2016/2016-review-1.html"&gt;Part 1: Running headfirst into a wall of pneumonia.&lt;/a&gt; (this post)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2016/2016-review-2.html"&gt;Part 2: So. many. words. I had no idea how many words.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Part 3: Podcasting: Winning Slowly, New Rustacean, and more!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Part 4: Writing software for Olo and for open source.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Part 5: Getting things done in 2016 and beyond.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Part 6: Plans for 2017!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Wait, hold on,&lt;/em&gt; you say. &lt;em&gt;Go back. How did you get walking pneumonia?&lt;/em&gt; This is a fun story, and it’s a huge part of what made the other parts of the latter half of 2016 go the way they did.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I went for what I expected to be a 15–16 mile long run as part of training for the half-marathon I signed up for this year. The previous week &lt;a href="http://runwith.chriskrycho.com/runs/12/" title="Run summary on runwith.chriskrycho.com"&gt;I’d done a 14-mile run&lt;/a&gt;, so 15–16 would have been no problem. I was feeling &lt;em&gt;awesome&lt;/em&gt; on the run, so decided to extend it to 17. This was right at the edge of what makes good sense for a week-over-week increase in mileage; you generally want to stick with ~10% increases and max out at 20%; but 17 is right at that limit relative to 14. So I turned right to cut through another nearby town instead of left to head directly home when I was at roughly the 11-mile mark.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then, where I &lt;em&gt;did&lt;/em&gt; cut back toward home, I took a wrong turn out of a five-way intersection. (You can see on the north end of the map, in Youngsville, &lt;a href="https://www.strava.com/activities/644619792" title="Run overview on Strava"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;). I realized this half a mile on, but figured there would be a spot to cut over. There is not. So I got back to where I had taken the wrong turn, filled up my water bottle and hit the bathroom, and made my way home. But at this point, I was already at ~15 miles, and ~4 miles from home. As I got back into our town, I decided: why not just go ahead and extend out to 20 miles?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And the truth is, that extra three quarters of a mile probably didn’t matter a bit. 19.25 vs. 20 miles? Same difference in its effect on my immune system, which is to say: it completely crashed it. A 42% week over week increase in mileage is no joke. The little cold I picked up from my 2-year-old daughter turned into borderline bronchitis. Yay.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What with a busy spring preceding—I had no idea how much busier I would be taking 2 classes and working 30 hours a week than I had been taking 3 classes and working 20 hours a week—I didn’t manage a triathlon. I had contented myself with the thought that I’d likely set another PR in my half marathon, but after weeks of recovery from walking pneumonia, that thought fell apart as well. I lost about a minute per mile in my pace, and my mileage was shot as well. I never got it back—not least because of a writing project which went south on me. I ended up being sick off and on all fall, and I’m only now getting my feet back under me. Sad to say, one of those times I got sick was the week of the half marathon I signed up for, and I’d been getting loud, clear signals from my body on previous runs that I was pushing too hard. So no race &lt;em&gt;at all&lt;/em&gt; this year. But better that than pushing and injuring myself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The year also saw a so-far unreversed weight gain that I find incredibly frustrating. In the first six months of 2016, I gained about ten pounds—despite keeping up the same basic activity level. I attribute this to a combination of factors: metabolic shifts in my late 20s, shifting back to doing almost purely running rather than a mix of running, swimming, and cycling, and the impact of acclimation to a workout load. I’m far from overweight, but I’m also slower and generally a bit flabbier as a result.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here’s hoping 2017 is &lt;em&gt;much&lt;/em&gt; better in all these regards! I plan to do a sprint-length triathlon and a full marathon. And I hope to lose those ten pounds again and get back to that healthier overall weight. That combo seems like the thing to do the year I turn thirty and graduate seminary.&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 27 Dec 2016 17:00:00 -0500</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2016-12-27:2016/2016-review-1.html</guid><category>writing</category><category>podcasting</category><category>software development</category><category>family</category><category>productivity</category><category>fitness</category><category>2016-in-review</category></item><item><title>2016 in Review, Introduction</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2016/2016-review-intro.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;i class='editorial'&gt;I originally drafted a single, mammoth post reflecting on this whole year—but at more than 6,000 words, that seemed like a bit much. As such, I’ve broken it into a series of posts, to be published daily through the start of the new year. Hopefully they’re a bit more digestible that way! This first day, you’re getting two posts; the rest of the year, one (at least: in this series!).&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2016/2016-review-intro.html"&gt;Introduction, or: a ridiculous year summarized&lt;/a&gt; (this post)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2016/2016-review-1.html"&gt;Part 1: Running headfirst into a wall of pneumonia.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2016/2016-review-2.html"&gt;Part 2: So. many. words. I had no idea how many words.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Part 3: Podcasting: Winning Slowly, New Rustacean, and more!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Part 4: Writing software for Olo and for open source.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Part 5: Getting things done in 2016 and beyond.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Part 6: Plans for 2017!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;2016 was a long, difficult, strange, sometimes wonderful and sometimes dreadful year for me. It was one of the most professionally and scholastically enjoyable and rewarding years of my life, and also one of the most exhausting. As I often do at years-end, I am taking stock publicly of what went well, what went poorly, and what I might do different in a variety of categories—here, mostly in terms of my public-facing endeavors. This year’s summing-up post will also (for, I think, the first time) include some numbers! But first, a few comments on the big picture.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the end of 2015, I &lt;a href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2015/thoughts-on-2015-and-2016.html"&gt;offered a similar set of reflections&lt;/a&gt;. At the end of it, I laid out some plans for 2016:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am going to set a single goal in each of five major categories in my life:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;spiritual:&lt;/strong&gt; everything in my walk with God, including my own personal devotions, my involvement in the life of the church, and my “ministry” actions in general&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;family:&lt;/strong&gt; both quantity and quality time spent with my wife and my quickly-growing-up little girls&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;personal:&lt;/strong&gt; podcasting, blogging, and writing for &lt;a href="http://mereorthodoxy.com/author/chris-krycho/"&gt;other outlets&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;professional:&lt;/strong&gt; working in my new job and as a consultant, and carrying on toward the conclusion of my M. Div.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;health/fitness:&lt;/strong&gt; continuing to stay healthy, including eating well and continuing to stay fit by running and doing triathlon work&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Early in the year, I made the habit of writing these out formally on a day-by-day basis—and I did this off and on. If you were to look at my little (Moleskine-branded and delightful-to-me) daily planner, you’d see streaks of weeks where I noted specific tasks and whether I hit them or not, punctuated by weeks and months where I did nothing of the sort. I have always found it difficult to stick with these kinds of things, in part because I usually have a pretty good idea what I need to do on any given day without writing it down somewhere. (I use &lt;a href="https://www.omnigroup.com/omnifocus/" title="OmniFocus"&gt;other tools&lt;/a&gt; for tracking mid- and long-term deadlines for school.) In July, I started mashing this idea up with &lt;a href="http://bulletjournal.com" title="Bullet Journal site"&gt;bullet journaling&lt;/a&gt;, and I found that I (a) really like the system and (b) also didn’t stick with it consistently. A lot of that came down to the fact that I got thrown off—horribly—by getting a mild-but-still-utterly-debilitating case of walking pneumonia in July. (On which, more in a moment.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So much for last year’s ideas about &lt;em&gt;how&lt;/em&gt; I was going to hit those goals. How did I actually do at addressing them? The answer is: &lt;em&gt;okay&lt;/em&gt;. 2016 was not an amazing year. It was not a terrible year. But it had as many downs as ups.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My own walk with God remains &lt;em&gt;steady&lt;/em&gt;. Nothing amazing to report here, but I’m more than okay with that. I will perhaps say more on this in another post, but the older I get the more convinced I am that emotional highs are a trap. Sentiment and true religion are &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; the same thing; and Scripture calls us to &lt;em&gt;faithfulness&lt;/em&gt;, not &lt;em&gt;spiritual feelings&lt;/em&gt;. As such, in a year with this many bumps, I am glad to say that I had no horrible falls, and I read my Bible nearly every day and prayed every single day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our family learned some Bible verses, and started working on the Heidelberg Catechism. We shared the gospel with people as we were able, and met faithfully with our church. We were not extraordinary, and we were far from flawless, but I think we did &lt;em&gt;well&lt;/em&gt;. I hope and pray in God’s grace we are able to continue in faithfully doing well in the years to come. Certainly if there is one thing I hope to do more of in 2017 it is spend time with my girls. I am not a huge “kid person,” but these years are precious and go by quickly; far better to spend more time with them and have a podcast episode or a writing project go out later (or not at all) than to miss these little years.&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 27 Dec 2016 16:00:00 -0500</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2016-12-27:2016/2016-review-intro.html</guid><category>writing</category><category>podcasting</category><category>software development</category><category>family</category><category>productivity</category><category>fitness</category><category>2016-in-review</category></item></channel></rss>