<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>chriskrycho.com</title><link href="http://chriskrycho.com/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://chriskrycho.com/feeds/all-en.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://chriskrycho.com/</id><updated>2014-01-07T23:40:00-05:00</updated><entry><title>A Study in Contrasts: 2 Kings 16–20</title><link href="http://chriskrycho.com/2014/study-in-contrasts-2-kings-16-20.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-01-07T23:40:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Chris Krycho</name></author><id>tag:chriskrycho.com,2014-01-07:2014/study-in-contrasts-2-kings-16-20.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;!--Template: devotions--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the recurring themes of the books of Kings (1 and 2 Samuel, 1 and 2 Kings) is the distinction between those who &amp;#8220;did what was right in the eyes of Yahweh&amp;#8221; and those who &amp;#8220;did what was evil in the sight of Yahweh&amp;#8221;, e.g. 15:34, 17:2 respectively&amp;#8212;-to name just two of the &lt;em&gt;many&lt;/em&gt; passages echoing this refrain in these books. Whereas 1 and 2 Samuel zoomed in on the contrast between Saul and David, 1 and 2 Kings take nearly all their successors at a very high level, often sparing them few more words than necessary to note their parentage, whether they did what was right or what was evil in the eyes of Yahweh, and a reference to other records of their&amp;nbsp;deeds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the dominant themes of these books, then, is that doing what is right in Yahweh&amp;#8217;s eyes has an enormous reward, while doing what is evil in his eyes eventually brings a great judgment. 2 Kings 17&amp;#8212;19 brings this message home, and hard. Centuries of rebellion on Israel&amp;#8217;s part culminated in the Assyrian capture of Samaria and the forcible exile of the Jews of Israel from their homeland. The author pauses from his otherwise quick-moving narrative to explain this point in detail for the better part of a chapter. Israel&amp;#8217;s fall was not the mere ordinary turn of regional political events it might have seemed. It was, instead, God&amp;#8217;s final judgment on a people who had continuously rebelled against him generation after generation, worshiping in a way they &lt;em&gt;knew&lt;/em&gt; was abhorrent to&amp;nbsp;him.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By contrast, when the same mighty king with his mighty army came to take Jerusalem, the city stood. Judah had its share of wicked kings, to be sure&amp;#8212;-but unlike Israel, it also had many kings who &amp;#8220;did what was right in the eyes of Yahweh&amp;#8221; and in particular it had Hezekiah, who &amp;#8220;trusted in Yahweh, the God of Israel, so that there was none like him among all the kings of Judah after him, nor among those who were before him&amp;#8221;&amp;nbsp;(18:5).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The armies of the greatest power in the region&amp;#8212;-unstoppable Assyria&amp;#8212;-surrounded the capital city en masse. Their leaders boasted in their victories, tried to bully Hezekiah and the people into surrendering without a fight, and insulted the name of Yahweh. Attacking the people of God is always a bad idea; attacking him directly is an even &lt;em&gt;worse&lt;/em&gt; idea. The Scriptures are a long record of the lengths to which God will go to defend his name: he will quite literally die to defend the glorious reality that he is most righteous and most powerful being there is, most worthy of worship. When Sennacherib boasted, &amp;#8220;Who among all the gods of the lands have delivered their lands out of my hand, that Yahweh should deliver Jerusalem out of my hand?&amp;#8221; (18:35), he missed something. Hezekiah points it out in his prayer: &amp;#8220;[They] were not gods, but the work of men&amp;#8217;s hands, wood and stone. Therefore they were destroyed. So now, O Yahweh our God, save us, please, from his hand, that all the kingdoms of the earth may know that you, O Yahweh, are God alone&amp;#8221;&amp;nbsp;(19:18b&amp;#8212;29).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;God has &lt;em&gt;always&lt;/em&gt; been about the business of making his name known to the ends of the earth. Not because he is a braggart, but because he is the end for which all things exist&amp;#8212;-the end for which &lt;em&gt;we&lt;/em&gt; exist. In setting ourselves against that, we are setting ourselves against reality. We are trying to fly by pushing away from the ground with the hairs on our head&amp;#8212;-and for some reason, gravity comes out victorious. So when God brings judgment on blasphemers, that is a &lt;em&gt;mercy&lt;/em&gt; to the nations who have a chance to repent and kneel before the king of&amp;nbsp;all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What is amazing to me is just how profoundly longsuffering God is. Were I so often insulted, ignored, and injuriously assaulted in character, I would not wait hundreds of years, sending prophet after prophet to give people opportunity after opportunity to respond. I sometimes have a hard time restraining my impatience for a few minutes with my wife or my child. And yet the God who ultimately struck down 185,000 Assyrians waited generation upon generation to bring his judgment on Israel&amp;#8212;-and he likewise gave the Assyrians the opportunity to repent (c.f. Jonah). This God is shockingly merciful, even as he brings&amp;nbsp;judgment.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="devotions"></category></entry><entry><title>Five Things Proverbs 6 Teaches</title><link href="http://chriskrycho.com/2014/five-things-proverbs-six.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-01-06T20:30:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Chris Krycho</name></author><id>tag:chriskrycho.com,2014-01-06:2014/five-things-proverbs-six.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;!--Template: devotions--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Proverbs 6 makes 5 points, rather distinctly and sharply. First a summary and then a few thoughts on&amp;nbsp;each.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Verses 1&amp;#8212;5:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;Being security for your neighbor&amp;#8212;-still less for a stranger&amp;#8212;-is a bad&amp;nbsp;idea.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This first point is perhaps the least obviously applicable to me today. I don&amp;#8217;t make a habit of pledging money or possessions for a friend&amp;#8217;s (still less a stranger&amp;#8217;s) poor money decisions. I might &lt;em&gt;give&lt;/em&gt; a friend (or even a stranger) money, but I can&amp;#8217;t imagine putting myself in the position of guaranteeing a loan for someone else. That just seems like a terrible idea. Of course, that&amp;#8217;s the point of these verses: it &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; a terrible idea. The counsel here is to get out of that kind of situation as fast as possible (and, by implication, to avoid getting into such a situation in the first&amp;nbsp;place).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Verses 6&amp;#8212;11:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;Laziness will prove ruinous. Industriousness will produce good&amp;nbsp;results.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have seen this proven true time and again in the lives of those around me. As a general rule, people who work hard do well for themselves, and people who are lazy do very poorly for themselves. As a rule, I say, because there are times when this is not true&amp;#8212;-there really are times when systemic injustices undermine even people&amp;#8217;s best efforts. This proverb is a proverb, not an iron-clad guarantee, and we would all do well to remember as much. That said: we would &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; do well to remember as much: if the political conservative&amp;#8217;s typical response is to simply point to this verse as a promise (which it is not), the political liberal&amp;#8217;s typical response is to act as though this verse has no bearing whatsoever. Sometimes, poverty has complex, structural, societal roots&amp;#8212;-but sometimes, people are just lazy. God calls us &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; to be lazy; work is a good thing that was instituted before the&amp;nbsp;Fall.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Verses 12&amp;#8212;15:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;The ultimate fate of a wicked person is&amp;nbsp;calamity.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is nothing terribly complicated here. There is, however, a great deal of hope here for those of us who have watched wicked people go around behaving wickedly and seemingly coming off no worse for wear every time. There will come a day of recompense for every wicked deed. Lord willing, for some of those people, that day came when Christ came, and they will join us in the company of saints as they abandon their wickedness and turn to God. But for those who don&amp;#8217;t, justice will come, and it will come&amp;nbsp;swiftly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Verses 16&amp;#8212;19:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;There are some things God truly&amp;nbsp;hates.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is almost &lt;em&gt;passe&lt;/em&gt; to note how distasteful this idea is in our culture today, but the words on the page could not be clearer. There are things that Yahweh hates, things that are an abomination to him. He hates pride. He abominates deceit. He hates the shedding of innocent blood. He abominates the plotting of wickedness. He hates the doing of evil. He abominates false witness to be borne. He hates dissension between&amp;nbsp;brothers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But more than this: he hates those who &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt; these things. This is dreadful&amp;#8212;-apart from the grace he shows us in&amp;nbsp;Christ.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Verses 20&amp;#8212;35:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;Adultery is folly. Wisdom runs the other&amp;nbsp;way.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="/2014/01/folly-of-sin"&gt;Once again&lt;/a&gt;, the proverbs hammer home the folly of adultery. It is not only that it does not give what it promises and brings spiritual ruin. It is that it also produces, at a purely practical level, destruction. A spouse&amp;#8217;s jealousy is (rightly) a fearful thing. Who in his right mind would sleep with another man&amp;#8217;s wife, knowing what the response would be? What woman would sleep with another woman&amp;#8217;s husband, knowing how her own rage would be? The implications just for one&amp;#8217;s own health&amp;#8212;-still less any other part of one&amp;#8217;s life&amp;#8212;-ought to be enough to warn us&amp;nbsp;away.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Proverbs remind me again and again that God cares about my life at every level. He is not distant or unengaged with these details; he cares about every aspect of human flourishing, and takes pains to make clear to us what that flourishing looks like&amp;#8212;-and what it&amp;nbsp;doesn&amp;#8217;t.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="devotions"></category></entry><entry><title>The Folly of Sin</title><link href="http://chriskrycho.com/2014/folly-of-sin.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-01-05T23:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Chris Krycho</name></author><id>tag:chriskrycho.com,2014-01-05:2014/folly-of-sin.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;!--Template: devotions--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Adultery. It has torn countless families and destroyed innumerable ministries over the years. Over and over again, the refrain is the same: &amp;#8220;I never thought it would happen to me!&amp;#8221; and &amp;#8220;I never meant for it to go this far!&amp;#8221;&lt;sup id="fnref:adultery-1"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:adultery-1" rel="footnote"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Given the evidence of the years, though, no one should ever cavalierly say, &amp;#8220;I&amp;#8217;ll never do that.&amp;#8221; Say it, yes. But back it up by making concrete choices every day not to break vows to your&amp;nbsp;spouse.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Proverbs 5 couldn&amp;#8217;t be clearer: adultery &lt;em&gt;looks&lt;/em&gt; good from the outside and feels good at the&amp;nbsp;outset:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;For&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;the&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;lips&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;of&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;a&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;forbidden&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;woman&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;drip&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;honey&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;and&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;her&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;speech&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;is&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;smoother&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;than&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;oil&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="n"&gt;but&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;in&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;the&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;end&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;she&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;is&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;bitter&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;as&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;wormwood&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;sharp&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;as&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;a&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;two&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;edged&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;sword&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No one commits adultery because it looks so dreadful. People commit this sin&amp;#8212;-like every other&amp;#8212;-because it looks good. The trick, of course, is that it is &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt;. The Proverb highlights the contradiction of sin powerfully: sin looks sweet, but proves bitter. It seems smooth, but only proves smoothly destructive as it slices away at everything you value. Sin always produces the opposite of what it promises. Adultery promises intimacy, but adultery &lt;em&gt;destroys&lt;/em&gt; intimacy. Drugs promise liberated minds; instead they produce addiction. Covetousness promises satisfaction; instead it produces only an ever-gnawing emptiness. Sin is like a sweet-tasting infection that rots us from the inside&amp;nbsp;out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But it is more than that. Sin is not bad only because it proves so ruinous to us&amp;#8212;-though certainly it is bad for that reason. Sin is bad because it is high treason, because it is at its core a rejection of the good, the true, the beautiful in that it is a rejection of God in the exaltation of self. Sin is ruinous to us in part because it is the undoing of everything of what we are: beings made to worship the Triune God, instead kneeling to our own reflection in the mirror instead of the one we were meant to&amp;nbsp;reflect.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But God is a righteous judge. He is holy. He does not tolerate sin. Psalm 5 puts it in sharp&amp;nbsp;relief:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;For&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;you&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;are&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;not&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;a&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;God&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;who&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;delights&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;in&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;wickedness&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;evil&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;may&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;not&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;dwell&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;with&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;you&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="n"&gt;The&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;boastful&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;shall&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;not&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;stand&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;before&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;your&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;eyes&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;you&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;hate&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;all&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;evildoers&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="n"&gt;You&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;destroy&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;those&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;who&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;speak&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;lies&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;Yahweh&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;abhors&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;the&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;bloodthirsty&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;and&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;deceitful&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;man&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;God detests sin.&lt;sup id="fnref:sin-sermon"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:sin-sermon" rel="footnote"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Not just the hot-button sin issues of our day (though those are not excluded), but our pettiness and jealousy, our deceptions great and small, our boasting and pride. We are &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; evildoers. And yet, wonder of wonders, we live still. Though God who made us and at whom we have all shaken our fists in rebellion would be perfectly within his rights to end us without a thought; he does not. He shows mercy. He forbears long. He waits to bring&amp;nbsp;judgment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He provides a way of escape. We, like David, can enter his house &amp;#8220;through the abundance of [his] steadfast love.&amp;#8221; That steadfast love, that covenant love, that almight love, has reached down and partaken of frail humanity and death and even of divine wrath, so that God might be glorified in his holiness. We are saved not because God is sentimental or sappy, but because he is righteous, and has already paid the price for our&amp;nbsp;sins.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hallelujah.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:adultery-1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And yes, sometimes also (even more sadly), &amp;#8220;I don&amp;#8217;t care; why shouldn&amp;#8217;t I be happy?&amp;#8221;&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:adultery-1" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:sin-sermon"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For more on all of this, I commend to you the &lt;a href="http://www.sermonaudio.com/sermoninfo.asp?sermonID=15141146471"&gt;sermon&lt;/a&gt; our primary preaching pastor delivered today.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:sin-sermon" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 2 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary><category term="devotions"></category></entry><entry><title>A Note to RSS Subscribers</title><link href="http://chriskrycho.com/2014/a-note-to-rss-subscribers.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-01-05T09:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Chris Krycho</name></author><id>tag:chriskrycho.com,2014-01-05:2014/a-note-to-rss-subscribers.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;A note to anyone who has subscribed to this &lt;span class="caps"&gt;RSS&lt;/span&gt; feed: you should resubscribe by
adding &lt;a href="http://chriskrycho.com/feed.xml"&gt;http://chriskrycho.com/feed.xml&lt;/a&gt; to your reader, as this feed location
is now defunct.&amp;nbsp;Thanks!&lt;/p&gt;</summary></entry><entry><title>Elijah and Elisha</title><link href="http://chriskrycho.com/2014/elijah-elisha.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-01-04T23:45:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Chris Krycho</name></author><id>tag:chriskrycho.com,2014-01-04:2014/elijah-elisha.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;!--Template: devotions--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One cannot help but notice, reading through 1 and 2 Kings, how much Elijah and Elisha echo Moses and foreshadow the Messiah. They perform miracles that show up the limitations of other so-called deities, part the Jordan, make clean what was impure, give miraculous children, raise the dead, multiply food for a meal for the hungry.&lt;sup id="fnref:bears"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:bears" rel="footnote"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; These men were prophets like Moses, but Israel knew that they were not &lt;em&gt;the&lt;/em&gt; prophet like Moses that the first savior of Israel had&amp;nbsp;promised.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reading through these books, it is interesting that Israel was eagerly awaiting another prophet like Elijah when Jesus came. Indeed, it is interesting that a later prophet would speak of Elijah coming again. Reading through this material&amp;#8212;-which was originally all a single book covering all of 1 Samuel through 2 Kings&amp;#8212;-one would not necessarily be inclined to call Elijah the greater of the pair. Indeed, Elisha both asked for and apparently received a double portion of the miraculous gift that Yahweh had given to Elijah. The text records far more miracles performed by Elisha than by Elijah. (Indeed, most of that list above belongs to Elisha and not to&amp;nbsp;Elijah.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Clearly, though, there was something special about&amp;nbsp;Elijah.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think it was his passion for the name of Yahweh, and I think the text makes this abundantly clear. It is not that Elisha was &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; passionate for the glory of Yahweh; it is that this is the main (and nearly the only) thing in view in Elijah&amp;#8217;s ministry. Elijah&amp;#8217;s responsibility was to point the people to repentance for their sins and to show up false religion for what it was. This he did. He stood for the name of Yahweh under the threat of death and all alone. Other faithful Yahweh-worshippers though there were in Israel at the time, it was Elijah alone on the mountain confronting the four hundred priests of Baal, and he alone who saw the mighty hand of Yahweh raised in triumph against Baalism. He, like John the Baptizer, was the lone voice in the wilderness, calling the people of Israel back to&amp;nbsp;God.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Elisha&amp;#8217;s role was different: he was the man of miracles and the fierce judge. He did the greatest miracles recorded in the Bible prior to the coming of the Messiah; only in Jesus himself was there a greater provider, healer, or resurrector. He pointed to the greatness of Yahweh through these miracles; unlike Elijah, he did so in a time when many others worshipped Yahweh. He stood on Elijah&amp;#8217;s shoulders, as it&amp;nbsp;were.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have often pondered over the last year or so that often it is the case that younger leaders can seem (and perhaps are) more effective than their elders&amp;#8212;-but that even when this is so, there is a foundation present &lt;em&gt;because&lt;/em&gt; of the elders that is too easily overlooked. Many young men&amp;#8217;s pastoral ministries are successful not only because of their own faithfulness, but because of the work of the pastors who preceded them. Many young men can be more doctrinally sound than or more effective preachers than their predecessors &lt;em&gt;because&lt;/em&gt; of their predecessors. Elisha did his miracles in a land that had already seen Baalism humbled under fire from Yahweh. I do my writing, ministry (such as it is), and even thinking in the context set for me by faithful Christians who have gone before, women and men who have diligently sought Christ and laid a foundation on which I might&amp;nbsp;build.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:bears"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To say nothing of cursing mockers to be attacked by bears, in one of the stranger passages in the old Testament.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:bears" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary><category term="devotions"></category></entry><entry><title>Finding God in Proverbs</title><link href="http://chriskrycho.com/2014/finding-god-proverbs.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-01-03T23:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Chris Krycho</name></author><id>tag:chriskrycho.com,2014-01-03:2014/finding-god-proverbs.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;!--Template: devotions--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the most helpful patterns I have developed in the last few years of Scripture reading is asking one simple question as I read: &lt;em&gt;What does this passage reveal about God?&lt;/em&gt; There are many other questions&amp;#8212;-good, important questions&amp;#8212;-to ask of the text. But this one, I find, yields the most fruit. The Bible is not just a book of moral teachings, nor a mere practical guide for our lives. It is the revelation of the living God to his people.&lt;sup id="fnref:1"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:1" rel="footnote"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So what do we do when we get to, say, Proverbs? At first blush, the question seems a good deal less tractable here than in many other places. However hairy, most narratives &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt; show us the character of God. Propositional content, whether in letters or sermons or parables or prophecies, likewise tends to make clear, succinct statements about the person and nature of God. The Proverbs, though? Well, sometimes they do, and sometimes they say things like, &amp;#8220;Do not contend with a man for no reason, when he has done you no harm.&amp;#8221; That&amp;#8217;s helpful, to be sure, but when you first read it, it&amp;#8217;s not obvious how that gets us back to God. We could try to hammer the Proverbs into some framework for understanding God, try to reduce their presence in the canon to a role in some theme or another.&lt;sup id="fnref:2"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:2" rel="footnote"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; In the end, though, any such reductive effort is going to run aground on the shoals of misunderstanding&amp;#8212;-quite the opposite of the intent of the&amp;nbsp;author.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Proverbs often show us God&amp;#8217;s character sideways. If we believe that the counsel offered by the Proverbs really is wise&amp;#8212;-that the glowing promises here in Proverbs 3 of blessing, gain, and profit from wisdom are true, that there really is nothing better than to have understanding&amp;#8212;-then we believe that they are insights into reality. And reality was made &lt;em&gt;by God&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;Yahweh&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;by&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;wisdom&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;founded&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;the&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;earth&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;by&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;understanding&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;he&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;established&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;the&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;heavens&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="n"&gt;by&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;his&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;knowledge&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;the&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;deeps&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;broke&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;open&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;and&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;the&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;clouds&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;drop&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;down&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;the&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;dew&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;Proverbs&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;3&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;19&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;--&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;20&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If we then start asking good questions of the text we find very quickly that we do have a path back to the person and nature of God. For example: &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt; should we not contend with a man when he has done us no harm? Well, we ought not do so because it will certainly stir up trouble, and we know God does not delight in strife. Moreover, picking a fight with someone without cause is unjust, and this same author has told us that wisdom comports with justice and righteousness, and that &lt;em&gt;God&lt;/em&gt; is&amp;nbsp;just.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Taking a further step back, we can ask why this proverb is included in the inspired Scriptures. Then we see even more: God cares about the way people interact with one another. He values human flourishing, and so has provided enormous guidance for us in the form of hundreds upon hundreds of practical insights into the way the world is. He delights in people so greatly that he crosses the boundary between transcendence and immanence to give us his very&amp;nbsp;words.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It turns out there is an awful lot to learn about God in the Proverbs&amp;#8212;-even the ones that do no mention&amp;nbsp;him.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That final phrase, &amp;#8220;to his people,&amp;#8221; is an important one for all hermeneutics; reading the Scriptures with faith makes a difference. &lt;a href="http://mereorthodoxy.com/"&gt;Matthew Lee Anderson&lt;/a&gt; makes this point helpfully and at some length in his excellent &lt;a href="http://www.amazon.com/End-Our-Exploring-Questioning-Confidence-ebook/dp/B00BUP1BQQ/?tag=krycho-20"&gt;&lt;em&gt;The End of Our Exploring&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:2"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is right here that many Biblical theologies&amp;#8212;-that&amp;#8217;s a specific discipline in theology, though admittedly poorly named&amp;#8212;-go amiss.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:2" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 2 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary><category term="devotions"></category></entry><entry><title>Kings in Contrast</title><link href="http://chriskrycho.com/2014/kings-contrast.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-01-02T21:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Chris Krycho</name></author><id>tag:chriskrycho.com,2014-01-02:2014/kings-contrast.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;!--Template: devotions--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tonight&amp;#8217;s reading in 1 Kings, Psalms, and Proverbs had some surprising overlaps. The material in 1 Kings covered a series of kings whose courses were largely &lt;em&gt;away&lt;/em&gt; from worshipping Yahweh and toward worshipping other gods. With only one exception, in fact, every single king listed in these five chapters rejected the God of Israel in favor of the gods of the nations which the Hebrews had driven out of Canaan. That exception, Asa, stands in sharp contrast to the litany of rebellious kings who preceded and followed him as being a man who followed God with his whole heart. Others, it seems, included Yahweh in their list of gods to worship, but never reverenced him as supreme and only. This list of wicked kings of both Israel and Judah climaxes with the appearance of Elijah, the righteous prophet who confronts the &lt;em&gt;most&lt;/em&gt; wicked king in the list, and who ultimately demonstrates Yahweh&amp;#8217;s superiority over the other gods the Hebrews&amp;nbsp;worshipped.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Proverbs 2 continues Solomon&amp;#8217;s exhortation to seek wisdom wholeheartedly, and his corresponding encouragement that Yahweh gives wisdom to those who seek it. But Solomon did not stop with the idea that knowledge and understanding are good&amp;#8212;-though this he certainly affirms. Rather, he continued on to emphasize that God&amp;#8217;s knowledge and discernment go hand in hand with his integrity and justice. Those who seek this wisdom walk in righteousness and justice and equity. A person of wisdom is kept safe from both evildoers and from doing evil him- or herself. That Solomon&amp;#8217;s own line, beginning with his own son and continuing on down through every king but Asa in these chapters in 1 Kings, went so far astray indicates how little these words were&amp;nbsp;heeded.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The picture painted by Psalm 2 stands in impossibly sharp contrast to these depraved kings. The Anointed One of the psalm is a messianic figure: those who take refuge in him find shelter, but those who rebel against him are broken under his rule. There is a king in view here who laughs at the rebellion of the rulers of every nation (Israel included), who scorns the folly of plotting against the Most High God. The king that Yahweh calls his Son will receive those same nations as his inheritance. He will be the king above all other kings. He will be both wrathful against rebellion and merciful to those who &amp;#8220;take refuge in him&amp;#8221; (v.&amp;nbsp;11&amp;#8212;12).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So we have set before us the history of wicked men rebelling against the very God who gave them their thrones, and a call to that same line of the kings to humbly seek wisdom from that God, and a poetic picture of the true king against whom any rebellion is folly. And running through all of these are both the wrath of God against the folly and sin of those rebelling against him, and his mercy. Yahweh saves his people from following other gods in that magnificent confrontation on the mountain, Elijah on one side and the priests of Baal on the other. He is the source of wisdom, and the one who keeps his people from walking in folly or wickedness. And he is the righteous king who gives his people peace and security. Not because he does not do justice or cares little about sin, but precisely &lt;em&gt;because&lt;/em&gt; he does justice and cares about sin. That Anointed One, that Son of the Most High, is Jesus Christ, who died in order that everything would be put under his feet. Every wicked king in 1 Kings points to the need for Jesus. He is the fulfillment of the wisdom promised in Proverbs 2. He is the Anointed One, the Son of Yahweh, who reigns the nations in righteousness.&amp;nbsp;Hallelujah.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="devotions"></category></entry><entry><title>A New Year of Devotions</title><link href="http://chriskrycho.com/2014/new-year-devotions.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-01-01T23:25:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Chris Krycho</name></author><id>tag:chriskrycho.com,2014-01-01:2014/new-year-devotions.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;!--Template: devotions--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have found, over the years, that writing is a remarkably helpful tool for thinking through the things I am learning. I have also found that I am often better able to remain consistent in my study of Scripture if I am writing regularly about it. That could be in a journal, or on a blog, or just about anywhere. In 2014, I am going to experiment with posting this writing on my blog&amp;#8212;-something I have done &lt;a href="http://2012-2013.chriskrycho.com/theology/topics/devotions/index.html"&gt;before&lt;/a&gt; to good effect for myself, and which a number of acquaintances seemed to like. After talking it through with my wonderful wife, I have set myself a limit of half an hour &lt;em&gt;total&lt;/em&gt; devoted to writing these posts. Hopefully it will prove&amp;nbsp;profitable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If it seems like 1 Kings 9&amp;#8212;13 is a funny place to start this sort of thing, that&amp;#8217;s because it is. But 1 Kings is where I am, and thus it is the place from which I will continue&amp;#8212;-I do not see a good reason to start over at the beginning &lt;em&gt;again&lt;/em&gt; just a few months after having done so&amp;nbsp;before.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A number of points stuck out at me as I worked through this passage. First, and most important, is one of the recurring themes of the whole book: the question of obedience to Yahweh,&lt;sup id="fnref:yahweh"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:yahweh" rel="footnote"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; and the consequences of rejecting him. From the promise God offers Solomon  in chapter 9 through the death of a prophet in chapter 13, the issue is clear. Obedience to God brings everlasting favor, and disobedience brings&amp;nbsp;death.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is not exactly a new theme for the Bible as a whole: it shows up all the way back in Genesis 3. Nor does it stop here (nor even under the New Covenant with Christ): submission to God is characteristic of all who believe. Why? Not because God is some cruel dictator, but because he is both omniscient and omnibenevolent. He knows what is best for us. Defying his ways is like defying gravity: it might make for a &lt;a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=FlMBcTGJ4YM&amp;amp;name=DefyingGravity"&gt;catchy tune&lt;/a&gt;, but the net result is always crashing hard to the&amp;nbsp;ground.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So: Yahweh promised Solomon great things if he would simply follow him alone and not worship other gods. Solomon did exactly the opposite of what God had commanded the kings of Israel, though: he married multiple foreign women who themselves worshiped other gods,&lt;sup id="fnref:1"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:1" rel="footnote"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; and ultimately he built altars to and sacrificed to those other gods himself. We see the same thing in Jeroboam&amp;#8217;s life: God made him promises of really marvelous import, if he would simply walk with Yahweh. Instead, as soon as he became king he led the people &lt;em&gt;away&lt;/em&gt; from Yahweh, reasoning that Yahweh-worship was a threat to his own power, even though it was a prophet of Yahweh who had first told him all that would happen and that it was Yahweh who would do it. A righteous prophet ends up dead because he disobeyed God&amp;#8217;s clear&amp;nbsp;instructions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In short: God means business, and we ought to pay attention when he commands us in a certain area. Again, not because he is a tyrant, but because he loves us and he is righteous. When we defy him, we are simultaneously wronging ourselves and committing cosmic treason. It&amp;#8217;s a bad move, and he rightly responds in judgment. That, in turn, though, takes me back to his &lt;em&gt;decisive&lt;/em&gt; act of judgment: the one the Godhead executed on itself, in the sacrificial, atoning death of Christ on my behalf. My motivation for obedience, then, is not only fear, but joyful&amp;nbsp;gratitude.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#8217;s a good start to the&amp;nbsp;year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:yahweh"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I know it is a bit unusual to spell out the name of God used in the Old Testament like this, but it is my preference. I think it makes many passages much clearer to read Yahweh instead of &lt;span style="font-variant: small-caps"&gt;Lord&lt;/span&gt;, and it&amp;#8217;s simply what&amp;#8217;s there in the original (even if the Jews historically have chosen not to say it&amp;#8212;-there&amp;#8217;s something interesting here, but I shall pass over it today).&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:yahweh" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note that the reason for the prohibition on marrying foreigners was always religious, not ethnic. Solomon&amp;#8217;s own lineage (and thus, Jesus&amp;#8217; too) includes several foreign women&amp;#8212;-each of whom worshiped Yahweh.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 2 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary><category term="devotions"></category></entry></feed>