<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Chris Krycho</title><link href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/feeds/art.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://www.chriskrycho.com/</id><updated>2015-05-27T11:15:00-04:00</updated><entry><title>Easier</title><link href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2015/easier.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-05-27T11:15:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Chris Krycho</name></author><id>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2015-05-27:2015/easier.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;’Tis easier, I confess,&lt;br /&gt;    to speak of savor than&lt;br /&gt;        in truth to taste&lt;br /&gt;            the goodness of our Savior&lt;br /&gt;            the sweetness of our God&lt;br /&gt;    to call to revel than&lt;br /&gt;        in truth to dance&lt;br /&gt;            for joy at what he’s done&lt;br /&gt;            for hope in what he’ll do&lt;br /&gt;    to write of change than&lt;br /&gt;        in truth to alter&lt;br /&gt;            habits of thought and deed&lt;br /&gt;            patterns of word and way&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These words will not suffice—&lt;br /&gt;no poetry alone will change produce—&lt;br /&gt;yet as a reminder and a warning,&lt;br /&gt;rhythm and letters on a page will do,&lt;br /&gt;and I will strive:&lt;br /&gt;    to savor and to taste,&lt;br /&gt;    to revel and to dance,&lt;br /&gt;    to alter and to change.&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><category term="poetry"></category></entry><entry><title>Airship</title><link href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2015/airship.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-04-30T06:05:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Chris Krycho</name></author><id>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2015-04-30:2015/airship.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Our airship sails,&lt;br /&gt;Ere sunrise,&lt;br /&gt;Above a foam-flecked sea&lt;br /&gt;Which gives way, sometimes&lt;br /&gt;To green and citied depths beneath.&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><category term="poetry"></category></entry><entry><title>April Is</title><link href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2015/april-is.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-04-19T14:25:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Chris Krycho</name></author><id>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2015-04-19:2015/april-is.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;April is—&lt;br /&gt;    blue and gray and blue and gray and&lt;br /&gt;        darker gray and deeper blue and&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;April is—&lt;br /&gt;    gold and green and gold and green and&lt;br /&gt;        richest green and brightest gold and&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;April is—&lt;br /&gt;    verdant, daily changing, sometimes&lt;br /&gt;        silent, sometimes&lt;br /&gt;        cantillating, always&lt;br /&gt;            altering and new&lt;br /&gt;                again.&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><category term="poetry"></category></entry><entry><title>Reflection demands</title><link href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2015/reflection-demands.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-03-28T07:40:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Chris Krycho</name></author><id>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2015-03-28:2015/reflection-demands.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Reflection demands&lt;br /&gt;    of its practitioners, like poetry,&lt;br /&gt;    like painting, dance, or ev’ry art,&lt;br /&gt;    pain and toil, labor and sacrifice&lt;br /&gt;        for—&lt;br /&gt;    mind, like limb&lt;br /&gt;    like bow-stroke on a violin, or brush-stroke on a page&lt;br /&gt;    is weak by nature: dull, dim, faint&lt;br /&gt;        for—&lt;br /&gt;    all our faculties, like autumn leaves,&lt;br /&gt;    like ancien régime, or crumbled-down façade,&lt;br /&gt;    are fallen, troubled, and woe’d&lt;br /&gt;        so—&lt;br /&gt;    loose the mind from surly bond!&lt;br /&gt;    set intellect free by striving hard!&lt;br /&gt;    free from ruinous decay, and&lt;br /&gt;    free from foolish sluggery&lt;br /&gt;    with ev’ry breath sing higher note&lt;br /&gt;    by ev’ry step climb further up&lt;br /&gt;        and—&lt;br /&gt;    so deliver to the self&lt;br /&gt;    what wisdom may be found.&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><category term="poetry"></category></entry><entry><title>Speak the Truth in Beauty</title><link href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2015/speak-the-truth-in-beauty.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-02-11T07:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Chris Krycho</name></author><id>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2015-02-11:2015/speak-the-truth-in-beauty.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;This is sort of a &lt;a href="http://mereorthodoxy.com/speak-truth-beauty-review-echoes-eden/"&gt;hybrid review and essay&lt;/a&gt;. The review proper concludes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In short, Echoes of Eden says all the right things. Barrs has provided a healthy, sound theology of the arts, reiterating and synthesizing the helpful work of Schaeffer, Lewis, Tolkien, O’Connor, and Dostoevsky. What is more, his survey of English literature grounds that theology in concrete examples we can follow. This is a solid book.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But there was a bit more to say about this, because…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There was one thing it lacked, though: beauty of its own. As Barrs himself says, “A book that is not well-written, no matter how compelling the story is, will not be reread multiple times” (114). I doubt I will read Echoes of Eden again, because this is true for non-fiction as well. Form matters. It may not be quite true that the way we say things is just as important as what we say—better to say the truth boringly than a lie splendidly—but it comes a close second. The truth is beautiful, and we should always aim to present it beautifully.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think you’ll find the rest interesting! &lt;a href="http://mereorthodoxy.com/speak-truth-beauty-review-echoes-eden/"&gt;Take a look.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A note: I actually meant to have this reviewed about 18 months ago. I got buried in Greek III and it totally slipped my mind! Gladly, the folks at Crossway who sent me the book were understanding.&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><category term="links"></category></entry><entry><title>I Wrote It Wrong</title><link href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2014/i-wrote-it-wrong.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-07-12T20:07:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Chris Krycho</name></author><id>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2014-07-12:2014/i-wrote-it-wrong.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I wrote a &lt;a href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2014/dont-be-rude.html"&gt;blog post&lt;/a&gt; earlier, and it seems I got it wrong (see the &lt;a href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2014/dont-be-rude.html#edit-and-addendum"&gt;addendum&lt;/a&gt; at the end of the post). That is always an unpleasant experience, to say the least.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The one upside to this whole affair? I took away two important lessons: The first was a reminder to read others generously, even when frustrated with them—a point I spelled out a bit in my &lt;a href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2014/dont-be-rude.html#edit-and-addendum"&gt;edit-and-addendum&lt;/a&gt; to the original post. The other about the effect of certain rhetorical structures in my writing. The &lt;em&gt;idea&lt;/em&gt; I had here was good (even if I may have misread the trigger for writing the post in the first place), but it was badly executed, and there were &lt;em&gt;structural&lt;/em&gt; reasons for that, having to do with the weight and balance in the original piece. What follows is just me self-critiquing in public: learning about the process of writing “out loud”, as it were.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Though the example I am critiquing is specifically a blog post, a lot of the principles here apply equally to other media, including forms as varied as long-form essays, preaching, lecturing, and even writing fiction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id="my-goals"&gt;My Goals&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I meant the story I offered as an illustrative example of a broader point. To wit, I had had a bad customer experience with a given company, and it left a bad taste in my mouth that pushed me away from using that company’s software in the future. The story was meant to illustrate that even a single bad experience with a company can emotionally outweight a lot of positive experience with the company, and that emotions tend to fade slowly over time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id="my-approach"&gt;My Approach&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I approached the piece with a fairly typical rhetorical structure for this kind of thing: introduce a thesis or idea, detour through a specific example to illustrate it, then come back and drive the main point home. This was a good idea, but the execution failed, and it failed for fairly obvious reasons on reflection.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id="the-problems"&gt;The Problems&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first problem was the distribution of the content. The original piece was right around a thousand words long. Of those, some six hundred words were devoted to specific details of my interaction with the company in question. Another hundred words had to do with my follow-up decisions about the products involved. In the whole piece, then, I spent over two thirds of my time talking about the specific example, and only about a third making the actual point I wanted to make. This weighted the content so that the focus was on the details of the story, rather than the bigger picture issue that I walked away with a bad taste in my mouth from my interactions with the company’s customer service representative.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Second, the story itself was &lt;em&gt;far&lt;/em&gt; too specific for my aims. I put in quotes from our email exchange, which entirely distracted from the point I wanted to make. It led readers to see whether they also perceived the emails as I had. While this was helpful for leading me to reevaluate the content of the emails, it also completely undercut the point of the post—a point, I should note, whose validity is entirely independent of the details of the incident I used to illustrate it. When I am illustrating a point, I need to let the illustration do the work of &lt;em&gt;illustrating&lt;/em&gt;, without letting the details of the illustration come to the fore in this way. That means eliding all details but those actually essential to make the point. The story isn’t the point, nor are its details. It is there to serve the end of the thesis, and nothing more. The minute it does more than that, it needs to get out of the way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id="lesson-learned"&gt;Lesson learned&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Those two issues combined to shift the rhetorical effect from what I intended—a general discussion of the need to make sure you treat customers with respect—to something else entirely. Instead of making my point, the example distracted from it. I hope in the future to learn from this by doing two things:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;keeping the emphasis on arguing for the thesis, &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; on an illustration present only to personalize the thesis, especially by keeping the length of the illustration down.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;keeping the details of any illustration used to the minimum essential to make the point at hand (whether illustrating the whole argument or just one part of it).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</summary></entry><entry><title>Let The Peoples Praise You</title><link href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2014/let-the-peoples-praise-you.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-03-31T20:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Chris Krycho</name></author><id>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2014-03-31:2014/let-the-peoples-praise-you.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I read Psalm 67 for my &lt;a href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2014/no-resurrection-no-dice.html"&gt;devotions&lt;/a&gt; today, and was reminded that I had set the text to music several years ago during my studies in music composition at OU. Unfortunately, I have never been able to have the piece performed (even with a piano reduction)—the position of choral director was in transition the semester I composed it, and I simply never got around to it afterward. Nonetheless, I think you may enjoy this digital version. You can, however, &lt;a href="/downloads/psalm-67.pdf"&gt;download the score&lt;/a&gt; so you can follow the text setting if you like.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe style="width: 100%; max-height: 6.556em; padding-top: 1em; padding-bottom: 1em;" scrolling="no" frameborder="no" src="https://w.soundcloud.com/player/?url=https%3A//api.soundcloud.com/tracks/142432628&amp;amp;color=5592c9&amp;amp;auto_play=false&amp;amp;hide_related=false&amp;amp;show_artwork=false"&gt;
&lt;/iframe&gt;
</summary><category term="music"></category></entry><entry><title>The Lamb Rampant</title><link href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2014/the-lamb-rampant.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-02-10T12:30:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Chris Krycho</name></author><id>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2014-02-10:2014/the-lamb-rampant.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Come and rest! Come and heal! Ev’ry traitor&lt;br /&gt;         Ev’ry wretch and stinking fiend: lay down your arms&lt;br /&gt;    Find comfort here, and respite, rest, rapport&lt;br /&gt;         All are welcome here, not one refused, none barred&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She wearied, wounded, sorrowed, battle-sore&lt;br /&gt;         Bids her children yet another weary soul embrace&lt;br /&gt;    Offer care and proffer aid, render service to her foes&lt;br /&gt;         As—though her progeny—once were as they&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Her march to war is ever triumph by defeat&lt;br /&gt;         Her shields and banners ’blazoned not with martial sign&lt;br /&gt;    Not lion proud nor weapons bright; instead a bleeding sheep&lt;br /&gt;         The lamb which piercèd, bruised and bloodied, died&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No stranger, prouder heraldry to march beneath&lt;br /&gt;         But under it she conquers all, so waves she bold&lt;br /&gt;    The lamb rampant! Dancing proud on trampled death&lt;br /&gt;         On mort laid low by low-laid, somehow mortal God&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Come and rest! she calls— Come and heal! Ev’ry traitor&lt;br /&gt;         Ev’ry wretch and stinking fiend: lay down your arms&lt;br /&gt;    Find comfort here, and respite, rest, rapport&lt;br /&gt;         All are welcome here, not one refused, none barred&lt;br /&gt;         Beneath the dancing banner: the piercèd, rampant lamb.&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><category term="poetry"></category></entry></feed>