<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Chris Krycho - automation</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/</link><description></description><lastBuildDate>Fri, 14 Dec 2018 22:15:00 -0500</lastBuildDate><item><title>Hey Siri, Record a Zettel</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2018/hey-siri-record-a-zettel.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.chriskrycho.com/2018/assumed-audiences.html"&gt;Assumed Audience:&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/b&gt; people interested in reading, writing, learning, and research systems—particularly on iOS, and particularly with automation in view.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A few evenings ago, I spent a little while building out some Siri Shortcuts to make the process of building out notes in &lt;a href="https://www.chriskrycho.com/zettelkasten"&gt;my Zettelkasten&lt;/a&gt; on the fly easier. Building them in Bear is easy &lt;em&gt;enough&lt;/em&gt;, but it’s even nicer to just be able to tap a button and have things like the date auto-generated for the note title in exactly the format I want: &lt;code&gt;YYYY.MM.DD.HHMM&lt;/code&gt;, like &lt;code&gt;2018.12.14.2205&lt;/code&gt; for a note created on December 14, 2018, at 10:05 pm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This timestamp format means I can always find notes by when they were written, and it’s easy to sort them by when I created them, which in turn seems the kind of thing that will prove helpful in the long-term, given how much our memories are &lt;em&gt;associative&lt;/em&gt;. (This insight is &lt;a href="https://zettelkasten.de/posts/no-categories/"&gt;not original&lt;/a&gt; by any means, but it’s something I’ve long valued in my &lt;a href="https://www.chriskrycho.com/2018/just-write-down-what-you-do.html"&gt;work&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So having a little tool that handles that part automatically is &lt;em&gt;great&lt;/em&gt;. The other thing that’s nice about using shortcuts is that I can use them in a hands-free context. I can now just say, “Hey Siri, record a new Zettel” and (since Shortcut configurations are shared across my iCloud account), I can do the whole process without typing a thing. Tagging is a bit harder here, but I can do well enough (it helps that I enunciate &lt;em&gt;extremely&lt;/em&gt; clearly).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One thing I wish is that iOS had support for doing these kinds of things when in do-not-disturb mode when driving. That’s the time when my “record a new Zettel” Siri Shortcut would be &lt;em&gt;most&lt;/em&gt; handy, and it’s not available. I’d be perfectly fine with having to come back and do a bit of cleanup later to get it &lt;em&gt;just right&lt;/em&gt;, as long as I could get the thought down somewhere I could come back to it later. You can do things like say “Hey Siri, in Bear, add a note,” and Siri will prompt you for its content—so clearly the functionality is there. SiriKit just needs to better support it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As for these particular shortcuts: I’m still working out the kinks, but for what it’s worth, here are the shortcuts I’ve built so far:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.icloud.com/shortcuts/c2406245de5846bebbda93d798034e25"&gt;Record a New Zettel&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.icloud.com/shortcuts/ae956fdd00454f0d824dd47ea69cecd2"&gt;Write a New Zettel&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.icloud.com/shortcuts/45a7c484309344c9a59e2f3e48a68083"&gt;Quote → Zettel&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m also thinking I’ll end up using the built-in hook Bear has to download a web page, but I haven’t worked that into my flow just yet.&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 14 Dec 2018 22:15:00 -0500</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2018-12-14:/2018/hey-siri-record-a-zettel.html</guid><category>Zettelkasten</category><category>automation</category><category>iOS</category><category>research</category><category>notes</category></item></channel></rss>