<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Chris Krycho</title><link href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/feeds/blog.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://www.chriskrycho.com/</id><updated>2014-05-24T00:07:00-04:00</updated><entry><title>The Long Race</title><link href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2014/the-long-race.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-05-24T00:07:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Chris Krycho</name></author><id>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2014-05-24:2014/the-long-race.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;It has been too long since I have written anything&amp;#8212;too long not for my
audience (small as it is), but for my soul. The last few weeks of class were of
course even busier than the rest of the semester, courtesy of a couple major
assignments I wrapped up and studying for and taking finals, all while doing my
normal work as a software developer on the side. Writing simply fell by the
wayside, alas. Even my devotions posts simply didn&amp;#8217;t happen. And that is all
right; there are seasons for all of these things, and it is not as if I didn&amp;#8217;t
write many thousands of words in late April and early May. They simply were not
&lt;em&gt;blogging&lt;/em&gt;&amp;nbsp;words.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So here I am tonight, writing simply to unwind. I spent much of the day working
on various software projects&amp;#8212;a pattern I expect to carry throughout the
summer. In addition to my regular work for Quest Consultants Inc. back in
Norman, I am picking up various web design and development jobs over the
summer. God has been gracious in answering prayers for opportunities to pick up
extra contracting work, and I have several really excellent opportunities to
supplement my 20 hours a week for Quest with other work. That is nice not only
financially, but also intellectually. The change of pace between different
kinds of work helps me stay fresh on all of them. My own personal &lt;a href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2014/a-little-crazy.html"&gt;side
projects&lt;/a&gt; are coming along slowly, but that is all right. Slow but steady
is the best way to go about those kinds of projects&amp;nbsp;anyway.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That lesson is one I have learned more and more from my ongoing and
ever-increasing delight in running. So far in May I have run about 125 miles; I
expect to run over 150 miles this month in total (though of course all such
plans are always subject to revision, and never more so than when one&amp;#8217;s wife is
37 weeks pregnant). I am now running easy, aerobic miles ten to fifteen seconds
faster per mile than I could manage in my personal best half marathon time a
few years ago. I run so (relatively) quickly now not because of any particular
innate athleticism&amp;#8212;quite the contrary, as anyone who has known me since high
school can attest. I can run as far and fast as I do only because I have stuck
with it and used a &lt;a href="http://markallenonline.com/maoArticles.aspx?AID=2" title="Working Your Heart"&gt;smart training plan&lt;/a&gt;. And really, as in most
parts of life, it is that sticking-with-it that leads to getting somewhere. Of
course, sticking with it is no guarantee that things will work out. It is
usually a requisite step along the way, though&amp;#8212;a
necessary-though-insufficient condition. That is simply the way God built the&amp;nbsp;world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Little Ellie is quickly wrapping up her second year of life in this big world.
She is saying lots of words (at last!), whining until she has driven Jaimie a
bit crazy (in too-typical toddler fashion), and growing up in big ways and
small. We are having a great deal of fun watching her start to be more socially
aware and active, even if it is a little strange to have a daughter old enough
that she has friends whom she loves and who love her in turn. She has also
discovered a deep love of &lt;em&gt;Star Wars&lt;/em&gt;&amp;#8212;no surprise for a daughter of ours,
though the intensity of her delight in the movies, for a girl who is not yet
two years old, did surprise both Jaimie and me a bit. You should hear her try
to say &amp;#8220;Darth Vader&amp;#8221; or &amp;#8220;Dark Side&amp;#8221; or &amp;#8220;Star Wars.&amp;#8221; It is impossibly&amp;nbsp;adorable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jaimie is, as noted above, some 37 weeks pregnant and quite ready to be done
carrying our second little gal on the inside. She is still plugging away slowly
at the &lt;a href="http://jaimiekrycho.com/shaking-epheria-pt-1/" title="Bloodlines: The Shaking of Epheria, Part I"&gt;second novella&lt;/a&gt; in her &lt;a href="http://www.amazon.com/Bloodlines-Epheria-The-Trilogy-ebook/dp/B00HY478QO/" title="Get Bloodlines of Epheria on Kindle!"&gt;Bloodlines&lt;/a&gt; fantasy trilogy.
She manages to keep Ellie entertained&amp;#8212;no small feat&amp;#8212;and does a remarkable
job taking care of things around the house so that I can focus on work and
school. Her struggle with &lt;a href="http://2012-2013.chriskrycho.com/theology/marriage-depression/" title="Marriage and Depression"&gt;depression&lt;/a&gt; has not diminished, but
God has given us grace to carry on and she and I have both learned to respond
in better, healthier, more helpful ways when the slumps&amp;nbsp;come.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As for the future, we really have no idea what the next several yeras will
hold. I plan to finish my Master of Divinity&amp;#8212;Lord willing, around December
2016. In the meantime, we will keep raising our little girls, I will keep
writing software, and we will keep exploring and seeing what we want to do and
how best to pursue those desires in a way that honors God. Who knows what those
years will hold? God only, and certainly not&amp;nbsp;us.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="software development"></category><category term="family"></category><category term="fitness"></category></entry><entry><title>Spinning!</title><link href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2014/spinning.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-03-20T19:10:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Chris Krycho</name></author><id>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2014-03-20:2014/spinning.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;As she so often does, Ellie simply delighted me tonight, in two wonderful&amp;nbsp;moments:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;As I was cleaning up the dishes and playing Max Richter&amp;#8217;s &lt;a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/album/memoryhouse/id545010150"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Memoryhouse&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; album, I saw Ellie dancing, and encouraged her to keep going. After a moment, I looked over to see her spinning in circles. And spinning in circles. And spinning in circles. When she finally stopped, she started freaking out as she couldn&amp;#8217;t get her balance. I swooped in and picked her up, laughing with her once she&amp;nbsp;recovered.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;After she calmed down, she started tugging on my shirt. It took me a few seconds to realize what she wanted, but then it clicked: she was trying to turn me by twisting my shirt. &amp;#8220;You want to spin?&amp;#8221; I asked her. She nodded vigorously. &amp;#8220;Is this a spinning song?&amp;#8221; Again, the vigorous nod. So I started spinning around and around with her in my arms, and the sheer joy in the grin plastered across her face was something to behold. We spun first one way, then the other, all the way through &lt;a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=BfoSv8iWA_I"&gt;&amp;#8220;The Twins (Prague)&amp;#8221;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moments like these are worth&amp;nbsp;remembering.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="family"></category><category term="Ellie"></category></entry><entry><title>On Days Off</title><link href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2014/on-days-off.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-02-23T10:30:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Chris Krycho</name></author><id>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2014-02-23:2014/on-days-off.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;These past few days I have completely missed my normal writing times&amp;#8212;no
devotions, and certainly not the other few pieces I had been planning to write.
This was disappointing: I have enjoyed the habit of writing regularly, and I
intend to keep it up. As I have often noted in the past (in more blog posts on
previous versions of the site than I can count, still less dig up at the
moment), writing serves to focus my thoughts as little else does. Moreover,
though my &lt;a href="/devotions"&gt;#devotions&lt;/a&gt; posts are not especially excellent as
writing goes, the discipline of writing is like many other things: sometimes it
matters most that you &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt; it more than the doing of it be particularly&amp;nbsp;magnificent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most of my running is this way. The vast majority of my runs are entirely
unexceptional and become notable only in their consistency. They are not tiring
and not particularly fast&amp;#8212;for me, at least! This is an important
qualification, I recognize, though one that is nonetheless closely tied to the
very ordinary nature of these runs. They become interesting, and are effective,
only in the aggregate. My entire training plan is built on going slowly and
training the &amp;#8220;easy&amp;#8221; side of my physiological response to running. The effect
over time is extraordinary, though: my easy runs with a toddler in a stroller
today are faster than my best runs alone were a few years&amp;nbsp;ago.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My hope for this year is to do something the same with my writing. I do not
expect that the majority of my words will be particularly elegant or well-put-
together. I expect most of my posts to go largely unread and unnoticed, and that
is perfectly fine with me&amp;#8212;indeed, &lt;em&gt;more&lt;/em&gt; than fine, because I am writing them
first of all as a double act of self-discipline. From those devotional posts I
hope to gain not an audience but the benefit of thoughtful reflection the
Scriptures I read and the helpful effect of regular writing on my &lt;em&gt;other&lt;/em&gt;&amp;nbsp;writing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So when, as in the last few days, I simply cannot get to that writing because
other things intrude, I have a double response. First, I recognize that this is
totally all right, under the circumstances. Jaimie and I have been spending time
with friends and each other, and my normal writing times in the evenings have
simply been elided by those other activities. Second, though, I recognize that
such things are likely to come up often, and as such am motivated to commit once
again to doing this writing in the mornings as much as&amp;nbsp;possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For several weeks in the beginning of the semester this spring, I was able to
get up, do my reading, and do my writing before I went to class at 8am. A few
weeks ago, Jaimie&amp;#8217;s grandmother passed away and we flew her out for the funeral,
and that weekend completely tossed my habits and schedule out of alignment.
Instead of my two normally scheduled tasks for the weekend (school and work), I
had three&amp;#8212;and one of them in the form of a teething toddler. The other two
slipped. I have only just finally caught up, and as such I am hoping that in the
week ahead I shall be able to resume my previously very effective habits of
doing all these things to &lt;em&gt;start&lt;/em&gt; the day rather than to finish&amp;nbsp;them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That, of course, assumes I get over this blasted cold that I seem to have caught
last night&amp;#8230; Life is a funny thing,&amp;nbsp;sometimes.&lt;/p&gt;</summary></entry><entry><title>Hey, Look—A Podcast!</title><link href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2014/hey-look-a-podcast.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-01-28T20:20:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Chris Krycho</name></author><id>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2014-01-28:2014/hey-look-a-podcast.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Today, I was happy to be able to finally go public with a project on which I
have been working for the last couple months (and for which I have been planning
since mid-fall): &lt;a href="http://www.winningslowly.org/"&gt;Winning Slowly&lt;/a&gt;. Winning Slowly is a biweeklypodcast by
yours truly and my good friend &lt;a href="http://stephencarradini.com"&gt;Stephen Carradini&lt;/a&gt; offering thoughtful
commentary on trends in culture, technology, religion, ethics, and&amp;nbsp;art.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of possible interest to my&amp;nbsp;readers:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You can listen to the first episode, &lt;a href="http://www.winningslowly.org/2014/01/we-need-some-context/"&gt;We Need Some&amp;nbsp;Context!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You can &lt;a href="http://www.winningslowly.org/feed.xml"&gt;subscribe to the feed&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You can follow and get updates via all sorts of social networks:&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Twitter: &lt;a href="https://twitter.som/winningslowly"&gt;@winningslowly&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;App.net: &lt;a href="http://app.net/winningslowly"&gt;@winningslowly&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://broadcast.app.net/40022/winning-slowly-episodes/"&gt;App.net broadcast&lt;/a&gt; &amp;#8211; notifications on your phone or emails as
  you&amp;nbsp;like&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://plus.google.com/u/0/+WinningslowlyOrgCast/"&gt;Google+&lt;/a&gt; (yes, shockingly&amp;nbsp;enough)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We&amp;#8217;re still very much in a &amp;#8220;beta&amp;#8221; phase. The audio quality needs significant
improvement, our back-and-forth needs to get smoother (and, at times, more back-
and-forth!), and so on. We&amp;#8217;d love to hear your feedback. But be&amp;nbsp;gentle.&lt;/p&gt;</summary></entry><entry><title>A Note to RSS Subscribers</title><link href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2014/a-note-to-rss-subscribers.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-01-05T09:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Chris Krycho</name></author><id>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2014-01-05:2014/a-note-to-rss-subscribers.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;A note to anyone who has subscribed to this &lt;span class="caps"&gt;RSS&lt;/span&gt; feed: you should resubscribe by
adding &lt;a href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/feed.xml"&gt;http://www.chriskrycho.com/feed.xml&lt;/a&gt; to your reader, as this feed
location is now defunct.&amp;nbsp;Thanks!&lt;/p&gt;</summary></entry></feed>