<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Chris Krycho - blogging</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/</link><description></description><lastBuildDate>Wed, 26 Sep 2018 20:15:00 -0400</lastBuildDate><item><title>Can’t Stop, Won’t Stop</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2018/cant-stop-wont-stop.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;A couple things have had me thinking about blogging today. I happened to end up reading &lt;a href="http://christineyen.com/2014/01/in-2014-reflection-consistency-and-balls/"&gt;this post by Christine Yen from 2014&lt;/a&gt; just a few hours after listening to &lt;a href="https://craigmod.com/onmargins/005/"&gt;Craig Mod’s interview with Jason Kottke&lt;/a&gt;. They have two very different takes on blogging. Yen’s piece has the sense so often echoed online: “I want to be blogging more.” Mod’s interview with Kottke notes how remarkable a 20-year-old website with daily blog-like entries throughout is, and Kottke emphasizes how he loves the work (and it is work!) that he does to keep it up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My relationship with blogging is somewhere nearer Kottke than Yen on that spectrum. While I have &lt;em&gt;occasionally&lt;/em&gt; resolved to blog more—and occasionally to &lt;a href="https://www.chriskrycho.com/2018/writing-plans-for-the-rest-of-2018.html"&gt;blog &lt;em&gt;less&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;!—I find that mostly my problem is that I cannot stop blogging even if I want to.&lt;a href="#fn1" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref1" role="doc-noteref"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the things that’s strange about &lt;a href="https://www.chriskrycho.com/burnout"&gt;burnout&lt;/a&gt; is that what constitutes &lt;em&gt;rest&lt;/em&gt; from the stressors will vary from person to person. Writing, for may people, might be a source of tension or stress. The perceived &lt;em&gt;obligation&lt;/em&gt; to generate content can be stressful.&lt;a href="#fn2" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref2" role="doc-noteref"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; But far more often, writing is restful for me. It is a way of &lt;a href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2018/blog-as-note-taking-tool.html"&gt;organizing my mental life&lt;/a&gt;—publicly, but (at least) as much for my own benefit as for that of potential readers—and organizing my mental life is somehow a good form of stress relief.&lt;a href="#fn3" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref3" role="doc-noteref"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; So it turns out that blogging—not on a schedule, not on a deadline, but whenever I feel like it (and that is obviously a lot)—is good for me in the midst of this. It seems to go in the same basic bucket as running.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So: my aim back in May, just before I realized what exactly I’m dealing with in burnout, to blog less in the interest of getting &lt;em&gt;other&lt;/em&gt; projects done? When I said this?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don’t think I could stop myself from blogging that way from time to time if I &lt;em&gt;wanted&lt;/em&gt; to. But it won’t be the focus, and if things are relatively quiet around here for much of the rest of the year, don’t worry… you know why!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, at this point I’ve let that go. Subconsciously at first. Now consciously. I wasn’t wrong when I said couldn’t stop myself from writing &lt;em&gt;entirely&lt;/em&gt;. Now I just know that I also &lt;em&gt;mostly shouldn’t.&lt;/em&gt; There may be points on other writing projects in the future, times when I’m not dealing with not-so-mild-anymore burnout, when I can and should. But not now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn1" role="doc-endnote"&gt;&lt;p&gt;In truth, as this blog post suggests, I cannot even stop blogging about blogging! I’ve been metablogging for over a decade now; don’t expect it to stop anytime soon!&lt;a href="#fnref1" class="footnote-back" role="doc-backlink"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn2" role="doc-endnote"&gt;&lt;p&gt;More than one thoughtful listener to my &lt;a href="https://newrustacean.com/show_notes/bonus/burnout/"&gt;most recent New Rustacean episode&lt;/a&gt; responded along these very lines; and it’s a point I haven’t made here before, so: consider it raised.&lt;a href="#fnref2" class="footnote-back" role="doc-backlink"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn3" role="doc-endnote"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Interpret that as you will. I have given it no small amount of thought myself. As I noted on the aforementioned latest New Rustacean episode: I am hypermetacognitive, and my incessant metacogitating is a source of alternating bemusement and frustration for my poor wife.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yes. I said “incessant metacogitating.” This is what poor Jaimie has to put up with.&lt;a href="#fnref3" class="footnote-back" role="doc-backlink"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 26 Sep 2018 20:15:00 -0400</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2018-09-26:/2018/cant-stop-wont-stop.html</guid><category>writing</category><category>blogging</category><category>burnout</category></item><item><title>Once More Around The Wheel</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2018/once-more-around-the-wheel.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;I very much wish my publishing needs were not so… complicated. Academic writing—though that’s done for a while—poetry, code, and a strong preference for semantic HTML to be generated by it along with an equally strong preference for plain text authoring…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nothing works for me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The only Markdown parser out there which does the right thing with all of those is &lt;a href="http://pandoc.org"&gt;Pandoc&lt;/a&gt;. The options for using Pandoc directly are not great. Shelling out to it via &lt;a href="https://getpelican.com"&gt;Pelican&lt;/a&gt; (my current strategy) works but is &lt;em&gt;slow&lt;/em&gt;. The implemented-in-Rust &lt;a href="https://www.getgutenberg.io"&gt;Gutenberg&lt;/a&gt; generator looks like &lt;em&gt;exactly&lt;/em&gt; what I want performance-wise, but its &lt;a href="https://github.com/google/pulldown-cmark" title="pulldown-cmark"&gt;underlying Markdown engine&lt;/a&gt; doesn’t support citations &lt;em&gt;or&lt;/em&gt; poetry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I keep coming back to the conclusion that I’m basically going to have to build whatever I want myself, if I want my desired publishing flow to exist. I don’t really &lt;em&gt;want&lt;/em&gt; to do that, though. It’s a boatload of work, even “just”—just!—to do something like (a) learn Haskell well enough to build on top of Pandoc directly or (b) build a good C-based API wrapper in Rust so that I can do it &lt;em&gt;that&lt;/em&gt; way or (c) extend &lt;a href="https://github.com/google/pulldown-cmark"&gt;pulldown-cmark&lt;/a&gt; to support poetry and citation management.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For lots of reasons (c) is probably what I’ll ultimately end up doing; I want that for more than just blogging. More on that eventually, I hope.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But in the meantime I really just… want someone else to have the same weird needs I do and build this for me. I just know full well at this point that that’s not going to happen, and accordingly am basically resigned to muddling along with Pelican and Pandoc until such a time as I can actually buckle down and build what I want and need.&lt;a href="#fn1" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref1" role="doc-noteref"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;em&gt;C’est la vie.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn1" role="doc-endnote"&gt;&lt;p&gt;As an aside: the prospect of buckling down and building things like that in my spare time is &lt;em&gt;much&lt;/em&gt; less appealing given my current &lt;a href="https://www.chriskrycho.com/burnout/"&gt;struggles with burnout&lt;/a&gt;, and as I’ll write about at some point in the future I feel a (perhaps-surprising to you, my reader) lack of confidence about my &lt;em&gt;ability&lt;/em&gt; to accomplish those things.&lt;a href="#fnref1" class="footnote-back" role="doc-backlink"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 31 Aug 2018 18:30:00 -0400</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2018-08-31:/2018/once-more-around-the-wheel.html</guid><category>writing</category><category>blogging</category><category>static site generators</category></item><item><title>Give Me Chronological Archives or Go Away</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2018/give-me-chronological-archives-or-go-away.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;I was looking at the (really excellent) content in Vaidehi Joshi’s &lt;a href="https://medium.com/basecs"&gt;basecs&lt;/a&gt; series, and it crystallized something for me: Algorithmically-sorted archives for blogs are hyper-user-hostile and I &lt;em&gt;hate&lt;/em&gt; them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Trying to just work through that series in chronological order of publication is &lt;em&gt;nearly&lt;/em&gt;—not quite &lt;em&gt;actually&lt;/em&gt;, but &lt;em&gt;nearly&lt;/em&gt;—impossible. Never mind that the series is a &lt;em&gt;series&lt;/em&gt;, and that most posts build on earlier posts, Medium wants to &lt;em&gt;foster engagement&lt;/em&gt; and tell you what other people have read most.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It keeps up this nonsense even when you pull the the Archive view: it displays the top 10 posts from 2017, sorted by which ones people read most. There’s no view of &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; the posts in the series, simply sorted by date, period. You can sort those top 10 posts by date, but to get to the series in chronological sequence, you have to click into each month… and then click the button &lt;em&gt;again&lt;/em&gt; to sort by date &lt;em&gt;for every single month&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This absurd focus on algorithmic sorting is an abomination—a desecration of all that is good and noble and beautiful about the format of the blog. It should die an ignominious death, unmourned by anyone but Silicon Valley venture capitalists thinking to make a quick buck on other people’s publishing efforts.&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 25 Aug 2018 12:15:00 -0400</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2018-08-25:/2018/give-me-chronological-archives-or-go-away.html</guid><category>writing</category><category>blogging</category><category>publishing</category><category>medium</category></item><item><title>Blog as Note-Taking Tool</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2018/blog-as-note-taking-tool.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;I have a habit that might not make sense to you. I reread my own blog posts fairly regularly. It’s not vanity—not some weird obsession with my own awesomeness in the form of my own writing or some such nonsense. It’s that in my blog posts over the last decade, I have a pretty serious backlog of &lt;em&gt;what I was thinking about at any given point in time.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s not exhaustive, by a long shot. It only includes things I actually decided to publish.&lt;a href="#fn1" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref1" role="doc-noteref"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; There are, sadly, not many short thoughts in the mix. Nor is it well-tagged or organized in any internally-consistent way—even in any single version of the site, much less across versions. But nonetheless the history is still there, and I &lt;em&gt;can&lt;/em&gt; traverse the various lines through it, such as they are. (Sometimes, even, the changes in organization and structure are illuminating about how I was thinking about things at the time!) In any case, my habit of linking to previous references to ideas has proven invaluable for the times when I want to trawl back through old posts and consider those old thoughts again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reading old blog posts is a strange experience, of course. The person who wrote these things was recognizably myself; but I am not who I then I was, and I sometimes disagree with myself on the substance and often on the style. (I occasionally find an old gem and wonder how I ever managed to write so well.) That very strangeness, it turns out, is why I do this every so often, though. Thinking well is often a matter of forging connections between ideas that were previously not connected for us. We cannot consciously hold in our minds even a fraction of all the things we have thought about or even written something about over the years. We can, however, jog our memories, and let new connections form. And rereading one’s own blog post is a great way to do that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’d not heard specifically of the &lt;a href="https://zettelkasten.de"&gt;Zettelkasten method&lt;/a&gt; until Alan Jacobs linked it a while back, but it fits this model pretty perfectly, and maps as well to ways I’ve been &lt;em&gt;trying&lt;/em&gt; to structure my note-taking and thinking for the past few years. (I’m going to be consciously doing more of this in &lt;a href="http://www.bear-writer.com"&gt;Bear&lt;/a&gt;, my current notes app of choice. I’ll probably write up my experience that way once I’ve actually had some experience!) But this also ties into some of the things Jacobs has been &lt;a href="https://blog.ayjay.org/the-blog-garden/" title="The Blog Garden"&gt;musing out loud&lt;/a&gt; about in his own blog over the last week. It’s not just that a blog can serve as a place to do some of the fleshing-out of ideas. It’s not just that a blog can be a record of the development of ideas. It can also serve to jog new ideas if you read yourself again, displaced (both literally and temporally) from the original writing of the thing. A blog is kind of like a public notebook, and while it &lt;em&gt;may&lt;/em&gt; be useful for others to browse through it, is &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; useful for me to browse back through it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn1" role="doc-endnote"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Though: if you look at the archives, especially including those on my &lt;a href="http://blog.chriskrycho.com" title="Thoughts; A Flame"&gt;first real blog&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="http://2012-2013.chriskrycho.com"&gt;the previous iteration of this site&lt;/a&gt;, you’ll notice that I published a lot of posts about a lot of subjects, whether my thoughts were especially well-formed or not.&lt;a href="#fnref1" class="footnote-back" role="doc-backlink"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 16 Jul 2018 07:00:00 -0400</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2018-07-16:/2018/blog-as-note-taking-tool.html</guid><category>Zettelkasten</category><category>notes</category><category>memory</category><category>writing</category><category>blogging</category></item><item><title>Continuing to Reflect on My Internet Presence</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2018/continuing-to-reflect-on-my-internet-presence.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;i class="editorial"&gt;A quick note: I drafted this back in June, but forgot to actually publish it!&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I find that I’m always reflecting on the shape I want my internet presence to take. Over the last month, in particular, I’ve been thinking about the kind of “link-blogging” and commentary-on-articles-I’ve-read that I’ve experimented with pushing into Pinboard for the last &lt;a href="https://www.chriskrycho.com/2017/pick-the-right-tool-for-the-job.html"&gt;year and some change&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the one hand, I’ve found that Pinboard is &lt;em&gt;great&lt;/em&gt; for two things:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;having an easy place to look up articles I’ve read but can’t necessarily remember the name of off the top of my head&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;being &lt;em&gt;a&lt;/em&gt; place with its own &lt;abbr&gt;RSS&lt;/abbr&gt; feed of that content, which is social-network-like in some ways but using open web tech like &lt;abbr&gt;RSS&lt;/abbr&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But what it isn’t is &lt;em&gt;integrated with my own site&lt;/em&gt;, or particularly easily discoverable &lt;em&gt;from&lt;/em&gt; my site. Adding a link to my public Pinboard feed would help, perhaps, but you wouldn’t know what I use it &lt;em&gt;for&lt;/em&gt; from seeing that link.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The thing is, I want this material here on this site. There remain two blockers to me there:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;ease of publishing&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;site design and structure&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the most part, I am happy enough with a static site generator setup. However, for this specific kind of use, I wish for a web front-end to my website (or, honestly, an easy way to integrate &lt;a href="https://www.ulyssesapp.com"&gt;Ulysses&lt;/a&gt; with it). The options which exist in that general space—WordPress and Ghost—both have their upsides, but also a great many downsides, and I find that I have no interest in using either.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You might find that an odd commitment; here’s an aside on why.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our &lt;a href="https://krycho.com"&gt;family blog&lt;/a&gt; is a Ghost install, and the previous iteration of this site ran on WordPress. Ghost is &lt;em&gt;fine&lt;/em&gt;, and for many setups it’s actually really good. For my fairly complex set of publishing requirements, it unfortunately doesn’t really do the trick. Some of those requirements (like integration with citation-management tooling) are &lt;em&gt;currently&lt;/em&gt; less pressing, but I don’t count on that being the case in the long term.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That said, one possible alternative here is simply to cross that bridge if or when I come to it and lean on the somewhat simpler tools that &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt; meet my needs for today. If I did that, it would certainly be with Ghost, because WordPress feels to me the same way Windows feels to me: technically very competent, but impossibly frustrating to use. (That’s not insulting either of the two; it’s a statement of my very—overly, perhaps!—specific aesthetic tastes and my corresponding—admittedly irrational!—response to the experience of using Windows or WordPress. Maybe it’s just the ‘W’s that start the names?)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is one reason I’ve seriously considered figuring out how to make my &lt;a href="https://github.com/chriskrycho/lightning-rs"&gt;long-on-hold site generator&lt;/a&gt; actually be a hybrid: never dynamically generating content, but with an &lt;abbr&gt;API&lt;/abbr&gt; to enable programmatic access, so that I &lt;em&gt;can&lt;/em&gt; put a web or app front end on it. (Existing solutions in that space, like &lt;a href="https://www.netlifycms.org"&gt;Netlify CMS&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href="https://forestry.io/"&gt;forestry.io&lt;/a&gt;, are really good, but don’t quite support everything I have historically committed to needing. They also don’t have anything like an iOS share sheet!)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The problem, of course, is that I’m not yet ready to spend my limited time building out my long-planned and long-delayed personal website generator tool. In short, I’m caught in a catch-22 of my own making.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In any case, I want to figure out a flow for sharing those kinds of notes-on-articles that works better for getting it onto my blog, rather than caught in the mostly-invisible space that is my Pinboard. I need a refreshed site design to support it effectively. I need different &lt;em&gt;tools&lt;/em&gt; to support that flow effectively. Which means I’m not going to end up doing it tomorrow or anything.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ll get to it eventually. Maybe. Hopefully. And in the meantime I’ll do one extra step when I see something worth linking, and copy it into a Ulysses document that I can publish shortly thereafter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is where every nerd ends up with their blogging software, I think: in a pit of good-enough-to-get-by but not-actually-satisfying. (But I’m not helping myself with how persnickety I am about these things.)&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 25 Jun 2018 06:15:00 -0400</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2018-06-25:/2018/continuing-to-reflect-on-my-internet-presence.html</guid><category>pinboard</category><category>writing</category><category>blogging</category></item></channel></rss>