<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Chris Krycho</title><link href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/feeds/blog.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://www.chriskrycho.com/</id><updated>2015-08-13T09:00:00-04:00</updated><entry><title>My dream of dreams</title><link href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2015/my-dream-of-dreams.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-08-13T09:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Chris Krycho</name></author><id>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2015-08-13:2015/my-dream-of-dreams.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Yes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my dream of dreams, Trump actually runs third party, which emboldens Bernie Sanders (should he not get the nom–whoa, Sanders vs. Trump would be the greatest political race &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;OF ALL TIME&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;) to also run third-party, since all of them have viable “cores,” and we get a four-party race that spawns four actual parties and American politics is freed from its bipartisan lock and a bald eagle screams across the sky while Stephen Colbert tears his shirt and flexes his muscles and fireworks explode in the shape of America over his head.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;div class="references"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
</summary><category term="quotes"></category></entry><entry><title>Faithfulness</title><link href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2015/faithfulness.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-06-18T17:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Chris Krycho</name></author><id>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2015-06-18:2015/faithfulness.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;It’s been a lot more than a month since the promised monthly update. I’ll blame it on a lack of self-discipline… or perhaps on the presence thereof.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Every day, we face choices about where to spend our time. In this particular season of life, that has often meant not writing, even things I &lt;em&gt;want&lt;/em&gt; to write. I have a family to care for, a church to serve, work to do, and schoolwork to accomplish. Family is a daily endeavor, work and school nearly so, and church regular if not quite daily. In the midst of that, I have to decide: &lt;em&gt;What will I do today?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our culture tends to put the question in terms of balance; my friend and pastor Ashok Nachnani suggested to me a while back that it is better to think in terms of &lt;em&gt;faithfulness&lt;/em&gt;. “Balance” suggests holding all these things in equal proportion, juggling them against each other. “Faithfulness” suggests fulfilling the responsibilities as best we can, with the time we are given. The actual day-to-day outcome may not look particularly different, but it is an important shift in the way we think nonetheless. To be faithful may mean letting some desireable things go, and it may mean doing some things in a different way or to a lesser degree than we might like.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Writing, for example.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I &lt;em&gt;love&lt;/em&gt; writing. I like keeping a public record for my friends and family to see how my life is. I enjoy stretching my mental muscles in the way that writing requires. I enjoy thinking through pen or keyboard. But faithfulness to the responsibilities God has given me right now means &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; trying to balance those desires against each other, and instead doing what is best for my family and my church. For the most part, right now that means not writing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I put it to Jaimie a while back, at this point in life I have time for one hobby—and only one. That hobby, at this point, is fitness. I run half marathons, and now I do triathlons (first one coming up in 10 days!). That takes up a non-trivial amount of time every week. It helps me in the other areas of my life, to be sure: it helps me be less physically tired, improves my focus in school and work, and serves to maintain my health. Nonetheless, it is hobby-like and it takes a substantial amount of time every day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So right now, I write a great deal less than I want, and a great deal less than I did in college or early in our marriage. I miss the days when I had time to work on poetry for hours at a stretch, or simply to muse for a few thousand words. But it is far more important for me to spend time with Ellie and Kate than it is to write poetry, or to compose music, right now. Lord willing, I have 55–60 years ahead of me. Of those years, they will be close only another 15–20, and they will be the age they are today &lt;em&gt;only for today&lt;/em&gt;. As much as writing and composing and hobby programming all look appealing to me, and as much as those really are good expressions of the ways God has gifted me, focusing on them would not be the most &lt;em&gt;faithful&lt;/em&gt; use of my time—not today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is not to say that writing and composing and developing interesting software are not important. Rather: they &lt;em&gt;are&lt;/em&gt; good and valuable things. But they are things to focus on at other times in life. As fast as this life goes, and I am increasingly aware that it goes quickly indeed, I can expect in the ordinary course of things to have &lt;em&gt;many&lt;/em&gt; years available for those things. I can exercise my gifts faithfully in the right time and season. Today, I can learn to love my little girls well, invest deeply in their lives, and savor moments that will never come back.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most of all, I must remind myself that teaching and shaping them is easily the most significant thing I will ever do. Should I write an essay that persuaded a thousand people to change their views on the arts, or to adopt a better view of the church, still my impact on two little lives would be more important. If I can point them faithfully to Christ and help them learn to walk faithfully with him as healthy members of his body, that will be a good life to have lived. Everything else is icing on the cake.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Icing is good, for the record. Sometimes, in these sorts of posts, we can mistake &lt;em&gt;relative importance&lt;/em&gt; for &lt;em&gt;absolute importance&lt;/em&gt;. I should, at various times in my life, make sure to exercise the good gifts God has given me in ways appropriate to that time and context. Right now, that means continuing to write, but less frequently. In the future, it will mean something else.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And all of this must stand in the context of resurrection hope. Too often, I live—too often, we &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; live—as though the next 60 years are all we may expect, the only time for writing and composing and so on. But it is not. I look forward to endless ages of creativity, exercising those gifts &lt;em&gt;more&lt;/em&gt; fully than I am able now. So: Lord Jesus, come soon. And in the meantime, may I be faithful in each season to do as well as I can.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="references"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
</summary><category term="family"></category><category term="writing"></category></entry><entry><title>These Are My People</title><link href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2015/these-are-my-people.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-05-17T22:25:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Chris Krycho</name></author><id>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2015-05-17:2015/these-are-my-people.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;At the end of April, I flew out to Seattle to &lt;a href="//www.chriskrycho.com/2015/tolle-lege.html"&gt;give a talk&lt;/a&gt; at &lt;a href="//bibletechconference.com"&gt;BibleTech&lt;/a&gt;, a conference hosted by Faithlife (the company that owns Logos Bible Software). What I found was not only a bunch of interesting content—though there was certainly plenty of that, and props to the Logos/Faithlife people for putting on a great event—but also an awful lot of people &lt;em&gt;a lot like me&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Those of you who know me well know this is rare. Finding people who share &lt;em&gt;one&lt;/em&gt; of my primary interests &lt;em&gt;and approach it the same way I do&lt;/em&gt; is relatively rare. Finding people who share an interest is not especially hard, but that qualification is extraordinarily important: I know lots of people interested in programming, and lots of people interested in theology, and not many at all who approach either the same way I do. Finding people who are interested in both software &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; theology (still less also music and linguistics and so on) has been so rare as to be a point of quiet but significant and ongoing frustration in my life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And then I went to BibleTech, and met a lot of amazing people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was reflecting on the experience today—thinking about why I’ve so deeply enjoyed not only the conference itself but &lt;a href="//bibletechnology-slack.herokuapp.com/"&gt;the community&lt;/a&gt; that has sprung out of it—I realized: &lt;em&gt;These are my people.&lt;/em&gt; They share a passion for software development, theology, linguistics, and in many cases even music. There may not be many of us in the world, but a substantial number were assembled in Seattle April 30–May 1, 2015. That’s no small thing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have no idea what the future holds for me—whether it will continue to include writing software for the Bible specifically or not—but I &lt;em&gt;can&lt;/em&gt; say that this phase of my life has been enormously beneficial in this one way if in no others. It is nice to find kindred spirits in the world, and to know that, even if I am pretty strange, there are other strange people out there, too, and that we can keep working in our strange ways to make the Word of God more available and more useful to people every day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Good work, BibleTech.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="references"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
</summary><category term="software development"></category><category term="joy"></category></entry><entry><title>The Brutality of Police Culture in Baltimore</title><link href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2015/the-brutality-of-police-culture-in-baltimore.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-04-28T18:20:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Chris Krycho</name></author><id>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2015-04-28:2015/the-brutality-of-police-culture-in-baltimore.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;When the police beat an 87-year-old grandmother who called 911 to get medical help for her grandson who had been shot—just because they don’t believe her—and suffer no consequences for it, the “law” as such has become wicked. This doesn’t excuse riots, but it sure as heck &lt;em&gt;explains&lt;/em&gt; them. Baltimore is broken, but primarily in a massive system of abuse. Yes, pray for peace. But remember that civic peace comes in large part through civic &lt;em&gt;justice&lt;/em&gt;; rule of law follows the law ruling justly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Connor Friedersdorf has a lot more; &lt;a href="http://www.theatlantic.com/politics/archive/2015/04/the-brutality-of-police-culture-in-baltimore/391158/"&gt;you need to read it&lt;/a&gt;, even though—or rather, precisely because—it is such a mess.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="references"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
</summary><category term="links"></category></entry><entry><title>Small Caps and Margins</title><link href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2015/small-caps-and-margins.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-03-13T23:30:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Chris Krycho</name></author><id>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2015-03-13:2015/small-caps-and-margins.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;In addition to the various other issues I tackled in the &lt;a href="http://mereorthodoxy.com/speak-truth-beauty-review-echoes-eden/"&gt;review&lt;/a&gt; I published at Mere O a few weeks ago, there was one other secondary but to my mind non-trivial issue with Barrs’ &lt;em&gt;Echoes of Eden&lt;/em&gt;. I left it aside because it certainly wasn’t Barrs’ fault, and would have seemed absurdly nitpicky to my audience there. But it bears comment nonetheless.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The small caps! The divine name appeared in a number of places throughout the books, as &lt;span class="smcp"&gt;Lord&lt;/span&gt; (just as it does in the Bible). Unfortunately, Crossway chose to use a Palatino variant without real &lt;a href="http://ilovetypography.com/2008/02/20/small-caps/"&gt;small capitals&lt;/a&gt;. Yes, I know: it’s a little detail, and in the grand scheme of things it isn’t &lt;em&gt;that&lt;/em&gt; important. But it’s the little details like that which add up to the difference between a so-so printing of a book and a truly delightful printing of a book. They make a big difference in the experience of reading the book (albeit usually a subconscious one, unless like me you are a typography nerd). I think that a book on the arts, of all books, should have really delightful typesetting. (Honestly, &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; books should have good typesetting, but the lack is even less excusable when the book is about beauty!)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today I started reading Bruce Ashford’s new book, &lt;em&gt;Every Square Inch&lt;/em&gt;. Five pages in, I’m enjoying his writing so far, but two things are making it a less-than-delightful experience. One is the typeface—the same custom serif used in Logos. It is functional, but there are many irritating details about it. Above all, it screams that it was designed for screens and has not been adjusted for use in print. The other major issue is the page margins. The inner margins are perfectly respectable; the outer margins are so narrow that my much-less-typographically-obsessive wife &lt;em&gt;also&lt;/em&gt; immediately noted and commented on them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These things matter. The old patterns of book-printing—careful designs of everything from leading to line length to the size of margins—were patterns for a reason. In the new digital-everything era, too many of these lessons have been forgotten or ignored by startup presses, and it’s making everyone’s reading experience unnecessarily worse. Typography is a skill and an art that can make an &lt;em&gt;enormous&lt;/em&gt; difference in the experience of reading a book; it is one we need publishers like Lexham Press and Crossway to reappropriate.&lt;a href="#fn1" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref1"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rant over. But please, publishers: work to make your typography &lt;em&gt;excellent&lt;/em&gt;, not just passable. Pay attention to your margins and your small capitals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="references"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;section class="footnotes"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn1"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Crossway I &lt;em&gt;know&lt;/em&gt; can do it, because their ESV line includes some of the best Bible typesetting done by &lt;em&gt;anyone&lt;/em&gt;. They just need to apply that everywhere!&lt;a href="#fnref1"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</summary></entry><entry><title>The State of Our Family in Early 2015</title><link href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2015/early-2015-family.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-02-10T20:30:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Chris Krycho</name></author><id>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2015-02-10:2015/early-2015-family.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;It has been a &lt;em&gt;long&lt;/em&gt; time since I wrote a family update here, and I skipped the Christmas letter this year because I was exhausted. I resolved at the beginning of the year to write at least one update every month, though. I want these updates here for &lt;em&gt;myself&lt;/em&gt;, if for no other reason. (Then, of course, I promptly missed January, but this is counting for that; there will be another post here at the end of the month.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What have we been up to, you ask? Well, quite a lot! Since the last time I wrote a blog post, we had a baby, who is now crawling around. (If you’re reading this, you probably already know that, of course.) Ellie is talking, constantly practicing saying things the right way and asking the names of things; Kate is scooting around the floor exploring everything and is increasingly verbal herself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They love playing together. Ellie and Kate are good friends—a while back Jaimie heard Ellie quietly talking to Katie in the back seat of the car, repeating, “You’re my best friend, Kate.” Sometimes when Ellie gives Kate a hug and a kiss goodnight every night, Kate goes into the most adorable squeals of delight. Indeed, no one elicits those squeals as much as Ellie. In addition to her scooting around the floor, Kate is happily eating solid foods—and the girl &lt;em&gt;loves&lt;/em&gt; her food. Today I put her in her high chair and she started laughing as I put the tray in front of her. She often thumps the tray, the table, or the floor to express her joy. And last but not least, this little gal is &lt;em&gt;strong&lt;/em&gt;. Her favorite time is getting in a bouncer and jumping for as long as we will let her.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src="/images/girls-games.jpg" title="My ladies playing Lego Star Wars"/&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;
My ladies playing &lt;i&gt;Lego Star Wars&lt;/i&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have been teaching Ellie a lot. Jaimie has slowly started working through the ABCs with her. She can count to 5, and she knows her way to 10, but sometimes gets sidetracked along the way. She is learning her colors and spent a while defaulting to calling everything “pink”… except for her favorite &lt;em&gt;purple&lt;/em&gt; dress. In the last month, she has started being able to identify the colors more reliably, along with lots of shapes. She loves cars and trucks and especially buses and fire trucks. She sings to herself and dances all the time. She loves building with blocks. She is learning to say “please” and “thank you”—learning, in this case, not because she doesn’t know how but because she has started &lt;em&gt;forgetting&lt;/em&gt;. She is learning to pray and to sing to God and learning the answer to simple questions like, “Who made you, Ellie?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jaimie has continued to write off and on, though the first many months we had Kate it was much spottier than it had been. She’s working on secret projects that are making her happy, and that makes me happy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As for why she didn’t get as much time, I was &lt;em&gt;busy&lt;/em&gt; last semester. I picked up a second contract, building the new &lt;a href="//holybible.com"&gt;HolyBible.com&lt;/a&gt;, and between that and my ongoing contract work and my one class, I pulled a lot of 50–60 hour weeks. That’s not particularly an experience we are keen to repeat, but it was the right call at the time: we were able to save up the money to fill up our six-month emergency fund and to pay for the rest of seminary. This semester is going a bit easier: I am taking Hebrew III and Baptist History and working ~30 hours a week instead of ~50–55. I &lt;em&gt;love&lt;/em&gt; my language classes; without a doubt Hebrew III and Greek III have been my very favorite classes since I started seminary.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I ran another half marathon in November, and set a PR at 1:25:37—a 6:32/mile pace. I was super happy with that outcome, and I plan to run the same race again for the third year in a row this coming fall, Lord willing. In the meantime, I have started swimming and cycling regularly with the aim of completing my first triathlon early this summer. (I’m going to stick to a short “sprint” tri to start, and work up from there.) While I love running, I would like to have the use of my joints in twenty (and forty, and sixty) years, and accordingly I need to make sure I do not keep putting over 1,000 miles a year on my legs. I have been going to a spinning class to get my legs in better cycling shape for the last month (and the last two weeks Jaimie has come with me!). We have also been doing a Pilates class weekly; my back needs to be a lot stronger and my legs a lot looser, and that is helping quite a bit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We continue to be extremely happy in our church here, FBC Durham. God has used our church to encourage and challenge us in a wide variety of ways—too many (and perhaps in many cases too subtle) even to summarize. We are excited to see what the years ahead hold for us there, as the church itself continues to flourish and grow and we seek opportunities to continue serving and building up this particular outpost of the body of Christ.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In short, life is &lt;em&gt;good&lt;/em&gt;. It is not perfect, of course; I long for Jesus’ return and the New Heavens and New Earth more and more all the time. But we see God’s faithfulness and goodness in the hard months no less than in the easy ones. We see the Spirit working in our hearts to make us more like Christ, and it is good.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I could go on, but a thousand words is enough. More again, and sooner than the last gap!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="references"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
</summary><category term="family"></category><category term="Ellie"></category><category term="Kate"></category><category term="Jaimie"></category></entry><entry><title>The Joy of Good Tools</title><link href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2015/joy-good-tools.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-01-09T18:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Chris Krycho</name></author><id>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2015-01-09:2015/joy-good-tools.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;i class="editorial"&gt;Note: This started out as a &lt;a href="https://alpha.app.net/chriskrycho/post/47820144"&gt;series of posts on App.net&lt;/a&gt;, but as I realized that it was growing a bit, I decided to &lt;a href="/2014/a-few-theses-on-blogging.html"&gt;take my own advice&lt;/a&gt; and turn it into a short blog post. (The first four paragraphs of this post are the same as the posts that spawned it.) And then, as so often happens with my writing, it rather took on a life of its own. So much for short.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After wrestling with Bitbucket issues again all day, I think I’ve finally hit the breaking point. Time to go ahead and drop the money on GitHub and migrate my private repos there. (Yes, GitLab is neat, but tool integrations matter, too.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think I’m also probably going to spring for a small subscription to Pivotal Tracker. It’s cheaper to do GitHub+PivotalTracker at my scale than to host GitLab and run YouTrack on a VPS. And that’s &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; counting my time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The big thing with Pivotal is that I &lt;em&gt;need&lt;/em&gt; the ability to estimate more effectively even than something like Trello affords (and I don’t want to spend time wrangling with Chrome plugins), and it gives me that. Totally worth the cost in saved pain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And as for GitHub as compared to the free GitLab… well, honestly, the F/OSS-copycat model bothers me on a lot of levels. The fact that their strategy is “copy GitHub as closely as possible, and charge for it” is not my idea of “winning slowly”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(“Winning slowly” is more than just the name of my &lt;a href="//www.winningslowly.org"&gt;podcast&lt;/a&gt;. In fact, it’s the opposite: we named the podcast that because it’s one of the core commitments in our lives.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I’m going to pay for Pivotal and GitHub. My time is worth something, and the quality of the tools I use matters, too. Ongoing irritation and frustration adds up over time. Good tools can make us happier. Bad tools can make work more frustrating than it needs to be. Given just how frustrating work can be anyway, the last thing in the world I want to do is unnecessarily spend my time being even more frustrated by my tools. And you know what? $7/month for each of those tools is absolutely worth more than the frustration of wrestling with tools that do the job less well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m actually really excited by this. Pivotal Tracker will help me avoid making the painful mistake of underestimation in the future, by helping me see how long things actually take and giving me a way to plan out major projects with that data immediately available. GitHub will be simultaenously more functional and much lovelier than Bitbucket—no strategy tax holding it back!—and will be much nicer to use.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the end of the day, it comes down to this: I’m happy to pay for good tools that make my work more enjoyable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To my surprise and amusement, this leads me to a closely related point I had been writing up in a separate blog post: the value of tools that &lt;em&gt;delight&lt;/em&gt;. It is not merely that bad tools make work unpleasant. Good tools can make work a &lt;em&gt;joy&lt;/em&gt;. Indeed, because my vocations is such a significant part of my life, few things bring me as much simple pleasure as a tool that does its job well, is pleasant to use, and is beautiful, all at once.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The latest example of this for me is &lt;a href="//www.neat.io/bee/index.html"&gt;Bee&lt;/a&gt;, a tool designed to make working with issue trackers like JIRA, GitHub Issues, and FogBugz easier and more pleasant. I use JIRA for one of my long-term contracts—I actually set it up for the company—and I have a love-hate relationship with it. JIRA’s power is great, but the web interface is slow and cluttered.&lt;a href="#fn1" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref1"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have used other desktop tools with JIRA before, and they were even worse than the web interface. I stumbled across Bee the other day (I cannot even remember how!), decided to try it out, and fell in love. It is simple, fast, and &lt;em&gt;elegant&lt;/em&gt;. That is a killer combination. I have been using it daily for over a week, and strange though it might be to say of a desktop client for issue trackers, I get genuine pleasure out of using it. (Yes, I know: that is a bit strange.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have the same experience with a number of other tools I use—&lt;a href="//www.git-tower.com"&gt;Tower&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="//bywordapp.com"&gt;Byword&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href="//www.jetbrains.com/idea/"&gt;IntelliJ IDEA&lt;/a&gt; to name just a few. This very post is written in Byword, and I’m &lt;em&gt;happy&lt;/em&gt; about it. I wish I felt that way about every tool I use.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And this goes beyond software. I have had the same experience driving a car. The Mazda3 I drove in and after college was a delight. The MUV&lt;a href="#fn2" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref2"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; we drive right now is sufficient. The Chevy Malibu we rented for driving to and from Texas in December was &lt;em&gt;irritating&lt;/em&gt;, with an inordinate number of small failures to consider how the thing would actually be used. I would buy another Mazda3 in a heartbeat; I would contentedly take another Lexus RX300-alike; I would avoid a Chevy Malibu like the plague.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Every&lt;/em&gt; category of tool is like this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The difference between a poor or mediocre tool and a good tool can make the difference between frustration and satisfaction. The difference between a good tool and a &lt;em&gt;great&lt;/em&gt; tool can make the difference between satisfaction and delight. That inspires me: it makes me want to make things so that they do more than &lt;em&gt;suffice&lt;/em&gt;—so that they &lt;em&gt;excel&lt;/em&gt;, so that they delight and energize their audience. Whether that is someone using a web application I write or someone listening to a piece of music I composed, I want them to experience more than good-enough. I want them to feel joy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is something profound here, I think, something that goes even deeper than just the experience of being happy enough with a good tool to pay money to use it. I think human beings are meant for that profound joy—meant for it in every breath. That these kinds of delights are rare, and so often marred even at their best by little failures, is a mark of the imperfection—and, in human terms at least, the &lt;em&gt;imperfectibility&lt;/em&gt;—of the world in which we live. But the fact that such moments will be rare until the eschaton neither undoes nor diminishes the imperative to strive after them—especially for those of us who, as Christians, affirm the goodness and the &lt;em&gt;telos&lt;/em&gt; of the created world. Quite the contrary. We have a responsibility and a charge as subcreators always to be able to say of the work we have done, “It is good.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am not there yet. I hope very much, though, that the work I do this year will be—for at least one person—a little sip from that deep well of delight. Whether I succeed or no, at least the bar is set where it ought to be.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="references"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;section class="footnotes"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn1"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Atlassian’s designers seem to be shooting for the kind of “flat” minimalism that is in right now… and missing the mark entirely. &lt;em&gt;All&lt;/em&gt; of their tools are a cluttered mess in the UI/X department.&lt;a href="#fnref1"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn2"&gt;&lt;p&gt;A “Mom Utility Vehicle”, my wry term for “SUV”-type vehicles sitting on standard car chasses.&lt;a href="#fnref2"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</summary><category term="software development"></category><category term="design"></category><category term="joy"></category></entry><entry><title>Public-ish Plans</title><link href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2015/public-ish-plans.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-01-02T20:15:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Chris Krycho</name></author><id>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2015-01-02:2015/public-ish-plans.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I have not (yet) made a formal list of goals for 2015, though I think I may do so on Sunday evening. While New Years’ resolutions can be silly and get us in trouble (when we set unrealistic goals, or unhelpful goals), the turning of the year can also be a helpful time to evaluate the way we spend our time and the things we want to accomplish.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What follows is a list of public-ish things I am &lt;em&gt;hoping&lt;/em&gt; to manage in 2015, in no particular order. Come the end of the year, I will Lord willing look back and see which of these I was able to pull off!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Publish at least two seasons of &lt;a href="//www.winningslowly.org"&gt;Winning Slowly&lt;/a&gt; with &lt;a href="//stephencarradini.com"&gt;Stephen Carradini&lt;/a&gt; just as we did last year—but better.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Get the site for Winning Slowly updated so that it paginates between seasons! This means writing an extension for &lt;a href="//docs.getpelican.com/en/3.5.0/"&gt;Pelican&lt;/a&gt; that can paginate on something besides page count. An excuse to write Python? I call that winning.&lt;a href="#fn1" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref1"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Migrate Jaimie’s &lt;a href="//jaimiekrycho.com"&gt;Jaimie’s professional writing website&lt;/a&gt; from WordPress to &lt;a href="//ghost.org"&gt;Ghost&lt;/a&gt;. (Maybe do something similar with her current &lt;a href="//jaimiedawn.blogspot.com"&gt;personal site&lt;/a&gt;, which runs on Blogger. Yuck.) I’ve gotten a bit of a start on that already, and I hope to knock it out sooner rather than later.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Get to a point where I’m hosting all my own sites on my own DigitalOcean droplet (or similar). I’ve been moving that direction slowly but steadily anyway—whereas I started and ran for a long time on simple shared hosting, I’ve been using &lt;a href="https://www.webfaction.com/?aid=67929"&gt;Webfaction&lt;/a&gt; for a good chunk of the past year, and now am pretty well ready to take the plunge this year into just running my own server. No skin off their backs; Webfaction has been great, as was &lt;a href="https://billing.stablehost.com/aff.php?aff=319"&gt;StableHost&lt;/a&gt; before them. I’m just ready to be in control (even with the bit of extra maintenance that entails).&lt;a href="#fn2" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref2"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Write at least three minutes of music, and post it to my &lt;a href="//soundcloud.com/chriskrycho"&gt;SoundCloud&lt;/a&gt; account. Preferably five minutes, but at least three.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Write some poetry.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Write a substantive essay and post it at least once a month.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Post at least a half dozen book reviews (which, among other things, means reading at least a half dozen books worth reviewing). These can be fiction or non-fiction. Personally, I’d like to get everything from Dostoevsky to Schreiner in there.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Add a picture to my &lt;a href="/about"&gt;About&lt;/a&gt; page!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Post a &lt;a href="/family"&gt;#family&lt;/a&gt; update at least once a month. It’ll be good for &lt;em&gt;me&lt;/em&gt;, just to have a better way of tracking what’s going on with our little gals, and I know my family would enjoy it, too.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In sum, I’d like to be doing &lt;em&gt;something&lt;/em&gt; in nearly every public-facing category in which I’m interested. Maybe it won’t be a lot, but keeping my musical skills doing matters to me. Keeping my brain engaged on a wide variety of topics matters to me. Keeping my writing skills sharp matters to me. I cannot &lt;em&gt;excel&lt;/em&gt; at all of those things, certainly—especially not if I wish to be a good husband and father! But keeping them active means keeping them from further atrophying, and that is something, at least. It will hopefully leave them more available to me for times in the future when I am able to dedicate more time to them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If 2014 and 2013 were both years in which I focused primarily on software—and all to the good!—then I hope 2015 will be a year in which I am able to broaden out again and focus on a wider variety of things!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You’ll note that there really aren’t any purely personal goals on this list. Not to worry: I have them, and I intend to formalize them in the next couple of days. But one of the things I have learned over the many years I have been blogging is that not everything needs to be public. Some things can be; indeed, some &lt;em&gt;should&lt;/em&gt; be. Some things &lt;em&gt;may&lt;/em&gt; be public but &lt;em&gt;need&lt;/em&gt; not, and yet others &lt;em&gt;should not&lt;/em&gt; be public. Right now, I am choosing to leave quite a few things in the “may be need not” category private. (This direction, I can always change my mind later. It’s essentially impossible to do the opposite in the internet era.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="references"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;section class="footnotes"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn1"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Slowly&lt;/em&gt;. Beat you to it.&lt;a href="#fnref1"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn2"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Note: those are both affiliate links; they’ll give me a slight kickback. For StableHost, you should also use the code &lt;code&gt;krycho50percent&lt;/code&gt; to get 50% off! I’d love it if you used it if you decide to sign up for either of them.&lt;a href="#fnref2"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</summary><category term="listicles"></category></entry><entry><title>Boosting My Productivity</title><link href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2014/boosting-my-productivity.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-12-18T08:05:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Chris Krycho</name></author><id>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2014-12-18:2014/boosting-my-productivity.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;This fall, I have had a lot on my plate: building HolyBible.com, continuing to work for Quest Consultants, and doing a pastoral ministry internship. I needed to be more productive—a lot more. Happily, I have been, and it only took three small changes.&lt;a href="#fn1" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref1"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section id="use-a-to-do-list" class="level2"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Use a To-Do List&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Making a list of items to accomplish has been incredibly helpful. I started using &lt;a href="https://www.omnigroup.com/omnifocus/"&gt;OmniFocus&lt;/a&gt; in August for class due dates and any work tasks not tracked in other ways.&lt;a href="#fn2" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref2"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; At that point, I organized everything—a bit too much, actually. Over the last couple months, I took some good advice I have seen in a number of places:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do not over-organize. Most tasks can go in a simple inbox.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hit your due dates. Making it a habit to hit every due date will help you not to miss important tasks.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do not put due dates on things that do not need them. You will eventually stop paying attention to them—and also to the due dates that &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt; matter.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I try to knock out a few small things from my Inbox every day, and hit all the due dates I set for myself. I am missing fewer things, getting more things done, and getting them done sooner than I did before. I like my app, but I know people who have just used an old-fashioned planner. The trick is to find a strategy that works for you.&lt;a href="#fn3" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref3"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="email-is-not-a-to-do-list" class="level2"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Email Is &lt;em&gt;Not&lt;/em&gt; A To-Do List&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At some point, I got in the habit of using my email as a to-do list. In theory, seeing a list of unanswered emails every day should have motivated me to respond to them. In reality, they just sat there and slowly piled up. At best, they nagged at me. At worst, I basically forgot them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I started using OmniFocus, I killed this habit. Now I make a task for anything I need to act on, and I delete or archive everything else.&lt;a href="#fn4" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref4"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;4&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; If the task is time-sensitive, I put a due date on it; otherwise, my third rule above applies. I also have a repeating task reminding me to empty my inbox at the end of each day (“Inbox Zero”). Having an empty inbox at the end of every day removes a certain amount of mental baggage: I have a task for everything I &lt;em&gt;need&lt;/em&gt; to act on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="take-breaks" class="level2"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Take breaks&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, I have started using the &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pomodoro_Technique"&gt;“pomodoro”&lt;/a&gt; technique. The basic approach is to work steadily for 25 minutes, then take a 5 minute break.&lt;a href="#fn5" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref5"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;5&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; After four such cycles, I take a slightly longer break—usually 15 minutes. On each break, I walk around and do something unrelated to whatever I am working on. I also write down a brief summary of what I did on that cycle.&lt;a href="#fn6" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref6"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;6&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; There is nothing complicated about this: I just use a simple timer to track the work and break cycles.&lt;a href="#fn7" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref7"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;7&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; I have seen a &lt;em&gt;dramatic&lt;/em&gt; improvement in my ability to sustain my concentration on my tasks throughout the day since I started.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are a few reasons for that improvement. First, I have dedicated break times, so I know that I can go check social media, read tech and news sites, etc. &lt;em&gt;later&lt;/em&gt;. That makes it easier to concentrate on work for the blocks in between; the distractions can wait. Second, it puts a limit on those break times. We have all been surprised to find we have lost an hour reading online; using a timer helps prevent that. Third, getting up and moving around helps keep my brain active—I can tell that the movement considerably improves my alertness and concentration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These breaks have other benefits, too. There is mounting evidence that sitting all day is terrible for our health. Even exercising as much as I do &lt;a href="http://www.npr.org/2011/04/25/135575490/sitting-all-day-worse-for-you-than-you-might-think" title="Sitting All Day: Worse For You Than You Might Think"&gt;cannot fully counteract&lt;/a&gt; a sedentary lifestyle. However, there is also evidence that getting up and moving on a regular basis &lt;em&gt;does&lt;/em&gt; help. Walking briskly, I usually manage a fifth or a quarter of a mile on a five-minute break. That adds up over the course of a day: if I am disciplined about walking on my breaks, I regularly walk 2–3 miles in a day, even with lunch and other non-walking breaks in the mix.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have also found the breaks spiritually helpful. One of the requirements for my pastoral ministry internship was to memorize Ephesians. Five-minute breaks are &lt;em&gt;perfect&lt;/em&gt; for memorizing and reviewing Scripture, so I was able to be productive on those breaks, even while letting my brain relax from my other work. It is similarly useful for dedicated times of prayer throughout the day. The combination of scripture memory and prayer has been invaluable in combatting sin and stirring up my affections for Christ.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In short, I get a triple benefit by doing pomodoros. I am more productive when I am working, my body will remain healthier because I am less sedentary, and I am growing in holiness and intimacy with God. Of all the changes I made this semester, incorporating pomodoros into my day has been the most important, and I plan to make it a regular part of my life henceforth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="references"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section class="footnotes"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn1"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is just what I do. It may not work for you. It may even drive you crazy.&lt;a href="#fnref1"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn2"&gt;&lt;p&gt;I.e., things not covered by JIRA, Trello, Bitbucket issues, etc.&lt;a href="#fnref2"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn3"&gt;&lt;p&gt;While &lt;a href="https://www.omnigroup.com/omnifocus/"&gt;OmniFocus&lt;/a&gt; suits me, I would recommend &lt;a href="https://en.todoist.com/"&gt;Todoist&lt;/a&gt; to most people instead: it is less expensive and easier to use, and while it does not do &lt;em&gt;everything&lt;/em&gt; OmniFocus does, it can easily do everything most people need.&lt;a href="#fnref3"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn4"&gt;&lt;p&gt;I archive order confirmations, messages from friends, and work conversations, and delete everything else.&lt;a href="#fnref4"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn5"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Why the 25/5 pattern? That seems to be a limit in human cognition; it lines up closely with research on student attention spans in the classroom.&lt;a href="#fnref5"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn6"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This helps me see what I have done over the course of a day and gives me a sense of progress. It is also extremely useful when writing up a weekly report for an employer.&lt;a href="#fnref6"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn7"&gt;&lt;p&gt;I have used &lt;a href="http://www.tomighty.org/"&gt;Tomighty&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/app/pomodoro-one/id907364780?mt=12"&gt;Pomodoro One&lt;/a&gt;, which are both free and work well. The app is not the point, though: an old-fashioned kitchen timer will do just as well.&lt;a href="#fnref7"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</summary></entry><entry><title>Whiplash</title><link href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2014/whiplash.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-07-14T23:15:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Chris Krycho</name></author><id>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2014-07-14:2014/whiplash.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I have a pretty severe case of emotional whiplash&lt;a href="#fn1" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref1"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; at the moment. In the last eight hours, I have gone from jubilant to the most worried I have ever been to simple, utter exhaustion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This afternoon, I heard back from a then-potential and now-actual client who hired me and a friend to design and build a web application for them. They are going to pay us a substantial sum to do it. This is &lt;em&gt;fantastic&lt;/em&gt;. I have been hoping this particular opportunity would come through, because everything about it is appealing to me. It is an interesting application; I like the material it involves (a &lt;em&gt;lot&lt;/em&gt;); I will learn a bit along the way; I will get to stretch my front-end design chops again; I will make some seriously good money at it. I am, in a word, stoked.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fast forward four and a half hours. Jaimie and I are helping Ellie wrap up her evening activities and getting ready to take her upstairs and put her to bed. Kate is lying in a little sleep-rocker—her favorite spot to sleep during the day. She makes a bit of a coughing noise; we note it but think little of it (babies &lt;em&gt;often&lt;/em&gt; make that kind of noise). A few minutes later, Jaimie is walking by and glances at Kate. Our baby girl is bright red and turning purple. She grabs her. “Kate! Breathe! Breathe, little girl!” She isn’t breathing; she is getting upset but she isn’t crying. (Babies cry at the drop of a hat.) Little bubbles at her mouth. Jaimie is doing the baby variation of the Heimlich maneuver. I am nearly helpless; I keep using my finger to pull Kate’s mouth open; she finally latches onto the finger, starts sucking, and breathes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thank God.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We hold her. She breathes—&lt;em&gt;mostly&lt;/em&gt; normally. We keep paying close attention to her. The couple times I let her lay down on her back she starts seizing up and turning red again within a few minutes until I pick her up and pat her vigorously and she calms down again. We manage to get Ellie in bed. We call the doctor; she sends us to the hospital. A friend comes to watch Ellie and we run out the door. It is a 30-minute drive (and I am speeding, and Jaimie is holding Kate to make sure she keeps breathing).&lt;a href="#fn2" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref2"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; Kate wheezes off and on the whole way there. She still isn’t crying, and she should be. She hasn’t eaten in six hours; she should be hungry. Why isn’t she hungry?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They admit us. They get all her vitals. The doctor is a kind, soft-spoken man with the last name Saad; I like him. He asks dozens of good questions. He tells us, “95–99% of the time, this is just reflux. We just care about that other 1% of the time.” There is no reliable way to stop a baby from choking on milk she spits up because of reflux.&lt;a href="#fn3" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref3"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; They are going to do an EKG and chest X-rays just to make sure she is okay.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She seems to be okay. She is eating again—like a champ, like she normally does, like she should be.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I go home to relieve the wonderful friends who are sitting in our house to make sure Ellie is fine. Ellie is still sleeping. Good.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Breathe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whiplash. I am no less excited about that project. And my youngest daughter almost died tonight. Had she started choking while we were upstairs, or while we were all asleep tonight, God only knows what would have happened. We are grateful to God that we were feet away from Kate, that Jaimie “happened” to look at her just then. We are grateful, too, for the extra money coming in; it will help with the so-very-worth-it-but-not-easy-on-a-seminary-budget cost of an emergency room visit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ice cream.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think I’m going to sleep now. Hopefully tomorrow is less extreme.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="references"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;section class="footnotes"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn1"&gt;&lt;p&gt;So much so that I am having a hard time spelling “whiplash” correctly. I keep typing “whiplast”.&lt;a href="#fnref1"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn2"&gt;&lt;p&gt;If a police officer stops us, I will explain. He or she will understand. They will help us get to the hospital faster.&lt;a href="#fnref2"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn3"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Terrifying, just a bit? Yes.&lt;a href="#fnref3"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</summary><category term="family"></category><category term="Kate"></category></entry><entry><title>A Few Theses on Blogging</title><link href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2014/a-few-theses-on-blogging.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-07-09T21:15:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Chris Krycho</name></author><id>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2014-07-09:2014/a-few-theses-on-blogging.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I am a habitually—even chronically—long-winded blogger. I always have been. I sat down a few weeks ago to write up an explanation of my running approach, and I haven’t finished it yet… because it is over 2,500 words long and growing rapidly longer. But as I have considered my approach to blogging of late, and as I have also been posting fairly regularly on App.net (my social media locale of choice), it occurred to me:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol type="1"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Blog posts do not have to be the lengthy things I usually make of them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I often write up a series of thoughts—not necessarily an “argument” or indeed anything more than a series of connected thoughts—on App.net, connecting them via the ‘reply’ mechanism and enumerating them. Rather like I am here.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Doing so inevitably clutters up the streams of anyone following me.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;That clutter may or may not be problematic: some folks may enjoy those connected thoughts. Others may not.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For those that &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt; enjoy those connected thoughts, a blog post like this would probably serve just as well.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For those who do &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; enjoy them… well, this sort of thing would be a welcome way to clear their streams up without causing me any particular difficulty.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Using lists does not automatically mean I have given in to the constant temptation to make my blogging about driving views.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Seriously.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This blog will &lt;em&gt;never&lt;/em&gt; drive substantial amounts of traffic. That is fine by me. Indeed, I would probably feel a bit odd if it did.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Therefore, when I have those sorts of thoughts-in-a-line in the future, I will do as I have done here. I will write a ‘listicle’ (the shame!) and share it for others to partake of—or not!—as they please.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Taking that approach will almost certainly free me up to blog more briefly when I feel like it, as well. That, too, can only be a good thing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;After all: I am happier when I am writing.&lt;a href="#fn1" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref1"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;div class="references"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;section class="footnotes"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn1"&gt;&lt;p&gt;As I have so often &lt;a href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2014/the-long-race.html"&gt;noted before&lt;/a&gt;…&lt;a href="#fnref1"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</summary><category term="listicles"></category></entry><entry><title>Three Month Cycles.</title><link href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2014/three-month-cycles.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-05-27T20:45:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Chris Krycho</name></author><id>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2014-05-27:2014/three-month-cycles.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Over the past few years, Jaimie and I have observed that I tend to go in cycles in my time-spending habits. The issue is not so much whether I spend my time well, but where I spend it. I will go on a blogging kick for a few months, as I did at the beginning of this year, then not write much at all for a few months—but in the interval spend gobs of time reading, or writing software, or so on. I am not sure what it is that triggers the change, but it has been a fairly regular fixture of my life for at least the length of our marriage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Every once in a while, I will even go on a weeks-long video games or television kick. This is bliss for Jaimie, as she finds spending time together playing video games or watching television shows we both enjoy to be one of our best connecting activities. But then the spell comes to an end, and I’m back off to a reading kick, or designing a new website, or embarking on some crazed software development scheme or another. It somewhat drives Jaimie crazy, I suspect.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am not entirely sure what makes me tick this way. I do know that in those dedicated phases of work I can knock out significant tasks in the given area where I am motivated at any given time. (I have no doubt, for example, that I could pull off the 50,000 words needed for National Novel Writing Month some November, if I were in a writing mode.) Being able to predict these things would be nice, though. I could make a plan for the year and have a good idea what projects I would accomplish. Instead, I find myself extraordinarily productive in &lt;em&gt;some&lt;/em&gt; area at any given time—but never sure what it will be a month later. That’s not a &lt;em&gt;problem&lt;/em&gt;. It is, however, a bit perplexing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To be sure, I can and do force myself to continue on with certain tasks even when they are not particularly holding my interest. Sometimes that discipline is really helpful, and I eventually break through to another extended session of productivity in the same area. Sometimes, though, the interval—whether it is switching from writing to software and back again, or from software to Doctor Who and back again—brings me back fresher and more energized to complete the tasks. That is no surprise; I see the same patterns play out on the time scale of hours and days with my paid work (where just taking a month off is not particularly workable). Again: I just wish I could get a handle on the timing, so I could take advantage of that in making plans.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Right now, I seem to be in a video games and general blogging mode. I &lt;em&gt;want&lt;/em&gt; to dig back in on my software projects, and I expect I’ll do so soon. And by “soon” I mean: whenever I quit playing more &lt;em&gt;Skyrim&lt;/em&gt;. Probably in about two weeks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the meantime, I think I’m going to start tracking the particular moods I am in so that I can see if there is an established pattern throughout the year. Whether it correlates with the season, my other activities, or nothing at all would be helpful to know. For Jaimie’s sanity, if nothing else.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="references"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
</summary></entry><entry><title>The Long Race</title><link href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2014/the-long-race.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-05-24T00:07:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Chris Krycho</name></author><id>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2014-05-24:2014/the-long-race.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;It has been too long since I have written anything—too long not for my audience (small as it is), but for my soul. The last few weeks of class were of course even busier than the rest of the semester, courtesy of a couple major assignments I wrapped up and studying for and taking finals, all while doing my normal work as a software developer on the side. Writing simply fell by the wayside, alas. Even my devotions posts simply didn’t happen. And that is all right; there are seasons for all of these things, and it is not as if I didn’t write many thousands of words in late April and early May. They simply were not &lt;em&gt;blogging&lt;/em&gt; words.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So here I am tonight, writing simply to unwind. I spent much of the day working on various software projects—a pattern I expect to carry throughout the summer. In addition to my regular work for Quest Consultants Inc. back in Norman, I am picking up various web design and development jobs over the summer. God has been gracious in answering prayers for opportunities to pick up extra contracting work, and I have several really excellent opportunities to supplement my 20 hours a week for Quest with other work. That is nice not only financially, but also intellectually. The change of pace between different kinds of work helps me stay fresh on all of them. My own personal &lt;a href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2014/a-little-crazy.html"&gt;side projects&lt;/a&gt; are coming along slowly, but that is all right. Slow but steady is the best way to go about those kinds of projects anyway.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That lesson is one I have learned more and more from my ongoing and ever-increasing delight in running. So far in May I have run about 125 miles; I expect to run over 150 miles this month in total (though of course all such plans are always subject to revision, and never more so than when one’s wife is 37 weeks pregnant). I am now running easy, aerobic miles ten to fifteen seconds faster per mile than I could manage in my personal best half marathon time a few years ago. I run so (relatively) quickly now not because of any particular innate athleticism—quite the contrary, as anyone who has known me since high school can attest. I can run as far and fast as I do only because I have stuck with it and used a &lt;a href="http://markallenonline.com/maoArticles.aspx?AID=2" title="Working Your Heart"&gt;smart training plan&lt;/a&gt;. And really, as in most parts of life, it is that sticking-with-it that leads to getting somewhere. Of course, sticking with it is no guarantee that things will work out. It is usually a requisite step along the way, though—a necessary-though-insufficient condition. That is simply the way God built the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Little Ellie is quickly wrapping up her second year of life in this big world. She is saying lots of words (at last!), whining until she has driven Jaimie a bit crazy (in too-typical toddler fashion), and growing up in big ways and small. We are having a great deal of fun watching her start to be more socially aware and active, even if it is a little strange to have a daughter old enough that she has friends whom she loves and who love her in turn. She has also discovered a deep love of &lt;em&gt;Star Wars&lt;/em&gt;—no surprise for a daughter of ours, though the intensity of her delight in the movies, for a girl who is not yet two years old, did surprise both Jaimie and me a bit. You should hear her try to say “Darth Vader” or “Dark Side” or “Star Wars.” It is impossibly adorable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jaimie is, as noted above, some 37 weeks pregnant and quite ready to be done carrying our second little gal on the inside. She is still plugging away slowly at the &lt;a href="http://jaimiekrycho.com/shaking-epheria-pt-1/" title="Bloodlines: The Shaking of Epheria, Part I"&gt;second novella&lt;/a&gt; in her &lt;a href="http://www.amazon.com/Bloodlines-Epheria-The-Trilogy-ebook/dp/B00HY478QO/" title="Get Bloodlines of Epheria on Kindle!"&gt;Bloodlines&lt;/a&gt; fantasy trilogy. She manages to keep Ellie entertained—no small feat—and does a remarkable job taking care of things around the house so that I can focus on work and school. Her struggle with &lt;a href="http://2012-2013.chriskrycho.com/theology/marriage-depression/" title="Marriage and Depression"&gt;depression&lt;/a&gt; has not diminished, but God has given us grace to carry on and she and I have both learned to respond in better, healthier, more helpful ways when the slumps come.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As for the future, we really have no idea what the next several yeras will hold. I plan to finish my Master of Divinity—Lord willing, around December 2016. In the meantime, we will keep raising our little girls, I will keep writing software, and we will keep exploring and seeing what we want to do and how best to pursue those desires in a way that honors God. Who knows what those years will hold? God only, and certainly not us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="references"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
</summary><category term="software development"></category><category term="family"></category><category term="fitness"></category></entry><entry><title>Spinning!</title><link href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2014/spinning.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-03-20T19:10:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Chris Krycho</name></author><id>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2014-03-20:2014/spinning.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;As she so often does, Ellie simply delighted me tonight, in two wonderful moments:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol type="1"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;As I was cleaning up the dishes and playing Max Richter’s &lt;a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/album/memoryhouse/id545010150"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Memoryhouse&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; album, I saw Ellie dancing, and encouraged her to keep going. After a moment, I looked over to see her spinning in circles. And spinning in circles. And spinning in circles. When she finally stopped, she started freaking out as she couldn’t get her balance. I swooped in and picked her up, laughing with her once she recovered.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;After she calmed down, she started tugging on my shirt. It took me a few seconds to realize what she wanted, but then it clicked: she was trying to turn me by twisting my shirt. “You want to spin?” I asked her. She nodded vigorously. “Is this a spinning song?” Again, the vigorous nod. So I started spinning around and around with her in my arms, and the sheer joy in the grin plastered across her face was something to behold. We spun first one way, then the other, all the way through &lt;a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=BfoSv8iWA_I"&gt;“The Twins (Prague)”&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moments like these are worth remembering.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="references"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
</summary><category term="family"></category><category term="Ellie"></category></entry><entry><title>On Days Off</title><link href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2014/on-days-off.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-02-23T10:30:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Chris Krycho</name></author><id>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2014-02-23:2014/on-days-off.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;These past few days I have completely missed my normal writing times—no devotions, and certainly not the other few pieces I had been planning to write. This was disappointing: I have enjoyed the habit of writing regularly, and I intend to keep it up. As I have often noted in the past (in more blog posts on previous versions of the site than I can count, still less dig up at the moment), writing serves to focus my thoughts as little else does. Moreover, though my &lt;a href="/devotions"&gt;#devotions&lt;/a&gt; posts are not especially excellent as writing goes, the discipline of writing is like many other things: sometimes it matters most that you &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt; it more than the doing of it be particularly magnificent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most of my running is this way. The vast majority of my runs are entirely unexceptional and become notable only in their consistency. They are not tiring and not particularly fast—for me, at least! This is an important qualification, I recognize, though one that is nonetheless closely tied to the very ordinary nature of these runs. They become interesting, and are effective, only in the aggregate. My entire training plan is built on going slowly and training the “easy” side of my physiological response to running. The effect over time is extraordinary, though: my easy runs with a toddler in a stroller today are faster than my best runs alone were a few years ago.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My hope for this year is to do something the same with my writing. I do not expect that the majority of my words will be particularly elegant or well-put-together. I expect most of my posts to go largely unread and unnoticed, and that is perfectly fine with me—indeed, &lt;em&gt;more&lt;/em&gt; than fine, because I am writing them first of all as a double act of self-discipline. From those devotional posts I hope to gain not an audience but the benefit of thoughtful reflection the Scriptures I read and the helpful effect of regular writing on my &lt;em&gt;other&lt;/em&gt; writing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So when, as in the last few days, I simply cannot get to that writing because other things intrude, I have a double response. First, I recognize that this is totally all right, under the circumstances. Jaimie and I have been spending time with friends and each other, and my normal writing times in the evenings have simply been elided by those other activities. Second, though, I recognize that such things are likely to come up often, and as such am motivated to commit once again to doing this writing in the mornings as much as possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For several weeks in the beginning of the semester this spring, I was able to get up, do my reading, and do my writing before I went to class at 8am. A few weeks ago, Jaimie’s grandmother passed away and we flew her out for the funeral, and that weekend completely tossed my habits and schedule out of alignment. Instead of my two normally scheduled tasks for the weekend (school and work), I had three—and one of them in the form of a teething toddler. The other two slipped. I have only just finally caught up, and as such I am hoping that in the week ahead I shall be able to resume my previously very effective habits of doing all these things to &lt;em&gt;start&lt;/em&gt; the day rather than to finish them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That, of course, assumes I get over this blasted cold that I seem to have caught last night… Life is a funny thing, sometimes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="references"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
</summary></entry><entry><title>Hey, Look—A Podcast!</title><link href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2014/hey-look-a-podcast.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-01-28T20:20:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Chris Krycho</name></author><id>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2014-01-28:2014/hey-look-a-podcast.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Today, I was happy to be able to finally go public with a project on which I have been working for the last couple months (and for which I have been planning since mid-fall): &lt;a href="http://www.winningslowly.org/"&gt;Winning Slowly&lt;/a&gt;. Winning Slowly is a biweeklypodcast by yours truly and my good friend &lt;a href="http://stephencarradini.com"&gt;Stephen Carradini&lt;/a&gt; offering thoughtful commentary on trends in culture, technology, religion, ethics, and art.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of possible interest to my readers:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You can listen to the first episode, &lt;a href="http://www.winningslowly.org/2014/01/we-need-some-context/"&gt;We Need Some Context!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You can &lt;a href="http://www.winningslowly.org/feed.xml"&gt;subscribe to the feed&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You can follow and get updates via all sorts of social networks:
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Twitter: &lt;a href="https://twitter.som/winningslowly"&gt;@winningslowly&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;App.net: &lt;a href="http://app.net/winningslowly"&gt;@winningslowly&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://broadcast.app.net/40022/winning-slowly-episodes/"&gt;App.net broadcast&lt;/a&gt; – notifications on your phone or emails as you like&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://plus.google.com/u/0/+WinningslowlyOrgCast/"&gt;Google+&lt;/a&gt; (yes, shockingly enough)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We’re still very much in a “beta” phase. The audio quality needs significant improvement, our back-and-forth needs to get smoother (and, at times, more back- and-forth!), and so on. We’d love to hear your feedback. But be gentle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id="references" class="references"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
</summary><category term="podcasting"></category></entry><entry><title>A Note to RSS Subscribers</title><link href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2014/a-note-to-rss-subscribers.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-01-05T09:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Chris Krycho</name></author><id>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2014-01-05:2014/a-note-to-rss-subscribers.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;A note to anyone who has subscribed to this RSS feed: you should resubscribe by adding &lt;a href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/feed.xml" class="uri"&gt;http://www.chriskrycho.com/feed.xml&lt;/a&gt; to your reader, as this feed location is now defunct. Thanks!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="references"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
</summary></entry></feed>