<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Chris Krycho</title><link href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/feeds/blog.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://www.chriskrycho.com/</id><updated>2015-01-02T20:15:00-05:00</updated><entry><title>Public-ish Plans</title><link href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2015/public-ish-plans.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-01-02T20:15:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Chris Krycho</name></author><id>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2015-01-02:2015/public-ish-plans.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I have not (yet) made a formal list of goals for 2015, though I think I
may do so on Sunday evening. While New Years&amp;#8217; resolutions can be silly
and get us in trouble (when we set unrealistic goals, or unhelpful
goals), the turning of the year can also be a helpful time to evaluate
the way we spend our time and the things we want to&amp;nbsp;accomplish.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What follows is a list of public-ish things I am &lt;em&gt;hoping&lt;/em&gt; to manage in
2015, in no particular order. Come the end of the year, I will Lord
willing look back and see which of these I was able to pull&amp;nbsp;off!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Publish at least two seasons of &lt;a href="//www.winningslowly.org"&gt;Winning Slowly&lt;/a&gt; with &lt;a href="//stephencarradini.com"&gt;Stephen
  Carradini&lt;/a&gt; just as we did last year&amp;#8212;but&amp;nbsp;better.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Get the site for Winning Slowly updated so that it paginates between
  seasons! This means writing an extension for &lt;a href="//docs.getpelican.com/en/3.5.0/"&gt;Pelican&lt;/a&gt; that can
  paginate on something besides page count. An excuse to write Python? I
  call that winning.&lt;sup id="fnref:slowly"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:slowly" rel="footnote"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Migrate Jaimie&amp;#8217;s &lt;a href="//jaimiekrycho.com"&gt;Jaimie&amp;#8217;s professional writing website&lt;/a&gt; from
  WordPress to &lt;a href="//ghost.org"&gt;Ghost&lt;/a&gt;. (Maybe do something similar with her current
  &lt;a href="//jaimiedawn.blogspot.com"&gt;personal site&lt;/a&gt;, which runs on Blogger. Yuck.) I&amp;#8217;ve gotten a
  bit of a start on that already, and I hope to knock it out sooner
  rather than&amp;nbsp;later.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Get to a point where I&amp;#8217;m hosting all my own sites on my own
  DigitalOcean droplet (or similar). I&amp;#8217;ve been moving that direction
  slowly but steadily anyway&amp;#8212;whereas I started and ran for a long time
  on simple shared hosting, I&amp;#8217;ve been using &lt;a href="https://www.webfaction.com/?aid=67929"&gt;Webfaction&lt;/a&gt; for a good
  chunk of the past year, and now am pretty well ready to take the
  plunge this year into just running my own server. No skin off their
  backs; Webfaction has been great, as was &lt;a href="https://billing.stablehost.com/aff.php?aff=319"&gt;StableHost&lt;/a&gt; before them. I&amp;#8217;m
  just ready to be in control (even with the bit of extra maintenance
  that entails).&lt;sup id="fnref:affiliate"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:affiliate" rel="footnote"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Write at least three minutes of music, and post it to my &lt;a href="//soundcloud.com/chriskrycho"&gt;SoundCloud&lt;/a&gt;
  account. Preferably five minutes, but at least&amp;nbsp;three.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Write some&amp;nbsp;poetry.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Write a substantive essay and post it at least once a&amp;nbsp;month.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Post at least a half dozen book reviews (which, among other things,
  means reading at least a half dozen books worth reviewing). These can
  be fiction or non-fiction. Personally, I&amp;#8217;d like to get everything from
  Dostoevsky to Schreiner in&amp;nbsp;there.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Add a picture to my &lt;a href="/about"&gt;About&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;page!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Post a &lt;a href="/family"&gt;#family&lt;/a&gt; update at least once a month. It&amp;#8217;ll be good for &lt;em&gt;me&lt;/em&gt;,
  just to have a better way of tracking what&amp;#8217;s going on with our little
  gals, and I know my family would enjoy it,&amp;nbsp;too.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In sum, I&amp;#8217;d like to be doing &lt;em&gt;something&lt;/em&gt; in nearly every public-facing
category in which I&amp;#8217;m interested. Maybe it won&amp;#8217;t be a lot, but keeping
my musical skills doing matters to me. Keeping my brain engaged on a
wide variety of topics matters to me. Keeping my writing skills sharp
matters to me. I cannot &lt;em&gt;excel&lt;/em&gt; at all of those things,
certainly&amp;#8212;especially not if I wish to be a good husband and father!
But keeping them active means keeping them from further atrophying, and
that is something, at least. It will hopefully leave them more available
to me for times in the future when I am able to dedicate more time to&amp;nbsp;them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If 2014 and 2013 were both years in which I focused primarily on
software&amp;#8212;and all to the good!&amp;#8212;then I hope 2015 will be a year in
which I am able to broaden out again and focus on a wider variety of&amp;nbsp;things!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You&amp;#8217;ll note that there really aren&amp;#8217;t any purely personal goals on this
list. Not to worry: I have them, and I intend to formalize them in the
next couple of days. But one of the things I have learned over the many
years I have been blogging is that not everything needs to be public.
Some things can be; indeed, some &lt;em&gt;should&lt;/em&gt; be. Some things &lt;em&gt;may&lt;/em&gt; be
public but &lt;em&gt;need&lt;/em&gt; not, and yet others &lt;em&gt;should not&lt;/em&gt; be public. Right now,
I am choosing to leave quite a few things in the &amp;#8220;may be need not&amp;#8221;
category private. (This direction, I can always change my mind later.
It&amp;#8217;s essentially impossible to do the opposite in the internet&amp;nbsp;era.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:slowly"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Slowly&lt;/em&gt;. Beat you to it.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:slowly" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:affiliate"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note: those are both affiliate links; they&amp;#8217;ll give me a
slight kickback. For StableHost, you should also use the code
&lt;code&gt;krycho50percent&lt;/code&gt; to get 50% off! I&amp;#8217;d love it if you used it if you
decide to sign up for either of them.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:affiliate" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 2 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary><category term="listicles"></category></entry><entry><title>Boosting My Productivity</title><link href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2014/boosting-my-productivity.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-12-18T08:05:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Chris Krycho</name></author><id>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2014-12-18:2014/boosting-my-productivity.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;This fall, I have had a lot on my plate: building HolyBible.com, continuing to
work for Quest Consultants, and doing a pastoral ministry internship. I needed
to be more productive&amp;#8212;a lot more. Happily, I have been, and it only took three
small changes.&lt;sup id="fnref:personal"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:personal" rel="footnote"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="use-a-to-do-list"&gt;Use a To-Do&amp;nbsp;List&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Making a list of items to accomplish has been incredibly helpful. I started
using &lt;a href="https://www.omnigroup.com/omnifocus/"&gt;OmniFocus&lt;/a&gt; in August for class due dates and any work tasks not tracked
in other ways.&lt;sup id="fnref:tracker"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:tracker" rel="footnote"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; At that point, I organized everything&amp;#8212;a bit too much,
actually. Over the last couple months, I took some good advice I have seen in a
number of&amp;nbsp;places:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do not over-organize. Most tasks can go in a simple&amp;nbsp;inbox.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hit your due dates. Making it a habit to hit every due date will help you
    not to miss important&amp;nbsp;tasks.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do not put due dates on things that do not need them. You will eventually
    stop paying attention to them&amp;#8212;and also to the due dates that &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt;&amp;nbsp;matter.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I try to knock out a few small things from my Inbox every day, and hit all the
due dates I set for myself. I am missing fewer things, getting more things done,
and getting them done sooner than I did before. I like my app, but I know people
who have just used an old-fashioned planner. The trick is to find a strategy
that works for you.&lt;sup id="fnref:app"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:app" rel="footnote"&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="email-is-not-a-to-do-list"&gt;Email Is &lt;em&gt;Not&lt;/em&gt; A To-Do&amp;nbsp;List&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At some point, I got in the habit of using my email as a to-do list. In theory,
seeing a list of unanswered emails every day should have motivated me to respond
to them. In reality, they just sat there and slowly piled up. At best, they
nagged at me. At worst, I basically forgot&amp;nbsp;them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I started using OmniFocus, I killed this habit. Now I make a task for
anything I need to act on, and I delete or archive everything else.&lt;sup id="fnref:email"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:email" rel="footnote"&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; If
the task is time-sensitive, I put a due date on it; otherwise, my third rule
above applies. I also have a repeating task reminding me to empty my inbox at
the end of each day (&amp;#8220;Inbox Zero&amp;#8221;). Having an empty inbox at the end of every
day removes a certain amount of mental baggage: I have a task for everything I
&lt;em&gt;need&lt;/em&gt; to act&amp;nbsp;on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="take-breaks"&gt;Take&amp;nbsp;breaks&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, I have started using the &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pomodoro_Technique"&gt;&amp;#8220;pomodoro&amp;#8221;&lt;/a&gt; technique. The basic approach is
to work steadily for 25 minutes, then take a 5 minute break.&lt;sup id="fnref:25/5"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:25/5" rel="footnote"&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; After four
such cycles, I take a slightly longer break&amp;#8212;usually 15 minutes. On each break,
I walk around and do something unrelated to whatever I am working on. I also
write down a brief summary of what I did on that cycle.&lt;sup id="fnref:summary"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:summary" rel="footnote"&gt;7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; There is
nothing complicated about this: I just use a simple timer to track the work and
break cycles.&lt;sup id="fnref:timer"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:timer" rel="footnote"&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; I have seen a &lt;em&gt;dramatic&lt;/em&gt; improvement in my ability to
sustain my concentration on my tasks throughout the day since I&amp;nbsp;started.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are a few reasons for that improvement. First, I have dedicated break
times, so I know that I can go check social media, read tech and news sites,
etc. &lt;em&gt;later&lt;/em&gt;. That makes it easier to concentrate on work for the blocks in
between; the distractions can wait. Second, it puts a limit on those break
times. We have all been surprised to find we have lost an hour reading online;
using a timer helps prevent that. Third, getting up and moving around helps keep
my brain active&amp;#8212;I can tell that the movement considerably improves my
alertness and&amp;nbsp;concentration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These breaks have other benefits, too. There is mounting evidence that sitting
all day is terrible for our health. Even exercising as much as I do &lt;a href="http://www.npr.org/2011/04/25/135575490/sitting-all-day-worse-for-you-than-you-might-think" title="Sitting All Day: Worse For You Than You Might Think"&gt;cannot
fully counteract&lt;/a&gt; a sedentary lifestyle. However, there is also evidence
that getting up and moving on a regular basis &lt;em&gt;does&lt;/em&gt; help. Walking briskly, I
usually manage a fifth or a quarter of a mile on a five-minute break. That adds
up over the course of a day: if I am disciplined about walking on my breaks, I
regularly walk 2&amp;#8211;3 miles in a day, even with lunch and other non-walking breaks
in the&amp;nbsp;mix.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have also found the breaks spiritually helpful. One of the requirements for my
pastoral ministry internship was to memorize Ephesians. Five-minute breaks are
&lt;em&gt;perfect&lt;/em&gt; for memorizing and reviewing Scripture, so I was able to be productive
on those breaks, even while letting my brain relax from my other work. It is
similarly useful for dedicated times of prayer throughout the day. The
combination of scripture memory and prayer has been invaluable in combatting sin
and stirring up my affections for&amp;nbsp;Christ.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In short, I get a triple benefit by doing pomodoros. I am more productive when I
am working, my body will remain healthier because I am less sedentary, and I am
growing in holiness and intimacy with God. Of all the changes I made this
semester, incorporating pomodoros into my day has been the most important, and I
plan to make it a regular part of my life&amp;nbsp;henceforth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:personal"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is just what I do. It may not work for you. It may even drive
you crazy.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:personal" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:tracker"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I.e., things not covered by &lt;span class="caps"&gt;JIRA&lt;/span&gt;, Trello, Bitbucket issues, etc.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:tracker" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 2 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:app"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While &lt;a href="https://www.omnigroup.com/omnifocus/"&gt;OmniFocus&lt;/a&gt; suits me, I would recommend &lt;a href="https://en.todoist.com/"&gt;Todoist&lt;/a&gt; to most people
instead: it is less expensive and easier to use, and while it does not do
&lt;em&gt;everything&lt;/em&gt; OmniFocus does, it can easily do everything most people need.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:app" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 3 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:email"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I archive order confirmations, messages from friends, and work
conversations, and delete everything else.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:email" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 4 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:25/5"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why the 25/5 pattern? That seems to be a limit in human cognition; it
lines up closely with research on student attention spans in the classroom.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:25/5" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 5 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:timer"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have used &lt;a href="http://www.tomighty.org/"&gt;Tomighty&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/app/pomodoro-one/id907364780?mt=12"&gt;Pomodoro One&lt;/a&gt;, which are both free and
work well. The app is not the point, though: an old-fashioned kitchen timer
will do just as well.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:timer" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 6 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:summary"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This helps me see what I have done over the course of a day and
gives me a sense of progress. It is also extremely useful when writing up a
weekly report for an employer.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:summary" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 7 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary></entry><entry><title>Whiplash</title><link href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2014/whiplash.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-07-14T23:15:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Chris Krycho</name></author><id>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2014-07-14:2014/whiplash.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I have a pretty severe case of emotional whiplash&lt;sup id="fnref:1"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:1" rel="footnote"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; at the moment. In the last
eight hours, I have gone from jubilant to the most worried I have ever been to
simple, utter&amp;nbsp;exhaustion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This afternoon, I heard back from a then-potential and now-actual client who
hired me and a friend to design and build a web application for them. They are
going to pay us a substantial sum to do it. This is &lt;em&gt;fantastic&lt;/em&gt;. I have been
hoping this particular opportunity would come through, because everything about
it is appealing to me. It is an interesting application; I like the material it
involves (a &lt;em&gt;lot&lt;/em&gt;); I will learn a bit along the way; I will get to stretch my
front-end design chops again; I will make some seriously good money at it. I am,
in a word,&amp;nbsp;stoked.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fast forward four and a half hours. Jaimie and I are helping Ellie wrap up her
evening activities and getting ready to take her upstairs and put her to bed.
Kate is lying in a little sleep-rocker&amp;#8212;her favorite spot to sleep during the
day. She makes a bit of a coughing noise; we note it but think little of it
(babies &lt;em&gt;often&lt;/em&gt; make that kind of noise). A few minutes later, Jaimie is walking
by and glances at Kate. Our baby girl is bright red and turning purple. She
grabs her. &amp;#8220;Kate! Breathe! Breathe, little girl!&amp;#8221; She isn&amp;#8217;t breathing; she is
getting upset but she isn&amp;#8217;t crying. (Babies cry at the drop of a hat.) Little
bubbles at her mouth. Jaimie is doing the baby variation of the Heimlich
maneuver. I am nearly helpless; I keep using my finger to pull Kate&amp;#8217;s mouth
open; she finally latches onto the finger, starts sucking, and&amp;nbsp;breathes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thank&amp;nbsp;God.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We hold her. She breathes&amp;#8212;&lt;em&gt;mostly&lt;/em&gt; normally. We keep paying close attention to
her. The couple times I let her lay down on her back she starts seizing up and
turning red again within a few minutes until I pick her up and pat her
vigorously and she calms down again. We manage to get Ellie in bed. We call the
doctor; she sends us to the hospital. A friend comes to watch Ellie and we run
out the door. It is a 30-minute drive (and I am speeding, and Jaimie is holding
Kate to make sure she keeps breathing).&lt;sup id="fnref:2"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:2" rel="footnote"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Kate wheezes off and on the whole
way there. She still isn&amp;#8217;t crying, and she should be. She hasn&amp;#8217;t eaten in six
hours; she should be hungry. Why isn&amp;#8217;t she&amp;nbsp;hungry?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They admit us. They get all her vitals. The doctor is a kind, soft-spoken man
with the last name Saad; I like him. He asks dozens of good questions. He tells
us, &amp;#8220;95&amp;#8211;99% of the time, this is just reflux. We just care about that other 1%
of the time.&amp;#8221; There is no reliable way to stop a baby from choking on milk she
spits up because of reflux.&lt;sup id="fnref:3"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:3" rel="footnote"&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; They are going to do an &lt;span class="caps"&gt;EKG&lt;/span&gt; and chest X-rays
just to make sure she is&amp;nbsp;okay.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She seems to be okay. She is eating again&amp;#8212;like a champ, like she normally
does, like she should&amp;nbsp;be.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I go home to relieve the wonderful friends who are sitting in our house to make
sure Ellie is fine. Ellie is still sleeping.&amp;nbsp;Good.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Breathe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whiplash. I am no less excited about that project. And my youngest daughter
almost died tonight. Had she started choking while we were upstairs, or while we
were all asleep tonight, God only knows what would have happened. We are
grateful to God that we were feet away from Kate, that Jaimie &amp;#8220;happened&amp;#8221; to look
at her just then. We are grateful, too, for the extra money coming in; it will
help with the so-very-worth-it-but-not-easy-on-a-seminary-budget cost of an
emergency room&amp;nbsp;visit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ice&amp;nbsp;cream.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think I&amp;#8217;m going to sleep now. Hopefully tomorrow is less&amp;nbsp;extreme.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So much so that I am having a hard time spelling &amp;#8220;whiplash&amp;#8221; correctly. I
keep typing &amp;#8220;whiplast&amp;#8221;.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:2"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If a police officer stops us, I will explain. He or she will understand.
They will help us get to the hospital faster.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:2" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 2 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:3"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Terrifying, just a bit? Yes.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:3" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 3 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary><category term="family"></category><category term="Kate"></category></entry><entry><title>A Few Theses on Blogging</title><link href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2014/a-few-theses-on-blogging.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-07-09T21:15:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Chris Krycho</name></author><id>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2014-07-09:2014/a-few-theses-on-blogging.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I am a habitually&amp;#8212;even chronically&amp;#8212;long-winded blogger. I always have been.
I sat down a few weeks ago to write up an explanation of my running approach,
and I haven&amp;#8217;t finished it yet&amp;#8230; because it is over 2,500 words long and growing
rapidly longer. But as I have considered my approach to blogging of late, and as
I have also been posting fairly regularly on App.net (my social media locale of
choice), it occurred to&amp;nbsp;me:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Blog posts do not have to be the lengthy things I usually make of&amp;nbsp;them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I often write up a series of thoughts&amp;#8212;not necessarily an &amp;#8220;argument&amp;#8221; or
    indeed anything more than a series of connected thoughts&amp;#8212;on App.net,
    connecting them via the &amp;#8216;reply&amp;#8217; mechanism and enumerating them. Rather like
    I am&amp;nbsp;here.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Doing so inevitably clutters up the streams of anyone following&amp;nbsp;me.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;That clutter may or may not be problematic: some folks may enjoy those
    connected thoughts. Others may&amp;nbsp;not.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For those that &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt; enjoy those connected thoughts, a blog post like this
    would probably serve just as&amp;nbsp;well.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For those who do &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; enjoy them&amp;#8230; well, this sort of thing would be a
    welcome way to clear their streams up without causing me any particular&amp;nbsp;difficulty.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Using lists does not automatically mean I have given in to the constant
    temptation to make my blogging about driving&amp;nbsp;views.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Seriously.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This blog will &lt;em&gt;never&lt;/em&gt; drive substantial amounts of traffic. That is fine by
    me. Indeed, I would probably feel a bit odd if it&amp;nbsp;did.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Therefore, when I have those sorts of thoughts-in-a-line in the future, I
    will do as I have done here. I will write a &amp;#8216;listicle&amp;#8217; (the shame!) and
    share it for others to partake of&amp;#8212;or not!&amp;#8212;as they&amp;nbsp;please.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Taking that approach will almost certainly free me up to blog more briefly
    when I feel like it, as well. That, too, can only be a good&amp;nbsp;thing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;After all: I am happier when I am writing.&lt;sup id="fnref:12"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:12" rel="footnote"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:12"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I have so often &lt;a href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2014/the-long-race.html"&gt;noted before&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#8230;&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:12" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary><category term="listicles"></category></entry><entry><title>Three Month Cycles.</title><link href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2014/three-month-cycles.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-05-27T20:45:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Chris Krycho</name></author><id>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2014-05-27:2014/three-month-cycles.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Over the past few years, Jaimie and I have observed that I tend to go in cycles
in my time-spending habits. The issue is not so much whether I spend my time
well, but where I spend it. I will go on a blogging kick for a few months, as I
did at the beginning of this year, then not write much at all for a few
months&amp;#8212;but in the interval spend gobs of time reading, or writing software, or
so on. I am not sure what it is that triggers the change, but it has been a
fairly regular fixture of my life for at least the length of our&amp;nbsp;marriage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Every once in a while, I will even go on a weeks-long video games or television
kick. This is bliss for Jaimie, as she finds spending time together playing
video games or watching television shows we both enjoy to be one of our best
connecting activities. But then the spell comes to an end, and I&amp;#8217;m back off to a
reading kick, or designing a new website, or embarking on some crazed software
development scheme or another. It somewhat drives Jaimie crazy, I&amp;nbsp;suspect.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am not entirely sure what makes me tick this way. I do know that in those
dedicated phases of work I can knock out significant tasks in the given area
where I am motivated at any given time. (I have no doubt, for example, that I
could pull off the 50,000 words needed for National Novel Writing Month some
November, if I were in a writing mode.) Being able to predict these things would
be nice, though. I could make a plan for the year and have a good idea what
projects I would accomplish. Instead, I find myself extraordinarily productive
in &lt;em&gt;some&lt;/em&gt; area at any given time&amp;#8212;but never sure what it will be a month later.
That&amp;#8217;s not a &lt;em&gt;problem&lt;/em&gt;. It is, however, a bit&amp;nbsp;perplexing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To be sure, I can and do force myself to continue on with certain tasks even
when they are not particularly holding my interest. Sometimes that discipline is
really helpful, and I eventually break through to another extended session of
productivity in the same area. Sometimes, though, the interval&amp;#8212;whether it is
switching from writing to software and back again, or from software to Doctor
Who and back again&amp;#8212;brings me back fresher and more energized to complete the
tasks. That is no surprise; I see the same patterns play out on the time scale
of hours and days with my paid work (where just taking a month off is not
particularly workable). Again: I just wish I could get a handle on the timing,
so I could take advantage of that in making&amp;nbsp;plans.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Right now, I seem to be in a video games and general blogging mode. I &lt;em&gt;want&lt;/em&gt; to
dig back in on my software projects, and I expect I&amp;#8217;ll do so soon. And by &amp;#8220;soon&amp;#8221;
I mean: whenever I quit playing more &lt;em&gt;Skyrim&lt;/em&gt;. Probably in about two&amp;nbsp;weeks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the meantime, I think I&amp;#8217;m going to start tracking the particular moods I am
in so that I can see if there is an established pattern throughout the year.
Whether it correlates with the season, my other activities, or nothing at all
would be helpful to know. For Jaimie&amp;#8217;s sanity, if nothing&amp;nbsp;else.&lt;/p&gt;</summary></entry><entry><title>The Long Race</title><link href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2014/the-long-race.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-05-24T00:07:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Chris Krycho</name></author><id>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2014-05-24:2014/the-long-race.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;It has been too long since I have written anything&amp;#8212;too long not for my
audience (small as it is), but for my soul. The last few weeks of class were of
course even busier than the rest of the semester, courtesy of a couple major
assignments I wrapped up and studying for and taking finals, all while doing my
normal work as a software developer on the side. Writing simply fell by the
wayside, alas. Even my devotions posts simply didn&amp;#8217;t happen. And that is all
right; there are seasons for all of these things, and it is not as if I didn&amp;#8217;t
write many thousands of words in late April and early May. They simply were not
&lt;em&gt;blogging&lt;/em&gt;&amp;nbsp;words.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So here I am tonight, writing simply to unwind. I spent much of the day working
on various software projects&amp;#8212;a pattern I expect to carry throughout the
summer. In addition to my regular work for Quest Consultants Inc. back in
Norman, I am picking up various web design and development jobs over the
summer. God has been gracious in answering prayers for opportunities to pick up
extra contracting work, and I have several really excellent opportunities to
supplement my 20 hours a week for Quest with other work. That is nice not only
financially, but also intellectually. The change of pace between different
kinds of work helps me stay fresh on all of them. My own personal &lt;a href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2014/a-little-crazy.html"&gt;side
projects&lt;/a&gt; are coming along slowly, but that is all right. Slow but steady
is the best way to go about those kinds of projects&amp;nbsp;anyway.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That lesson is one I have learned more and more from my ongoing and
ever-increasing delight in running. So far in May I have run about 125 miles; I
expect to run over 150 miles this month in total (though of course all such
plans are always subject to revision, and never more so than when one&amp;#8217;s wife is
37 weeks pregnant). I am now running easy, aerobic miles ten to fifteen seconds
faster per mile than I could manage in my personal best half marathon time a
few years ago. I run so (relatively) quickly now not because of any particular
innate athleticism&amp;#8212;quite the contrary, as anyone who has known me since high
school can attest. I can run as far and fast as I do only because I have stuck
with it and used a &lt;a href="http://markallenonline.com/maoArticles.aspx?AID=2" title="Working Your Heart"&gt;smart training plan&lt;/a&gt;. And really, as in most
parts of life, it is that sticking-with-it that leads to getting somewhere. Of
course, sticking with it is no guarantee that things will work out. It is
usually a requisite step along the way, though&amp;#8212;a
necessary-though-insufficient condition. That is simply the way God built the&amp;nbsp;world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Little Ellie is quickly wrapping up her second year of life in this big world.
She is saying lots of words (at last!), whining until she has driven Jaimie a
bit crazy (in too-typical toddler fashion), and growing up in big ways and
small. We are having a great deal of fun watching her start to be more socially
aware and active, even if it is a little strange to have a daughter old enough
that she has friends whom she loves and who love her in turn. She has also
discovered a deep love of &lt;em&gt;Star Wars&lt;/em&gt;&amp;#8212;no surprise for a daughter of ours,
though the intensity of her delight in the movies, for a girl who is not yet
two years old, did surprise both Jaimie and me a bit. You should hear her try
to say &amp;#8220;Darth Vader&amp;#8221; or &amp;#8220;Dark Side&amp;#8221; or &amp;#8220;Star Wars.&amp;#8221; It is impossibly&amp;nbsp;adorable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jaimie is, as noted above, some 37 weeks pregnant and quite ready to be done
carrying our second little gal on the inside. She is still plugging away slowly
at the &lt;a href="http://jaimiekrycho.com/shaking-epheria-pt-1/" title="Bloodlines: The Shaking of Epheria, Part I"&gt;second novella&lt;/a&gt; in her &lt;a href="http://www.amazon.com/Bloodlines-Epheria-The-Trilogy-ebook/dp/B00HY478QO/" title="Get Bloodlines of Epheria on Kindle!"&gt;Bloodlines&lt;/a&gt; fantasy trilogy.
She manages to keep Ellie entertained&amp;#8212;no small feat&amp;#8212;and does a remarkable
job taking care of things around the house so that I can focus on work and
school. Her struggle with &lt;a href="http://2012-2013.chriskrycho.com/theology/marriage-depression/" title="Marriage and Depression"&gt;depression&lt;/a&gt; has not diminished, but
God has given us grace to carry on and she and I have both learned to respond
in better, healthier, more helpful ways when the slumps&amp;nbsp;come.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As for the future, we really have no idea what the next several yeras will
hold. I plan to finish my Master of Divinity&amp;#8212;Lord willing, around December
2016. In the meantime, we will keep raising our little girls, I will keep
writing software, and we will keep exploring and seeing what we want to do and
how best to pursue those desires in a way that honors God. Who knows what those
years will hold? God only, and certainly not&amp;nbsp;us.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="software development"></category><category term="family"></category><category term="fitness"></category></entry><entry><title>Spinning!</title><link href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2014/spinning.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-03-20T19:10:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Chris Krycho</name></author><id>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2014-03-20:2014/spinning.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;As she so often does, Ellie simply delighted me tonight, in two wonderful&amp;nbsp;moments:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;As I was cleaning up the dishes and playing Max Richter&amp;#8217;s
    &lt;a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/album/memoryhouse/id545010150"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Memoryhouse&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; album, I saw Ellie dancing, and encouraged her to keep
    going. After a moment, I looked over to see her spinning in circles. And
    spinning in circles. And spinning in circles. When she finally stopped, she
    started freaking out as she couldn&amp;#8217;t get her balance. I swooped in and
    picked her up, laughing with her once she&amp;nbsp;recovered.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;After she calmed down, she started tugging on my shirt. It took me a few
    seconds to realize what she wanted, but then it clicked: she was trying to
    turn me by twisting my shirt. &amp;#8220;You want to spin?&amp;#8221; I asked her. She nodded
    vigorously. &amp;#8220;Is this a spinning song?&amp;#8221; Again, the vigorous nod. So I started
    spinning around and around with her in my arms, and the sheer joy in the
    grin plastered across her face was something to behold. We spun first one
    way, then the other, all the way through &lt;a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=BfoSv8iWA_I"&gt;&amp;#8220;The Twins (Prague)&amp;#8221;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moments like these are worth&amp;nbsp;remembering.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="family"></category><category term="Ellie"></category></entry><entry><title>On Days Off</title><link href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2014/on-days-off.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-02-23T10:30:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Chris Krycho</name></author><id>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2014-02-23:2014/on-days-off.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;These past few days I have completely missed my normal writing times&amp;#8212;no
devotions, and certainly not the other few pieces I had been planning to write.
This was disappointing: I have enjoyed the habit of writing regularly, and I
intend to keep it up. As I have often noted in the past (in more blog posts on
previous versions of the site than I can count, still less dig up at the
moment), writing serves to focus my thoughts as little else does. Moreover,
though my &lt;a href="/devotions"&gt;#devotions&lt;/a&gt; posts are not especially excellent as
writing goes, the discipline of writing is like many other things: sometimes it
matters most that you &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt; it more than the doing of it be particularly&amp;nbsp;magnificent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most of my running is this way. The vast majority of my runs are entirely
unexceptional and become notable only in their consistency. They are not tiring
and not particularly fast&amp;#8212;for me, at least! This is an important
qualification, I recognize, though one that is nonetheless closely tied to the
very ordinary nature of these runs. They become interesting, and are effective,
only in the aggregate. My entire training plan is built on going slowly and
training the &amp;#8220;easy&amp;#8221; side of my physiological response to running. The effect
over time is extraordinary, though: my easy runs with a toddler in a stroller
today are faster than my best runs alone were a few years&amp;nbsp;ago.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My hope for this year is to do something the same with my writing. I do not
expect that the majority of my words will be particularly elegant or
well-put-together. I expect most of my posts to go largely unread and unnoticed,
and that is perfectly fine with me&amp;#8212;indeed, &lt;em&gt;more&lt;/em&gt; than fine, because I am
writing them first of all as a double act of self-discipline. From those
devotional posts I hope to gain not an audience but the benefit of thoughtful
reflection the Scriptures I read and the helpful effect of regular writing on my
&lt;em&gt;other&lt;/em&gt;&amp;nbsp;writing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So when, as in the last few days, I simply cannot get to that writing because
other things intrude, I have a double response. First, I recognize that this is
totally all right, under the circumstances. Jaimie and I have been spending time
with friends and each other, and my normal writing times in the evenings have
simply been elided by those other activities. Second, though, I recognize that
such things are likely to come up often, and as such am motivated to commit once
again to doing this writing in the mornings as much as&amp;nbsp;possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For several weeks in the beginning of the semester this spring, I was able to
get up, do my reading, and do my writing before I went to class at 8am. A few
weeks ago, Jaimie&amp;#8217;s grandmother passed away and we flew her out for the funeral,
and that weekend completely tossed my habits and schedule out of alignment.
Instead of my two normally scheduled tasks for the weekend (school and work), I
had three&amp;#8212;and one of them in the form of a teething toddler. The other two
slipped. I have only just finally caught up, and as such I am hoping that in the
week ahead I shall be able to resume my previously very effective habits of
doing all these things to &lt;em&gt;start&lt;/em&gt; the day rather than to finish&amp;nbsp;them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That, of course, assumes I get over this blasted cold that I seem to have caught
last night&amp;#8230; Life is a funny thing,&amp;nbsp;sometimes.&lt;/p&gt;</summary></entry><entry><title>Hey, Look—A Podcast!</title><link href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2014/hey-look-a-podcast.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-01-28T20:20:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Chris Krycho</name></author><id>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2014-01-28:2014/hey-look-a-podcast.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Today, I was happy to be able to finally go public with a project on which I
have been working for the last couple months (and for which I have been planning
since mid-fall): &lt;a href="http://www.winningslowly.org/"&gt;Winning Slowly&lt;/a&gt;. Winning Slowly is a biweeklypodcast by
yours truly and my good friend &lt;a href="http://stephencarradini.com"&gt;Stephen Carradini&lt;/a&gt; offering thoughtful
commentary on trends in culture, technology, religion, ethics, and&amp;nbsp;art.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of possible interest to my&amp;nbsp;readers:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You can listen to the first episode, &lt;a href="http://www.winningslowly.org/2014/01/we-need-some-context/"&gt;We Need Some&amp;nbsp;Context!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You can &lt;a href="http://www.winningslowly.org/feed.xml"&gt;subscribe to the feed&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You can follow and get updates via all sorts of social networks:&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Twitter: &lt;a href="https://twitter.som/winningslowly"&gt;@winningslowly&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;App.net: &lt;a href="http://app.net/winningslowly"&gt;@winningslowly&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://broadcast.app.net/40022/winning-slowly-episodes/"&gt;App.net broadcast&lt;/a&gt; &amp;#8211; notifications on your phone or emails as
  you&amp;nbsp;like&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://plus.google.com/u/0/+WinningslowlyOrgCast/"&gt;Google+&lt;/a&gt; (yes, shockingly&amp;nbsp;enough)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We&amp;#8217;re still very much in a &amp;#8220;beta&amp;#8221; phase. The audio quality needs significant
improvement, our back-and-forth needs to get smoother (and, at times, more back-
and-forth!), and so on. We&amp;#8217;d love to hear your feedback. But be&amp;nbsp;gentle.&lt;/p&gt;</summary></entry><entry><title>A Note to RSS Subscribers</title><link href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2014/a-note-to-rss-subscribers.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-01-05T09:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Chris Krycho</name></author><id>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2014-01-05:2014/a-note-to-rss-subscribers.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;A note to anyone who has subscribed to this &lt;span class="caps"&gt;RSS&lt;/span&gt; feed: you should resubscribe by
adding &lt;a href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/feed.xml"&gt;http://www.chriskrycho.com/feed.xml&lt;/a&gt; to your reader, as this feed
location is now defunct.&amp;nbsp;Thanks!&lt;/p&gt;</summary></entry></feed>