<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Chris Krycho - blogging</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/</link><description></description><lastBuildDate>Mon, 25 Jun 2018 06:15:00 -0400</lastBuildDate><item><title>Continuing to Reflect on My Internet Presence</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2018/continuing-to-reflect-on-my-internet-presence.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;i class="editorial"&gt;A quick note: I drafted this back in June, but forgot to actually publish it!&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I find that I’m always reflecting on the shape I want my internet presence to take. Over the last month, in particular, I’ve been thinking about the kind of “link-blogging” and commentary-on-articles-I’ve-read that I’ve experimented with pushing into Pinboard for the last &lt;a href="https://www.chriskrycho.com/2017/pick-the-right-tool-for-the-job.html"&gt;year and some change&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the one hand, I’ve found that Pinboard is &lt;em&gt;great&lt;/em&gt; for two things:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;having an easy place to look up articles I’ve read but can’t necessarily remember the name of off the top of my head&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;being &lt;em&gt;a&lt;/em&gt; place with its own &lt;abbr&gt;RSS&lt;/abbr&gt; feed of that content, which is social-network-like in some ways but using open web tech like &lt;abbr&gt;RSS&lt;/abbr&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But what it isn’t is &lt;em&gt;integrated with my own site&lt;/em&gt;, or particularly easily discoverable &lt;em&gt;from&lt;/em&gt; my site. Adding a link to my public Pinboard feed would help, perhaps, but you wouldn’t know what I use it &lt;em&gt;for&lt;/em&gt; from seeing that link.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The thing is, I want this material here on this site. There remain two blockers to me there:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;ease of publishing&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;site design and structure&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the most part, I am happy enough with a static site generator setup. However, for this specific kind of use, I wish for a web front-end to my website (or, honestly, an easy way to integrate &lt;a href="https://www.ulyssesapp.com"&gt;Ulysses&lt;/a&gt; with it). The options which exist in that general space—WordPress and Ghost—both have their upsides, but also a great many downsides, and I find that I have no interest in using either.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You might find that an odd commitment; here’s an aside on why.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our &lt;a href="https://krycho.com"&gt;family blog&lt;/a&gt; is a Ghost install, and the previous iteration of this site ran on WordPress. Ghost is &lt;em&gt;fine&lt;/em&gt;, and for many setups it’s actually really good. For my fairly complex set of publishing requirements, it unfortunately doesn’t really do the trick. Some of those requirements—like integration with citation-management tooling, are &lt;em&gt;currently&lt;/em&gt; less pressing, but I don’t count on that being the case in the long term.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That said, one possible alternative here is simply to cross that bridge if or when I come to it and lean on the somewhat simpler tools that &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt; meet my needs for today. If I did that, it would certainly be with Ghost, because WordPress feels to me the same way Windows feels to me: technically very competent, but impossibly frustrating to use. (That’s not insulting either of the two; it’s a statement of my very—overly, perhaps!—specific aesthetic tastes and my corresponding—admittedly irrational!—response to the experience of using Windows or WordPress. Maybe it’s just the ‘W’s that start the names?)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is one reason I’ve seriously considered figuring out how to make my &lt;a href="https://github.com/chriskrycho/lightning-rs"&gt;long-on-hold site generator&lt;/a&gt; actually be a hybrid: never dynamically generating content, but with an &lt;abbr&gt;API&lt;/abbr&gt; to enable programmatic access, so that I &lt;em&gt;can&lt;/em&gt; put a web or app front end on it. (Existing solutions in that space, like &lt;a href="https://www.netlifycms.org"&gt;Netlify CMS&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href="https://forestry.io/"&gt;forestry.io&lt;/a&gt;, are really good, but don’t quite support everything I have historically committed to needing. They also don’t have anything like an iOS share sheet!)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The problem, of course, is that I’m not yet ready to spend my limited time building out my long-planned and long-delayed personal website generator tool. In short, I’m caught in a catch-22 of my own making.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In any case, I want to figure out a flow for sharing those kinds of notes-on-articles that works better for getting it onto my blog, rather than caught in the mostly-invisible space that is my Pinboard. I need a refreshed site design to support it effectively. I need different &lt;em&gt;tools&lt;/em&gt; to support that flow effectively. Which means I’m not going to end up doing it tomorrow or anything.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ll get to it eventually. Maybe. Hopefully. And in the meantime I’ll do one extra step when I see something worth linking, and copy it into a Ulysses document that I can publish shortly thereafter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is where every nerd ends up with their blogging software, I think: in a pit of good-enough-to-get-by but not-actually-satisfying. (But I’m not helping myself with how persnickety I am about these things.)&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 25 Jun 2018 06:15:00 -0400</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2018-06-25:/2018/continuing-to-reflect-on-my-internet-presence.html</guid><category>pinboard</category><category>writing</category><category>blogging</category></item></channel></rss>