<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Chris Krycho - book reviews</title><link>http://v4.chriskrycho.com/</link><description></description><lastBuildDate>Sat, 17 Aug 2019 09:25:00 -0400</lastBuildDate><item><title>Review: Shades of Milk and Honey</title><link>http://v4.chriskrycho.com/2019/review-shades-of-milk-and-honey.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;a href="https://v4.chriskrycho.com/2018/assumed-audiences.html"&gt;Assumed Audience&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/b&gt; book lovers!&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;i class=editorial&gt;I keep my book review ratings simple—they’re either &lt;em&gt;required&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;recommended&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;recommended with qualifications&lt;/em&gt;, or &lt;em&gt;not recommended&lt;/em&gt;. If you want the TL;DR, this is it:&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Recommended:&lt;/b&gt; Regency period piece styled with language and plot reminiscent of an Austen novel… but with more magic and less irony and social commentary. I picked it up because I &lt;a href="https://v4.chriskrycho.com/2018/the-calculating-stars.html"&gt;loved&lt;/a&gt; her Lady Astronaut books and Jaimie has loved this series for years. In a turn I did not expect (because, well, this is not my genre!), it proved not only to be &lt;em&gt;good&lt;/em&gt; (which I did expect) but also to be a genuine page-turner; I stayed up late one night last week to finish it. A nice little magic system, excellent use of period literary style, good characters, engaging plot. Will read the rest of the series!&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 17 Aug 2019 09:25:00 -0400</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:v4.chriskrycho.com,2019-08-17:/2019/review-shades-of-milk-and-honey.html</guid><category>book reviews</category><category>fantasy</category><category>reading</category></item><item><title>Review: Retrieving Eternal Generation</title><link>http://v4.chriskrycho.com/2019/review-retrieving-eternal-generation.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;i class=editorial&gt;I keep my book review ratings simple—they’re either &lt;em&gt;required&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;recommended&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;recommended with qualifications&lt;/em&gt;, or &lt;em&gt;not recommended&lt;/em&gt;. If you want the TL;DR, this is it:&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Required:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;cite&gt;Retrieving Eternal Generation&lt;/cite&gt;, edited by Fred Sanders and Scott R. Swain, is a collection of essays defending the doctrine of eternal generation from recent criticism (“recent” meaning the last half century or more) and aiming to show how the traditional, creedal, catholic&lt;a href="#fn1" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref1" role="doc-noteref"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; articulation of the relationship of the Father and the Son is indeed &lt;em&gt;correct&lt;/em&gt;. Surprisingly even for an anthology volume, and in my view quite effective in achieving its aims: most anthologies of essays end up being a very mixed bag. Even given my long-standing appreciation of Fred Sanders, I was not expecting &lt;cite&gt;Retrieving Eternal Generation&lt;/cite&gt; to be an exception to that nearly iron-clad rule. Every essay brings something distinctive to the table and its theological scholarship is of the best sort: simultaneously engaged with current research programs and the Great Tradition of the church… while still being readable. This is for theology nerds, but it should absolutely be required reading if you &lt;em&gt;are&lt;/em&gt; a theology nerd.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn1" role="doc-endnote"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Note the little ‘c’ here: ‘catholic’ as in &lt;i&gt;universal&lt;/i&gt;.&lt;a href="#fnref1" class="footnote-back" role="doc-backlink"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 16 Jul 2019 08:05:00 -0400</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:v4.chriskrycho.com,2019-07-16:/2019/review-retrieving-eternal-generation.html</guid><category>book reviews</category><category>Christology</category></item><item><title>Review: All That’s Good</title><link>http://v4.chriskrycho.com/2019/review-all-thats-good.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;i class=editorial&gt;I keep my book review ratings simple—they’re either &lt;em&gt;required&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;recommended&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;recommended with qualifications&lt;/em&gt;, or &lt;em&gt;not recommended&lt;/em&gt;. If you want the TL;DR, this is it:&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Recommended:&lt;/strong&gt; Hannah Anderson’s &lt;cite&gt;All That’s Good&lt;/cite&gt; is a popular theological treatment of the idea of “discernment”. The first several chapters are worth the price of the book; after that, it’s &lt;em&gt;fine&lt;/em&gt; but not &lt;em&gt;amazing&lt;/em&gt;, and seemed very much a product of the demands of the publishing industry (it read like “This could use a relatively basic exposition of the fruit of the Spirit to appeal more/fill out the page count”). Nonetheless, recommended in general and probably a very valuable book for women’s groups (to whom it seems targeted)—men would benefit equally, but the marketing will likely make that a harder sell.&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 16 Jul 2019 08:00:00 -0400</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:v4.chriskrycho.com,2019-07-16:/2019/review-all-thats-good.html</guid><category>book reviews</category><category>discernment</category></item><item><title>Review: The Rust Programming Language</title><link>http://v4.chriskrycho.com/2018/review-the-rust-programming-language.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;i class=editorial&gt;I intended to publish this review months ago, but the single hardest month of my career punched me in the face repeatedly and I just found myself entirely unable to write for all of September and most of October. Here it is at last, with apologies to No Starch for the delay!&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No Starch Press kindly provided me with a review copy of &lt;a href="https://nostarch.com/Rust"&gt;&lt;cite&gt;The Rust Programming Language&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, by Steve Klabnik and Carol Nichols, with contributions from the Rust community. A &lt;em&gt;real-world, physical&lt;/em&gt; review copy. And it’s magnificent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src="https://f001.backblazeb2.com/file/chriskrycho-com/images/trpl.jpg" alt="The Rust Programming Language" /&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;cite&gt;The Rust Programming Language&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ve read the vast majority of this book (as well as the previous edition) online over the last couple years as Steve and Carol have worked on it; it has been an invaluable resource for many a &lt;a href="https://newrustacean.com"&gt;New Rustacean&lt;/a&gt; episode. (Bonus: you can hear me talk with Carol about working on &lt;cite&gt;The Rust Programming Language&lt;/cite&gt; in &lt;a href="https://newrustacean.com/show_notes/interview/_3/index.html"&gt;my interview with her back in 2016&lt;/a&gt;! And yes: writing the book took that long.) This is in some sense &lt;em&gt;the&lt;/em&gt; authoritative book on Rust.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You might wonder why you’d pick up a physical copy of this book given that it is available online for free. There are a few reasons that come to mind:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol type="1"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The quality of the online book is in many ways a direct result of No Starch Press’ deep investment in the text. They’re not making any money from the online copy. They &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt; recoup some of their costs when we buy ebook or physical copies. So that’s one good reason: a way of saying “thank you!” and investing in the continued existence of No Starch and projects like this.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I used the word &lt;em&gt;magnificent&lt;/em&gt; above to describe this, and I mean it. This printing is a fabulous example of really excellent book design. I take typography and presentation seriously, and not a whit less for programming books than for copies of &lt;cite&gt;The Lord of the Rings&lt;/cite&gt;. Everything in this printing is top-notch. Little details like the way that code listings are displayed—right down to the way some text is faded away to emphasize what’s &lt;em&gt;new&lt;/em&gt; in a listing—make this one of the most readable programming texts I’ve ever seen.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;As delightful and powerful as hypertext is, the physicality of a book is equally delightful and powerful, just in different ways. There is nothing quite like the tactile experience of flipping through a book. Nothing in digital text lets you forge connections to learning the way that scribbling notes in a margin does. And the sheer physicality of a volume this large gives you mental hooks to hang what you’re learning on: you can remember that it felt like &lt;em&gt;this&lt;/em&gt; to have the book open to where you learned it.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(That last point is an argument in favor of printed books in general. You can expect me to come back to that theme time and again in this space, even while I continue to value digital spaces like this one for what &lt;em&gt;they&lt;/em&gt; uniquely do.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No Starch sent me this copy to review with no expectation of a positive review—but even if they’d been paying me, they couldn’t make me say that this book is &lt;em&gt;great&lt;/em&gt;. But great it is. If you have any interest in &lt;a href="https://www.rust-lang.org/en-US/"&gt;Rust&lt;/a&gt;, you should grab a copy!&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 07 Nov 2018 07:00:00 -0500</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:v4.chriskrycho.com,2018-11-07:/2018/review-the-rust-programming-language.html</guid><category>book reviews</category><category>rust</category><category>programming languages</category></item><item><title>Ringworld Review</title><link>http://v4.chriskrycho.com/2018/ringworld-review.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;i class=editorial&gt;I keep my book review ratings simple—they’re either &lt;em&gt;required&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;recommended&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;recommended with qualifications&lt;/em&gt;, or &lt;em&gt;not recommended&lt;/em&gt;. If you want the TL;DR, this is it:&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Recommended:&lt;/strong&gt; In want of a bit of classic sci-fi, I recently picked up Larry Niven’s &lt;cite&gt;Ringworld&lt;/cite&gt; and read it this week. I enjoyed it, but more than that I find it hard to say. I’m still not sure exactly what to describe it as: an exploratory high concept romp, maybe. The characters were fine, the plot serviceable, and the two high concepts very high indeed. (Certainly the more interesting of those conceits is the one &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; advertized by the title of the book.) I’m not sad I read it; I also don’t think I’d read it again. I might even call it a bit overrated.&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 14 Oct 2018 17:30:00 -0400</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:v4.chriskrycho.com,2018-10-14:/2018/ringworld-review.html</guid><category>science fiction</category><category>book reviews</category><category>reading</category></item><item><title>Review: The Fated Sky</title><link>http://v4.chriskrycho.com/2018/review-the-fated-sky.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;i class=editorial&gt;I keep my book review ratings simple—they’re either &lt;em&gt;required&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;recommended&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;recommended with qualifications&lt;/em&gt;, or &lt;em&gt;not recommended&lt;/em&gt;. If you want the TL;DR, this is it:&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Recommended:&lt;/strong&gt; Mary Robinette Kowal picks up her alt-history of the space program after a meteor strike and continues doing what sci-fi does best: throwing new light on present-day cultural issues by showing something that &lt;em&gt;isn’t&lt;/em&gt; the present day. Where the first book looked head-on at sexism, the second carries that line forward but digs in on racism as well. And all this while still being an exciting &lt;em&gt;novel&lt;/em&gt; with interesting characters and an engaging (if never quite surprising) novel. It doesn’t have quite the same magic &lt;em&gt;The Calculating Stars&lt;/em&gt; did, but I still enjoyed it very thoroughly.&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 31 Aug 2018 07:00:00 -0400</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:v4.chriskrycho.com,2018-08-31:/2018/review-the-fated-sky.html</guid><category>book reviews</category><category>science fiction</category><category>sexism</category><category>mental illness</category><category>racism</category></item><item><title>Review: The Calculating Stars</title><link>http://v4.chriskrycho.com/2018/the-calculating-stars.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;i class=editorial&gt;I keep my book review ratings simple—they’re either &lt;em&gt;required&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;recommended&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;recommended with qualifications&lt;/em&gt;, or &lt;em&gt;not recommended&lt;/em&gt;. If you want the TL;DR, this is it:&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Required:&lt;/strong&gt; Mary Robinette Kowal’s alt-history of the space program (after a meteor strike!) is wonderful—smashingly-good plotting which somehow makes a half decade span feel &lt;em&gt;urgent&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;fast-paced&lt;/em&gt;; a fantastic lead character; an interesting examination of women’s friendships; and frank treatment of both sexism and mental illness without being preachy about either. This was one of my favorite pieces of science-fiction I’ve read in a long time.&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 19 Aug 2018 16:00:00 -0400</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:v4.chriskrycho.com,2018-08-19:/2018/the-calculating-stars.html</guid><category>book reviews</category><category>science fiction</category><category>sexism</category><category>mental illness</category></item><item><title>Agent of Change</title><link>http://v4.chriskrycho.com/2018/agent-of-change.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;i class=editorial&gt;I keep my book review ratings simple—they’re either &lt;em&gt;required&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;recommended&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;recommended with qualifications&lt;/em&gt;, or &lt;em&gt;not recommended&lt;/em&gt;. If you want the TL;DR, this is it:&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Recommended:&lt;/strong&gt; Sometimes you just need “popcorn”—and Sharon Lee and Steve Miller’s first novel is exactly that. (Just… pardon the frequent POV switches.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At my friend &lt;a href="http://stephencarradini.com"&gt;Stephen&lt;/a&gt;’s recommendation (“a surprisingly fun sci-fi adventure romp. Lots of romantic tension, surprisingly chaste (and pretty satisfying) payoff [with] some of the coolest, most interesting protagonist aliens I’ve read about in a long time”) I picked up Sharon Lee and Steve Miller’s &lt;em&gt;Agent of Change&lt;/em&gt;,&lt;a href="#fn1" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref1" role="doc-noteref"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and I quite enjoyed it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sometimes, in the midst of hammering away at work and dealing with the tumult of moving into a new house, it’s nice to grab the literary equivalent of a bag of chips or a bowl of popcorn. This is that. There was nothing in this book that was anything like as interesting or engaging as sci-fi &lt;a href="http://v4.chriskrycho.com/2017/icehenge.html" title="Icehenge (review on this site)"&gt;can be&lt;/a&gt;—but it was, in Stephen’s words, an &lt;em&gt;adventure romp&lt;/em&gt;, and that was perfect. The characters are fun, well-drawn if never particularly surprising. The plot is essentially an escape story (and in more ways than it first appears).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The only real &lt;em&gt;problem&lt;/em&gt; on display with the book is that it completely disregards anything like modern conventions around point-of-view. A paragraph break is sufficient for a total change of internal perspective. This drove me crazy the entire book.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Might I read another entry in this universe, the next time I’m looking for merely a romp? Indeed I might.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn1" role="doc-endnote"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Agent of Change&lt;/em&gt; is the first book in their Liaden series. It’s also listed as anything &lt;em&gt;but&lt;/em&gt; the first book, because republication and branding have dropped it at its chronological position in their larger universe… but book &lt;em&gt;nine&lt;/em&gt; it is not, whatever Amazon tells you.&lt;a href="#fnref1" class="footnote-back" role="doc-backlink"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 16 Feb 2018 06:30:00 -0500</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:v4.chriskrycho.com,2018-02-16:/2018/agent-of-change.html</guid><category>book reviews</category><category>science fiction</category></item><item><title>Icehenge</title><link>http://v4.chriskrycho.com/2017/icehenge.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;i class=editorial&gt;I keep my book review ratings simple—they’re either &lt;em&gt;required&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;recommended&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;recommended with qualifications&lt;/em&gt;, or &lt;em&gt;not recommended&lt;/em&gt;. If you want the TL;DR, this is it:&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Recommended:&lt;/strong&gt; this is good sci-fi—the kind that makes you think while also being a bit of a page-turner.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kim Stanley Robinson comes highly recommended, so in a moment of overwhelming need to read science fiction the other evening, I snagged a novel of his in ebook form, and read it over the weekend. I loved it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Do you remember being 6? I have only the barest glimmers of it. An image will come rushing back sometimes, of something I experienced then—a moment of delight, or horror, all at once, full of sensation and bright color and feeling. Or a smell will bring something from my teenage years back: cut grass makes me think of two-a-day practices for football, without fail. But the past is behind me in a way that is hard to describe, and which I have often thought about, but rarely so much as in the days I was reading (and in the days since finished reading) this little novel about the politics of Mars and a slowly-colonizing Solar System.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because &lt;em&gt;Icehenge&lt;/em&gt;, its name notwithstanding, really isn’t much at all about a massive Stonehenge-like construction, all of ice, on Pluto. It’s about memory, and what it would be like to live to 600 in a body that ages slowly but with a mind still incapable of holding on to the past, and the stories we tell to make sense of the world, and the hunger for truth, and the things that get in the way of the pure pursuit of the truth, and power, and loneliness, and what the past means and how we get at it in the present.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I expect to be reading considerably more of KSR.&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 14 Aug 2017 21:00:00 -0400</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:v4.chriskrycho.com,2017-08-14:/2017/icehenge.html</guid><category>book reviews</category><category>science fiction</category><category>mars</category></item><item><title>Beren and Lúthien</title><link>http://v4.chriskrycho.com/2017/beren-and-luthien.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;i class=editorial&gt;I keep my book review ratings simple—they’re either &lt;em&gt;required&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;recommended&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;recommended with qualifications&lt;/em&gt;, or &lt;em&gt;not recommended&lt;/em&gt;. If you want the TL;DR, this is it:&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Recommended:&lt;/strong&gt; This is a beautiful book—not, perhaps, for everyone, but truly delightful for its intended audience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Beren and Lúthien&lt;/em&gt; is a beautiful collection detailing the progression of what was perhaps J. R. R. Tolkien’s personally most-treasured tale he wrote. This slim little volume was also likely the last of Tolkien’s works to be published by his now very-old son Christopher, who has made the history of his father’s literary creation his own latter life’s work. At 92, he is (as he notes in this volume’s foreword) unlikely to publish any more material. This was a good note to end on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But this is not a book I would hand to just anyone. As a picture of the development of one of the central tales in Tolkien’s legendarium, it is fascinating—though little of the material is new; much of it was presented already in the various histories Christopher Tolkien compiled over the past decades. For a casual reader of fantasy, or even a casual fan of Tolkien himself, it is unlikely to be interesting at all. But for those who love Tolkien’s work, and especially those who love this particular tale, this is a little treasure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The version of the tale in &lt;em&gt;The Silmarillion&lt;/em&gt; is quite beautiful in its own right—I read it aloud to Jaimie many years ago, on a night when the only thing that would calm baby Ellie was the combination of Jaimie holding her and the sound of my voice, and it made Jaimie weep. Tolkien could do that. But the version in which his elegant and lyrical tone finds its fullest expression (and the best version of the tale) is here, in &lt;em&gt;The Lay of Leithian&lt;/em&gt;. The love story in poetic form—sadly, unfinished—is utterly lovely. I couldn’t have been happier, in literary terms, than when I was reading its many lines of coupled verse.&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 09 Aug 2017 18:00:00 -0400</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:v4.chriskrycho.com,2017-08-09:/2017/beren-and-luthien.html</guid><category>book-reviews</category></item><item><title>The Book of F♯</title><link>http://v4.chriskrycho.com/2017/the-book-of-f.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;i class=editorial&gt;I keep my book review ratings simple—they’re either &lt;em&gt;required&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;recommended&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;recommended with qualifications&lt;/em&gt;, or &lt;em&gt;not recommended&lt;/em&gt;. If you want the TL;DR, this is it:&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Recommended With Qualifications:&lt;/strong&gt; This book is just okay, and at this point it’s a bit outdated—but if you’re in its fairly narrow target audience, it’s a decent way to get up to speed on F#.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Book of F♯: Breaking Free With Managed Functional Programming&lt;/em&gt; is a No Starch Press publication by Dave Fancher, published in 2014. I read it over the course of the last four or so months, just plugging away in my spare cycles. A couple qualifications on the short list of observations that follow:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol type="1"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I don’t have any experience whatsoever writing production F♯ (though I have &lt;em&gt;read&lt;/em&gt; a fair bit of it). I am interested because it’s a functional programming language on the .NET stack—which isn’t my own personal favorite stack, but &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; the stack at Olo. If we’re going to ship functional code on the server, it’ll be in F♯.&lt;a href="#fn1" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref1" role="doc-noteref"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I am also not a C♯ developer. As such, I’m &lt;em&gt;explicitly&lt;/em&gt; not the audience of this book. As Fancher put it in the intro:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wrote this book for people like me: experienced .NET developers looking to break into functional programming while retaining the safety net of the tools and libraries they’re already using.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The net of that is that a lot of what frustrated me about the book is just a result of my not being the target audience.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Those qualifications aside, some assorted thoughts on the book:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, as the intro and my above qualification suggest: this is &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; not interesting or useful as a general introduction to F♯. Throughout, it assumes a very high baseline of C♯ knowledge. In fact, the majority of the discussion of F♯, even in the section of the book which turns away from object oriented programming toward functional programming, focuses on comparing F♯ to C♯. This makes sense for the target audience, but this is &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; the book for you if you’re not a C♯ developer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That said, if you &lt;em&gt;are&lt;/em&gt; a C♯ developer, this could be a useful resource as you’re spinning up. It also might be a useful book to work through with a group of C♯ developers who want to learn F♯. The comparisons &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt; generally work in F♯’s favor, even when doing exactly what you would be doing in the C♯, which makes it an easier “sell” in that regard.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Along the same lines, the book is structured as a &lt;em&gt;very gradual&lt;/em&gt; introduction to functional programming ideas. Roughly the first half of the book emphasizes F♯’s object-oriented programming abilities, and only in the second half does Fancher turn to a functional style. Again, this is probably the right move given the audience, but it means the book spends a &lt;em&gt;lot&lt;/em&gt; of time on kinds of F♯ you won’t actually be writing very often once you’re going. Idiomatic F♯ isn’t object-oriented. But as a way of helping someone make the transition, it’s not a bad plan: object-oriented F♯ is briefer and nicer in many ways than the exact same code in C♯. It meant that the first half of the book was completely uninteresting to &lt;em&gt;me&lt;/em&gt;, though: I don’t want to write a line of object-oriented F♯.&lt;a href="#fn2" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref2" role="doc-noteref"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All of this had a pretty serious downside even for existing C♯ developers, though: the book often ends up seeming like it’s sort of apologizing for or defending F♯ against an expected audience of people asking “What’s wrong with C♯?” And even though there’s a real sense in which that’s true—that &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; what a lot of the audience is asking, no doubt—it became quite annoying rhetorically.&lt;a href="#fn3" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref3" role="doc-noteref"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; It’s also unnecessary: if someone is picking up a book on F♯, you can assume that they’re alredy at least a little interested in the language and what it might offer! Along those lines, I much prefer the tack taken in what I’ve seen of Scott Wlaschin’s upcoming &lt;em&gt;Domain Modeling Made Functional: Tackle Software Complexity with Domain-Driven Design and F♯&lt;/em&gt; (The Pragmatic Bookshelf, expected in fall 2017)—which shows not how to do the same things as in C♯, just more briefly; but how to solve the same problems much more effectively.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Those problems aside, the book was… &lt;em&gt;fine&lt;/em&gt;. I wouldn’t call it scintillating reading, but this kind of technical writing, especially at this length, is really hard work. Credit to Fancher for managing an introduction to an entire programming language in a relatively approachable way, and credit to him and his editors for making sure it remains lucid throughout. Still: I’d love to see the bar for programming books be higher. We need more books which are genuinely engaging in the world of programming language texts. These things are &lt;em&gt;interesting&lt;/em&gt;; we don’t have to make them dry and dull! (And if you want a pretty good example of that: everything I’ve read of Edwin Brady’s &lt;em&gt;Type-Driven Development with Idris&lt;/em&gt; hits the mark.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A few other observations about the language itself from reading the book.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;First,&lt;/strong&gt; reading this highlighted a lot of strange things about F♯, all of which ultimately come down to the ways F♯’s development has been driven by concerns for interoperability with C♯. Worse, there are a lot of places where the influence of C♯ casts this shadow &lt;em&gt;entirely unnecessarily&lt;/em&gt;. One particular expression of this which drove me crazy: F♯ far too often uses exceptions instead of &lt;code&gt;Option&lt;/code&gt;s. It’s &lt;a href="http://v4.chriskrycho.com/2017/better-off-using-exceptions.html"&gt;one thing&lt;/a&gt; to make sure the language gracefully handle exceptions: you &lt;em&gt;will&lt;/em&gt; have them coming from outside contexts. It is another entirely to design core parts of the language to throw exceptions where it doesn’t have to.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perhaps the most prominent example is the &lt;code&gt;List.head&lt;/code&gt; function. Its type signature is &lt;code&gt;'T list -&amp;gt; 'T&lt;/code&gt;, where I would expect it to be &lt;code&gt;'T list -&amp;gt; 'T option&lt;/code&gt;. If you call &lt;code&gt;List.head&lt;/code&gt; on an empty list, you get an exception. It would make far more sense for it to return an &lt;code&gt;Option&lt;/code&gt; and just give you &lt;code&gt;None&lt;/code&gt; if there’s no item. Then you’re not worried about &lt;code&gt;try&lt;/code&gt; expressions and the type system will actually help you! This is one of the most valuable parts of having a type system like F♯’s! I really don’t understand a lot of these decisions, not least since this isn’t for interop with C♯ collections—these are for native F♯ collections.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Second,&lt;/strong&gt; the use of things like computation expressions instead of type machinery has an interesting effect: it makes it simpler to read when you first encounter it, but harder to compose, build, etc.—and it’s more syntax to remember. Computation expressions just end up being a way to do “monadic” transformations, from what I can tell. But as I noted often in my discussion of &lt;a href="http://v4.chriskrycho.com/rust-and-swift.html"&gt;Rust and Swift&lt;/a&gt;, I profoundly prefer approaches that build on the same existing machinery—even in the surface syntax of the language—rather than constantly building new machinery. It makes it easier to deeply internalize new concepts and to &lt;em&gt;understand&lt;/em&gt; the language (rather than just being able to &lt;em&gt;use&lt;/em&gt;) the language. It also seems (from my admittedly limited vantage point) that computation expressions are as a result much less &lt;em&gt;composable&lt;/em&gt; than actual type machinery of the sort available in other languages (Haskell, Idris, etc.).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, the tradeoff there is that adding those adds a lot of complexity both to the compiler and to the libraries people are apt to write; there’s a reason Elm has totally eschewed that kind of type machinery to date. But Elm has also refused to just add syntax around ideas like this the way F♯ has here, and it makes for a much cleaner and frankly &lt;em&gt;nicer&lt;/em&gt; language.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And that brings me to my &lt;strong&gt;third and final&lt;/strong&gt; point: I’m really glad F♯ exists, and that it’s providing a pretty good experience of functional programming on the &lt;abbr title='Common Language Runtime'&gt;CLR&lt;/abbr&gt;. But—and I fully grant that a fair bit of this kind of thing is almost entirely subjective—it doesn’t &lt;em&gt;feel&lt;/em&gt; good in the same way that Elm or Rust do. There is something very difficult to nail down here, but I get a vsiceral experience of joy when writing some languages and not others. Again: that will vary person to person, but I think there are things that make it more or less likely. Things that make it more likely, at least for me, include everything from self-consistency and predictability at the semantic level to the way the code lays out and flows at the visual/syntactical level.&lt;a href="#fn4" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref4" role="doc-noteref"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;4&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; Sadly, F♯ just doesn’t hit the right notes&lt;a href="#fn5" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref5" role="doc-noteref"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;5&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; for me. I’ll be much, much happier to write it than C♯ at work… but I really just want Elm and Rust and Idris to come save the day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn1" role="doc-endnote"&gt;&lt;p&gt;I am of course writing a &lt;em&gt;lot&lt;/em&gt; of functional code in our JavaScript; JavaScript is a surprisingly good language for it.&lt;a href="#fnref1" class="footnote-back" role="doc-backlink"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn2" role="doc-endnote"&gt;&lt;p&gt;It’s not that OOP is &lt;em&gt;bad&lt;/em&gt;, exactly; it’s just that what passes for OOP in languages like C♯, Java, and yes, F♯, is relatively low utility to me—and I think OOP ideas are much more interesting and useful when applied at a systems level, e.g. in an Actor system, than at the level of individual “actors” within the system. Compare Erlang/Elixir: functional components, organized in what is arguably an &lt;em&gt;incredibly&lt;/em&gt; object-oriented way.&lt;a href="#fnref2" class="footnote-back" role="doc-backlink"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn3" role="doc-endnote"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The temptation extends beyond this book; O’Reilly’s &lt;em&gt;Programming Rust&lt;/em&gt; (Jim Blandy and Jason Orendorff) reads as the same kind of defensive introduction to Rust for C++ developers.&lt;a href="#fnref3" class="footnote-back" role="doc-backlink"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn4" role="doc-endnote"&gt;&lt;p&gt;And yes, nerds, syntax &lt;em&gt;does&lt;/em&gt; matter. Try reading this sentence, nicely punctuated, and with spaces and capitalization. Now: tryreadingthissentencewithoutpunctuationorspacesorcapitalization. There may be a point after which it becomes less important, and a range of things which are equally good in an absolute sense, but it matters.&lt;a href="#fnref4" class="footnote-back" role="doc-backlink"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn5" role="doc-endnote"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Pun not intended, but inevitable given the language names here.&lt;a href="#fnref5" class="footnote-back" role="doc-backlink"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 21 Jul 2017 19:30:00 -0400</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:v4.chriskrycho.com,2017-07-21:/2017/the-book-of-f.html</guid><category>book-reviews</category><category>programming languages</category><category>fsharp</category><category>writing</category><category>pedagogy</category></item><item><title>Thinking, Fast and Slow: A Review</title><link>http://v4.chriskrycho.com/2017/thinking-fast-and-slow-a-review.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;I keep my book review ratings simple—they’re either &lt;em&gt;required&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;recommended&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;recommended with qualifications&lt;/em&gt;, or &lt;em&gt;not recommended&lt;/em&gt;. If you want the TL;DR, this is it:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Recommended:&lt;/strong&gt; Kahneman is a talented writer, has a fascinating research history, and makes a good case; there’s a lot to learn here, and the quibbles I have are just that: quibbles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ve heard &lt;em&gt;very&lt;/em&gt; good things about Daniel Kahneman’s &lt;em&gt;Thinking, Fast and Slow&lt;/em&gt;, so when friends asked what they might get me for my birthday, it came to mind quickly. I didn’t spend long second-guessing the choice, and it’s not one I’ve regretted in the least (even though I have my differences with the book). That experience—an immediate choice, based on some degree of prior knowledge (but not &lt;em&gt;that&lt;/em&gt; much); followed by basic continuation along the same judgment without giving it much further thought—is itself representative of many of the themes of the book. How do we choose? What makes us decide the things we do, and why? How can we make better decisions? Why do we so often make irrational choices, and so quickly, over and against what we might choose if we slowed down to think through our decisions?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Thinking, Fast and Slow&lt;/em&gt; takes up all of those questions and runs with them. Kahneman, a Nobel Prize winner in economics but himself a psychologist by training and decades of practice, produced here a popularization of decades of research on how people think. His basic thesis is that we have two systems of thought: One is quick to the point of immediacy and even functioning unconsciously, intuitionist or heuristic in nature, and extremely effective and reliable for &lt;em&gt;many&lt;/em&gt; situations—but because it is intuitionist or heuristic, also biased in certain predictable ways. The other is much slower, but capable of careful and rational consideration, not prone to the same kinds of mistakes as the first but also substantially more work to engage and itself readily enough misled by the judgments we make with that first system of thinking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the first quarter or so of the book, Kahneman makes his case that these two systems actually do characterize human thought, at least in broad strokes. And it’s a good case that he makes. Many of the examples he cites I was readily enough able to see playing out in my own mind, whether in real-time or by reflecting on past decision-making and judgment-making instances. This is also the part of the book on the strongest research ground, from what I can tell as an outsider. On the whole, I came away convinced of that basic theme. Whatever other places I differ with him, and there are a few, I &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt; recommend the book for its first quarter at a minimum.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The latter parts of the book shift into examinations of specific ways that those two systems-of-thinking actually play out in practice, and here the material, though still strong overall, was a great deal more arguable. Much of this draws heavily on studies in psychology—and some of those studies have since run into some really serious problems with reproducibility. So much so that Kahneman—himself a popularizer rather than a producer of those specific experiments—wrote an open letter to the community of researchers asking them to do the hard work of either reproducing their results or walking back their claims.&lt;a href="#fn1" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref1" role="doc-noteref"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; As such, even if I agreed with Kahneman philosophically throughout (and I don’t; more on that in a moment), there would be some gaps in the final section of the book.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Beyond some of these kinds of overall weaknesses, there’s also a downside to the rhetorical approach Kahneman takes. Throughout, he adopts an extremely conversational style, addressing the reader quite directly. As such, many of his claims take the form “You did &lt;em&gt;something&lt;/em&gt; when you encountered &lt;em&gt;some test&lt;/em&gt; in the text.” Many of these work and prove accurate… but quite a few of them don’t, too. The specifics will differ for everyone, of course, based on how well-trained they are at certain kinds of reasoning, their backgrounds, their ethical systems, and the like. But it happens, and it happened to me fairly often during the course of reading the book. One of the most striking examples was near the end, where Kahneman was trying to show that we often will assign different values to given things when evaluated independently than when evaluated side-by-side. He made there a claim about what the reader did or didn’t do in evaluating the needs of humans vs. evaluating the need for dolphins—specifically, that the specific valuation of humans over dolphins didn’t emerge until the two were compared more directly. But it &lt;em&gt;did&lt;/em&gt; for me; it was the first thought I had. I’ll grant his broader point, of course, and I don’t doubt that in many cases the studies he cites represent real tendencies. I can certainly think of &lt;em&gt;other&lt;/em&gt; scenarios where a similar kind of comparison might break down. But it’s an interesting place where the conversational style breaks down: you can only assert so much and get away with it. On the other hand, a book full of questions of the “Did you think &lt;em&gt;something&lt;/em&gt;?” sort would get old quickly. This is a hard line to walk, and on the whole I think the style worked—but it had that nagging weakness, which stuck out to me fairly frequently when reading the book.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also found, unsurprisingly, that Kahneman and I differ fairly strongly in our view of both ethics and human nature. On the whole, this didn’t directly impact my appreciation of the book. On occasion, however, his view of human nature diverged quite sharply from the Christian view. In particular, he left little room for the idea of our nature being &lt;em&gt;designed&lt;/em&gt; to have certain kinds of limitations about it and majored heavily on rationalism as &lt;em&gt;ideal&lt;/em&gt;. I don’t think strict rationalism &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; in fact ideal, and whereas he contents himself with describing &lt;a href="http://www.claremont.org/crb/article/econs-and-humans/"&gt;Econs&lt;/a&gt; as an &lt;em&gt;incomplete&lt;/em&gt; view of how humans work (but one that he often refers to in rather aspirational ways), I would go much further: it would in fact be &lt;em&gt;wrong&lt;/em&gt; for humans to act as the purely “rational” agents of much standard economic theory, because that kind of rationalism is in fact merely a particular brand of utilitarianism. I’d go further still and say that utilitarianism is itself a kind of irrationality, and that one of the ways human nature continues to function as a divine image is in our deep-seated and nearly inescapable distinguishing between kinds of things that economists tell us are of &lt;em&gt;equal utility&lt;/em&gt;: for so they may be, but there is more to God’s green earth than the uses to which we may put it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But important though those differences are, they are also far afield of the thesis and even the majority emphasis of the book. Indeed, precisely because it does acknowledge so clearly the way humans actually work, the book can serve as a helpful entry-point for conversation about the limits of utilitarianism. If utility is not a perfect description of how humans do work, perhaps it also behooves us to consider if it’s a good description of how we &lt;em&gt;ought&lt;/em&gt; to work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More than that, the book as a whole is a genuinely good and insightful volume. Many of the kinds of biases and errors Kahneman point out are unarguably problems—and many of them contribute significantly to systematic issues in the world at large. Being more aware of how our ability to think clearly and rightly degrades when we are, say, tired and hungry, should make us think carefully about assigning a judge a long docket of cases to sentence: why should two men who committed the same crime get different punishments simply because one received his sentence in the morning when the judge was alert and fresh off her breakfast and coffee, and the other late in the morning when she was feeling hungry and drained? There are not easy solutions to these kinds of problems, but we cannot even begin to address them unless we know they exist in the first place. Similarly, at a personal level, knowing these things about ourselves can help us be aware of where we’re vulnerable to them and adjust accordingly—whether by aiming to increase our awareness of them situation-by-situation, or (better) by making careful choices when able to do so which we can then lean on in the situations where we have to make snap judgments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There’s a lot more to say about that latter point, not least on the topic of Christian formation, discipleship, and catechesis. But that’s for another post. Read at least the first section of &lt;em&gt;Thinking, Fast and Slow&lt;/em&gt;: you’ll profit from it, and you’ll enjoy it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn1" role="doc-endnote"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Hat tip to &lt;a href="https://srconstantin.wordpress.com/2017/06/27/in-defense-of-individualist-culture/"&gt;Sarah Constantin&lt;/a&gt; for bringing that letter to my attention. Her &lt;a href="https://srconstantin.wordpress.com"&gt;blog&lt;/a&gt; is well worth your time in general: you’ll learn from her even when you disagree with her, as I often do.)&lt;a href="#fnref1" class="footnote-back" role="doc-backlink"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 11 Jul 2017 20:30:00 -0400</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:v4.chriskrycho.com,2017-07-11:/2017/thinking-fast-and-slow-a-review.html</guid><category>books</category><category>book-reviews</category></item><item><title>An Apology and a Hermeneutic</title><link>http://v4.chriskrycho.com/2015/an-apology-and-a-hermeneutic.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Jesus and the Victory of God: Christian Origins and the Question of God, Volume Two&lt;/em&gt;, by N. T. Wright, Minneapolis: Fortress, 1996, 741 pages. Reviewed by Christopher Krycho.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section id="introduction" class="level2"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Few books can claim to represent a substantive entry in both apologetics and hermeneutics, yet this is precisely what N. T. Wright’s &lt;em&gt;Jesus and the Victory of God&lt;/em&gt; accomplishes. In this book, the second in Wright’s massive work on Christians origins,&lt;a href="#fn1" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref1" role="doc-noteref"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; he treats the question of the historical Jesus via a thorough survey of the modern history of interpretation and the contents of the synoptic gospels themselves. The result is a telling well within historic Christian orthodoxy, though often at sharp angles to current historical approaches to Jesus. Along the way, he also marks out a fruitful interpretive path for Christians reading the gospels. The picture he paints of Jesus—a first-century prophet-Messiah who saw himself standing at the capstone of Israel’s history, fulfilling Yahweh’s plans for his people, but in a way no one in his day seemed to expect—is both apologetically compelling and spiritually illuminating.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="overview" class="level2"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Overview&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wright begins with an introduction designed to orient the reader to the basic challenges confronting any would-be interpreter of Jesus in the modern era. Critical issues abound, and it is impossible to return to a pre-critical reading of the text. But though the historian must deal with any number of problems in interpreting the person of Jesus, these problems are not specific to him; they are endemic to the task of history.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wright therefore begins by establishing his criteria for evaluating interpretations of Jesus’ person and program. Any such theory must account for the transition from Judaism to Christianity; it must therefore present Jesus, the lynchpin of that transformation, as not only &lt;em&gt;dissimilar&lt;/em&gt; to both worldviews, but also &lt;em&gt;similar&lt;/em&gt; to both (132). Jesus must have made sense to his Jewish contemporaries, but also profoundly theologically innovative, to create an entirely new community with its own theology and practice. Wright argues Jesus accomplished this via a program in which “[the] symbolic world of first-century Judaism has been rethought from top to bottom, even while its underlying theology (monotheism, election, and eschatology) has been retained” (218)—with Jesus himself at the center of the plan of Israel’s god, uniquely embodying a father-son relationship with &lt;span class="divine-name tetragrammaton"&gt;YHWH&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He argues this thesis in two major parts, one focusing on the work and teachings of Jesus as a messianic prophet, the other focusing on the Jesus’ aims and beliefs as he carried out his program. Along the way, Wright examines a wide and representative sample of Jesus’ reported deeds and teachings. In each case, the data fits the thesis: Jesus was retelling Israel’s story in a new way, with himself at the center of God’s plan to end his people’s long exile. By the end of the volume, Wright can thus conclude:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[Jesus] believed himself called, by Israel’s god, to &lt;em&gt;evoke&lt;/em&gt; the traditions which promised &lt;span class="divine-name tetragrammaton"&gt;YHWH&lt;/span&gt;’s return to Zion, and the somewhat more nebulous but still important traditions which spoke of a human figure sharing the divine throne; to &lt;em&gt;enact&lt;/em&gt; those traditions in his own journey to Jerusalem, his messianic act in the Temple, and his death at the hands of the pagans (in the hope of subsequent vindication); and thereby to &lt;em&gt;embody&lt;/em&gt; &lt;span class="divine-name tetragrammaton"&gt;YHWH&lt;/span&gt;’s return. (651)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is not a simple restatement of typical Christian belief, though of course it accords with it. It goes further, making sense of Jesus’ words and deeds in a way that meets Wright’s criterion of double dissimilarity and double similarity. The thesis passes the test.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="assessment" class="level2"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Assessment&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wright’s volume has much to commend it: its historical method, its thoroughness, its broad engagement with opposing views, even its style. Its most significant contributions, though, fall under two basic headings: a challenge to many modern (atheological or even anti-theological) re-readings of the gospels, and a challenge to many current evangelical interpretation of the gospels. Both of these are successful in large measure because of Wright’s care (and flare) in dealing with the material and with other (contrary) treatments of the same data, but it is Wright’s ability to build cogent arguments with that material on this scale which makes this more than a tedious summary of data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Against secular, demythologizing, and materialist interpretations of the text, Wright mounts a serious and substantive case for a traditional (though not uncritical) assessment of the historical reliability of the synoptics and their picture of Jesus. Many critics suppose that the picture of Jesus painted by the gospellers must be anachronistic, ideologically-driven or situationally-motivated, or inflated by faith in contradistinction to history. Such readings of Jesus paint him as any variety of figures: a sadly-mistaken apocalyptic prophet; a Stoic philosopher in first century garb; a preacher of progressive ideas of love and tolerance; the author of a new, non-Jewish religion; a preacher of Jewish (or timeless) verities. One suspects, with Wright, that many of these readings find their source not in the text but in the prejudices or preferences of the commentators. Wright’s argument, by contrast, is far more credible than any of these—and not simply because it aligns with the historic confession of Jesus as Messiah and Lord. Rather, his picture of a distinctly Jewish apocalyptic prophet makes the best sense of the actual evidence from the earliest texts, including not only the synoptic gospels but also the early epistles and even the non-canonical literature like the Gospel of Thomas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second major value of the book is its (usually, but not always, quiet) challenge to many &lt;em&gt;Christian&lt;/em&gt; readings of the gospels. Wright accurately notes that many Christian interpreters, perhaps especially in the Protestant tradition, have struggled to make sense of the gospels. Many evangelical readings of the gospels find little or no connection between what Jesus said and did and his crucifixion and resurrection. Indeed, no few of the commentaries this author has read sturggle to make much of the Pharisees’ and Sadducees’ mutual hostility toward Jesus without reducing them to caricatures, or to make sense of many of the parables or their role in Jesus’ ministry. The interpretation Wright proposes accounts for all these issues, and provides a helpful hermeneutic for untangling many of the otherwise perplexing passages in the gospels.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wright’s work thus walks a helpful middle ground between misinterpretations on either side. Anachronistic tendencies among both secular and Christians interpreters lead both astray. He was not a modern progressive, nor an unfortunately mistaken apocalyptic street preacher, nor a teller of timeless ethical truths, nor a preacher of a new religion of grace oddly disconnected from Judaism. Rather, he was a Jewish prophet going about the business of offering a subversive interpretation—though one deeply in touch with the Law and Prophets—of &lt;span class="divine-name tetragrammaton"&gt;YHWH&lt;/span&gt;’s promises to his. This is unsurprising. After all, this is precisely how the gospels present Jesus: dissimilar in certain ways from both the Judaism that preceded him and the Christianity that followed him (again: Wright’s criteria of double dissimilarity). Any telling of the historical Jesus must provide an explanation for the transition from Second Temple Judaism to Christianity, and do so on historically plausible grounds. So must any right interpretation of the gospels for Christian piety. Wright’s theory accomplishes this handily.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perhaps even more important is the way in which Wright’s work strikes at a kind of nascent docetism among many Christians. While Jesus’ full humanity may be an article of faith for orthodox believers, many fail to think of what exactly that means. Jesus was not merely as a divine mystery speaking timeless truths and then fulfilling a cruciform commission strangely disconnected from his parable-telling, paralytic-healing ministry. Rather, he was a &lt;em&gt;man&lt;/em&gt; standing at the conclusion the line of Jewish men who had called Israel back to faithfulness and proclaimed that Israel’s God was about saving the whole world. Not only does Wright have a Chalcedonian Christology, he is &lt;em&gt;more&lt;/em&gt; orthodox than many believers: the Jesus painted in this portrait is no less human than divine. Jesus’ sense of vocation, his real temptations and struggles to fulfill that vocation, and even his not-rare, but unconventionally-embodied, claim to Messiahship were the actions of a first-century Jewish &lt;em&gt;man&lt;/em&gt;. To see this clearly is to see exactly what the Fathers meant in their confession of “our Lord Jesus Christ, the same perfect in Godhead and manhood, truly God and truly man… consubstantial with us according to the Manhood, in all things like unto us, without sin…”&lt;a href="#fn2" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref2" role="doc-noteref"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; To miss it is to risk missing the humanity of Christ in all its glory.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="application-and-conclusion" class="level2"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Application and Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wright’s work is to be commended on a number of levels. Its scholarly depth makes it a formidable resource when discussing the historical Jesus, particularly with those who reject the gospels’ claims to present Jesus accurately. Wright’s enjoyable wit makes the length of the work far more manageable. His proposed hermeneutic, though it can be pressed too far, provides a helpful tool for interpreting the synoptics. Most of all, his reminder of the real and true humanity of Jesus is a sharp rejoinder to the functional docetism all too common in evangelicalism. The book is therefore very helpful for both apologetics and exegesis. Whatever their other differences with Wright, pastors and teachers would do well to digest Wright’s work here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn1" role="doc-endnote"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The New Testament and the People of God&lt;/em&gt;; &lt;em&gt;Jesus and the Victory of God&lt;/em&gt;; &lt;em&gt;The Resurrection of the Son of God&lt;/em&gt;; and &lt;em&gt;Paul and the Faithfulness of God&lt;/em&gt; (in two volumes).&lt;a href="#fnref1" class="footnote-back" role="doc-backlink"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn2" role="doc-endnote"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Chalcedonian Definition.&lt;a href="#fnref2" class="footnote-back" role="doc-backlink"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 01 Dec 2015 09:00:00 -0500</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:v4.chriskrycho.com,2015-12-01:/2015/an-apology-and-a-hermeneutic.html</guid><category>M. Div.</category><category>SEBTS</category><category>papers</category><category>book reviews</category></item><item><title>Spirit Empowered Preaching</title><link>http://v4.chriskrycho.com/2015/spirit-empowered-preaching.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Arturo G. Azurdia III spent several decades preaching and pastoring. He was thus well-experienced in the week-to-week work of preparing sermons and the burden of caring for a congregation. During his years of pastoral work, however, he also studied at Westminster Theological Seminary; he was at the time of the book’s publication a professor at Western Seminary. Thus, he also brought to the table academic knowledge helpful for situating his developing understanding of the role of the Holy Spirit in a preaching ministry. Accordingly, Azurdia brings both Scripture and experience to bear in &lt;em&gt;Spirit Empowered Preaching&lt;/em&gt;: the lessons he learned in seminary, he then applied in the context of his ongoing ministry, and was able to filter his experience through careful reflection on the Scriptures. &lt;em&gt;Spirit Empowered Preaching&lt;/em&gt; was published not at the beginning of that career, but after considerable time behind the pulpit of an ordinary church, after he had moved into a teaching role.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Azurdia’s aim in &lt;em&gt;Spirit Empowered Preaching&lt;/em&gt; is twofold: to demonstrate the necessity of the Holy Spirit’s work in the preacher for effective preaching, and to describe how the preacher should go about seeking the Spirit’s work in his preaching. He argues in his introduction that “the greatest deficiency in contemporary expositional ministry is powerlessness; in other words, preaching that is devoid of the vitality of the Holy Spirit” (12). That is, although right preaching necessarily entails careful exegesis and attention to the “literal, grammatical, historical, contextual, redemptive” details of a text (11), no amount of mere intellectual study on its own will accomplish God’s purposes for preaching. If the church is to be encouraged, challenged, and built up; and if outsiders are to be convicted, the Holy Spirit must be present and working efficaciously through the preacher. Only the Spirit can change human hearts. This was true for the early church, and it is true today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Azurdia lays out his thesis in a brief introduction. Following that, he does not simply repeat the thesis chapter by chapter, however. Instead, he builds a broader theology of preaching and connects the different elements of the preaching ministry back to the central theme of the text. Thus, in Chapter 1, he starts by arguing that the “greater works” the disciples would do were the advancement of the gospel through the nations, and notes how Christ explicitly tied this to the coming of the promised Holy Spirit. The advance of the gospel was for the disciples, and is for modern preachers, utterly dependent on the work of God. Chapter 2 describes who the Spirit is and what he does in the life of the minister—and what goes wrong in the ministry when the Spirit is neglected. In Chapter 3, Azurdia argues for Christocentric preaching, since the Spirit is &lt;em&gt;Christ’s&lt;/em&gt; Spirit and glorifies him. Chapter 4 carries this theme further: the priority of every preacher must be glorifying Christ, not merely meeting the felt needs of the people. Every topic must be heard in light of the finished work of the Savior, not standing on its own as abstract ethical instruction. In Chapter 5, he argues that the first responsibility of both the minister and the church is preaching—and that, as such, the church should understand when the pastor spends most of his time preparing for sermon delivery, rather than on other concerns. Here he also takes time to critique ministry methodologies which do not align with the gospel, especially those in many seeker-sensitive churches which have run to extremes of entertainment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Chapter 6, Azurdia comes to the core of his message: the preacher must be both generally filled with the Spirit (i.e. regenerate) and specifically filled time and again by the Spirit for preaching. Here he draws upon the frequent language of being “filled with the Holy Spirit” in Acts as well as the affirmations of preachers like Martyn Lloyd Jones. Chapter 7 is an examination of the flip-side of the necessity of the Spirit’s filling: the frustration of the pastor’s own inability. If the work of the Spirit is utterly essential for preaching to have any effect whatsoever, then all the pastor’s efforts may be for naught. This may lead to either despair (for the self-dependent man) or greater faith (for the man who trusts Christ).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Chapter 8, Azurdia turns to the nature and life of a man called to this ministry: he “&lt;em&gt;must devote himself to a consistent pattern of fervent intercession&lt;/em&gt;” (135, emphasis original). That the Spirit must be present for preaching to be effective is not grounds for pastors to abdicate their own responsibility. Rather, it increases their responsibility to pray for the Spirit to work through their preaching. Chapter 9 continues this focus on the life of the preacher. He must be prayerful, diligent in study, and prayerful in his study. He must remember in all this prayer that the Spirit is not a &lt;em&gt;tool&lt;/em&gt; but a &lt;em&gt;person&lt;/em&gt;, someone who can be grieved. The preacher must keep himself holy, and so must his congregation—because either may drive away the Spirit by their unrepentance. Chapter 10 illustrates and emphasizes this necessity of prayer in the life of both preacher and congregation. Finally, Azurdia briefly summarizes his argument: “&lt;em&gt;Spirit empowered preaching is the principle means of advancing the kingdom of God…. will be evangelical in emphasis…. is the responsibility of the church&lt;/em&gt;” (179–181, emphasis original).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The book is persuasive and thorough, but neither as effective or as persuasive as it might have been. Azurdia’s comments on the “greater ministry” the disciples were to have are perhaps the most helpful material in the book. In general, his attention to the roles the Spirit plays in the life of the church is a helpful corrective both to the neglect the Spirit often receives from non-charismatic churches and the misinterpretations proffered by many in the charismatic movement. Likewise, his call to prayerful as well as well-studied preaching is a helpful reminder especially for preachers tempted to rely on their own intellectual merits. Gladly, and unlike E. M. Bounds’ work on prayer, he does so without ever denigrating the value of intellectual engagement and deep study. Azurdia’s counsel to study hard, pray hard, and pray during the time of study is well-taken. Those who preach should devote meaningful parts of their preparation time not only to exegesis but to fellowship with God by &lt;em&gt;prayerful&lt;/em&gt; interaction with the text.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perhaps the greatest strength of the book is Azurdia’s emphasis on the nature and person of the Spirit. As noted above, he refuses to indulge in the mistaken charismatic emphases on the miraculous gifts over the more central work of the Spirit: revealing Christ. All the focus on sign gifts can quickly lead people to forget that the Spirit was sent to make Christ known and glorify him. His diagnostic question is extremely helpful (and not only for evaluating charismatics, but for evaluating anyone claiming God’s hand on his ministry): “&lt;em&gt;Does this ministry reveal and glorify Jesus Christ?&lt;/em&gt;” (50, emphasis original). Again, the Spirit is the spirit of truth, sent by the Father to empower the church to know and make known the Son. As such, no ministry which claims the Spirit’s power but focuses on anything other than knowing and proclaiming Christ is legitimate. At the same time, this does not mean the church should shun the Spirit to avoid those missteps—rather, the church should point to a better understanding of the Spirit’s mission, and respond in faith. A church that understands the Spirit’s proclamatory and instructing role will follow Azurdia’s counsel and dedicate itself to prayer, cognizant that apart from the Spirit the church and her pastor can do nothing. Congregations should also learn to ask that same question of &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; sermons and preachers and experiences: does it reveal and glorify Jesus Christ?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, weaknesses emerge in a number of areas which substantially lessen the book’s impact. First, Azurdia makes the same move many Reformed and evangelical preachers do, elevating the preaching of the word to the primary (and nearly the sole) responsibility of the preacher. This move seems unwarranted in light of the distinction between ordinary pastors and the apostles on whose actions (in Acts 6) the view is grounded. As such, Azurdia simply passed over the many other responsibilities enjoined of shepherds in the pastoral epistles. To be sure, preaching is a necessity in the life of the church. However, it is only one of the pastor’s responsibilities, and he will find it difficult to carry it out effectively if he is not sharing life with his sheep. Thus, pastors ought to dedicate much of their time to &lt;em&gt;shepherding&lt;/em&gt;: to caring for the ordinary soulish needs of their people and not only for the times of preaching. This is doctrinally necessary, and practically helpful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More problematic was Azurdia’s conflation of the Spirit’s filling with an experience or sense of that filling. Like Lloyd-Jones and others he cites, Azurdia describes the anointing or unction of the Spirit as a particular sense the preacher and congregation have of the Spirit’s working through him in a unique way. Curiously, Azurdia also affirms that there may be times the Spirit is moving powerfully but the preacher is unaware of it, as in the common case of a man who preached and felt it accomplished nothing but heard later from members of his congregation how the Spirit used it in their lives. Too often in evangelicalism, &lt;em&gt;feeling&lt;/em&gt; is mistaken for &lt;em&gt;reality&lt;/em&gt;. Nowhere in the New Testament is the Spirit’s presence described in terms of a feeling in the preacher. Rather, it is born out by the effects of the preaching. To be sure, the Spirit may graciously grant the pastor a clear sense of his presence and power on some days, and that sense is a blessing. However, the absence of such a sense does not indicate the Spirit’s absence; neither does a strong feeling necessarily indicate his presence in power. In encouraging pastors to think in these terms, Azurdia ultimately plants seeds of discouragement in the lives of those who may preach diligently and prayerfully—and effectively—for many years without that particular experience, which is promised no one. As he notes of many experiences in charismatic circles, “we need to be concerned that the spiritual development of well-meaning Christians can become vulnerable to the law of diminishing returns… Often, the inevitable consequence is spiritual emptiness” (49). This is no less a danger for the preacher expecting a strong internal sense of anointing than for the believer wanting a fresh anointing for speaking in tongues. Preachers should indeed dedicate themselves to prayer and come with an expectation that they can accomplish nothing on their own, but they should reject as unbiblical and unhelpful the idea that their internal sense of the Spirit’s presence is accurate or indicative of his work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Still, on the whole, Azurdia’s point is well-taken. The church desperately needs the Holy Spirit for her efficacy in ministry. Lives will not change unless God works: sermons will fall on deaf ears, and congregations’ ministries may produce physically helpful outcomes while leaving sinners damned. Preachers and their people must recover prayerful dependence on the third person of the Trinity. They must ask constantly of their ministries, “Does this show Christ clearly and make him look glorious?” They must plead for the Spirit to come and work. But (contra Azurdia) they must never mistake their perceived experience of the Spirit for the actual work of the Spirit.&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 08 Sep 2015 12:05:00 -0400</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:v4.chriskrycho.com,2015-09-08:/2015/spirit-empowered-preaching.html</guid><category>M. Div.</category><category>SEBTS</category><category>papers</category><category>book reviews</category></item><item><title>Be Holy!</title><link>http://v4.chriskrycho.com/2014/be-holy.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;i class="editorial"&gt;I would like to preface the following review by noting that Andy Davis is not just any author, and indeed not just any pastor. He is one of &lt;em&gt;my&lt;/em&gt; pastors. This makes the task of writing a critical book review somewhat strange. On the one hand, I wanted to write this review as I would any such. On the other hand, I wanted to take care to show respect to a man whom God has used to shepherd me and my family for the past two years since we moved to North Carolina, and whom I regard very highly for his faithfulness in serving the church gathered as First Baptist Church of Durham. I hope I have struck the balance appropriately. And as I hope will become clear, though there were a few places where this book could be stronger, it is nonetheless extraordinarily valuable. I have been challenged and indeed have grown in holiness because of having read it. I commend it to you.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;An Infinite Journey: Growing toward Christlikeness&lt;/em&gt;, by Andrew M. Davis, Greenville: Ambassador International, 2014, 480 pages.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section id="overview" class="level2"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Overview&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Andrew Davis’ &lt;em&gt;An Infinite Journey&lt;/em&gt; is a careful, thorough, heavy exploration of the doctrine and practice of sanctification in the Christian life. Davis, the long-time pastor of First Baptist Church in Durham, North Carolina and an adjunct professor at nearby Southeastern Baptist Theological Seminary, has clearly dedicated considerable time and consideration to the topic of holiness and growth in the Christian life, and this consideration is on display throughout what is ultimately a very helpful book.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Davis begins by introducing the concepts which permeate the rest of the book: the saving work of God in Christ and the Christian’s lasting dependence on the Holy Spirit. Perhaps surprisingly (at least to the casual reader), he opens not with the topic of sanctification, but with justification, arguing that all real Christian growth must be predicated on a right understanding of the gospel. Thus, he spends some time tracing out the story of salvation, culminating in Christ’s atoning death on the cross and resurrection, and his institution of the church and sending the Holy Spirit to save and then shape the internal lives of Christians throughout the ages. He further argues that all Christians are involved in two “infinite journeys”—the external journey of evangelism and discipleship, and the internal journey of growth in holiness. Both, he notes, are essential for the health of the Christian: to be deficient in either is to demonstrate either ignorance or hard-heartedness toward the things of God.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After this introduction, Davis turns to a map of the second of these journeys: the internal path of growing Christ-likeness. His thesis is that sanctification is a four-part process, involving a continuous sequence of knowledge, faith, character, and action, each feeding into the next. Knowledge of God produces faith; increasing faith produces Christlike character; a more Christlike character results in more Godward actions; and those Godward actions in turn lead to a greater knowledge of God himself. Davis dedicates a section of the book to each of these ideas, examining in detail Scriptural support for the concept and then examples of the element in the lives of figures in Scripture, especially Christ. Finally, he turns to a section dedicated to application, looking at the knowledge-faith-character-action cycle as a whole in both Scripture and a variety of day-to-day scenarios.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="analysis" class="level2"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Analysis&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Davis’ treatment of the doctrines of sanctification is thorough and compelling, most of all because it is drenched in Scripture. Early in the book, Davis explicitly spells out his commitment to the centrality, sufficiency, and authority of Scripture, and the text of the book backs this up. It is common to hear authors affirm the importance of Scripture; it is rare to see it so born out so clearly in their writing. Even apart from the explicit references on nearly every page, the text bears the unmistakable imprint of Davis’ own practice of memorizing books of the Bible. Allusions, near quotes, and implicit references to Scripture appear multiple times on nearly every page.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This Scriptural emphasis leads to the book’s other great strengths. First, Davis makes no point without basing the assertion on Scripture, and he draws on every section of the Bible to demonstrate the importance of each aspect of his map for growth in holiness. Moreover, he follows Scripture’s lead in grounding sanctification in the work of Christ mediated to us by the Holy Spirit. Davis’ emphasis on the work of the Spirit is especially helpful. Though he is by no means a charismatic in the modern sense of the word, it is clear that he is gripped by the reality that sanctification simply does not happen without the work of the Holy Spirit. This is an essential corrective for two kinds of churches: those tempted to ignore the Spirit, and those tempted to ignore all the works of the Spirit apart from those that result in visible signs. Rightly, Davis’ doctrine of sanctification is trinitarian: holy people whole-heartedly worship the Father in Spirit-empowered dependence on the finished work of the Son.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Second, this Scriptural care allows Davis to navigate the difficult topic of Spirit-dependent human effort that characterizes Biblical sanctification. Because sanctification is the one aspect of salvation in which people are called to work (e.g. in Phil. 2:12), many believers are tempted to treat sanctification as a wholly human endeavor. Davis repudiates this notion, showing again and again that sanctification—like the justification that precedes it and the glorification that will follow it—is ultimately a work of God and one that brings him all glory. No person will be able to claim the credit for their own sanctification before God at the day of judgment. At the same time, he also rejects a Keswickian spirituality (“let go and let God”), even when dressed up as mere gospel dependence. However much in vogue the notion may be that we can do nothing and God does everything for us, it is simply not true. God requires us actively to seek him and his holiness. Davis rightly recognizes both these dangers and charts a course between them. The pursuit of holiness is empowered by the Holy Spirit, and believers must always fix their eyes on the finished work of Christ and the promise of future glory. Yet believers keep their eyes on Christ and rely on the Spirit &lt;em&gt;to work&lt;/em&gt;—not to sit still and trust God to float them toward holiness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The book does have a few weaknesses. First, although the book’s length and thoroughness are valuable in many ways, they also make this a difficult sell for anyone who is not already a dedicated reader. Moreover, while much of the length was inevitable in a work this thorough on a topic this complex, the book could be substantially shorter were it edited more carefully. Trimming the lengthy introduction and removing some repetition, unnecessary explanations, and clarifications would make the work stronger as well as shorter and more approachable. Given Davis’ goals—to stir up believers to pursuing holiness—this would be profoundly helpful, as it would allow for the book to be used in a broader variety of contexts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Second, a number of Davis’ references to words’ meanings in Greek are either extraneous or inaccurate. In particular, he regularly committed the so-called etymological fallacy, ascribing meaning to words based on their components rather than their actual use in the language. (This led him several times to disagree with every modern major translation!) He also sometimes referenced English words derived from Greek terms, but in cases where the derivation is irrelevant to the present meaning of the English word (e.g. &lt;em&gt;poem&lt;/em&gt; from &lt;em&gt;poiema&lt;/em&gt;). Gladly, no major issues in the text hung on these cases. Nonetheless, the misuses were distracting, and since in most cases they were also unnecessary, they actually &lt;em&gt;weakened&lt;/em&gt; the book for me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That these are the only significant issues in such a large and thorough book is a significant achievement, and both could readily be addressed in future editions of the work. Taken as a whole, Davis’ book shines. As Davis points out, holiness necessarily entails both knowledge of the things of God and zeal for his glory. The book drips with Davis’ passion for God and his urgent desire that God’s people seek holiness, and it lays out a thoughtful and (most importantly) Scriptural plan for how his people shall become holy. Lord willing, the volume will be a reliable guide to sanctification for the church for years to come.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note on publication:&lt;/strong&gt; This paper was first published online on January 1, 2015. However, I wrote this and submitted it in mid-December, and have backdated it accordingly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 10 Dec 2014 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:v4.chriskrycho.com,2014-12-10:/2014/be-holy.html</guid><category>M. Div.</category><category>SEBTS</category><category>FBC Durham</category><category>papers</category><category>book reviews</category></item><item><title>Halfway to His Own Thesis</title><link>http://v4.chriskrycho.com/2014/halfway-to-his-own-thesis.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;cite&gt;Five Smooth Stones for Pastoral Work&lt;/cite&gt;, by Eugene H. Peterson. Grand Rapids: Eerdmans, 1980. 241 pp. $20.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section id="overview" class="level2"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Overview&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In &lt;em&gt;Five Smooth Stones for Pastoral Work&lt;/em&gt;, Eugene Peterson advocates for a biblically grounded rather than psychologically-driven approach to pastoral work. He argues that the idea that pastors must first of all be up to date and current has things precisely backwards: the pastor’s responsibility is to lead his congregation back to timeless realities, not into the hippest fads of the day. He suggests that the &lt;em&gt;Megilloth&lt;/em&gt;, the “five scrolls” of Songs of Songs, Ruth, Lamentations, Ecclesiastes, and Esther, have particular lessons to teach pastors as they seek to bring “what is essential in the human condition, not what is accicental” (p. 2) down into the “idiosyncrasies of the local and the personal” (p. 5). A failure either to hold fast to the eternal word and will of God, or to bring it home to those to whom the pastor ministers, will leave the people without what they most deeply need: a shepherd through the vagaries and trials of life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Peterson provides a substantial introduction to the book (some ten percent or so of the book’s text), in which he traces out his thesis in detail. He then divides the rest of the book into five discussions of pastoral work, grounding each in one of those “five scrolls.” In each, Peterson interacts with the psychologizing tendency of the present day, the history of the interpretation of the Biblical book in question, and how pastors might learn from and apply the lessons of the book to their own work in their own congregations. For Peterson, Song of Songs is a model for directing God’s people into richer prayer, Ruth is a picture of situating individual stories in the context of salvific history, Lamentations is a guide to walking with people through their suffering, Ecclesiastes is a help in rejecting false religion in place of the fear of God, and Esther is a pointer to the essentially communal nature of the people of God.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="analysis" class="level2"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Analysis&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Curiously, the most significant problem with the book might at first appear to be one of its great strengths. Peteron’s skill as a writer is such that he can sometimes carry the reader along by sheer rhetorical effect—but this is in some sense a result antithetical to the purpose of the text. In a text explicitly and self-consciously aiming to point pastors away from technique and the tendency to mistake emotion for changed lives, the contrast with what Peterson actually does in large swaths of the book is striking and unfortunate. There are too many places where Peterson relies on the emotional impact of his words rather than on the text itself. Nearly the whole chapter on Esther falls into this trap, as do large swaths of the chapters on Ecclesiastes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is not so much that the points Peterson makes in these chapters are wrong: many of them are quite on target. It is that, disconnected from the text from which he purports to draw them, they become mere floating assertions about the world—assertions that, however beautifully made, we may take or leave as they strike us. There is too much technique in Peterson’s theologizing and too little of the Scripture to which he enjoins his readers to return.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Granted that Peterson makes no claim to be writing exegetical commentaries on the text, but he opens the book with the reminder that “we don’t, and we must not, lay our own foundations” (p. 11). Indeed, he (quite rightly) spends the whole introduction pleading for pastors to ground their work not in the trends of the day but in the “eternal will and word of God” (p. 5). It is a strange thing that he should then spend so much of the book on his own ruminations and not wrestling with the particulars of those texts. This is a significant loss, because when Peterson does remain more closely engaged with the text, as in his chapters on Ruth and Lamentations, and as in some parts of his treatment of Ecclesiastes, the effect is marvelous. The reader is drawn into wonder at the way God’s word guides us effectively for pastoral ministry. The pastor is reminded that the circumstances and trials he and his flock face are not things newly sprung up in the late twentieth or early twenty-first century, but the sorts of things for which God has already supplied guides and instruction in the Scriptures.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But this is no surprise: this is Peterson’s own thesis. The power of our faith, the fruitfulness of pastoral ministry (and the effectiveness of our books thereon) is not in our technique but in grappling deeply with the word of God in our own situations. The more he grapples with the Scriptures, the more his technique serves the text, the better Peterson’s book is—and vice versa. Where technique serves exposition, the reader is built up. Where exposition falls aside and rhetoric reigns, the reader may be moved emotionally, but little remains when that glow fades.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thus, for four of the five chapters in the book, Peterson’s success in advancing his thesis may largely be measured by the extent to which he engages the text. In Ruth and Lamentations, the narrative and poetry respectively drive the discussion, and so the chapters are profoundly helpful. The discussion of Ruth helps the pastor see his peoples’ personal stories rightly—and thus, to help his people see their own stories rightly. They are not the end-all and be-all that modern psychology might make them out to be, but neither are they insignificant. Indeed, they are all the more significant precisely &lt;em&gt;because&lt;/em&gt; they are part of something much bigger than themselves. The discussion of Lamentations helps a pastor to see the necessity both of walking &lt;em&gt;through&lt;/em&gt; suffering and sorrow with his flock and of helping them come to resolution in the right time. Petersons’ treatment of Ecclesiastes, as a guide to saying &lt;em&gt;no&lt;/em&gt; to false religion, seems to be an accurate analysis of the book, but Peterson veers away from the Text. He deals too little with the specific ways in which &lt;em&gt;Qoheleth&lt;/em&gt; confronts our culture and too much in the sweeping generalizations about the value of those confrontations. Least helpful of all is his treatment of Esther, in which he rightly diagnoses severe problems in the culture around us but leaves aside almost everything in the book itself. We desperately need the kind of rebuke to individualism he suggests here. Whether Esther can support that kind of rebuke, still less offer an alternative vision of the people of God, is left aside in favor of a good but largely-unrelated discussion of Saul and Amalek and the shape of ministry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Peterson’s treatment of the Song of Songs deserves its own analysis. The text is notoriously hard to interpret, and has been subject to countless different readings. Peterson falls squarely into the allegorical camp, though he gives the allegorical reading something of a twist. The urgency of romantic (both emotional and sexual) desire so prominent in the book he transmutes into a picture of the Christian’s right desire for communion with God. This was the chapter in which Peterson hewed &lt;em&gt;most&lt;/em&gt; closely to the text, and so it was the chapter least susceptible to the problems outlined above. As with all treatments of the Song, though, the effectiveness of the chapter hinges on whether one finds Peterson’s interpretation accurate. (I did not.) Insofar as one grants Peterson’s interpretation, though, the chapter is an effective argument for the necessity of prayer, and especially of the pastor leading his people to pray with greater fervency.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="conclusion" class="level2"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Five Smooth Stones for Pastoral Work&lt;/em&gt; is in some ways a very good book, but in others it falls short—an especially unfortunate reality given the very real problems at which it aimed. That Peterson wants to see pastors grounding their &lt;em&gt;pastoring&lt;/em&gt; in the Scriptures as well as their preaching and teaching is clear. Less clear is whether this book will be as effective as it could have been in accomplishing that end. Good pastoral work does not run aground only on the rocks of psychology. Rhetoric is an equally deadly reef, and it may be the more tempting to a skilled writer passionate for the recovery of Biblical pastoral work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The chapters on Ruth and Lamentations were excellent and profoundly helpful treatments of the topics they addressed, and Peterson’s treatment of Song of Songs was at least interesting. Because he exchanged exposition for effect in his treatments of Ecclesiastes and Esther, though, the book falters. Though his words never failed to pack an emotional punch, they were too often hollowed out by their lack of a connection to the text. In this, these chapters serve as an accidental and unfortunate illustration of the necessity of Peterson’s own thesis. We need not more effective psychology, nor more powerful lnaguage, but a deeper reliance on and connection to the word of God.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 12 Apr 2014 08:00:00 -0400</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:v4.chriskrycho.com,2014-04-12:/2014/halfway-to-his-own-thesis.html</guid><category>M. Div.</category><category>SEBTS</category><category>book reviews</category></item><item><title>The Atonement, Leon Morris</title><link>http://v4.chriskrycho.com/2014/the-atonement-leon-morris.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;i class="editorial"&gt;I wrote the following review after reading the book when it was assigned for my Christian Theology II class, covering Christology and soteriology, at Southeastern Baptist Theological Seminary. Most of my readings for that class were &lt;em&gt;great&lt;/em&gt;. This one? Well, you’ll see.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Leon Morris’ &lt;em&gt;The Atonement&lt;/em&gt; is, as near as I can tell, fairly well regarded. Given the importance of the doctrine of the atonement to our faith, I had hoped that the book would be a profitable read when I saw that it was assigned as reading for one of my classes this semester. Unfortunately, the book fell far short of my hopes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The problems with the book are manifold. To begin, Morris is simply not a very good writer. Run-on sentences crop up regularly. He seems to be aiming for both a friendly conversational tone and erudition. (Conversational and scholarly writing are both fine; the combination fails miserably for nearly anyone but G.K. Chesterton or C.S. Lewis. Take it from me: I should know.) Most importantly, Morris’ chapters are essentially thesis-less, and the “conclusions” to which he comes rarely follow from the material presented in the rest of the chapter. The section on redemption was particularly egregious in this regard: he turned from a long discussion of redemption practices in the ancient world to a short summary focusing on the Christian view of sin in contrast to the modern world’s view of the human situation—with no transition or connection between the two.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is one of the two basic problems with the book, in fact. His chapters are essentially aiming to do two different things. On the one hand, Morris is clearly interested in laying out the historical and linguistic background of the various ideas associated with the atonement (the sacrificial system, Passover, redemption, etc.). On the other hand, he clearly wants to find points of application to the Christian life. In each chapter, he spends most of his time on the first, then makes a rushed switch to the second for the final pages of the chapter. At no point is this transition well-written, and in no chapter does the application follow closely from the points he made in the background material. Even within the background material which dominates each chapter, Morris wanders. It is as if he is not sure whether he wanted to provide an informative overview of the context, to argue against various views others have offered regarding that background,&lt;a href="#fn1" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref1" role="doc-noteref"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; or to make some sort of theological argument. Thus, he bounces between each of these modes rather haphazardly, sometimes even within a single paragraph.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This emphasis on background also rather defeats the purpose of the book. If the aim is to help people see and savor the glory of Christ’s atoning work on their behalf—a noble and worthy goal—then Morris simply did the wrong thing. He spends most of his time in the book on word studies, historical context, and so on. When he does get to his “application” sections,&lt;a href="#fn2" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref2" role="doc-noteref"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; he usually has said very little about Scripture’s teaching on the atonement. Telling people what words mean, or explaining the rabbis’ records of Second Temple Judaism practice, is not the same as explaining the Scriptures. The book reads like a sermon series from the historical-grammatical school where the background has been mistaken for the content instead of as a helpful tool where the content is not clear.&lt;a href="#fn3" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref3" role="doc-noteref"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; Morris wastes his readers’ time with secondary matters and speeds over the riches of the text itself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When Morris &lt;em&gt;does&lt;/em&gt; pay attention to the actual content of Scripture rather than its background, he tends to dwell on his hobby-horses instead of letting Scripture speak for itself. He often writes things like, “Of course, Scripture &lt;em&gt;does&lt;/em&gt; include (one idea), but really we should take it (in some other way).”— where the latter is his preferred reading, and the former the way the text actually reads. Unsurprisingly, then, the best chapters in the book are those where his hobby-horses are nearest the actual point of the text in question. In the final three chapters of the book, he veers away into secondary matters much less and focuses on the text much more. It made for a significant improvement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alas, even this improvement did nothing to help resolve the other significant problem with the book. In short, Morris’ approach to New Testament doctrine is hopelessly reductionistic. Everything comes down to the idea of payment for the guilt of sin, even in chapters where he tries to talk about other things. Morris set out to write a book on the atonement, and instead of spending his time tracing out the atonement itself, he tried to make every other aspect of our salvation a part of the atonement. The book might have worked had it been titled &lt;em&gt;Salvation&lt;/em&gt;, but in seeking to make every part of God’s saving work into a mere aspect of atonement, Morris both diminished those other parts and failed to spend much time discussing the atonement itself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this Morris is very much typical of evangelicalism, sad to say. We are a crucicentric people, and though this has its upsides, it also means we tend to rewrite all of our doctrines in terms of penal subtitutionary atonement, rather than letting them all work together as they do in the Bible. Atonement is one central and crucial (pun intended) part of our salvation, but it is not the whole of our salvation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Morris’ book could have been a helpful volume; a robust doctrine of the atonement is a wonderful thing. I am sad to say that &lt;em&gt;The Atonement&lt;/em&gt; simply wasn’t very good. There are helpful bits scattered throughout, but to find them one must wade through a great deal of poorly written, unnecessarily polemical, disorganized, distracted meandering about things that are &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; the atonement (though they are themselves wonderful). I cannot recommend it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn1" role="doc-endnote"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Including, unfortunately, the occasional joke about the Church Fathers’ views on aspects of the atonement are. At one point, he goes so far as to describe the Fathers’ “ransom view” of the atonement as silly and only worth laughing at. We might &lt;em&gt;disagree&lt;/em&gt; with the Fathers’ ransom view of the atonement, with God paying Satan—I do—but we hardly ought to laugh at them. This is chronological snobbery of the worst sort.&lt;a href="#fnref1" class="footnote-back" role="doc-backlink"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn2" role="doc-endnote"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Usually focusing on the shape of the Christian life—an odd choice in a book one would think would focus on the gospel itself. To be sure, I think that the atonement has enormous implications for the Christian life. Morris never shows &lt;em&gt;how&lt;/em&gt; they connect, though, and he doesn’t spend any time talking about the marvel of the atonement itself for the Christian, either. It is just strange.&lt;a href="#fnref2" class="footnote-back" role="doc-backlink"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn3" role="doc-endnote"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is the way that the historical-grammatical approach normally goes wrong. Other approaches have their own typical foibles, of course.&lt;a href="#fnref3" class="footnote-back" role="doc-backlink"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 16 Mar 2014 19:50:00 -0400</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:v4.chriskrycho.com,2014-03-16:/2014/the-atonement-leon-morris.html</guid><category>book reviews</category></item></channel></rss>