<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Chris Krycho - bullet journal</title><link>http://v4.chriskrycho.com/</link><description></description><lastBuildDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2019 07:40:00 -0400</lastBuildDate><item><title>Stealing a Page From Bullet Journals</title><link>http://v4.chriskrycho.com/2019/stealing-a-page-from-bullet-journals.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;a href="https://v4.chriskrycho.com/2018/assumed-audiences.html"&gt;Assumed Audience&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/b&gt; people already persuaded of the value—at least to some extent—of “getting things done” strategies.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have tried &lt;a href="https://www.tinyrayofsunshine.com/blog/bullet-journal-guide"&gt;bullet journaling&lt;/a&gt; as a full-on way of tracking and planning my work in the past. It never stuck. The &lt;a href="https://v4.chriskrycho.com/2018/just-write-down-what-you-do.html"&gt;system&lt;/a&gt; I’ve landed on instead—making heavy use of &lt;a href="https://bear.app"&gt;Bear&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://tadamapp.com"&gt;a pomodoro timer&lt;/a&gt;—has been &lt;em&gt;fantastic&lt;/em&gt;. However… I realized yesterday that the way I take notes during the workday in a notebook already has a lot in common with bullet journaling. So I’m trying something new, and we’ll see how it goes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For my daily task logging, I’m still going to use Bear in exactly the way I have been already. However, I’m writing down notes in my notebook in the bullet journal style:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;dots for to-dos&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;putting an ‘x’ through the dots when I’ve done them&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;turning them into an arrow if I move them into Bear to tackle later (the next day, the next week, the next month, etc.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;dashes for information I learned&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don’t need to bother with all the things that never actually worked for me in bullet journaling, like keeping an index, various kind of date logs, collections, etc.: my logging and note-taking system in Bear already handles all of that in a way that I like much better. But stealing the lightweight notation and the idea of pulling incompleted tasks into a place where I &lt;em&gt;can&lt;/em&gt; use them later? That’s worth stealing, I think. We’ll see how it goes.&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2019 07:40:00 -0400</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:v4.chriskrycho.com,2019-08-29:/2019/stealing-a-page-from-bullet-journals.html</guid><category>bullet journal</category><category>pomodoro</category><category>getting things done</category><category>productivity</category></item></channel></rss>