<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Chris Krycho - burnout</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/</link><description></description><lastBuildDate>Mon, 27 May 2019 21:40:00 -0400</lastBuildDate><item><title>Finishing Things on the Internet</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2019/finishing-things-on-the-internet.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.chriskrycho.com/2018/assumed-audiences.html"&gt;Assumed audience:&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/b&gt; most anyone, but especially people who have followed along with New Rustacean, my experience with burnout, or both!&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;I am cross-posting this to this site and &lt;a href="https://buttondown.email/chriskrycho"&gt;my newsletter&lt;/a&gt;, and the reason it is a couple days late will be apparent in the content below. A &lt;em&gt;good&lt;/em&gt; thing, but a big thing!&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have in mind today the finishing of things. No surprise, given that today &lt;a href="https://newrustacean.com/show_notes/meta/_3/"&gt;I concluded&lt;/a&gt; a 3¾-year-long project: my Rust programming language podcast, &lt;a href="https://newrustacean.com"&gt;New Rustacean&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This conclusion has been a long time coming. I had meant it to happen last year, originally planned it to coincide with the Rust 2018 Edition release, when &lt;em&gt;that&lt;/em&gt; was planned for October. The Edition release slipped till December, and this conclusion slipped till now: the end of May, 2019. The reason will be clear to anyone who has followed along with me: &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.chriskrycho.com/burnout"&gt;burnout&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;. 2018 took a serious toll on me, and so this act of finishing was much delayed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But more than 100 episodes along, with more than 165,000 words of material—I don’t know the actual final length of the show in minutes, though I have a mind to figure it out sometime in the next few days—New Rustacean is &lt;em&gt;concluded&lt;/em&gt;. That’s a really good feeling. It is also, I note, a &lt;em&gt;rare&lt;/em&gt; feeling as an adult. I &lt;a href="https://www.chriskrycho.com/2019/a-new-job.html#ii.-on-the-experience-of-change-as-an-adult" title="A New Job – On the Experience of Change as an Adult"&gt;noted this&lt;/a&gt; back when I moved from Olo to LinkedIn:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Life changes like this are simultaneously momentous and strangely quiet. When I was younger, I expected large shifts in life to have some sense of their importance: a “big bang” feeling to them, and a feeling of finality. It would seem that days like yesterday — as I wrapped up everything that was on my plate and even had a little (all-remote!) hang-out to say goodbye — would lend themselves to just such a sense of import and finality. Instead, it was mostly a day like any other, and at the end of it I was left only with a lingering melancholy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The mix of emotions is different today—but that it is a &lt;em&gt;mix&lt;/em&gt;, and that there is no &lt;em&gt;big bang&lt;/em&gt; feeling to it, are the same.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is not only that the &lt;em&gt;feeling&lt;/em&gt; of finishing a thing is rare, though. It is that, in many cases, actually properly concluding a thing at all is rare. Or at least, in my experience it has been. I have yet to both &lt;em&gt;start&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;finish&lt;/em&gt; a given major project in any of my “regular” day jobs. I have managed major milestones in some of them, and in my consulting work I have finished a few projects as well. But much of my work life has consisted of carrying the ball a few yards further down the field and then setting it down for someone else to do the same.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;New Rustacean is &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; like that. I started it back in September 2015, and I finished it today. It has a real beginning and a real end, and the end is not merely a petering-out, a slowly-giving-up, but rather a long-planned specific conclusion to the project. I started the show to teach people Rust. I stopped when I felt I had done so to my own satisfaction. As I said in the final episode, it is not that there is not an endless array of more I could cover: but that I have covered &lt;em&gt;enough&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Conclusions like this are good for the soul. They are good for the individual soul, to be sure: my own feels lighter and freer and I am very ready for this next phase (the research writing app I have mentioned here before). But I also think that conclusions are good for the public soul, as it were. We burn people out—and I use that phrase advisedly!—by expecting their efforts to go on so long as we, their consumers, enjoy them. By contrast, it seems to me, seeing someone carefully and actively &lt;em&gt;finish&lt;/em&gt; a thing helps us remember that people’s lives [have seasons], and that no one can (much less &lt;em&gt;should&lt;/em&gt;) do a given thing indefinitely, and above all that people exist with lives and interests of their own beyond the ways we may encounter them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is perhaps doubly true on the internet, where we have but these small windows into people’s souls. Not that we have perfect windows in person—but people far more often let down their guard and let us see them as they really are (even on accident) when face-to-face than when avatar-to-avatar. Too easily does avarice for attention corrupt—even when we aim at authenticity. And too easily does our communication devolve to perfectly curated self-presentation: even our online authenticity is often performative. It makes it easy to forget how human people are, how we need to find these moments of closure, how much we are &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; mere factories-of-content but people, possibly with other dreams.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(I’m grateful to report that I have only rarely had nastily-communicated demands from listeners of New Rustacean. But it &lt;em&gt;has&lt;/em&gt; happened!)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Conclusions serve as those kinds of reminders. Projects can be good and still come to a close! Sometimes, even, projects are best precisely when they &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt; have definite ends. I hope and think that is so with New Rustacean: that in ending it as I have, I will let it be not something that I burn out on and which someday pitifully trails off, but instead a thing good in its wholeness and its completeness. So I hope, and I can but act, and hope!&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 27 May 2019 21:40:00 -0400</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2019-05-27:/2019/finishing-things-on-the-internet.html</guid><category>podcasting</category><category>writing</category><category>burnout</category></item><item><title>Burnout, Six Months Later</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2019/burnout-six-months-later.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.chriskrycho.com/2018/assumed-audiences.html"&gt;Assumed Audience&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/b&gt; anyone who cares about mental health and recovery… but perhaps especially people who have been following me on &lt;a href="https://www.chriskrycho.com/burnout"&gt;this journey&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It has been just over six months since I hit the rock-bottom point in my experience of burnout: when I had a panic attack… because a programming task came back with a list of small things that needed tweaking. I have made a lot of changes since then, and am—&lt;a href="https://www.chriskrycho.com/2018/stewarding-my-reserves.html"&gt;as I wrote earlier this year&lt;/a&gt;—not &lt;i&gt;recovered&lt;/i&gt; but &lt;i&gt;recovering&lt;/i&gt;. I am trying to write about &lt;em&gt;this&lt;/em&gt; part of the process too: burnout itself is under-discussed in many ways, but the process of &lt;em&gt;recovering&lt;/em&gt; from burnout is not something I have seen discussed at all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section id="signs-of-recovery" class="level2"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Signs of recovery&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So… what does recovery look like so far? And how does it compare with when I was &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; recovering?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section id="i-am-sleeping-my-normal-amount-again." class="level3"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;1. I am sleeping my normal amount again.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For much of late last year I simply had to turn my alarm off and sleep as much as I slept… and that was a good 8½–9 hours. That was pretty unusual: as an adult, I have normally only needed 7–7½ hours. I tried setting an alarm for a bit earlier this year, but found I wasn’t ready for it yet. I kept finding myself unable to drag myself into consciousness most days. Other times, I would manage it, but then find myself exhausted the rest of the week. The tradeoff wasn’t worth it, so I went back to sleeping till I woke up—no alarm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over the past few weeks, I’ve been returning to that previous baseline naturally. Still setting no alarm, I have been awakening after 7–7½ hours normally. Some of that is no doubt helped by the early sunrises of late spring, but I have also not been &lt;em&gt;tired&lt;/em&gt; at all—I’m ready to go as soon as I wake up, and have the energy to get through the rest of the day and indeed the rest of the week.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a relatively quiet change, but it feels rather significant. When people have asked me about my productivity over the years, this is one of the things I’ve pointed to. It is far easier to get a lot done if you only need 7–7½ hours of sleep than if you need 8½–9. That’s an extra 7–14 hours a week!&lt;a href="#fn1" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref1" role="doc-noteref"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; I honestly wasn’t sure if those hours were ever coming back. That they have is a huge relief, and it has been a huge boon to my ability to do the things I want to do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="i-am-reading-again" class="level3"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;2. I am reading again&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the earliest signs that I was dealing with burnout was that I largely stopped reading books on theology, culture, ethics, etc. I didn’t stop &lt;em&gt;completely&lt;/em&gt;, mind—but my pace slowed to a crawl, and I had a hard time maintaining momentum. From roughly June 2016 until the last month or so, reading anything more than popcorn-level fiction just felt like &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; hard work. I could rarely make myself get through anything longer than an essay.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I made myself do some anyway. With friends, I worked through &lt;cite&gt;Evolution and the Fall&lt;/cite&gt; in 2017, and over the course of 2017 and 2018 I read &lt;em&gt;most&lt;/em&gt; of Oliver O’Donovan’s &lt;cite&gt;Resurrection and Moral Order&lt;/cite&gt; and a good chunk of each of Stewart Brand’s &lt;cite&gt;How Buildings Learn&lt;/cite&gt; and &lt;cite&gt;Theology and the Mirror of Scripture&lt;/cite&gt; by Kevin Vanhoozer and Daniel Treier. I started working through Augustine’s &lt;cite&gt;City of God&lt;/cite&gt; with friends in 2018… and dropped out because I couldn’t make myself get to it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I read roughly an order of magnitude less than what’s normal for me over those years. To describe this as “out of character” for me is to understate things rather a lot. By the same token, the return of my appetite for books means feeling normal and healthy again in a way that I can hardly put into words. This week I ordered &lt;em&gt;three&lt;/em&gt; books—having dug into the first a fair bit via the ebook preview!—and read most of one of them the day it arrived.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src="https://f001.backblazeb2.com/file/chriskrycho-com/images/3-new-books.jpeg" title="Sanders and Swain&amp;#39;s Retrieving Eternal Generation, Barth&amp;#39;s Dogmatics in Outline, and Anderson&amp;#39;s All That&amp;#39;s Good, sitting next to each other on a table." alt="3 new books!" /&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;3 new books!&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="i-am-excited-about-projects-again" class="level3"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;3. I am excited about projects again&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Keeping up any kind of momentum on personal projects over the course of 2018 was difficult at best. I mostly managed to keep &lt;a href="https://newrustacean.com/"&gt;New Rustacean&lt;/a&gt; going; &lt;a href="https://winningslowly.org"&gt;Winning Slowly&lt;/a&gt; took a worse beating; and &lt;a href="https://massaffection.com"&gt;Mass Affection&lt;/a&gt;, sadly, stopped basically entirely. (Curiously, I’ve observed that my interest in playing video games at all seems to have waned and waxed in fairly direct proportion to my burnout.) My other outside interests all ground to a halt as well. I did no writing other than blogging, and a good deal of the blogging I did was publicly reflecting on burnout itself. My open-source software contributions were minimal: only what was absolutely necessary to keep those projects moving.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the last 6 weeks, my interest in those projects has been reviving. I actually started working on in earnest &lt;a href="https://buttondown.email/rewrite"&gt;a project I have been planning for ages&lt;/a&gt;—including by doing some work to clear the deck for it in my schedule. I’ll probably play a session of &lt;cite&gt;Mass Effect&lt;/cite&gt; with Jaimie &lt;em&gt;tonight&lt;/em&gt; and we’ll record and publish the corresponding another day this week. I’m more excited by and engaged with Winning Slowly than I have been since late 2016.&lt;a href="#fn2" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref2" role="doc-noteref"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; I am, as you can see, blogging again (though, &lt;a href="https://www.chriskrycho.com/2018/some-closing-thoughts.html#reading-and-writing-1"&gt;as promised&lt;/a&gt;, I intend to keep a relatively tight limit on this for the sake of actually making good progress on other projects).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="signs-im-still-recovering" class="level2"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Signs I’m Still Recovering&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The net of all these steps forward is that I feel a good deal more &lt;em&gt;myself&lt;/em&gt; than I have in a very long time. But there are also signs that I am not yet recovered. In particular, I continue to have less emotional reserves is normal for me. Grief comes bursting out at unexpected times—and, unfortunately, also in unhelpful ways. I find myself fighting hard not to let little annoyances blow up into big frustration or anger. I sometimes get hit by whole days of deep inability to think or concentrate. One day last week I simply had to take a sick day and spent a good chunk of it napping. (And I. do. not. take. naps.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One aspect of this is that the original triggering stressors that pushed me from &lt;i&gt;deeply (but not consciously) emotionally fatigued&lt;/i&gt; to &lt;i&gt;burned out&lt;/i&gt; are largely out of the way. This means I have the mental and emotional space to decompress a bit. But when you’re as compressed as I was, decompressing means little bursts of emotional steam come jetting out at surprising moments and in surprising ways. Coupled with all those other symptoms, this is a good sign! It is also a bit hard, but I think that is to be expected.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another aspect is that the process of unwinding and disentangling the mess that got me here in the first place is &lt;em&gt;ongoing&lt;/em&gt;. Identifying, and reckoning with, the pains that I set aside for &lt;i&gt;later&lt;/i&gt; until later became &lt;i&gt;right now&lt;/i&gt; is a slow process. I had intended to block out some Saturday mornings this spring to go sit with a journal and work through some of those; I found myself too busy to do so. This has to change! It’s no good at all if I let even those good things keep me from dealing with these deeper-seated problems. Letting them go so long un-dealt-with is a major part of what got me here in the first place. I have bumped that up in priority for the months ahead, and have told people close to me so they can hold me to it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More soon. (But not too soon! I have things to do that aren’t blogging! I have to keep reminding myself of this…)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn1" role="doc-endnote"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Another major factor I point to in my output is not having a commute—which makes for &lt;em&gt;at least&lt;/em&gt; another 5 hours.&lt;a href="#fnref1" class="footnote-back" role="doc-backlink"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn2" role="doc-endnote"&gt;&lt;p&gt;I loved what we did in Season 6—though it didn’t quite achieve what we were hoping for, in no small part because of my experience with burnout.&lt;a href="#fnref2" class="footnote-back" role="doc-backlink"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 05 May 2019 19:15:00 -0400</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2019-05-05:/2019/burnout-six-months-later.html</guid><category>burnout</category><category>mental health</category><category>writing</category><category>podcasting</category></item><item><title>On Burnout and My Recent Job Change</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2019/on-burnout-and-my-recent-job-change.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.chriskrycho.com/2018/assumed-audiences.html"&gt;Assumed Audience&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/b&gt; People who have followed or are interested in my experiences with &lt;a href="https://www.chriskrycho.com/burnout/"&gt;burnout&lt;/a&gt;, or are curious about my new job change.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I &lt;a href="https://www.chriskrycho.com/2019/a-new-job.html"&gt;posted&lt;/a&gt; a week ago about my (then-impending, now-quite-actual!) transition from &lt;a href="https://www.olo.com"&gt;Olo&lt;/a&gt; to &lt;a href="https://linkedin.com"&gt;LinkedIn&lt;/a&gt;. My friend &lt;a href="https://stephencarradini.com"&gt;Stephen&lt;/a&gt; pointed out that, especially for long-time readers of this blog, it seemed a bit odd to write about a job change without so much as mentioning my &lt;a href="https://www.chriskrycho.com/2018/burnout-symptoms.html"&gt;rather painful experience&lt;/a&gt; of &lt;a href="https://www.chriskrycho.com/2018/dealing-with-burnout-in-public.html"&gt;job-triggered burnout&lt;/a&gt; in 2018. He was right!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I chose not to talk about the relationship between this job change and burnout in that particular post because it’s rather complicated. I did not move to fix the burnout. As a number of things from my writing over the last few months likely indicated to attentive readers,&lt;a href="#fn1" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref1" role="doc-noteref"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; I have been slowly but steadily &lt;em&gt;recovering&lt;/em&gt; since mid-October.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mid-October was when I hit rock bottom. On October 15th, I had a panic attack. Thankfully, it was brief and I was at home. (It was just a few hours after I wrote &lt;a href="https://www.chriskrycho.com/2018/neither-being-dumb-nor-giving-in.html"&gt;this post&lt;/a&gt;, actually.) As is often the case with panic attacks (from what I have read), the specific trigger was not itself that big of a deal; but it was more stress than I could handle. My body responded to one more little stressor by &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;freaking out&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At that point, I pinged my manager at Olo and said, “Hey, I just had a panic attack; we need to change something.” I immediately handed over some high-urgency projects I was working on and took the rest of the week off. It helped. And it helped among other things because it gave me time to get some clarity on why the stressors I was experiencing at Olo were affecting me the ways they were, and what kinds of changes would need to happen for them &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; to have that kind of affect on me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I worked with my manager at Olo to make a bunch of changes there which made Olo much better for me. I remain very grateful for those. And I am also grateful that I was able to have a lot of very productive conversations with not just him but others at Olo, including in engineering leadership, which helped me further clarify whether Olo was going to be a good long-term fit for me or not. That I ultimately concluded &lt;i&gt;not&lt;/i&gt; is a credit to the openness of Olo’s leadership to having those conversations with me and their desire to see their people succeed. I was not exaggerating &lt;a href="https://www.chriskrycho.com/2019/a-new-job.html"&gt;when I wrote&lt;/a&gt; that Olo was the best place I had ever worked.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But I should also note that I was looking around and starting the ball rolling on interviews as far back as September—precisely because of my experience with burnout, and specifically the values mismatch that it had so thoroughly exposed. Note that when I say “values” I don’t mean in the sense of the ethics with which Olo conducts its business—I found Olo consistently exemplary in that regard, in fact. Instead, I mean that Olo is operating in ways that most people agree make sense for a late-stage startup tracking toward some kind of exit event.&lt;a href="#fn2" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref2" role="doc-noteref"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; Unfortunately this left me misaligned with Olo in a very important way &lt;em&gt;besides&lt;/em&gt; the scale questions I hit on in &lt;a href="https://www.chriskrycho.com/2019/a-new-job.html"&gt;my announcement post last week&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That phase of a company built in the way Olo has been—by way of venture capital, with the requisite &lt;em&gt;need&lt;/em&gt; for an exit—just necessarily &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; high on acquiring market share and low on the kind of slow, steady work &lt;a href="https://winningslowly.org"&gt;I so highly value&lt;/a&gt;. This means that I constantly found myself at odds with company decisions—not because those decisions were morally wrong themselves, but because I’m increasingly at odds with the entire system of venture capital-driven business development! But every time the company made one of those decisions—however much sense it made for the company—I grew more frustrated. And that frustration was a major factor in my burnout.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(Attentive readers will note that I didn’t go into details about this during the worst of it. This was for two reasons: First, I didn’t trust myself to be able to write &lt;em&gt;well&lt;/em&gt; about it given my emotional state at the time. The couple times I started to I found that I could not correctly convey that I &lt;em&gt;both&lt;/em&gt; continued to respect and care about my colleagues at Olo &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; was deeply frustrated by the state of affairs there. Second, and closely related to the first, I wanted to avoid burdening my colleagues with my own doubts and frustrations as much as possible. We were in the middle of a pretty intense deadline push, the stresses of which were enough &lt;em&gt;without&lt;/em&gt; watching a colleague melt down because of how this particular crunch loudly surfaced his deep conflicts with venture capitalism. Better, I concluded, to gesture in the general direction of the sources of my burnout and leave this for a later time. And, should any of my former colleagues be reading this now: yes, I disagreed with our taking on that particular project; but you all did a really amazing job executing on it and have my lasting respect and admiration.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The net of all of that was that changing jobs was an important part of helping me avoid getting burnt out &lt;em&gt;again&lt;/em&gt;. The things Olo &lt;em&gt;will&lt;/em&gt; be doing at this point in the business’ lifecycle would simply continue to frustrate me, and it could not afford me the opportunities I want professionally. That mismatch is simply too much when stacked on on top of all the other emotional weights of the last several years—some of which I have written about publicly, some of which I may write about publicly in the future, and some of which will never be for general public consumption (though of course I talk about them with dear friends). And, more, a new job with less of that mismatch is the lever I could pull most easily and effectively—a way I could give myself the space I need to deal with everything else which contributed to my burnout.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That analysis carries with it the important corollary that changing jobs is only one part of avoiding further burnout, though. Avoiding overcommitment, keeping what commitments I do make well-aligned with my priorities, taking time to rest, taking time to &lt;a href="https://www.chriskrycho.com/2019/time-does-not-heal.html"&gt;grieve deep pains&lt;/a&gt;: &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; of these are necessary components of avoiding falling back into burnout once again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More on this—and, hopefully, some of the promised &lt;a href="https://www.chriskrycho.com/2018/dealing-with-burnout-in-public.html"&gt;theological reflection&lt;/a&gt; on the subject—as I am able, while not overdoing it!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn1" role="doc-endnote"&gt;&lt;p&gt;the decrease in frequency of posts on the subject, a post explicitly about &lt;a href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2018/stewarding-my-reserves.html"&gt;recovering from burnout&lt;/a&gt;, past tense language when I &lt;a href="https://www.chriskrycho.com/2018/some-closing-thoughts.html"&gt;did&lt;/a&gt; talk about it…&lt;a href="#fnref1" class="footnote-back" role="doc-backlink"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn2" role="doc-endnote"&gt;&lt;p&gt;whether that be an &lt;abbr title="initial public offering"&gt;IPO&lt;/abbr&gt;, an acquisition, or something else—I am obviously not privy to any information about that; Olo’s CEO Noah Glass has made public statements pointing to exit event in the last month.&lt;a href="#fnref2" class="footnote-back" role="doc-backlink"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 02 Feb 2019 13:00:00 -0500</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2019-02-02:/2019/on-burnout-and-my-recent-job-change.html</guid><category>burnout</category><category>career</category></item><item><title>2018: Some Closing Thoughts</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2018/some-closing-thoughts.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.chriskrycho.com/2018/assumed-audiences.html"&gt;Assumed Audience:&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/b&gt; mostly my future self!—but you’re welcome to read along and see my thoughts on how 2018 went for me and what I hope 2019 will look like.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As has long been my tradition&lt;a href="#fn1" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref1" role="doc-noteref"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; I’m wrapping up the year by looking back at what happened in it and thinking about what I’d like to do in the year ahead. I say little here about family or church, but that should not be taken as an indicator of importance: in fact, my commitments in those two spheres deeply inform everything else!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section id="section" class="level2"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;2018&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;2018 was not the year I hoped or expected it might be. It was difficult in a great many ways, and the more so as the year went on. It was not the single hardest year I’ve had—that title goes without question to 2016—but it’s up there. There’s still a lot of good in the mix, but it was hard.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section id="podcasting" class="level3"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Podcasting&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had intended to publish about twice as many episodes of &lt;a href="https://newrustacean.com"&gt;New Rustacean&lt;/a&gt; this year as I was ultimately able to release. My goal was actually to be releasing 3–4 episodes each month, and to cover most of the rest of the language! As it turned out, I was able to release only 1–2 episodes per month. I’m nonetheless very happy with the episodes I &lt;em&gt;did&lt;/em&gt; release this year. And &lt;a href="https://newrustacean.com/show_notes/bonus/burnout/"&gt;my episode on burnout&lt;/a&gt; may end up being one of the most important things to come out of the show, from the email responses I’ve received about it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We launched a new design of the &lt;a href="https://winningslowly.org"&gt;Winning Slowly website&lt;/a&gt; and we were able to record and publish about three quarters of the episodes we had planned for Season 6 before the burnout tanked me. There’s a wrap-up episode we recorded and which should be out in a few days (after I edit it!). We also released our 100th episode, which was fun! It was frustrating not to be able to finish everything we had planned, but I remain proud of the work we’ve done there over the last five years, and this season had a couple really important episodes in it. If you didn’t listen to anything else, I’d commend &lt;a href="https://winningslowly.org/6.04/"&gt;6.04: Move Slowly and Fix Things&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://winningslowly.org/6.06/"&gt;6.06: A Kind of Blindness&lt;/a&gt;. The latter, on “big data” and the difference between information and wisdom, is one of my single favorite episodes of the show.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="reading-and-writing" class="level3"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Reading and writing&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also set out this year to read a lot of books—I had a list of a 14 pieces of nonfiction on the list—and in the end I finished &lt;em&gt;none&lt;/em&gt; of them. I participated in a reading group which covered much of &lt;cite&gt;Domain Modeling Made Functional&lt;/cite&gt;, and I made it through the first fifth or so of St. Augustine’s &lt;cite&gt;City of God&lt;/cite&gt;, but I didn’t even manage to finish a few books I had started &lt;em&gt;last&lt;/em&gt; year! The only things I managed to finish were novels:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I finished rereading &lt;cite&gt;The Wheel of Time&lt;/cite&gt; and enjoyed some new-to-me “popcorn” in the form of &lt;a href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2018/agent-of-change.html"&gt;&lt;cite&gt;Agent of Change&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I devoured Mary Robinette Kowal’s &lt;a href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2018/the-calculating-stars.html"&gt;&lt;cite&gt;The Calculating Stars&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2018/review-the-fated-sky.html"&gt;&lt;cite&gt;The Fated Sky&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I read a couple Hugo and Nebula award winners: Larry Niven’s &lt;a href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2018/ringworld-review.html"&gt;&lt;cite&gt;Ringworld&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and N.K. Jemisin’s &lt;cite&gt;The Fifth Season&lt;/cite&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While those novels were basically the only thing I read, I very much like the habit of writing very short reviews I started with those novels. I expect to keep that habit, and it should be useful as I dig back into nonfiction in the future!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Speaking of writing: for all that this year felt like it was unproductive in some ways, I still ended up blogging to the tune of somewhere around 75,000 words across about 95 posts.&lt;a href="#fn2" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref2" role="doc-noteref"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; That’s a solid showing for a year full of burnout (even if burnout itself &lt;a href="https://www.chriskrycho.com/burnout"&gt;ended up being the subject of no few of those&lt;/a&gt;: about 6,000 words).&lt;a href="#fn3" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref3" role="doc-noteref"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; But one of my goals for the year was to publish a few longer-form essays, possibly even getting paid for them. That certainly did not happen; I did not manage to publish even a single essay at Mere Orthodoxy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="health" class="level3"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Health&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I ran a fair bit, and am slowly adjusting to living at roughly 7,000 feet above sea level instead of about 400 feet above sea level. But for the third year in a row, I did &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; manage to run a race. I can still feel, and the more so at this altitude, the lingering effects of the mild case of walking pneumonia I came down with in the summer of 2016. The one thing I did manage in terms of exercise and health was a &lt;em&gt;lot&lt;/em&gt; of cycling. Despite my dad’s being in the midst of ongoing monthly chemo treatments for a brain tumor, he and I rode 80 miles in two days together for the &lt;a href="http://www.childrenscoloradofoundation.org/courage-classic"&gt;Courage Classic&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="work" class="level3"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Work&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Work has been a mixed bag. On the one hand, I accomplished a lot this year. Despite a number of large roadblocks that were entirely outside my control, I led a very important effort to hit several meaningful milestones. I also kept pushing the state of our tooling forward, including some important open-source work, and at the end of November gave a “tech talk” on technical costs which seems to have made a real (if, so far, still small!) impact on the entire organization.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, work directly triggered the burnout I experienced. To be sure, I had plenty of existing stressors from moving across and walking through my dad’s fight with cancer with the rest of my family. But the things that pushed me over the edge from &lt;i&gt;tired and worn down&lt;/i&gt; to &lt;i&gt;burnout&lt;/i&gt; were challenges at work. There were the aforementioned roadblocks. There were some high-stress projects. But most of all, there is a lack of alignment between my engineering and business philosophies and those in play at Olo. Those aren’t &lt;em&gt;moral&lt;/em&gt;, but prudential and strategic, kinds of differences—but that does not make them unimportant! More on this below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="in-sum" class="level3"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;In sum&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In spite of the burnout, and notwithstanding all the things I did not get done, I’m grateful for this year. My dad has so far not only survived his battle with a brain tumor but is thriving overall. I managed to come through my experience of burnout mostly okay. Our new church has been a great blessing to us, and we’ve been able to step into serving in many ways already.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="section-1" class="level2"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;2019&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So looking forward into 2019, my hopes (I dare not call them plans anymore):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section id="podcasting-1" class="level3"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Podcasting&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I want to publish the dozen more episodes of &lt;a href="https://newrustacean.com"&gt;New Rustacean&lt;/a&gt; that I had planned for 2018! At my current rate of about two a month, that’ll take me the first six months or so of the year. Once I’m through that list, I’ll have covered the entirety of the language and quite a few of the most important crates in the ecosystem. But there are always new things happening, so I’ll have some interesting decisions to make about where to take the show.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m also going to keep producing &lt;a href="https://winningslowly.org"&gt;Winning Slowly&lt;/a&gt; with Stephen Carradini. We have not yet nailed down what Season 7 will focus on or look like yet, but we’re far from done. The issue is not finding something to talk about, but narrowing it down to which specific things we want to zoom in on! We also have an interview lined up in January (which will come out as an inter-season standalone episode) which we’re &lt;em&gt;very&lt;/em&gt; excited about. It’ll be quite different from the other interviews we’ve done, and represents an important step forward for the show.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="reading-and-writing-1" class="level3"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Reading and Writing&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My reading and writing goals for the year ahead are intentionally modest. I’ve consistently failed to achieve my more ambitious goals over the past few years, and I’m rather chastened by that. I also have to remind myself fairly often that I will, Lord willing, have many decades of life when I &lt;em&gt;don’t&lt;/em&gt; have my kids around. That means both that there is plenty of time to spend on reading and writing later and that there is &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; very much time to spend with my daughters later. Insofar as I want to continue reading and writing in important ways—and I do!—I need to make my reading and writing time count by approaching them in more focused and targeted ways.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have people ask me quite regularly for recommendations on various topics, and I simply can’t give them! That needs to change, so I want to read at least four popular level books on theology or culture—about one a quarter. My plan is to review them in this space, but also (more importantly!) to be able to point people in my church toward or away from them. In the long-term, I would love to take up a role (official or not) as a custodian of our church’s library.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also want to keep my mind sharp and growing on theology, culture, politics, art, etc. I’ve very much felt the lack of engagement on that over the last few years (and have said so here more than once). In that connection, I aim to work through two academic works on theology, and two on some other aspect of culture. I have yet to decide what those will be. Most likely I’ll start by finishing the volumes I already started, but I also expect to spend a bit of time on Patristic Christology, as I’m teaching a class on the person and nature of Jesus in August for our church.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Writing-wise, I know that I’ll continue blogging here. However, I actually hope to blog &lt;em&gt;less&lt;/em&gt; overall. The time I spent writing 70,000 words this year was time well-spent, but as I note &lt;a href="https://www.chriskrycho.com/2018/intentional-cyclicality.html" title="Intentional Cyclicality (March)"&gt;time&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://www.chriskrycho.com/2018/writing-plans-for-the-rest-of-2018.html" title="Writing Plans for the Rest of 2018 (May)"&gt;again&lt;/a&gt;, I have a hard time &lt;a href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2018/cant-stop-wont-stop.html" title="Can’t Stop, Won’t Stop (September)"&gt;&lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; blogging&lt;/a&gt;. I plan to work on that in a couple ways.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, I’m going to try to evaluate, with each idea I have, whether it should be a blog post or just go in my &lt;a href="https://www.chriskrycho.com/zettelkasten/"&gt;Zettelkasten&lt;/a&gt;. So much of my writing over the last decade has been a kind of &lt;a href="https://www.chriskrycho.com/2018/blog-as-note-taking-tool.html"&gt;public thinking-out-loud&lt;/a&gt;. That’s good, but I also feel much more need to polish something if I’m going to publish it than if it’s a private note. The way I polish a blog post is nothing like the way I polish essays, of course, but I do spend some time clarifying and adding nuance. Even when &lt;a href="https://www.chriskrycho.com/2018/assumed-audiences.html"&gt;specifying an assumed audience&lt;/a&gt;, I need to be more careful if I am writing for others than if I am working something out by writing about it for myself. As a result, I expect a lot of things which might have ended up on the blog in the past to just go in &lt;a href="https://bear.app"&gt;Bear&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Second, I plan (and we’ll see how this goes), I’m going to try &lt;em&gt;very&lt;/em&gt; hard to write fewer blog posts in favor of more well-developed essays. About a month ago, I started drafting an essay which seems like it might be legitimately important. Unfortunately, even though it is certainly more worth my time than the things I &lt;em&gt;have&lt;/em&gt; written since then (&lt;a href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2018/internal-and-external-parameter-names-in-javascript-and-typescript.html"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2018/starting-to-build-a-zettelkasten.html"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2018/zettelkasten-update-all-in-on-bear.html"&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2018/stewarding-my-reserves.html"&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2018/hey-siri-record-a-zettel.html"&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2018/javascript-is-c.html"&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;), I have not made progress since the day I started it. It’s not that my notes on research and note-taking are worthless. Rather, it’s that there is a cost to spending my limited time on writing those instead of more important writing efforts.&lt;a href="#fn4" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref4" role="doc-noteref"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;4&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; At a minimum, I intend to do even &lt;em&gt;less&lt;/em&gt; polish on those posts than I have to date, when I let myself write them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="health-1" class="level3"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Health&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have a handful of goals for this year in terms of physical health:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I want to lose about 10 pounds. I’m at a healthy weight currently, but I felt and performed at my best a few years ago when I was down in my target weight range. This is going to require tweaking the &lt;em&gt;content&lt;/em&gt;, rather than the &lt;em&gt;quantity&lt;/em&gt;, of what I eat, and introduce more variation into the kinds of exercise I’m doing. I can tell both that my metabolism has shifted as I’ve hit my 30’s, and that I’ve acclimated to the workout load that I’ve more-or-less consistently held over the last eight years. It’s annoying, honestly!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I plan to participate in the &lt;a href="http://www.childrenscoloradofoundation.org/courage-classic"&gt;Courage Classic&lt;/a&gt; again with my dad, and I’d like to do the 80-mile route at least one of the days. Maybe both days, if he and I are both trained for it! Unfortunately, this probably means investing in a new bike. The one I have currently is almost twenty years old, and it’s a good bike… but it’s increasingly going to need parts replaced. So: CraigsList here I come.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I’d like to complete another half marathon, probably in May. I don’t particularly care what my pace ends up being: I just want to get back in the rhythm and routine of training and completing the event. I went through a similar push after we moved to North Carolina, and 30 months later I ran the best race of my life. Now, I know that &lt;a href="https://runkeeper.com/user/chriskrycho/activity/684713960"&gt;the sub-1:25 time I ran back in 2015&lt;/a&gt; is not something I’m apt to see again, especially at altitude, but I’d like to get back to that kind of consistency and discipline (and I’ll see where it gets me!).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Given that I’m currently planning two events in late spring and summer, I also need to find something to do in the fall and winter next year, just to keep up my fitness level &lt;em&gt;for&lt;/em&gt; something. Previous years, I had the same issue for the spring, and the year I was in my very best shape, I played Ultimate in the spring and fall &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; did a super sprint triathlon in the summer. So: something like that again, perhaps.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="work-1" class="level3"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Work&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I close in on the end of the first decade of my career, I’m &lt;a href="https://www.chriskrycho.com/2018/career-trajectory.html"&gt;thinking a lot&lt;/a&gt; about what I want the next decade of my career to look like. I don’t expect to be able to figure it all out ahead of time, of course. At the same time, I’m resolved to find opportunities that align more with my values and the general aims for my career I’ve started developing. As I suggested above, I’ve found that I’m not on the same page as, well, &lt;em&gt;most&lt;/em&gt; businesses about how to approach a great many questions. There is no short-term fix for this; but in the longer-term I want to have enough independence to do things more in line with my &lt;a href="https://winningslowly.org"&gt;“winning slowly”&lt;/a&gt; view of the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One part of that is that I intend to push forward on a few things I’ve been plotting for a few years now. I started learning Rust back in the summer of 2015 for a &lt;em&gt;reason&lt;/em&gt;, and I’m coming back to that reason this year. I don’t in the least regret the detour that I’ve gone on in the meantime: New Rustacean remains one of my favorite things I’ve done, and is certainly a more important contribution than any code I could have written in that time. But the project that got this all started has my attention again, and I will be spending some of my personal time on it this year.&lt;a href="#fn5" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref5" role="doc-noteref"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;5&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; It’s the kind of thing that I rather hope &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; my career a few years down the line—but there’s a boatload of work to do to get there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another part is looking at a much longer horizon even. Over the past three years, I’ve become increasingly interested in programming language theory and practice. I have some ideas and insights I think are genuinely valuable and &lt;em&gt;relatively&lt;/em&gt; unique (at a minimum they’re not currently in use in industry anywhere, and I’ve yet to find any papers touching on them) and I would like to see them land at some point. Getting there is a long game; I am not exaggerating when I say that if I ever really make this happen, I expect it to be in my 40s. Probably my &lt;em&gt;late&lt;/em&gt; 40s. But that gives me time to learn in the meantime: to build small languages and see what that process is like, to find ways to collaborate on existing language projects, to learn a wide array of existing languages in more detail, and so on. If the ideas I have are ever to come to fruition, all of those things are necessary precursors for my efforts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here in late 2018, I have &lt;em&gt;just&lt;/em&gt; started on much of that: I am reading a book on programming language development and taking an awful lots of notes along the way. I will be completing the exercises in the book, and I will also be trying to learn enough to build my own little toy languages along the way. I am getting some practice in the pragmatics of it by collaborating with Dave Herman on &lt;a href="https://github.com/tc39/proposal-do-expressions"&gt;the &lt;code&gt;do&lt;/code&gt; expressions JavaScript proposal&lt;/a&gt;, which we hope to make substantial progress on in 2019. These kinds of programming language ideas will &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; be the emphasis in 2019, but they will be a piece, in the interest of laying the foundations I will need later.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="in-sum-1" class="level3"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;In sum&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hope 2019 is a less difficult year than 2018 was. I am also aiming to be more effective in accomplishing the things I care about, in part by setting more modest goals for myself. Keep podcasting. Read a few books of a few specific sorts. Write some essays, at the expense of some blog posts. Start on some new projects, but not in a hurry or a rush. Love my family and love my church.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn1" role="doc-endnote"&gt;&lt;p&gt;I’ve been doing this since 2007, but I’m not linking you to the blog post I wrote that year. There’s nothing quite like reading things I wrote halfway through college to make me cringe. There is some good stuff there, but also: 20-year-old Chris Krycho was, uhh… &lt;em&gt;very&lt;/em&gt; emotional. And the way I approach my faith has shifted a lot since then.&lt;a href="#fnref1" class="footnote-back" role="doc-backlink"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn2" role="doc-endnote"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Running &lt;code&gt;wc -w&lt;/code&gt; on the posts I wrote in 2018 reports 80,911 words, but that number includes all the post metadata. Assuming an average of 65 words of metadata per post, across the 96 posts I wrote, that comes out to around 6,250 words. So: very roughly 75,000, for an average of about 780 words per post. Not too shabby!&lt;a href="#fnref2" class="footnote-back" role="doc-backlink"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn3" role="doc-endnote"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Meta note: that includes this post. So the final count depends on how long I make the previous footnote. And this one. Such recursion!&lt;a href="#fnref3" class="footnote-back" role="doc-backlink"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn4" role="doc-endnote"&gt;&lt;p&gt;So: what of this kind of year-end review, which is itself not exactly one of those more important writing projects? Good point. I find his exercise helpful, though, and I’d almost certainly be doing it privately in nearly identical terms. I have found this practice helpful over the years, despite never coming near accomplishing the specific goals I’ve set myself, so I expect to keep up this habit.&lt;a href="#fnref4" class="footnote-back" role="doc-backlink"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn5" role="doc-endnote"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is another reason for the emphasis on focusing my writing time on high-value projects. Time I spend writing random blog posts is time I am &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; spending on these programming efforts.&lt;a href="#fnref5" class="footnote-back" role="doc-backlink"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 23 Dec 2018 14:35:00 -0500</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2018-12-23:/2018/some-closing-thoughts.html</guid><category>writing</category><category>reading</category><category>podcasting</category><category>burnout</category><category>fitness</category><category>health</category><category>career</category></item><item><title>Stewarding My Reserves</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2018/stewarding-my-reserves.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.chriskrycho.com/2018/assumed-audiences.html"&gt;Assumed Audience:&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/b&gt; anyone and everyone, but &lt;em&gt;especially&lt;/em&gt; people who have followed along as &lt;a href="https://www.chriskrycho.com/burnout/"&gt;I have written about my experience of burnout&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ve slowly but surely been coming out of this burnout over the last seven weeks or so. I pulled &lt;em&gt;hard&lt;/em&gt; on some levers at work and got some changes there, which gave me the space to start recovering. I have also been working aggressively at identifying what steps I need to take to deal with my mental health more generally—including dealing with a bunch of griefs that have mounted up over many, many years, and which I have (for various reasons, many of them good) simply set aside to deal with later. Do that too long, and later becomes &lt;em&gt;now&lt;/em&gt;, whether you want it to or not.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I find that this recovery phase has its own dangers, subtler but no less real than being in the thick of the burnout was. Now, I’m tempted to dive back into the deep end—to forget just how rough a spot I was in not that many weeks ago, and pick up too much, and… land myself back in that mess. As one of my pastors put it to me last week (putting to words things I’d been thinking), it’s easy to forget that just because we’re through the burnout doesn’t mean we have any reserves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Spoiler: he was right. I don’t have any reserves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I felt, this week, a bit of a slide toward the same malaise and cynicism and deep fatigue that characterized me for a good long chunk of the year—and it’s no surprise why. We’ve been going nonstop since before Thanksgiving. I drove away from my house for a quick personal trip only twelve hours after we got back from visiting Jaimie’s family in Texas over that holiday. I gave one of the best (and probably one of the most important) tech talks I’ve ever given at Olo the day after I got back from that trip. I helped finish getting &lt;a href="https://blog.rust-lang.org/2018/11/29/a-new-look-for-rust-lang-org.html"&gt;the Rust website redesign&lt;/a&gt; out the door in time for the &lt;a href="https://blog.rust-lang.org/2018/12/06/Rust-1.31-and-rust-2018.html"&gt;Rust 2018 Edition launch&lt;/a&gt; this week.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And it is very obvious to me that this has been &lt;em&gt;too much&lt;/em&gt;. I need to steward my recovery carefully, so that it proves to be a genuine recovery and not merely a little upswing before dipping back into burnout. I need to go ahead and deal with those unprocessed griefs. I need to say no to more things outside my family and work, no matter how good or appealing those things are. In the medium term, I need to build better patterns of life around all these things, so that I don’t end up again where I was in early October.&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 09 Dec 2018 18:15:00 -0500</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2018-12-09:/2018/stewarding-my-reserves.html</guid><category>burnout</category><category>productivity</category><category>rest</category></item><item><title>Neither Being Dumb Nor Giving In</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2018/neither-being-dumb-nor-giving-in.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;One of the ways I respond to my experience of burnout is &lt;em&gt;refusing&lt;/em&gt; to let the fact that I’m experiencing burnout set the terms of my life. I cannot ignore the fact that I’m burnt out unless I want to make things worse. But I also recognize that with experiences like burnout, letting them dominate our mental lives can make things significantly worse, too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is a fine little dance here: acknowledging the reality of the hard things we experience, while not narrowing our lives to &lt;em&gt;merely&lt;/em&gt; those hard things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An example of the way I try to walk this line in my own life: I am not holding myself to some of the exercise goals I set for myself before the worst of the burnout set in… but I am still exercising every day. That half marathon I wanted to run at the end of this month? I’m not running it. On too many runs in the last few weeks my body has simply shut down a few miles into a run. Two miles in, six miles in, three miles in… none of them are anything like 13.1 miles. So while I’ve managed a 14-mile run this training season, in the weeks since I did I have gotten loud, clear signals that continuing to push myself toward the race was a bad idea.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That doesn’t mean I’m going to stop running, though. It means I’m going to be careful and wise about it. I’m going to listen to my body even more carefully when I’m out on a run than I normally do (and I’m not one of those people who keeps running when they shouldn’t anyway!). I’m going to switch some days over to doing Pilates with my wife instead of running. But also, on days like this past Saturday, when I felt &lt;em&gt;terrible&lt;/em&gt; emotionally and wanted nothing more than to lay in bed… I got up and went for a 4-mile run. It helped.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Again: I won’t be dumb about my response to my burnout and pretend it doesn’t exist. But I also refuse to let especially the emotional experience of burnout be wholly determinative of what I do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An aside, and a thing I will come back to in the future: you may have noticed that I have avoided writing of burnout as something external to me. This is intentional. Too often in our discussions of burnout, depression, or the like, we externalize them—a way of distancing ourselves from them, usually aimed at the same kinds of things I’ve gestured at in this little post. For reasons I’ll come back to, I don’t think that’s quite the right solution: burnout is not a foe outside myself to vanquish, but a set of emotional, physical, and spiritual things &lt;em&gt;about&lt;/em&gt; myself. Again: more on that in the future.&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 15 Oct 2018 09:20:00 -0400</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2018-10-15:/2018/neither-being-dumb-nor-giving-in.html</guid><category>burnout</category><category>exercise</category><category>running</category></item><item><title>Burnout Symptoms</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2018/burnout-symptoms.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Some of the symptoms I’ve had while experiencing burnout, all of which are exceedingly unusual in life for me normally:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;aches and pains:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;headaches: from low-level and relatively minor, to shooting pain in the temples or behind the eyes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;backaches and neckaches: unrelieved (and unrelievable, no matter the Pilates routine) sensations of muscle tension, including everything from the lower back to the base of my skull—likely a partial cause of the low-level headaches&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;stomachaches: so far, only when feeling exceptionally stressed, but regularly and often when feeling particularly stressed&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;occasional pains in my limbs unrelated to exercise I’ve done&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;fatigue:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I only sleep 7–7½ hours of sleep a night but now am needing 8½–9 hours to feel even somewhat rested&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;decreased ability while exercising: though I have kept exercising anyway, my general athletic performance is much degraded and on a semi-regular basis I’m unable to complete workouts normally&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;cynicism&lt;/strong&gt;: finding it difficult to think the best of decisions others make, even when I can explain them in rational and reasonable ways&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;severe demotivation:&lt;/strong&gt; having difficulty getting to work and through work; and having a hard time doing any of my normal side projects. The only hobby which has felt &lt;em&gt;doable&lt;/em&gt; for most of the last few months has been &lt;a href="https://www.chriskrycho.com/2018/making-things-helps.html" title="Making Things Helps"&gt;writing on and working on this website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;crying, of all sorts:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;streams of silent tears: not in the “I have something in my eye” sense but in the “I have tears streaming down my face” sense—but with no trigger&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;quietly sobbing, with or without any trigger—but never triggers that would ordinarily prompt much of a reaction at all, much less crying&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;outright weeping, to date only with a trigger—but again, with triggers of the sort that would normally just make me roll my eyes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;anger:&lt;/strong&gt; seething frustration boiling over into white-hot rage or cold furies—not things I am prone to, and often over the smallest provocations from work. (Never from family! This is one of the clearest signals that I’m dealing with &lt;em&gt;burnout&lt;/em&gt;.) I carefully contain these, effectively practicing various ways of calming myself—especially prayer, recitation of Scripture, and singing hymns—and I &lt;em&gt;never&lt;/em&gt; allow myself to lash out at the people around me. It is nonetheless strange and disconcerting to have minor nuisances provoke such deep anger.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;cravings:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;for sugary foods: occasionally sated with a good chocolate chip cookie, but more usually with a good piece of fruit&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;for alcohol: &lt;em&gt;always&lt;/em&gt; set aside when I feel a “need” for it, lest it become a crutch or a means of self-medication&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Burnout is &lt;em&gt;strange&lt;/em&gt;. Our bodies and minds tell us the story of the stresses we experience, whether we want to hear the story or not. (I’m listening clearly, and making lots of moves to deal with it. More on that in the weeks ahead.)&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 11 Oct 2018 20:20:00 -0400</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2018-10-11:/2018/burnout-symptoms.html</guid><category>burnout</category><category>exercise</category><category>health</category></item><item><title>Making Things Helps</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2018/making-things-helps.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;As a small bit of follow-up to my recent post on &lt;a href="https://www.chriskrycho.com/2018/cant-stop-wont-stop.html" title="Can’t Stop, Won’t Stop"&gt;blogging as part of what helps with my burnout&lt;/a&gt;, I thought it worth noting that this principle is a bit broader than just &lt;em&gt;blogging&lt;/em&gt; for me. Writing (currently mostly expressed in the form of blogging) is deep in me, and so blogging remains a helpful outlet.&lt;a href="#fn1" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref1" role="doc-noteref"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; But so a fair number of other things which might look like &lt;em&gt;work&lt;/em&gt; to other people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tonight I started putting together some thoughts on what some extensions to an open source software library I maintain might look like.&lt;a href="#fn2" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref2" role="doc-noteref"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; This after what has to be a record-setting week: the kind in which I reviewed and merged 60 pull requests for a ridiculous crunch of a project I’m on at work. I’m exhausted. I had another one of those moments this evening where I started crying a bit as I was sitting down to eat dinner and praying beforehand. Why? Just because I’m &lt;em&gt;that&lt;/em&gt; emotionally wrung out: nothing was wrong in the particular moment at all, and probably the “trigger” was actually the small bit of relief of being &lt;em&gt;away&lt;/em&gt; from the particular (very weird) stressors of this project at work for a while.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So why in the world did I start writing up thoughts about an open-source library after that? And why have I been spending my evenings reading all about a particularly nerdy bit of computer science this week?&lt;a href="#fn3" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref3" role="doc-noteref"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; Because, as I suggested at the beginning, these things are what end up feeling restful or re-energizing to me. (That might make me weird. I’m okay with that. I’ve been weird for a long time.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Much of the advice around burnout emphasizes “not working.” There’s good reason for that, but it’s important to understand the underlying reasons for that advice. Burnout &lt;em&gt;usually&lt;/em&gt; stems from work-related stress, for an appropriately broad definition of “work.”&lt;a href="#fn4" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref4" role="doc-noteref"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;4&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; Besides the stressors themselves, many of us—whether we admit it or not!—put far too much of our self-worth into our work. Putting it aside leaves us feeling worthless or useless. If your burnout is coming from the combo of stress and having invested your self-worth in your work, then you’re not likely to get better until you disengage from that work &lt;em&gt;entirely&lt;/em&gt; for large stretches of time: that is, until you are &lt;em&gt;forced&lt;/em&gt; to divest your self-worth from your work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But there are other ways burnout comes to pass. For me, it’s a combination of particular work stressors with the stress my family has undergone over the last year: a cross-country move, building a house, and most of all my father’s (so far blessedly successful) fight with a brain tumor. The work stressors are largely not related to the work &lt;em&gt;load&lt;/em&gt;, though; and I have by God’s grace kept my personal sense of meaning and value detached from my job. Insofar as my work is involved, the burnout is much more about frustrations and stymied aims and boredom with certain parts of the job than it is about overwork! The net of that is that doing some open-source brainstorming in the evenings is not a way of reinforcing the things that have caused this (though it very well &lt;em&gt;could&lt;/em&gt; become that). Rather, left in the same kinds of space as my blogging (“not on a schedule, not on a deadline, but whenever I feel like it”), it ends up being a &lt;em&gt;counter&lt;/em&gt; to burnout.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All of which is a long way of saying: if you’re experiencing burnout, you need to figure out &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt; if you want to have a chance of getting through it. Otherwise good advice will actually mislead you otherwise. If your problem is that you’ve dumped all your self-worth into your open-source work, &lt;em&gt;stop doing open-source work&lt;/em&gt;. On the other hand, if the cause of your burnout is that you’re deeply invested in caretaking for someone in your family, it might well be that doing something that looks like &lt;em&gt;work&lt;/em&gt; to someone else—even writing a novel or something similarly massive in scale—might be a genuine relief and outlet for you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For me, &lt;em&gt;genuine rest&lt;/em&gt; often includes writing and learning and thinking and creating—not by themselves, but as part of a healthy mix that includes many other good things: a healthy dose of exercise and building LEGO contraptions with my daughters and watching &lt;cite&gt;The Expanse&lt;/cite&gt; with my wife, and enjoying the company of good friends over good food and good drinks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn1" role="doc-endnote"&gt;&lt;p&gt;I’ve actually been blogging longer than I’ve been writing software in any meaningful way. I did tiny bits of Visual Basic and C++ in middle school and high school, and I started picking up &lt;abbr&gt;HTML&lt;/abbr&gt; and &lt;abbr&gt;CSS&lt;/abbr&gt; for the sake of my website and blog in college. I didn’t pick up programming in a more general sense until I learned Fortran for my senior capstone project in physics!&lt;a href="#fnref1" class="footnote-back" role="doc-backlink"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn2" role="doc-endnote"&gt;&lt;p&gt;I’m thinking about &lt;code&gt;Future&lt;/code&gt; and/or &lt;code&gt;Task&lt;/code&gt; extensions to &lt;a href="https://github.com/chriskrycho/true-myth"&gt;True Myth&lt;/a&gt;, for those of you interested in the details. I’ll have a GitHub issue up sometime soon-ish, and might blog about it here as well.&lt;a href="#fnref2" class="footnote-back" role="doc-backlink"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn3" role="doc-endnote"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Conflict-free_replicated_data_type"&gt;&lt;abbr title="Conflict-free Replicated Data Type"&gt;CRDT&lt;/abbr&gt;s&lt;/a&gt;, for my fellow software nerds out there. &lt;a href="http://archagon.net/blog/2018/03/24/data-laced-with-history/" title="Data Laced With History"&gt;This introduction&lt;/a&gt; is absolutely outstanding, as are a number of the pieces it links to. Among other things, I actually &lt;em&gt;understand&lt;/em&gt; a few concepts in set theory I’ve had a hard time wrapping my head around in the past, because the explanations here are so good.&lt;a href="#fnref3" class="footnote-back" role="doc-backlink"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn4" role="doc-endnote"&gt;&lt;p&gt;As I talked about in my &lt;a href="https://newrustacean.com/show_notes/bonus/burnout/"&gt;New Rustacean episode about burnout&lt;/a&gt;, lots of things which &lt;em&gt;aren’t&lt;/em&gt; “work” in the “what I do to pay the bills” sense can also be triggers.&lt;a href="#fnref4" class="footnote-back" role="doc-backlink"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 28 Sep 2018 20:45:00 -0400</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2018-09-28:/2018/making-things-helps.html</guid><category>burnout</category><category>open-source software</category><category>productivity</category><category>rest</category></item><item><title>Can’t Stop, Won’t Stop</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2018/cant-stop-wont-stop.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;A couple things have had me thinking about blogging today. I happened to end up reading &lt;a href="http://christineyen.com/2014/01/in-2014-reflection-consistency-and-balls/"&gt;this post by Christine Yen from 2014&lt;/a&gt; just a few hours after listening to &lt;a href="https://craigmod.com/onmargins/005/"&gt;Craig Mod’s interview with Jason Kottke&lt;/a&gt;. They have two very different takes on blogging. Yen’s piece has the sense so often echoed online: “I want to be blogging more.” Mod’s interview with Kottke notes how remarkable a 20-year-old website with daily blog-like entries throughout is, and Kottke emphasizes how he loves the work (and it is work!) that he does to keep it up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My relationship with blogging is somewhere nearer Kottke than Yen on that spectrum. While I have &lt;em&gt;occasionally&lt;/em&gt; resolved to blog more—and occasionally to &lt;a href="https://www.chriskrycho.com/2018/writing-plans-for-the-rest-of-2018.html"&gt;blog &lt;em&gt;less&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;!—I find that mostly my problem is that I cannot stop blogging even if I want to.&lt;a href="#fn1" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref1" role="doc-noteref"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the things that’s strange about &lt;a href="https://www.chriskrycho.com/burnout"&gt;burnout&lt;/a&gt; is that what constitutes &lt;em&gt;rest&lt;/em&gt; from the stressors will vary from person to person. Writing, for may people, might be a source of tension or stress. The perceived &lt;em&gt;obligation&lt;/em&gt; to generate content can be stressful.&lt;a href="#fn2" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref2" role="doc-noteref"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; But far more often, writing is restful for me. It is a way of &lt;a href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2018/blog-as-note-taking-tool.html"&gt;organizing my mental life&lt;/a&gt;—publicly, but (at least) as much for my own benefit as for that of potential readers—and organizing my mental life is somehow a good form of stress relief.&lt;a href="#fn3" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref3" role="doc-noteref"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; So it turns out that blogging—not on a schedule, not on a deadline, but whenever I feel like it (and that is obviously a lot)—is good for me in the midst of this. It seems to go in the same basic bucket as running.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So: my aim back in May, just before I realized what exactly I’m dealing with in burnout, to blog less in the interest of getting &lt;em&gt;other&lt;/em&gt; projects done? When I said this?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don’t think I could stop myself from blogging that way from time to time if I &lt;em&gt;wanted&lt;/em&gt; to. But it won’t be the focus, and if things are relatively quiet around here for much of the rest of the year, don’t worry… you know why!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, at this point I’ve let that go. Subconsciously at first. Now consciously. I wasn’t wrong when I said couldn’t stop myself from writing &lt;em&gt;entirely&lt;/em&gt;. Now I just know that I also &lt;em&gt;mostly shouldn’t.&lt;/em&gt; There may be points on other writing projects in the future, times when I’m not dealing with not-so-mild-anymore burnout, when I can and should. But not now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn1" role="doc-endnote"&gt;&lt;p&gt;In truth, as this blog post suggests, I cannot even stop blogging about blogging! I’ve been metablogging for over a decade now; don’t expect it to stop anytime soon!&lt;a href="#fnref1" class="footnote-back" role="doc-backlink"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn2" role="doc-endnote"&gt;&lt;p&gt;More than one thoughtful listener to my &lt;a href="https://newrustacean.com/show_notes/bonus/burnout/"&gt;most recent New Rustacean episode&lt;/a&gt; responded along these very lines; and it’s a point I haven’t made here before, so: consider it raised.&lt;a href="#fnref2" class="footnote-back" role="doc-backlink"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn3" role="doc-endnote"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Interpret that as you will. I have given it no small amount of thought myself. As I noted on the aforementioned latest New Rustacean episode: I am hypermetacognitive, and my incessant metacogitating is a source of alternating bemusement and frustration for my poor wife.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yes. I said “incessant metacogitating.” This is what poor Jaimie has to put up with.&lt;a href="#fnref3" class="footnote-back" role="doc-backlink"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 26 Sep 2018 20:15:00 -0400</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2018-09-26:/2018/cant-stop-wont-stop.html</guid><category>writing</category><category>blogging</category><category>burnout</category></item><item><title>Burnout (New Rustacean)</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2018/burnout-new-rustacean.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Insofar as I have a platform and a voice on this blog and &lt;a href="https://www.chriskrycho.com/podcasts.html"&gt;my podcasts&lt;/a&gt;, I hope to use it to help &lt;em&gt;others&lt;/em&gt; who experience burnout as well. So, the only episode I’ve managed to release of New Rustacean so far in September is &lt;a href="https://newrustacean.com/show_notes/bonus/burnout/"&gt;this one, on burnout&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 22 Sep 2018 21:30:00 -0400</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2018-09-22:/2018/burnout-new-rustacean.html</guid><category>burnout</category><category>links</category><category>podcasting</category></item><item><title>Going Offline</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2018/going-offline.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Several times this week, I signed out of both my company Slack and the &lt;a href="https://embercommunity.slack.com/"&gt;Ember Community Slack&lt;/a&gt; and just worked in “solitude” for about six and a half of the eight hours I was working. It was, in a word, &lt;em&gt;bliss&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over the past few years, I’ve come to enjoy a lot of chatting during the day while at work, and the social interaction is very much a &lt;em&gt;must&lt;/em&gt; in a lot of ways for someone who works remotely. The flip side, however, is that chat is a huge time-suck, and more than that it’s a constant drain on attention. I’m far from the first person to see this or to say it, of course, and I’ve experienced it before. But it struck me much more forcefully this week than it usually has in the past.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some of that, I suspect, is the effect of the burnout I’ve been experiencing: I’m much more taxed by social interaction and by shifts in attention right now than I have been in the past. More and more, though, I’ve also become aware of the effect the constant distraction of chat has on me. I am much less effective as a software developer when I am constantly switching modes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To be sure: some tasks are more mentally demanding than others. Some days I get done &lt;em&gt;plenty&lt;/em&gt; while still switching contexts often—less, perhaps, than I might if I were not being interrupted, but also perhaps &lt;em&gt;more&lt;/em&gt; in the sense that enabling others to finish &lt;em&gt;their&lt;/em&gt; tasks is also important. When I need to dive deep on something hard, though—or even when I just need to get after a &lt;em&gt;large&lt;/em&gt; task—the kind of mental silence that signing out of chat affords is very helpful. I plan to make this a regular habit.&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 01 Sep 2018 09:00:00 -0400</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2018-09-01:/2018/going-offline.html</guid><category>chat</category><category>remote work</category><category>productivity</category><category>Slack</category><category>burnout</category></item><item><title>Dealing With Burnout In Public</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2018/dealing-with-burnout-in-public.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;For the last several months, I’ve been experiencing what I &lt;a href="https://www.chriskrycho.com/2018/some-mild-burnout.html" title="Some Mild Burnout"&gt;initially described&lt;/a&gt; as &lt;em&gt;mild burnout&lt;/em&gt;. I’m not sure how mild it is at this point, but I’m definitely still experiencing it. As a result, I’m still thinking about how to mitigate it, minimize the length of it, and not least to walk through it well as a Christian.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of my aims–we will see how this plays out, but it is an aim–is to walk through this experience of burnout as publicly as seems appropriate. My reason is basically the same as I noted at the end of the post where I first noted publicly my experience of burnout. Seeing that others have gone through this, and seeing what helped them, can sometimes be a help to us as we walk through things. My experience won’t totally generalize. Some of the things I conclude aren’t going to stick for others because they reject my priors–more on that in a moment. But nonetheless, having something of a public record of dealing with something like this seems to me to be a broadly good thing if it’s done well. I hope to do it well. (I also hope you’ll bear with me insofar as I don’t!)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I noted that one of my interests is in what it looks like to walk through burnout as a Christian, specifically. This seems to be an interesting and relatively open topic. Most of the literature I’ve bumped into on the subject is explicitly secular, and it uses language and approaches I find &lt;em&gt;partial&lt;/em&gt; at best and &lt;em&gt;outright wrong&lt;/em&gt; at worst. I have a good resource paper to work through from my pastor–who, in God’s providence, wrote an academic research paper on the question for part of his D. Min. work–and I expect to be leaning a fair bit on the things I find there and in further secondary resources.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the same time, if my experience watching my wife walk through serious clinical depression over the last decade is any guide, there is a lot yet to be thought through and written about in this space. Nearly all the material I’ve encountered on depression in that time–&lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; all, but nearly all–misses the boat in one way or another. On just one of the many poles: the approaches tend either to wholly medicalize depression, or to throw medical factors out the window. Both of these responses seem to me very specifically &lt;em&gt;sub&lt;/em&gt;-Christian in their view of the human person.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So likewise does much of the literature I have found on burnout so far. The language of “self-care,” for example, is well-intentioned and much of the advice that comes with it is good. (I’ll try to unpack some of that at some point.) Yet I also think that framing does as much harm as good. My response to burnout is not merely a matter of taking care of myself as though my being happy and healthy is an end in and of itself. Rather, in a Christian frame, I ought to think in terms of &lt;em&gt;wisely stewarding my body and mind&lt;/em&gt;–a very different thing. The language of “stewardship” implies the end of the things I choose to do and not to do: not merely my own well-being, but my being able to steadfastly and faithfully honor God and serve the church and love all those around me well (Christian and non-Christian alike!).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is not merely a semantic game. The language we use, the way we choose to frame our lives, &lt;em&gt;matters&lt;/em&gt;. Self-care is about me. Stewardship involves me but is not about me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, much of the Christian discussion of issues like depression or burnout seems (curiously) narrow in its understanding of how to treat these problems. They are very often reduced simply to a question of one’s faith: if one were only more intent on taking joy in salvation, this problem would go away. To which I say: &lt;em&gt;have you read the Psalms?&lt;/em&gt; And more: &lt;em&gt;have you read Genesis 3?&lt;/em&gt; And not least: &lt;em&gt;have you read the gospels?&lt;/em&gt; When above I described what I have read as “sub-Christian,” I had these kinds of things in mind no less than the more “secular” advice. This kind of advice–to pray more and read one’s Bible more and repent of sin more–is not wrong, but it is desperately incomplete. When “seek joy more!” is &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; that is on offer, what is evidenced is an impoverished anthropology, a view of human nature that forgets our physicality or diminishes it to an ancillary to the &lt;em&gt;real&lt;/em&gt;, spiritual self; and which fails to grasp the ways our brokenness is not merely a matter of our choices but also of the world we encounter and the bodies and minds we find ourselves bearing as their own kinds of crosses in this age.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My own thoughts here are still nascent in many ways, though already shaped in many ways by the experience of watching my wife bear up well under her own burdens these last ten years. But I hope that as I trace them out–and also simply explain &lt;em&gt;how things are&lt;/em&gt;–that it will be helpful and encouraging to some other travelers along this particularly thorny way.&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 20 Aug 2018 07:00:00 -0400</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2018-08-20:/2018/dealing-with-burnout-in-public.html</guid><category>burnout</category><category>writing</category><category>depression</category></item><item><title>Imprecatory Psalms and Comfort for Weary Souls</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2018/imprecatory-psalms-and-comfort-for-weary-souls.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;I read Psalm 94 in my devotions this morning—one of the “imprecatory psalms” which prays for God to judge the wicked. After the last couple days I’ve had, I joked with my wife that I was praying it against Microsoft Windows.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The imprecatory content of the psalm is a deep well I shall not plumb today; in any case Windows is not an “enemy” the way the psalmist meant it. The thing I noticed as I reflected on the psalm, though, was how much it did that &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; good and right for me to imitate. This is not merely a prayer for God to deliver from oppression and to right wrongs. It is also a prayer that simultaneously demonstrates and practices trust in God: &lt;em&gt;demonstrates&lt;/em&gt;, because only one who trusts God can pray like this; and &lt;em&gt;practices&lt;/em&gt;, because the act of prayer is the necessary outworking of that trust. This is the right model for us whatever our circumstances—including for me, in the midst of some burnout and some particularly deep frustrations with the &lt;a href="http://bib.ly/Ge3.17-19" title="Genesis 3:17–19"&gt;thorns and thistles&lt;/a&gt; of work and labor in this life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Put more directly: If a man facing enemies of the murderous sort could say “When I thought, ‘My foot slips,’ / your steadfast love, oh &lt;span class="divine-name"&gt;Lord&lt;/span&gt;, held me up. // When the cares of my heart are many, / your consolations cheer my soul,” then I can—and must—say the same with him.&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 08 Aug 2018 07:00:00 -0400</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2018-08-08:/2018/imprecatory-psalms-and-comfort-for-weary-souls.html</guid><category>psalms</category><category>prayer</category><category>burnout</category></item><item><title>Some Mild Burnout</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2018/some-mild-burnout.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;I came to terms with reality a bit last week. It wasn’t fun. I concluded something attentive folks around me have likely known for a bit: I am dealing with low-level &lt;a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/healthy-lifestyle/adult-health/in-depth/burnout/art-20046642" title="The Mayo Clinic’s summary of burnout"&gt;burnout&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Have you become cynical or critical at work?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do you drag yourself to work and have trouble getting started once you arrive?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Have you become irritable or impatient with co-workers, customers or clients?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do you lack the energy to be consistently productive?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do you lack satisfaction from your achievements?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do you feel disillusioned about your job?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Are you using food, drugs or alcohol to feel better or to simply not feel?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Have your sleep habits or appetite changed?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Are you troubled by unexplained headaches, backaches or other physical complaints?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Mayo Clinic (the source for that list) notes that if you’re suffering from any &lt;em&gt;one&lt;/em&gt; of those, you may be experiencing burnout. By my count, I am experiencing &lt;em&gt;six&lt;/em&gt;. If you’re looking at the list and wondering: the first six. No changes to sleep, no abuse of food or drugs or alcohol, and I haven’t started having physical problems yet, which is why I classify what I’m experiencing as low-level or mild. But burnout is tricky. I’ve know a number of people who’ve had more serious cases—cases which led into significant physical problems that took them years to recover from.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my experience, when people think about burnout, they tend to think of the kind that comes from &lt;em&gt;overwork&lt;/em&gt; or from a lack of rest. You certainly can (indeed: certainly will) burn out by pulling 80-hour weeks for years on end. But those are not the only way you can burn out. You can also do it by ending up in a spot where you have too much responsibility, or deep and lasting conflict within your working environment, or sharp ethical disagreements with your leadership, or even just—“just” being the wrong word here—lasting mismatches between your tasks and the things you care about.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The particular reasons for my mild case of burnout aren’t the stereotypical kind. I get plenty of sleep, I enjoy my hobbies, I exercise and eat well, and I very carefully maintain a limit on the hours I work every week. I’m not &lt;em&gt;overworked&lt;/em&gt;. It’s a mix of other factors I won’t go into. The details aren’t actually that important here, and in any case my (genuinely excellent) manager knows them well and we are working on them together.&lt;a href="#fn1" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref1" role="doc-noteref"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What is important is trying to figure out how to keep the burnout from getting worse. And acknowledging that it can happen to anyone. And that you may not see it coming, may deny you’re experiencing till something finally makes it click for you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What made this all finally click for me? It was &lt;a href="http://www.alliancenet.org/mos/postcards-from-palookaville/six-years-on#.W0vQM4pMFvI" title="Six Years On"&gt;this post by Carl Trueman&lt;/a&gt;, reflecting on his own &lt;em&gt;very&lt;/em&gt; different vocation—specifically, his bivocational work as both a pastor and a professor:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A few months into my pastorate, an academic friend who had done the same thing for nine years wrote me a letter and urged me to be careful – as soon as I ceased to enjoy the hobbies and casual pleasures of life, he warned, I would be close to burn-out and would need to step down. I was glad of the warning – every minister I have ever know who has burned out has told me that there was no obvious warning: one day everything seemed fine, the next they were barely able to get out of bed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That started me thinking on my own experience, and if I’m not quite there, I can see warning signs. The biggest danger sign, for me, is an utter lack of motivation around some of my hobbies. I generally relax, as my wife can attest, in &lt;em&gt;weird&lt;/em&gt; ways—by writing, by building an open-source library, by reading hard-and-interesting books. For the last several months, I have had almost no interest in doing any of that. So I’ve a mild case at the moment, and I’m doing everything I can to keep it from getting worse.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Burnout like I have right now is not the end of the world, to be clear. It &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; manageable. Many people—including people in my own family—carry much more significant burdens in terms of physical and mental health. But it is real, and it’s dangerous in no small part because it can cascade into really serious mental and physical health problems if you let it spiral out of control.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, two things:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol type="1"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;If I’m a bit slower on open-source projects for a while, you know why.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I’d like to be that blog post for someone else. If you’re experiencing the things on that list, figure out how to change &lt;em&gt;something&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;section class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn1" role="doc-endnote"&gt;&lt;p&gt;You can assume that it’s not sharp conflict over ethical issues, because nothing in the world would make me jet from a job faster than that would&lt;a href="#fnref1" class="footnote-back" role="doc-backlink"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 15 Jul 2018 17:15:00 -0400</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2018-07-15:/2018/some-mild-burnout.html</guid><category>burnout</category><category>work</category><category>productivity</category></item><item><title>On Steam (Specifically, Running Out of It)</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2018/on-steam-specifically-running-out-of-it.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;I find myself this morning almost unable to write at all, and quite unable to write what I was &lt;em&gt;planning&lt;/em&gt; to be writing today. (I’ve been steadily pushing forward on &lt;a href="https://github.com/typed-ember/ember-typings/issues/14"&gt;a big “quest”-style issue for an open source software project I help maintain&lt;/a&gt;, and that’s how I planned to spend my writing time today.) But I’m feeling quite keenly the need of some time away from that project and indeed from a lot of the things that have had me burning the candle at both ends.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ve noted before that I &lt;a href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2018/intentional-cyclicality.html"&gt;go in cycles&lt;/a&gt;; one thing that I’ve also started to notice is that those cycles, unsurprisingly, include points where I’m just &lt;em&gt;done&lt;/em&gt;. I’m all out of steam. And I seem to have hit one of those just this week.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It makes sense: since last October, as a family we’ve moved across the country; lived with my parents for three months, during which time we learned that my dad had brain cancer and helped him and my mom through the surgery, recovery, and early parts of chemo and radiation); then moved into a new house; and joined a new church.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On top of that I’ve personally continued working on &lt;a href="https://newrustacean.com"&gt;New Rustacean&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://winningslowly.org"&gt;Winning Slowly&lt;/a&gt;, helped ship the most important release of &lt;a href="https://github.com/typed-ember/ember-cli-typescript"&gt;ember-cli-typescript&lt;/a&gt; in the project’s history, taught a workshop on TypeScript at EmberConf, and helped kick off one of the most important front-end development projects in Olo’s history.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of &lt;em&gt;course&lt;/em&gt; I’m tired. Of &lt;em&gt;course&lt;/em&gt; I feel like I’m just out of steam.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The trick, for the moment, is that there are some things I really feel I should carry to some specific points &lt;em&gt;before&lt;/em&gt; I take a week or two off. Getting that quest issue that I was going to be writing this morning done, and a related &lt;a href="https://github.com/emberjs/rfcs"&gt;Ember.js RFC&lt;/a&gt; on the relationship of TypeScript and Ember.js, and getting the first of our beta releases for this project at Olo out the door… all of those are things that really just &lt;em&gt;need&lt;/em&gt; to happen before I take that time off. After I get through those, though, I think I’m taking a week or so off. Maybe time it with Memorial Day to make it a full 10 days or something.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And in the meantime, I do things like write little blog posts thinking about “running out of steam” not because it’s all that important for the world to know, but because it’s a way of keeping &lt;em&gt;some&lt;/em&gt; degree of forward momentum, continuing to maintain my &lt;a href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2017/momentum.html"&gt;daily writing habit&lt;/a&gt;, and generally doing all the little things that make it possible for me to actually get across the finish line on those projects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because—weird though it may seem in some ways—even when I’m tired like it, I know through long experience that the way I actually get across those finish lines is by keeping up my forward motion. It’s very much like the feeling in the last 5k of a half marathon. (A half marathon is two five-milers and a 5k, and thinking about it that way is the way to run it effectively.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Everything hurts. You don’t feel like you have anything left. But in fact, if you’ve done the right things up to that point, you &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt; have enough left. The way to finish well is not only to keep putting one foot in front of the other, but also to push a little harder, and a little harder, and a little harder, until you hit the finish line. You have to watch out, of course, and not hurt yourself. That’s the trick with mental fatigue, too. Burnout is a real thing. But, as with running, if you’ve built up your mental muscles well and built up the reserves of &lt;em&gt;experience&lt;/em&gt; that you need, you know the difference. You know when you need to stop early for a day and go read a novel. You know when to push through. You know when to take a day off of the quest issue and write a quirky, and not-all-that-coherent, blog post about the experience of fatigue and thinking about pushing on. And you know that you still need to finish.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Edit (October 11, 2018):&lt;/strong&gt; I’ve added my &lt;a href="https://www.chriskrycho.com/burnout/"&gt;#burnout&lt;/a&gt; tag to this post retroactively because I now recognize much of what I wrote here as some of the earlier symptoms of what I didn’t concretely identify until &lt;a href="https://www.chriskrycho.com/2018/some-mild-burnout.html"&gt;a bit later&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 05 Apr 2018 07:00:00 -0400</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2018-04-05:/2018/on-steam-specifically-running-out-of-it.html</guid><category>productivity</category><category>writing</category><category>open-source software</category><category>burnout</category></item></channel></rss>