<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Chris Krycho - burnout</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/</link><description></description><lastBuildDate>Sat, 22 Sep 2018 21:30:00 -0400</lastBuildDate><item><title>Burnout (New Rustacean)</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2018/burnout-new-rustacean.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Insofar as I have a platform and a voice on this blog and &lt;a href="https://www.chriskrycho.com/podcasts.html"&gt;my podcasts&lt;/a&gt;, I hope to use it to help &lt;em&gt;others&lt;/em&gt; who experience burnout as well. So, the only episode I’ve managed to release of New Rustacean so far in September is &lt;a href="https://newrustacean.com/show_notes/bonus/burnout/"&gt;this one, on burnout&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 22 Sep 2018 21:30:00 -0400</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2018-09-22:/2018/burnout-new-rustacean.html</guid><category>burnout</category><category>links</category><category>podcasting</category></item><item><title>Going Offline</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2018/going-offline.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Several times this week, I signed out of both my company Slack and the &lt;a href="https://embercommunity.slack.com/"&gt;Ember Community Slack&lt;/a&gt; and just worked in “solitude” for about six and a half of the eight hours I was working. It was, in a word, &lt;em&gt;bliss&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over the past few years, I’ve come to enjoy a lot of chatting during the day while at work, and the social interaction is very much a &lt;em&gt;must&lt;/em&gt; in a lot of ways for someone who works remotely. The flip side, however, is that chat is a huge time-suck, and more than that it’s a constant drain on attention. I’m far from the first person to see this or to say it, of course, and I’ve experienced it before. But it struck me much more forcefully this week than it usually has in the past.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some of that, I suspect, is the effect of the burnout I’ve been experiencing: I’m much more taxed by social interaction and by shifts in attention right now than I have been in the past. More and more, though, I’ve also become aware of the effect the constant distraction of chat has on me. I am much less effective as a software developer when I am constantly switching modes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To be sure: some tasks are more mentally demanding than others. Some days I get done &lt;em&gt;plenty&lt;/em&gt; while still switching contexts often—less, perhaps, than I might if I were not being interrupted, but also perhaps &lt;em&gt;more&lt;/em&gt; in the sense that enabling others to finish &lt;em&gt;their&lt;/em&gt; tasks is also important. When I need to dive deep on something hard, though—or even when I just need to get after a &lt;em&gt;large&lt;/em&gt; task—the kind of mental silence that signing out of chat affords is very helpful. I plan to make this a regular habit.&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 01 Sep 2018 09:00:00 -0400</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2018-09-01:/2018/going-offline.html</guid><category>chat</category><category>remote work</category><category>productivity</category><category>Slack</category><category>burnout</category></item><item><title>Dealing With Burnout In Public</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2018/dealing-with-burnout-in-public.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;For the last several months, I’ve been experiencing what I &lt;a href="https://www.chriskrycho.com/2018/some-mild-burnout.html" title="Some Mild Burnout"&gt;initially described&lt;/a&gt; as &lt;em&gt;mild burnout&lt;/em&gt;. I’m not sure how mild it is at this point, but I’m definitely still experiencing it. As a result, I’m still thinking about how to mitigate it, minimize the length of it, and not least to walk through it well as a Christian.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of my aims–we will see how this plays out, but it is an aim–is to walk through this experience of burnout as publicly as seems appropriate. My reason is basically the same as I noted at the end of the post where I first noted publicly my experience of burnout. Seeing that others have gone through this, and seeing what helped them, can sometimes be a help to us as we walk through things. My experience won’t totally generalize. Some of the things I conclude aren’t going to stick for others because they reject my priors–more on that in a moment. But nonetheless, having something of a public record of dealing with something like this seems to me to be a broadly good thing if it’s done well. I hope to do it well. (I also hope you’ll bear with me insofar as I don’t!)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I noted that one of my interests is in what it looks like to walk through burnout as a Christian, specifically. This seems to be an interesting and relatively open topic. Most of the literature I’ve bumped into on the subject is explicitly secular, and it uses language and approaches I find &lt;em&gt;partial&lt;/em&gt; at best and &lt;em&gt;outright wrong&lt;/em&gt; at worst. I have a good resource paper to work through from my pastor–who, in God’s providence, wrote an academic research paper on the question for part of his D. Min. work–and I expect to be leaning a fair bit on the things I find there and in further secondary resources.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the same time, if my experience watching my wife walk through serious clinical depression over the last decade is any guide, there is a lot yet to be thought through and written about in this space. Nearly all the material I’ve encountered on depression in that time–&lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; all, but nearly all–misses the boat in one way or another. On just one of the many poles: the approaches tend either to wholly medicalize depression, or to throw medical factors out the window. Both of these responses seem to me very specifically &lt;em&gt;sub&lt;/em&gt;-Christian in their view of the human person.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So likewise does much of the literature I have found on burnout so far. The language of “self-care,” for example, is well-intentioned and much of the advice that comes with it is good. (I’ll try to unpack some of that at some point.) Yet I also think that framing does as much harm as good. My response to burnout is not merely a matter of taking care of myself as though my being happy and healthy is an end in and of itself. Rather, in a Christian frame, I ought to think in terms of &lt;em&gt;wisely stewarding my body and mind&lt;/em&gt;–a very different thing. The language of “stewardship” implies the end of the things I choose to do and not to do: not merely my own well-being, but my being able to steadfastly and faithfully honor God and serve the church and love all those around me well (Christian and non-Christian alike!).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is not merely a semantic game. The language we use, the way we choose to frame our lives, &lt;em&gt;matters&lt;/em&gt;. Self-care is about me. Stewardship involves me but is not about me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, much of the Christian discussion of issues like depression or burnout seems (curiously) narrow in its understanding of how to treat these problems. They are very often reduced simply to a question of one’s faith: if one were only more intent on taking joy in salvation, this problem would go away. To which I say: &lt;em&gt;have you read the Psalms?&lt;/em&gt; And more: &lt;em&gt;have you read Genesis 3?&lt;/em&gt; And not least: &lt;em&gt;have you read the gospels?&lt;/em&gt; When above I described what I have read as “sub-Christian,” I had these kinds of things in mind no less than the more “secular” advice. This kind of advice–to pray more and read one’s Bible more and repent of sin more–is not wrong, but it is desperately incomplete. When “seek joy more!” is &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; that is on offer, what is evidenced is an impoverished anthropology, a view of human nature that forgets our physicality or diminishes it to an ancillary to the &lt;em&gt;real&lt;/em&gt;, spiritual self; and which fails to grasp the ways our brokenness is not merely a matter of our choices but also of the world we encounter and the bodies and minds we find ourselves bearing as their own kinds of crosses in this age.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My own thoughts here are still nascent in many ways, though already shaped in many ways by the experience of watching my wife bear up well under her own burdens these last ten years. But I hope that as I trace them out–and also simply explain &lt;em&gt;how things are&lt;/em&gt;–that it will be helpful and encouraging to some other travelers along this particularly thorny way.&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 20 Aug 2018 07:00:00 -0400</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2018-08-20:/2018/dealing-with-burnout-in-public.html</guid><category>burnout</category><category>writing</category><category>depression</category></item><item><title>Imprecatory Psalms and Comfort for Weary Souls</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2018/imprecatory-psalms-and-comfort-for-weary-souls.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;I read Psalm 94 in my devotions this morning—one of the “imprecatory psalms” which prays for God to judge the wicked. After the last couple days I’ve had, I joked with my wife that I was praying it against Microsoft Windows.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The imprecatory content of the psalm is a deep well I shall not plumb today; in any case Windows is not an “enemy” the way the psalmist meant it. The thing I noticed as I reflected on the psalm, though, was how much it did that &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; good and right for me to imitate. This is not merely a prayer for God to deliver from oppression and to right wrongs. It is also a prayer that simultaneously demonstrates and practices trust in God: &lt;em&gt;demonstrates&lt;/em&gt;, because only one who trusts God can pray like this; and &lt;em&gt;practices&lt;/em&gt;, because the act of prayer is the necessary outworking of that trust. This is the right model for us whatever our circumstances—including for me, in the midst of some burnout and some particularly deep frustrations with the &lt;a href="http://bib.ly/Ge3.17-19" title="Genesis 3:17–19"&gt;thorns and thistles&lt;/a&gt; of work and labor in this life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Put more directly: If a man facing enemies of the murderous sort could say “When I thought, ‘My foot slips,’ / your steadfast love, oh &lt;span class="divine-name"&gt;Lord&lt;/span&gt;, held me up. // When the cares of my heart are many, / your consolations cheer my soul,” then I can—and must—say the same with him.&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 08 Aug 2018 07:00:00 -0400</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2018-08-08:/2018/imprecatory-psalms-and-comfort-for-weary-souls.html</guid><category>psalms</category><category>prayer</category><category>burnout</category></item><item><title>Some Mild Burnout</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2018/some-mild-burnout.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;I came to terms with reality a bit last week. It wasn’t fun. I concluded something attentive folks around me have likely known for a bit: I am dealing with low-level &lt;a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/healthy-lifestyle/adult-health/in-depth/burnout/art-20046642" title="The Mayo Clinic’s summary of burnout"&gt;burnout&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Have you become cynical or critical at work?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do you drag yourself to work and have trouble getting started once you arrive?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Have you become irritable or impatient with co-workers, customers or clients?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do you lack the energy to be consistently productive?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do you lack satisfaction from your achievements?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do you feel disillusioned about your job?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Are you using food, drugs or alcohol to feel better or to simply not feel?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Have your sleep habits or appetite changed?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Are you troubled by unexplained headaches, backaches or other physical complaints?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Mayo Clinic (the source for that list) notes that if you’re suffering from any &lt;em&gt;one&lt;/em&gt; of those, you may be experiencing burnout. By my count, I am experiencing &lt;em&gt;six&lt;/em&gt;. If you’re looking at the list and wondering: the first six. No changes to sleep, no abuse of food or drugs or alcohol, and I haven’t started having physical problems yet, which is why I classify what I’m experiencing as low-level or mild. But burnout is tricky. I’ve know a number of people who’ve had more serious cases—cases which led into significant physical problems that took them years to recover from.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my experience, when people think about burnout, they tend to think of the kind that comes from &lt;em&gt;overwork&lt;/em&gt; or from a lack of rest. You certainly can (indeed: certainly will) burn out by pulling 80-hour weeks for years on end. But those are not the only way you can burn out. You can also do it by ending up in a spot where you have too much responsibility, or deep and lasting conflict within your working environment, or sharp ethical disagreements with your leadership, or even just—“just” being the wrong word here—lasting mismatches between your tasks and the things you care about.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The particular reasons for my mild case of burnout aren’t the stereotypical kind. I get plenty of sleep, I enjoy my hobbies, I exercise and eat well, and I very carefully maintain a limit on the hours I work every week. I’m not &lt;em&gt;overworked&lt;/em&gt;. It’s a mix of other factors I won’t go into. The details aren’t actually that important here, and in any case my (genuinely excellent) manager knows them well and we are working on them together.&lt;a href="#fn1" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref1"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What is important is trying to figure out how to keep the burnout from getting worse. And acknowledging that it can happen to anyone. And that you may not see it coming, may deny you’re experiencing till something finally makes it click for you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What made this all finally click for me? It was &lt;a href="http://www.alliancenet.org/mos/postcards-from-palookaville/six-years-on#.W0vQM4pMFvI" title="Six Years On"&gt;this post by Carl Trueman&lt;/a&gt;, reflecting on his own &lt;em&gt;very&lt;/em&gt; different vocation—specifically, his bivocational work as both a pastor and a professor:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A few months into my pastorate, an academic friend who had done the same thing for nine years wrote me a letter and urged me to be careful – as soon as I ceased to enjoy the hobbies and casual pleasures of life, he warned, I would be close to burn-out and would need to step down. I was glad of the warning – every minister I have ever know who has burned out has told me that there was no obvious warning: one day everything seemed fine, the next they were barely able to get out of bed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That started me thinking on my own experience, and if I’m not quite there, I can see warning signs. The biggest danger sign, for me, is an utter lack of motivation around some of my hobbies. I generally relax, as my wife can attest, in &lt;em&gt;weird&lt;/em&gt; ways—by writing, by building an open-source library, by reading hard-and-interesting books. For the last several months, I have had almost no interest in doing any of that. So I’ve a mild case at the moment, and I’m doing everything I can to keep it from getting worse.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Burnout like I have right now is not the end of the world, to be clear. It &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; manageable. Many people—including people in my own family—carry much more significant burdens in terms of physical and mental health. But it is real, and it’s dangerous in no small part because it can cascade into really serious mental and physical health problems if you let it spiral out of control.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, two things:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol type="1"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;If I’m a bit slower on open-source projects for a while, you know why.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I’d like to be that blog post for someone else. If you’re experiencing the things on that list, figure out how to change &lt;em&gt;something&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;section class="footnotes"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn1"&gt;&lt;p&gt;You can assume that it’s not sharp conflict over ethical issues, because nothing in the world would make me jet from a job faster than that would&lt;a href="#fnref1" class="footnote-back"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 15 Jul 2018 17:15:00 -0400</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2018-07-15:/2018/some-mild-burnout.html</guid><category>burnout</category><category>work</category><category>productivity</category></item></channel></rss>