<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Chris Krycho - career</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/</link><description></description><lastBuildDate>Tue, 13 Nov 2018 19:50:00 -0500</lastBuildDate><item><title>Just Write Down What You Do</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2018/just-write-down-what-you-do.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;i class=editorial&gt;&lt;b&gt;Assumed audience:&lt;/b&gt; people already persuaded of the value—at least to some extent—of “getting things done” strategies and having an idea of what you accomplished over the course of the year.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the last few years, I’ve had a habit—not kept perfectly, but done more often than not, courtesy of my daily &lt;a href="https://www.chriskrycho.com/pomodoro/"&gt;pomodoro&lt;/a&gt; discipline—of writing down what I do each day. Then, every week, I take a look at what I did each day, and turn that into a summary for the week. And every month, I look over my notes for weeks that made up that month, and write down what I did that month.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This has been &lt;em&gt;fantastic&lt;/em&gt; for me professionally. For one thing, it gives me a quick and easy way to see what I’ve done over the past however-long-between-performance-evaluations. The inevitable “What did you accomplish this year?” question has an an easy answer: I can look over my month-level summaries and summarize &lt;em&gt;those&lt;/em&gt;. (I’m inevitably frustrated by the months where I slacked off and don’t actually know what I did when do this exercise!)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Writing things down like this is also a helpful tool personally. I can look back at long stretches where I feel like I didn’t get a lot done and realize just many things I &lt;em&gt;did&lt;/em&gt; actually do. I have found this a helpful way of staving off the malaise that inevitably comes from months where there are just too many meetings, for example. What did I do? I &lt;i&gt;effected these changes&lt;/i&gt; (even if they weren’t in the form of code!).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I use &lt;a href="https://bear.app"&gt;Bear&lt;/a&gt; for this, but you could do it anywhere: a Word document or Google Doc, a notepad on your desk, in Emacs’ &lt;a href="https://orgmode.org"&gt;Org Mode&lt;/a&gt;, with &lt;a href="https://www.taskpaper.com"&gt;TaskPaper&lt;/a&gt;, or in &lt;a href="#"&gt;Trello&lt;/a&gt; (like my friend and colleague Ben Collins &lt;a href="https://benjamincollins.com/blog/using-trello-to-organize-my-daily-work/"&gt;does&lt;/a&gt;), or, well… whatever gets the job done.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The main thing is: write down what you did! Write it down at each of these scales, because it’s far easier to write down the larger scales if you wrote down the smaller scales. Once you start doing this regularly, you’ll probably find yourself frustrated at the times you failed to do it. (If you’re like me, those times will exist. It’s okay. Just start back up.) And again: make it fit you. But it’s one of the best tools I know of for personal and professional development, so I commend it to you!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;section id="bonus-my-bear-templates" class="level2"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Bonus: My Bear Templates&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In case you’re curious or want to copy my approach, here are the templates I use in Bear for each of my logs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section id="daily-log" class="level3"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Daily Log&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The daily log is the core of my entire productivity approach system, as well as the foundation of this specific logging strategy. These entries each includes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The date, which I format &lt;code&gt;YYYY.MM.DD&lt;/code&gt;—today would be &lt;code&gt;2018.11.13&lt;/code&gt;. A numeric year/month/day makes correctly sorting the notes easy. I use a period for the separator mostly because it looks nice in the font I use in Bear.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;A link to the parent week for the day, to make it easy to jump back and forth between individual day logs and a weekly log (as you’ll see below).&lt;a href="#fn1" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref1"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;A set of goals. I set the goals either at the beginning of the day, at the end of the preceding work day, or a combination of the two. I usually limit myself to 3 goals, unless I &lt;em&gt;know&lt;/em&gt; I have a bunch of very small tasks.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;A list of pomodoro sessions. The pomodoro technique is &lt;em&gt;most&lt;/em&gt; effective for getting things done—both in my experience and as others describe it—when each block has both a discrete goal and what you actually got done. This helps me keep my focus during that session rather than getting sidetracked. I further break these down with &lt;strong&gt;Session 1&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;Break&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;Session 2&lt;/strong&gt;, etc. subheads—not because this makes me productive, but just because I like it.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;A summary of the day as a whole. At the end of the day, I look back over the sessions and my goals, and write a sentence or two about what I did. This is also often a good time for me to write up the next day’s overarching goals and first session goal: I have a much better idea what I should be doing next when I’m wrapping things up for the day than I will the next morning!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;A set of checkboxes for me to track whether I succeed in breaking my day into 15 discrete pomodoro sessions,&lt;a href="#fn2" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref2"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and in standing at least 5 hours out of the day every day.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;pre class="md"&gt;&lt;code&gt;# &amp;lt;YYYY.MM.DD&amp;gt;

**Week:** [[]]

## Goals

- [ ] ::TODO::

---

## Details
### Session 1

1. **Goal:** ::TODO:: **Actual:** ::TODO::

---

## Summary

::TODO::

---

## Rhythm
### Pomodoro

- [ ] 1
- [ ] 2
- [ ] 3
- [ ] 4
- [ ] 5
- [ ] 6
- [ ] 7
- [ ] 8
- [ ] 9
- [ ] 10
- [ ] 11
- [ ] 12
- [ ] 13
- [ ] 14
- [ ] 15

### Stand

- [ ] 1
- [ ] 2
- [ ] 3
- [ ] 4
- [ ] 5
- [ ] 6
- [ ] 7
- [ ] 8
- [ ] 9
- [ ] 10&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="weekly-log" class="level3"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Weekly log&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The weekly log is just a place for me to be able to easily capture the results of my daily efforts. It links to the monthly log at the top just like the daily logs link to the month: for easy jumping back and forth. Each of the bullet points under &lt;strong&gt;Details&lt;/strong&gt; gets linked to a daily log entry, and the &lt;code&gt;::TODO::&lt;/code&gt; items get replaced with the &lt;strong&gt;Summary&lt;/strong&gt; from the daily log. At the end of the week, I write a summary of the whole week.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;Goals&lt;/strong&gt; heading here is new, something I only just started doing in the last couple of weeks, but so far it has proven helpful for me as I orient myself to what I want to get done on any given day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="md"&gt;&lt;code&gt;# &amp;lt;YYYY.MM.DD&amp;gt; – &amp;lt;YYYY.MM.DD&amp;gt;

**Month:** [[]]

## Goals

- [ ] ::TODO::

## Details

- [[]]: ::TODO::
- [[]]: ::TODO::
- [[]]: ::TODO::
- [[]]: ::TODO::
- [[]]: ::TODO::

## Summary

::TODO::&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="monthly-log" class="level3"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Monthly log&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The monthly log is exactly like the weekly log, but one level higher. It links back to individual weeks for easy jumping back and forth between the two views, and it newly has month-level goals. (As with weeks, I’m still experimenting with those!) The &lt;strong&gt;Details&lt;/strong&gt; bullets get filled in with links to weeks and the summary of each week copied over. At the end of the month, I take a few minutes to summarize those weeks. Unlike the lower-level summaries, I let that month-level summary expand out to a paragraph if need be. A lot tends to happen in a month!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="md"&gt;&lt;code&gt;# &amp;lt;YYYY.MM&amp;gt;

## Goals

- [ ] ::TODO::

## Details

- [[]]: ::TODO::
- [[]]: ::TODO::
- [[]]: ::TODO::
- [[]]: ::TODO::

## Summary

::TODO::&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section class="footnotes"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn1"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[[&amp;lt;some text&amp;gt;]]&lt;/code&gt; is Bear’s way of doing internal links to a note named &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;some text&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;a href="#fnref1" class="footnote-back"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn2"&gt;&lt;p&gt;15, not 16, because of the slop that ends up in most days. Most days, more than one session ends up being 35 minutes instead of 25. Over the course of the day, those come out to being the remaining half hour in the full 8 hours I make sure I give my employer. I know that from measuring consistently when I was working as a consultant: my &lt;a href="https://toggl.com"&gt;Toggl&lt;/a&gt; logs told the story clearly.&lt;a href="#fnref2" class="footnote-back"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 13 Nov 2018 19:50:00 -0500</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2018-11-13:/2018/just-write-down-what-you-do.html</guid><category>career</category><category>productivity</category><category>getting things done</category></item><item><title>Career Trajectory</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2018/career-trajectory.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;I’ve been thinking a bit, for the last year or so, about my &lt;em&gt;career trajectory&lt;/em&gt;. Where do I want to go, and what do I want to do, over the next 5–10 years?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the first seven years or so of my working life, I was just learning everything I could in software, following my interests but without much of a conscious plan, and making sure I put food on the table for my family. And I think that was absolutely the right tack to take! I &lt;em&gt;did&lt;/em&gt; learn a ton, across a relatively wide swath of the industry. I have worked:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;as a cog in megacorporation with over 100,000 employees, writing C targeting a real-time operating system;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;as the sole dedicated software developer in a company where I was the 12th employee, maintaining decades-old Fortran and C and C++ and writing a fair bit of Python in a scientific computing and physics modeling context;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;as a subcontractor for a small consultancy doing PHP and jQuery and (both My- and Postgre)SQL;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;as a solo consultant on projects ranging from WordPress setups to building a small but non-trivial application front-to-back in JavaScript;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;and, most lately, at a VC-funded startup in the very-tricky scale-up phase, writing JavaScript, TypeScript, and a smidge of C&lt;sup&gt;♯&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a result, I’ve seen nearly every part of the stack to some degree—from writing a lex/yacc parser spike for a one-off assembly language to building rich browser client applications—and I’ve seen a lot of the kinds of companies that exist in our industry. I’ve also seen (and created!) a pretty remarkable amount of tech debt.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All of which means that, at 30 (almost 31!) and about a year from the end of my first decade in this industry, I’m starting to have a pretty good sense of the things I like, the things I don’t, and some of the directions I might like to go in the future.&lt;a href="#fn1" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref1"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; It actually feels a little odd, precisely &lt;em&gt;because&lt;/em&gt; I just went where my interests and reasonably good opportunities appeared.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But it’s also important. I know better now than I did a decade ago the things that bring me joy and the places where I’m best equipped to contribute effectively to a team. (I am of course also far better equipped to contribute effectively to a team than I was when I started!) I find that I care enormously about what to build as well as how to build it—my instincts and interests seem to be roughly 25% product person, 25% mentor and teacher, and 50% individual contributor, with a particular interest in building enabling tools for others.&lt;a href="#fn2" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref2"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; I have no idea where that will take me in the future, and I’m working closely with my (really excellent) manager at Olo to find ways to both use and develop those effectively where I am.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are two upshots to all of this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol type="1"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;If you’re a young developer (or, &lt;em&gt;probably&lt;/em&gt;, early on in almost any field), getting as varied—but not shallow!—experience you can in the early years is incredibly valuable. That goes double if you’re coming in from a “non-traditional” background as I did, because it’s a great way to get exposed practically to a lot of the different parts of software and to computer science ideas you won’t if you stay in just one spot. That’s obviously a hard luxury to come by in some ways, but if you &lt;em&gt;can&lt;/em&gt; manage it, it pays huge dividends.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I’m happy to be starting to have a sense of &lt;em&gt;direction&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;trajectory&lt;/em&gt;. I’m in the early stages of that, though; I’m curious to see what I sort out in conversation with Jaimie and my church community and others I trust, as well as my leadership at Olo, over the next year.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;section class="footnotes"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn1"&gt;&lt;p&gt;To be clear to any fellow &lt;a href="https://www.olo.com"&gt;Olo&lt;/a&gt;-ers who might read this: I’m not planning to go anywhere soon. This isn’t &lt;em&gt;that&lt;/em&gt; kind of post.&lt;a href="#fnref1" class="footnote-back"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn2"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Hello, &lt;a href="https://newrustacean.com"&gt;New Rustacean&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://github.com/typed-ember/ember-cli-typescript"&gt;ember-cli-typescript&lt;/a&gt;…&lt;a href="#fnref2" class="footnote-back"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 02 May 2018 07:00:00 -0400</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2018-05-02:/2018/career-trajectory.html</guid><category>work</category><category>software development</category><category>career</category></item></channel></rss>