<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Chris Krycho - church</title><link>http://v4.chriskrycho.com/</link><description></description><lastBuildDate>Sun, 11 Aug 2019 20:15:00 -0400</lastBuildDate><item><title>Christology: God With Us and For Us</title><link>http://v4.chriskrycho.com/2019/christology-god-with-us-and-for-us.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;For the four Sundays starting today, I’m teaching a class at &lt;a href="https://forestgate.org"&gt;our church&lt;/a&gt;, “Christology: God With Us and For Us”. The summary for the class:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The topic of Christology probably sounds important, but it might also seem a little abstract or heady. But—as Colossians and Hebrews and many saints along the years will help us see—while Christology is indeed a feast for our minds, it is also comfort for our weary souls, because it’s our truest, deepest, richest picture of God’s love for us. By God’s grace, we’ll all come out encouraged by Jesus the Son’s work on our behalf, and stirred up to love and worship him more!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you’re interested, you can find each week’s notes and audio on the &lt;a href="https://forestgate.org/sunday-school/christology-god-with-us-and-for-us"&gt;dedicated page for the class&lt;/a&gt; (as on &lt;a href="https://forestgate.org/sunday-school/christology-god-with-us-and-for-us/2019/8/11/week-1-introduction-and-the-eternal-son"&gt;the page for today’s lesson&lt;/a&gt;), or you can follow along by subscribing in any podcast player in the teaching and sermons feed I set up for these kinds of things a few years ago:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://podcasts.apple.com/us/podcast/sermons-by-chris-krycho/id1083193863"&gt;Apple Podcasts&lt;/a&gt; (might take a day or two to show up as the feed was dormant for three years!)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://overcast.fm/itunes1083193863/teaching-and-sermons-by-chris-krycho"&gt;Overcast&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://v4.chriskrycho.com/sermons.xml"&gt;RSS&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(Note that, per my &lt;a href="https://v4.chriskrycho.com/2016/dont-be-a-brand.html"&gt;standing principle&lt;/a&gt; of avoiding self-promotion and branding, this is the only time I’ll post about this series.)&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 11 Aug 2019 20:15:00 -0400</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:v4.chriskrycho.com,2019-08-11:/2019/christology-god-with-us-and-for-us.html</guid><category>Christology</category><category>teaching</category><category>podcasting</category><category>church</category></item><item><title>Why We Gather</title><link>http://v4.chriskrycho.com/2016/why-we-gather.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;One of the reasons we meet together as a church every Sunday, no matter what; and one of the beauties of taking the Lord’s supper together every Sunday, no matter what, is this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today, my morning so far has involved one child being mildly fussy, and the other having a series of protracted meltdowns which including urinating on me. It includes the dreadful strains of children’s entertainment in the background as I write these very words: the kind of thing that seems calculated to annoy me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But this is the Lord’s day. Not mine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We will gather in a few hours to proclaim the one who lived in this same world, in all its brokenness. We will sing to remind each other of the way Jesus fulfilled and finished the hope of Israel, of how he died, of how he &lt;em&gt;lives&lt;/em&gt;. We will hear the word of our Lord preached, words that are true and lasting. We will take the Lord’s supper together as a lasting reminder of what he did, as a sign of his lasting presence with us today, and as a promise of the future wedding feast that we will partake of together. We will share the week’s joys and sorrows with each other. It will be imperfect, messy, possibly out of tune and with more than a few crumbs on the floor. But it will be &lt;em&gt;good&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We gather regardless of how we feel, or of what our circumstances are. We need each other, and we need the reminder that the things we experience day-in and day-out are not final or ultimate. We gather as a reminder that the little tastes we find of the Kingdom in the gathering are tastes of a future that really is coming.&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 03 Apr 2016 10:11:00 -0400</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:v4.chriskrycho.com,2016-04-03:/2016/why-we-gather.html</guid><category>family</category><category>church</category></item></channel></rss>