<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Chris Krycho</title><link href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/feeds/classwork.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://www.chriskrycho.com/</id><updated>2014-04-22T08:15:00-04:00</updated><entry><title>Right Standing Before God</title><link href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2014/right-standing-before-god.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-04-22T08:15:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Chris Krycho</name></author><id>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2014-04-22:2014/right-standing-before-god.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Any discussion of the work of God in Christ has to include the idea of
justification: it is an important throughout the Bible, and is especially
prominent in Paul&amp;#8217;s writings on salvation (which comprise a substantial part of
the New Testament and most of our systematically theological reflection on
salvation arises). The word &amp;#8220;justify&amp;#8221; and its nominal forms are used to
translate words from the &lt;em&gt;dikaoō&lt;/em&gt;  (δικαιόω) word group in Greek, which includes
a number of related concepts, all circling in various ways around the notion of
justice and right action and just and righteous character. Since &amp;#8220;justification&amp;#8221;
&amp;#8212;being justified&amp;#8212;before God is a central idea in Scripture and an essential
element of our salvation, we should be careful to understand what exactly this
concept&amp;nbsp;means.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most basically, for a person to be justified is for him or her to righteous, and
correspondingly to have acted rightly&amp;#8212;in the eyes of God. At a bare minimum,
this of course requires both the performance of good works and the rejection of
sin. However, justification means more than simply having checked off a series
of boxes corresponding to specific good works while having avoided other boxes
corresponding to bad or sinful actions. It means being regarded as having done
righteously and justly by God, and God sees our hearts, so even doing what is
right and shunning what is wrong may not be sufficient: we often have entirely
the wrong motives in such actions. We seek the approval of men instead of to
please God; we want the social or personal benefits that follow from doing nice
things for others; we enjoy stoking the fires of our own pride. In any case, we
do not even act rightly, still less do so for the glory of God. So the idea that
we might be justified on our own merits is&amp;nbsp;hopeless.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Second, we should note that ordinary notions of justification often tend to
include many of the right (that is, Biblical) concepts of justification in them,
but in shallower forms than Scripture supplies. In particular, the use of the
term has shifted somewhat from when it was used to translate the  word group
from Greek into English. When we say, &amp;#8220;he was justified,&amp;#8221; we do not mean that
someone did the right thing, but that whatever someone did, he had grounds for
doing. We can of course turn this back to our needs by noting that we have
grounds only for right-hearted obedience and none for sinning. Still, this is
less than the biblical idea of justification&amp;#8212;of being considered to have done
rightly in every&amp;nbsp;way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the &amp;#8220;Christian&amp;#8221; to be justified, we must be able to stand before God and he
consider us righteous in every word and deed and thought and attitude of the
heart. This happens in two ways (inseparable from each other): forensic
justification and imputed righteousness through union with Christ. In &amp;#8220;forensic
justification,&amp;#8221; God legally acquits us of guilt for committed sin and righteous
deeds left undone. The list of offenses we committed was nailed to the cross
(cf. Colossians 2:13&amp;#8211;15). This can happen because we are united with Jesus the
Son of God by the Spirit of God. As Paul notes in 2 Corinthians 5:21, the
sinless Christ became sin that we might become the righteousness of God. All
that is Christ&amp;#8217;s is ours; we are one with him and so we have all his
righteousness. (The word &amp;#8220;righteousness&amp;#8221; here derives from the same root as we
translate &amp;#8220;justification&amp;#8221;&amp;#8212;these ideas are inextricably linked.) Finally, God
himself justifies us, calling us righteous, because Jesus Christ has both lived
in perfect righteousness and paid the penalty for our sins, propitiating the
wrath of God (cf. Romans&amp;nbsp;3).&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="M. Div."></category><category term="SEBTS"></category></entry></feed>