<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Chris Krycho</title><link href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/feeds/classwork.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://www.chriskrycho.com/</id><updated>2014-04-08T08:00:00-04:00</updated><entry><title>The Spirit and Christian Formation</title><link href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2014/the-spirit-and-christian-formation.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-04-08T08:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Chris Krycho</name></author><id>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2014-04-08:2014/the-spirit-and-christian-formation.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Discussions of the person of the Holy Spirit in modern Christianity tend to
focus on the third person of the Trinity&amp;#8217;s obviously miraculous activity in the
world&amp;#8212;the &amp;#8220;gifts&amp;#8221; that characterize the charismatic movement and the
associated controversy. Though these gifts are certainly part of the recorded
history of the Spirit&amp;#8217;s work, the church&amp;#8217;s focus thereupon (whether positive or
negative) on the gifts has had the unfortunate side effect of hiding many of the
other, arguably more central and essential actions of the Spirit in the life of
the believer. Just as the Spirit is the person who mediates to us the work of
Christ in our salvation and brings about our conversion, the Spirit is the one
who leads us into greater participation in the renewed humanity the Son has
accomplished in his incarnation, life, death, resurrection, and ascension. The
Spirit is the one who progressively deepens our union with Christ and reshapes
us to be like Him who saved&amp;nbsp;us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Spirit accomplishes these ends in a variety of ways, all of which are
themselves worthy of further reflection. First of all, it was the Spirit who
superintended the writing of Scripture, the self-revelation of the Triune
Godhead for our salvation and sanctification. If Christian formation is in no
small measure a matter of growing to know our Creator&amp;#8212;if we are being restored
to active relationship with one who made us for that very relationship&amp;#8212;then
the ways in which our Creator has revealed himself are supremely important.
Without Scripture, we would know little of God; through it we enter in the deep
mysteries. The first part the Spirit plays in our formation, then, is in having
guided every hand from Moses&amp;#8217; to John&amp;#8217;s in the writing of the word of God. Upon
this foundation comes the Spirit&amp;#8217;s second work: opening our eyes to understand
that Scripture. The things of God are foolishness to unregenerate people, but
beautiful and savory to those who have been given spiritual life. The word of
God can seem dense and opaque to those who do not believe, but every believer in
Christ finds that more and more these mysteries unfold: this is the Spirit at&amp;nbsp;work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As we come to understand the person of God and the things he has commanded us in
his word, we find that we are still weak and struggle to do them. Here, too, the
Spirit is at work, for it is the Spirit who empowers our obedience. We know that
the same Spirit that raised Christ from the dead is at work in us&amp;#8212;and this is
the only hope we have of overcoming sin and growing in holiness. Part and parcel
of this, the Spirit empowers us to endure the suffering that God uses to make us
more dependent on him and more faithful to him. Likewise, when in the course of
our lives we are tempted to fall away, it is the Spirit who helps us continue to
hold fast to the faith. Moreover, the Spirit intercedes for us when we do not
know how to pray ourselves. When we are beset by temptation, when tempted to
fall away, when exhausted from the battle, when wearied of the pursuit of
holiness, the Spirit prays for us. Nor is the Spirit&amp;#8217;s work directed solely to
individuals. All of these realities are corporate, and in all of them we grow in
unity and kindness toward one another. The Spirit is our bond of&amp;nbsp;peace.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In summary, then, we have both the Spirit and the Son praying for us to the
Father who delights to answer those prayers, and the Spirit empowering us walk
in the Son&amp;#8217;s life with the&amp;nbsp;Father&amp;#8212;hallelujah!&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="M.&amp;hairsp;Div."></category></entry></feed>