<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Chris Krycho - coffee</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/</link><description></description><lastBuildDate>Thu, 23 Feb 2017 20:10:00 -0500</lastBuildDate><item><title>Corraling My Coffee Habit</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2017/corraling-my-coffee-habit.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Because we buy good coffee and good coffee is expensive, and because we’re trying very hard to save for a house, I’ve been thinking about how to corral that particular budget line.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For a bit of context, we use &lt;a href="https://www.youneedabudget.com" title="You Need A Budget"&gt;&lt;abbr&gt;YNAB&lt;/abbr&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, and we have two ways we spend money on coffee: going out to coffee shops, and as groceries. Perhaps surprisingly, it has been the latter of those two which has been giving us trouble: that second cup of coffee every day—you know, for the pick-me-up in the early afternoon—adds up in a hurry, especially when you’re buying &lt;a href="https://counterculturecoffee.com/"&gt;Counter Culture&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href="https://bluebottlecoffee.com/"&gt;Blue Bottle&lt;/a&gt; or the like.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I decided this week to make one small tweak to our budgeting flow which should help stem this tide of coffee a bit. Namely: we now have an allocated amount of coffee per day, and if we go past that, a corresponding amount of money moves from our coffee shop budget into our grocery budget.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here’s how that works in practice. Our last bag of Counter Culture cost $17.61. I allot myself 8 ounces per day. On Tuesday, I drank an extra 6-ounce cup in the afternoon. The bag is 12 ounces of coffee beans, which is 340 grams. A 6-ounce cup, made the way I make it, uses 11 grams of beans. So then I did a little math: &lt;code&gt;(11 / 340) * 17.61 ~= 0.57&lt;/code&gt; – so I moved $0.57 from my coffee shop budget to my grocery budget. I did the same with the extra 4-ounce cup I had yesterday and the extra 2 ounces I had in my cup this morning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Is this budgeting done in excruciatingly minute detail? Yes. Is it helpful to me? Also yes. Do I recommend it? Not unless you’re in the same ballpark of obsessiveness as I am!&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 23 Feb 2017 20:10:00 -0500</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2017-02-23:/2017/corraling-my-coffee-habit.html</guid><category>coffee</category><category>finances</category></item></channel></rss>