<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Chris Krycho - community</title><link>http://v4.chriskrycho.com/</link><description></description><lastBuildDate>Sat, 15 Sep 2018 09:10:00 -0400</lastBuildDate><item><title>Your Job Is Not Your Community</title><link>http://v4.chriskrycho.com/2018/your-job-is-not-your-community.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Skimming through Twitter this morning, two threads caught my attention.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://mobile.twitter.com/kyleshevlin/status/1040674991392452608"&gt;The first&lt;/a&gt;, by Kyle Shevlin, pushes back on the idea that people should be expected to just pick up and move across the country for a job—never mind the personal and communal costs to them. This stands at the crux of the point he’s making (but the whole thread is good; I encouraged him to turn it into a blog post):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We don’t even pay attention to this [i.e. the lack of communal ties and third spaces in our lives]. The pastor/philosopher in me gets frustrated with the lack of concern over the loss of community. Instead, we have tried to replace our relationship to other people with the relationship to our work and work place.&lt;br /&gt;
—&lt;a href="https://mobile.twitter.com/kyleshevlin/status/1040674981468758016"&gt;@kyleshevlin &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://mobile.twitter.com/sehurlburt/status/1040778111057444866"&gt;The second&lt;/a&gt;, by Stephanie Hurlburt, gently but firmly tells guys to stop trying to &lt;em&gt;flirt&lt;/em&gt; with the women they meet at professional meetups.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am noticing a trend in women age 18-22 I’m mentoring— they try to network and get mentoring and go to meetups and literally every guy they try to talk with gets flirty&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They’re &lt;em&gt;blocked&lt;/em&gt; from this professional advancement because so many guys jump straight into trying to date&lt;br /&gt;
—&lt;a href="https://mobile.twitter.com/sehurlburt/status/1040778111057444866"&gt;@sehurlburt&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I agree with Stephanie’s point here, but it was the juxtaposition with Kyle’s point that particularly caught my attention.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Without excusing the young men who turn from professional networking to flirting immediately on encountering an attractive woman at a tech meetup—again, don’t do that!—it’s also worth addressing the structural reasons why move is so tempting. (As usual, these kinds of things are worth addressing &lt;a href="https://winningslowly.org/season-5"&gt;both individually and structurally&lt;/a&gt;, and in fact &lt;em&gt;have&lt;/em&gt; to be addressed both ways to see real change.) One of the structural issues which leads to “see an attractive woman at a JavaScript meetup, decide to flirt with her” is the thing Kyle is pointing at. Namely: we’ve offloaded the vast majority of our social existence to work.&lt;a href="#fn1" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref1" role="doc-noteref"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; Given that many of these young men have no other social contexts… where exactly &lt;em&gt;are&lt;/em&gt; they going to flirt?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s good and right to do as Stephanie does here and say, “This isn’t the right place for this, guys.” But—and this is no critique of Stephanie’s point; not every blog post or every tweet is responsible to cover every angle on a topic!—we also need to substantially reorient our understanding of the place of professional contexts in our lives. Leaders need to stop framing their companies as “a family”&lt;a href="#fn2" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref2" role="doc-noteref"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and, even more, need to recognize that companies are not &lt;em&gt;and cannot be&lt;/em&gt; the solution to this problem. To the contrary. When a company responds to their employees’ felt need for more community by trying to become that community, it reinforces the actual problem. Counterintuitive though it might seem, the best thing company leaders can do for their employees is make sure that their company is &lt;em&gt;just a job&lt;/em&gt;. (If you want to do more than this, find healthy local community spaces and support &lt;em&gt;those&lt;/em&gt;—financially, by promoting them, etc.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Neighborhood book clubs, churches, recreational sports, local art-making of all sorts, topical discussion groups, political activism, community service… these are the actual kinds of activities and institutions we need more of. Not more of company-as-community, professional-as-identity. If we work hard to build those thicker, healthier kinds of spaces, then professionally-focused spaces actually can remain professional. They won’t have to do work they aren’t meant to do, and ultimately can’t do well without compromising their primary work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn1" role="doc-endnote"&gt;&lt;p&gt;and social media, but that’s a different blog post—it exacerbates these issues as well, to be sure&lt;a href="#fnref1" class="footnote-back" role="doc-backlink"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn2" role="doc-endnote"&gt;&lt;p&gt;something my own employer has been guilty of, and on which I have prodded them!&lt;a href="#fnref2" class="footnote-back" role="doc-backlink"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 15 Sep 2018 09:10:00 -0400</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:v4.chriskrycho.com,2018-09-15:/2018/your-job-is-not-your-community.html</guid><category>sexism</category><category>community</category><category>remote work</category><category>corporatism</category></item><item><title>A Humanist Frame</title><link>http://v4.chriskrycho.com/2018/a-humanist-frame.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;A few thoughts this morning on technologies, community, and the need for a positive (as well as a negative) vision of technology, cities, and indeed liberty—taking &lt;a href="https://tinyletter.com/lmsacasas/letters/the-convivial-society-no-4-community" title="No. 4: Community"&gt;the latest issue&lt;/a&gt; of Michael Sacasas’ newsletter &lt;a href="https://tinyletter.com/lmsacasas/archive"&gt;The Convivial Society&lt;/a&gt; as a jumping off point.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;aside&gt;
I don’t expect to link quite so often to the same writer, so don’t worry: this isn’t about to become a secondary feed for Sacasas’ writing. I do commend the newsletter, and especially this issue of it, to you. This essay, which I quote in brief, does something I hope to be able to do in a piece of writing someday: it &lt;em&gt;hangs together&lt;/em&gt; marvelously. There are standout paragraphs, but each one connects to those before and after it, and the essay is—in the best way—not excerpt-able. You should read the whole thing. If you have to choose, read that instead of this (seriously).
&lt;/aside&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Early in the newsletter, Sacasas offers this note on technological visionaries stretching back to the telegraph (at least):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It seems that none of these visionaries ever took into consideration the possibility that the moral frailties of human nature would only be amplified by their new technologies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He shortly thereafter suggests why that vision proved so alluring—the too-readily amplified frailties of human nature notwithstanding:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The rise of communication technologies from the mid-19th century through today has roughly coincided with the dissolution and degradation of the traditional communities, broken and often cruel though they may have been, that provided individuals with a relatively integrated experience of place and self. In 1953, the sociologist Robert Nisbett could write of the “quest for community” as the “dominant social tendency of the twentieth century.” Framing a new technology as a source of community, in other words, trades on an unfulfilled desire for community.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What strikes me as most interesting here is that Sacasas notes, even if only as an aside, one of the most important things that most critics of our current techno/cultural milieu seem entirely content to skip over: that the traditional communities &lt;em&gt;were&lt;/em&gt; “broken and often cruel.” One of the reasons that the social revolutions of the last 150 years have had such force is precisely this: that the traditional communities so casually valorized today (though not by Sacasas himself) may have helped people have “an integrated experience of place and self”—but that experience was, often as not, one of &lt;em&gt;abuse&lt;/em&gt;: of ethnic minorities, of women, of anyone outside the gentry…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sacasas’ description—“broken and often cruel”—is more right than is usually granted in these discussions. If we want to escape the shackles of atomistic individualism, we had best be thinking of something other than the glorious past, because the past was not glorious.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Third, and closely related to the above considerations: Sacasas closes the newsletter with a quote from Willa Cather’s &lt;em&gt;O Pioneers!&lt;/em&gt;, adding his own emphasis. I’ll reproduce the quotation in full here as he gave it (so: emphasis his) and then comment below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“You see,” he went on calmly, “measured by your standards here, I’m a failure. I couldn’t buy even one of your cornfields. I’ve enjoyed a great many things, but I’ve got nothing to show for it all.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“But you show for it yourself, Carl. I’d rather have had your freedom than my land.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Carl shook his head mournfully. “&lt;strong&gt;Freedom so often means that one isn’t needed anywhere.&lt;/strong&gt; Here you are an individual, you have a background of your own, you would be missed. But off there in the cities there are thousands of rolling stones like me. We are all alike; we have no ties, we know nobody, we own nothing. When one of us dies, they scarcely know where to bury him. Our landlady and the delicatessen man are our mourners, and we leave nothing behind us but a frock-coat and a fiddle, or an easel, or a typewriter, or whatever tool we got our living by. All we have ever managed to do is to pay our rent, the exorbitant rent that one has to pay for a few square feet of space near the heart of things. We have no house, no place, no people of our own. We live in the streets, in the parks, in the theaters. We sit in restaurants and concert halls and look about at the hundreds of our own kind and shudder.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alexandra was silent. She sat looking at the silver spot the moon made on the surface of the pond down in the pasture. He knew that she understood what he meant. At last she said slowly, “And yet I would rather have Emil grow up like that than like his two brothers. We pay a high rent, too, though we pay differently. We grow hard and heavy here. We don’t move lightly and easily as you do, and our minds get stiff. If the world were no wider than my cornfields, if there were not something beside this, I wouldn’t feel that it was much worth while to work. No, I would rather have Emil like you than like them. I felt that as soon as you came.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sacasas—with many others who are rightly critical of the social situation we have made for ourselves here in late modernity, including many of my friends over at &lt;a href="https://mereorthodoxy.com/book-review-liberalism-failed-patrick-deneen/" title="Example: Jake Meador&amp;#39;s sympathetic review of Deneen&amp;#39;s Why Liberalism Failed"&gt;Mere Orthodoxy&lt;/a&gt;—calls out the ways that our unrestrained freedom has come at a great cost to us. These critics are right to do so. But the bit that caught my attention as &lt;em&gt;equally&lt;/em&gt; worthy of notice in the section from Cather is Alexandra’s response (emphasis mine):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We pay a high rent, too, though we pay differently. We grow hard and heavy here. We don’t move lightly and easily as you do, and our minds get stiff. If the world were no wider than my cornfields, if there were not something beside this, I wouldn’t feel that it was much worth while to work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is something in this exchange of the tension between agrarianism and urbanism that seems to come up every time Wendell Berry is mentioned. It is true that cities (and late modernity!) often offer a kind of freedom that itself is slavery. But it is also true that the slavery of freedom is not the only kind of slavery.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It remains one of my chief concerns that few who &lt;em&gt;are&lt;/em&gt; taking seriously the problems we have made for ourselves in modernity seem interested in finding solutions that work &lt;em&gt;in cities&lt;/em&gt;. It is one thing to have a healthy suspicion of the kind of city-centrism and techno-centrism and indeed techno-fundamentalism that is largely the order of the day. It is something else entirely, however, to fail to imagine either city or technological milieu as &lt;em&gt;possibly good&lt;/em&gt;. (To be clear, this does not seem to be the tack that Sacasas is taking; and it is not so much that someone like my friend Jake Meador is &lt;em&gt;hostile&lt;/em&gt; to cities as that his own sympathies run more to rural life.) This is, I think, part of what &lt;a href="http://stephencarradini.com"&gt;Stephen Carradini&lt;/a&gt; has been getting at in his own more optimistic view in especially our &lt;a href="https://winningslowly.org/6.04/" title="6.04: Move Slowly and Fix Things"&gt;most recent Winning Slowly episode&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We must reject techno-utopianism; we must repent of our worship of technique. But we &lt;em&gt;must not&lt;/em&gt; make the usual conservative mistake and stop with the mere rejection of something bad. &lt;a href="http://bib.ly/luke11.24-26" title="Luke 11:24–26"&gt;That tends not to go so well.&lt;/a&gt; Instead, we need to consciously develop a frame that situates technology as properly subordinate to the humane, and which sets cities and farms and small towns and moon colonies not in opposition to each other but as complements.&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 01 May 2018 07:00:00 -0400</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:v4.chriskrycho.com,2018-05-01:/2018/a-humanist-frame.html</guid><category>ethics</category><category>community</category></item></channel></rss>