<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Chris Krycho</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/</link><description></description><atom:link href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/feeds/ellie.xml" rel="self"></atom:link><lastBuildDate>Thu, 02 Jun 2016 20:40:00 -0400</lastBuildDate><item><title></title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2016/02-2040.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;I think our day trip to the beach was a success. At dinner, Ellie said, “This was the best day ever!”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id="refs" class="references"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 02 Jun 2016 20:40:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2016-06-02:2016/02-2040.html</guid><category>family</category><category>ellie</category><category>travel</category></item><item><title></title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2016/2016-04-10-1005.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;After we &lt;a href="/2016/2016-04-10-0956.html"&gt;watched the installation&lt;/a&gt;, Ellie said, “Next time the space ship comes out, can we watch?” &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Of course I said yes.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id="refs" class="references"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 10 Apr 2016 10:05:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2016-04-10:2016/2016-04-10-1005.html</guid><category>ellie</category><category>space</category></item><item><title></title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2016/2016-04-10-0956.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Watching the &lt;a href="http://www.nasa.gov/content/spacex-crs-8-briefings-and-events"&gt;SpaceX&lt;/a&gt; with my four-year-old. This is amazing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id="refs" class="references"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 10 Apr 2016 09:56:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2016-04-10:2016/2016-04-10-0956.html</guid><category>ellie</category><category>space</category></item><item><title></title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2016/2016-04-06-1135.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Ellie just spotted a bald eagle out our back window. How cool is that?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id="refs" class="references"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 06 Apr 2016 11:35:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2016-04-06:2016/2016-04-06-1135.html</guid><category>ellie</category></item><item><title></title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2016/2016-04-02-0629.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Eventually, my daughters are going to discover that I am not, in fact, &lt;em&gt;cool&lt;/em&gt;. I’m going to enjoy it as long as it lasts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id="refs" class="references"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 02 Apr 2016 06:29:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2016-04-02:2016/2016-04-02-0629.html</guid><category>ellie</category><category>kate</category><category>family</category></item><item><title></title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2016/2016-03-30-2103.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;A really splendid moment this evening: I looked up just as we got out of our car after small group, and got to see the &lt;a href="https://www.nasa.gov/mission_pages/station/main/index.html"&gt;ISS&lt;/a&gt; pass overhead (and showed Ellie!).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id="refs" class="references"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 30 Mar 2016 21:03:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2016-03-30:2016/2016-03-30-2103.html</guid><category>space</category><category>ellie</category></item><item><title></title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2016/2016-03-06-0819.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ellie:&lt;/strong&gt; “Yeah, then I’ll be ready for kindergarten!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“… What’s kindergarten?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id="refs" class="references"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 06 Mar 2016 08:19:00 -0500</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2016-03-06:2016/2016-03-06-0819.html</guid><category>family</category><category>ellie</category></item><item><title></title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2016/2016-03-05-0711.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;I am increasingly persuaded that there is a law of the universe which states: &lt;em&gt;On any morning in which parents intend to sleep in at all, their children will awaken early, and with an overabundance of energy.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id="refs" class="references"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 05 Mar 2016 07:11:00 -0500</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2016-03-05:2016/2016-03-05-0711.html</guid><category>family</category><category>ellie</category><category>kate</category></item><item><title></title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2016/2016-02-24-0833.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Jaimie put on a recording of “All I Have is Christ.” And Ellie is singing along. I think my brain might explode from the wonderfulness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id="refs" class="references"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 24 Feb 2016 08:33:00 -0500</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2016-02-24:2016/2016-02-24-0833.html</guid><category>family</category><category>ellie</category></item><item><title></title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2015/2015-10-04-1159.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Ellie has invented her first totally-original (as opposed to borrowed from a TV show) imaginary friend. Her name, apparently, is “Ballerina”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id="refs" class="references"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 04 Oct 2015 11:59:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2015-10-04:2015/2015-10-04-1159.html</guid><category>ellie</category><category>family</category></item><item><title></title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2015/2015-08-28-1905.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Last night as we were coming home from dinner with friends, the CD changer switched from one album to the next and Ellie delightedly said, “What’s this? &lt;a href="https://geo.itunes.apple.com/us/album/pride-prejudice-music-from/id89675842?at=1001l4KM&amp;amp;mt=1&amp;amp;app=music"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Pride and Prejudice&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;!” Cuteness overload.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id="refs" class="references"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 28 Aug 2015 19:05:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2015-08-28:2015/2015-08-28-1905.html</guid><category>Ellie</category><category>music</category></item><item><title></title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2015/2015-08-10-1533.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Just a few minutes ago, I heard Ellie singing a song that mashed together “Let It Go” with something about munchkins. People who know me well know where the munchkins bit came from. “The apple doesn’t fall far from the tree!” Jaimie immediately opined. 😏&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id="refs" class="references"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 10 Aug 2015 15:33:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2015-08-10:2015/2015-08-10-1533.html</guid><category>ellie</category></item><item><title></title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2015/2015-08-08-0642.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Ellie and Kate &lt;em&gt;consistently&lt;/em&gt; get up half an hour to an hour earlier on Saturday mornings than any other day of the week. Coincidentally—&lt;em&gt;or is it?&lt;/em&gt;—Saturday is also the only day we try to sleep in. It’s like they know, and plot against us!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id="refs" class="references"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 08 Aug 2015 06:42:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2015-08-08:2015/2015-08-08-0642.html</guid><category>family</category><category>kate</category><category>ellie</category></item><item><title></title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2015/2015-08-07-1820.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Quote of the week (3-year-old Ellie talking to her mom, who has been learning Python): “Mommy! I have a function for you!”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id="refs" class="references"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 07 Aug 2015 18:20:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2015-08-07:2015/2015-08-07-1820.html</guid><category>ellie</category><category>software development</category><category>jaimie</category></item><item><title></title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2015/2015-08-04-1855.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;A minute ago, Ellie asked me to play with her and Kate. I started to answer, “No, I need to finish publishing Winning Slowly.” Then I remembered: putting that first would be pretty much &lt;em&gt;exactly the opposite&lt;/em&gt; of &lt;a href="http://www.winningslowly.org/1.02" title="1.02: On Family"&gt;Winning Slowly&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id="refs" class="references"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 04 Aug 2015 18:55:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2015-08-04:2015/2015-08-04-1855.html</guid><category>family</category><category>ellie</category><category>kate</category><category>podcasting</category></item><item><title></title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2015/2015-07-06-0852.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Me:&lt;/b&gt; I’m really delighted by the big girl you’re growing into, Ellie, and I love you &lt;em&gt;so&lt;/em&gt; much!&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;b&gt;Ellie:&lt;/b&gt; I really love my magazine!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id="refs" class="references"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 06 Jul 2015 08:52:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2015-07-06:2015/2015-07-06-0852.html</guid><category>Ellie</category></item><item><title>Snow Days and Friends Moving</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2015/snow-days-and-friends-moving.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Another month gone, another bunch of little changes, and a few bigger changes, too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;February marked the final burst of winter here. We had a number of days of wintry weather, leading to several days where Southeastern’s campus was closed—though none on days when I had class! One of those days included well over doc inches of snow, and marked the first time Ellie has ever been able to play in the snow. Though she was a little nervous at first, she loosened up as she watched a neighbor kid play and was soon having a blast working on snowmen and a snow fort. She even tried to throw a few snowballs, but—like her momma—she didn’t much care for having them tossed her way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kate quite enjoyed the snow as well, even though her snow clothes were still a bit too big for her.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the meantime, I kept plugging away at work and school. His past week was Spring Break for us, but “breaks” here usually just mark an opportunity for me to get ahead on my class assignments. I wrote one of my three papers for the semester—the shortest, but it’s helpful to have it out of the way nonetheless.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This week also saw our friends PJ and Katie finish packing up their apartment here to &lt;a href="http://www.adoptedbytheking.com/2015/03/from-wake-forest-with-love.html"&gt;move to Texas&lt;/a&gt;, and we helped them wrap that up and participated in a few get-togethers to give them a good send-off. We are simultaneously glad for them, because this seems like it will be a very good thing for them, and incredibly sad, because we will miss them dearly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Good friends are a rare and precious thing, and we have been blessed in ways that are hard to describe in our friendship with PJ and Katie. Having them live in the same town as us for that past couple years, and then less than a mile away for the last year, has been wonderful. We are blessed to live in a time when it is easy to stay in touch, of course, but no amount of Skype or FaceTime can make up for being unable to share a meal. Gladly, we are hoping to see them again in just a few months at the Southern Baptist Convention (which I am planning to attend for class credit at SEBTS), and that softens the blow, if only a little. Too, they are moving to be only about 90 minutes’ drive from where Jaimie’s parents live, so we will certainly see them when we visit there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Still, I am sad, and so is Jaimie. Ellie hasn’t really understood it yet, but she will no doubt be sad as it comes home to her over the next few weeks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So it goes until Christ comes again. &lt;em&gt;Maranatha.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id="refs" class="references"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 14 Mar 2015 13:30:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2015-03-14:2015/snow-days-and-friends-moving.html</guid><category>family</category><category>Jaimie</category><category>Ellie</category><category>Kate</category></item><item><title>The State of Our Family in Early 2015</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2015/early-2015-family.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;It has been a &lt;em&gt;long&lt;/em&gt; time since I wrote a family update here, and I skipped the Christmas letter this year because I was exhausted. I resolved at the beginning of the year to write at least one update every month, though. I want these updates here for &lt;em&gt;myself&lt;/em&gt;, if for no other reason. (Then, of course, I promptly missed January, but this is counting for that; there will be another post here at the end of the month.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What have we been up to, you ask? Well, quite a lot! Since the last time I wrote a blog post, we had a baby, who is now crawling around. (If you’re reading this, you probably already know that, of course.) Ellie is talking, constantly practicing saying things the right way and asking the names of things; Kate is scooting around the floor exploring everything and is increasingly verbal herself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They love playing together. Ellie and Kate are good friends—a while back Jaimie heard Ellie quietly talking to Katie in the back seat of the car, repeating, “You’re my best friend, Kate.” Sometimes when Ellie gives Kate a hug and a kiss goodnight every night, Kate goes into the most adorable squeals of delight. Indeed, no one elicits those squeals as much as Ellie. In addition to her scooting around the floor, Kate is happily eating solid foods—and the girl &lt;em&gt;loves&lt;/em&gt; her food. Today I put her in her high chair and she started laughing as I put the tray in front of her. She often thumps the tray, the table, or the floor to express her joy. And last but not least, this little gal is &lt;em&gt;strong&lt;/em&gt;. Her favorite time is getting in a bouncer and jumping for as long as we will let her.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src="/images/girls-games.jpg" title="My ladies playing Lego Star Wars"/&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;
My ladies playing &lt;i&gt;Lego Star Wars&lt;/i&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have been teaching Ellie a lot. Jaimie has slowly started working through the ABCs with her. She can count to 5, and she knows her way to 10, but sometimes gets sidetracked along the way. She is learning her colors and spent a while defaulting to calling everything “pink”… except for her favorite &lt;em&gt;purple&lt;/em&gt; dress. In the last month, she has started being able to identify the colors more reliably, along with lots of shapes. She loves cars and trucks and especially buses and fire trucks. She sings to herself and dances all the time. She loves building with blocks. She is learning to say “please” and “thank you”—learning, in this case, not because she doesn’t know how but because she has started &lt;em&gt;forgetting&lt;/em&gt;. She is learning to pray and to sing to God and learning the answer to simple questions like, “Who made you, Ellie?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jaimie has continued to write off and on, though the first many months we had Kate it was much spottier than it had been. She’s working on secret projects that are making her happy, and that makes me happy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As for why she didn’t get as much time, I was &lt;em&gt;busy&lt;/em&gt; last semester. I picked up a second contract, building the new &lt;a href="//holybible.com"&gt;HolyBible.com&lt;/a&gt;, and between that and my ongoing contract work and my one class, I pulled a lot of 50–60 hour weeks. That’s not particularly an experience we are keen to repeat, but it was the right call at the time: we were able to save up the money to fill up our six-month emergency fund and to pay for the rest of seminary. This semester is going a bit easier: I am taking Hebrew III and Baptist History and working ~30 hours a week instead of ~50–55. I &lt;em&gt;love&lt;/em&gt; my language classes; without a doubt Hebrew III and Greek III have been my very favorite classes since I started seminary.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I ran another half marathon in November, and set a PR at 1:25:37—a 6:32/mile pace. I was super happy with that outcome, and I plan to run the same race again for the third year in a row this coming fall, Lord willing. In the meantime, I have started swimming and cycling regularly with the aim of completing my first triathlon early this summer. (I’m going to stick to a short “sprint” tri to start, and work up from there.) While I love running, I would like to have the use of my joints in twenty (and forty, and sixty) years, and accordingly I need to make sure I do not keep putting over 1,000 miles a year on my legs. I have been going to a spinning class to get my legs in better cycling shape for the last month (and the last two weeks Jaimie has come with me!). We have also been doing a Pilates class weekly; my back needs to be a lot stronger and my legs a lot looser, and that is helping quite a bit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We continue to be extremely happy in our church here, FBC Durham. God has used our church to encourage and challenge us in a wide variety of ways—too many (and perhaps in many cases too subtle) even to summarize. We are excited to see what the years ahead hold for us there, as the church itself continues to flourish and grow and we seek opportunities to continue serving and building up this particular outpost of the body of Christ.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In short, life is &lt;em&gt;good&lt;/em&gt;. It is not perfect, of course; I long for Jesus’ return and the New Heavens and New Earth more and more all the time. But we see God’s faithfulness and goodness in the hard months no less than in the easy ones. We see the Spirit working in our hearts to make us more like Christ, and it is good.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I could go on, but a thousand words is enough. More again, and sooner than the last gap!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id="refs" class="references"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2015 20:30:00 -0500</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2015-02-10:2015/early-2015-family.html</guid><category>family</category><category>Ellie</category><category>Kate</category><category>Jaimie</category></item><item><title>Spinning!</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2014/spinning.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;As she so often does, Ellie simply delighted me tonight, in two wonderful moments:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol type="1"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;As I was cleaning up the dishes and playing Max Richter’s &lt;a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/album/memoryhouse/id545010150"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Memoryhouse&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; album, I saw Ellie dancing, and encouraged her to keep going. After a moment, I looked over to see her spinning in circles. And spinning in circles. And spinning in circles. When she finally stopped, she started freaking out as she couldn’t get her balance. I swooped in and picked her up, laughing with her once she recovered.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;After she calmed down, she started tugging on my shirt. It took me a few seconds to realize what she wanted, but then it clicked: she was trying to turn me by twisting my shirt. “You want to spin?” I asked her. She nodded vigorously. “Is this a spinning song?” Again, the vigorous nod. So I started spinning around and around with her in my arms, and the sheer joy in the grin plastered across her face was something to behold. We spun first one way, then the other, all the way through &lt;a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=BfoSv8iWA_I"&gt;“The Twins (Prague)”&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moments like these are worth remembering.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id="refs" class="references"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 20 Mar 2014 19:10:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2014-03-20:2014/spinning.html</guid><category>family</category><category>Ellie</category></item></channel></rss>