<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Chris Krycho - emberjs</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/</link><description></description><lastBuildDate>Mon, 08 May 2017 22:00:00 -0400</lastBuildDate><item><title>Typing Your Ember, Part 2</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2017/typing-your-ember-part-2.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;i class='series-overview'&gt;You write &lt;a href="https://emberjs.com"&gt;Ember.js&lt;/a&gt; apps. You think &lt;a href="http://www.typescriptlang.org"&gt;TypeScript&lt;/a&gt; would be helpful in building a more robust app as it increases in size or has more people working on it. But you have questions about how to make it work.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;i class='series-overview'&gt;This is the series for you! I’ll talk through everything: from the very basics of how to set up your Ember.js app to use TypeScript to how you can get the most out of TypeScript today—and I’ll be pretty clear about the current tradeoffs and limitations, too.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;i class='series-overview'&gt;&lt;a href="/typing-your-ember.html"&gt;(See the rest of the series. →)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the [first part] of this series, I described how to set up a brand new Ember.js app to use TypeScript. In this part, I’m going to talk about starting to use TypeScript in the context of an existing Ember.js app.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is, in many ways, even simpler than setting up an app for the first time, because you already have almost everything you need. The steps here are exactly what you’re used to if you’re used to using the Ember CLI ecosystem:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol type="1"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Install &lt;code&gt;ember-cli-typescript&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="sh"&gt;&lt;code&gt;ember install ember-cli-typescript&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Start using TypeScript wherever you want in your app.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It really is that simple, for the most part. There are a couple qualifications, and a couple tips, though.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s start with &lt;strong&gt;qualifications&lt;/strong&gt;. There are open, unresolved &lt;a href="https://github.com/emberwatch/ember-cli-typescript/issues/"&gt;issues&lt;/a&gt; about using &lt;code&gt;ember-cli-typescript&lt;/code&gt; in your app in certain contexts. For example: &lt;a href="https://github.com/emberwatch/ember-cli-typescript/issues/8"&gt;using it with &lt;code&gt;ember-browserify&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. While everything will &lt;em&gt;build&lt;/em&gt; correctly in that case (even if the TypeScript compiler complains about being unable to resolve some things, the Ember CLI build pipeline will still work as expected), your editor integration won’t. There are a bunch of corners like this we’re still hammering out; those are the main things we need to get resolved before we can call this a “1.0.” We have the &lt;em&gt;main&lt;/em&gt; stuff working, but, well… there’s more to do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Along those same lines, you should take a close look at the &lt;a href="https://github.com/emberwatch/ember-cli-typescript#not-yet-supported"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Not yet supported&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; section of the README. There are parts of Ember’s programming model which TypeScript certainly &lt;em&gt;can&lt;/em&gt; support, but which we haven’t done the lifting to get the type declaration file to help with yet. (Looking for a place to pitch in and already comfortable doing some heavy lifting with some of TypeScript’s &lt;a href="http://www.typescriptlang.org/docs/handbook/mixins.html"&gt;most advanced type features&lt;/a&gt;? We could use the help.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One other thing to be aware of is that your &lt;code&gt;tsconfig.json&lt;/code&gt; settings will affect what kind of resolution your editor gives you. If you have &lt;code&gt;allowJs&lt;/code&gt; set to &lt;code&gt;true&lt;/code&gt; in your &lt;code&gt;tsconfig.json&lt;/code&gt;, your editors will resolve JS modules. Otherwise, they’ll &lt;em&gt;only&lt;/em&gt; resolve TS modules. This can be incredibly annoying at times. However, this isn’t something we’ve nailed down in terms of what the default should be yet. (You can &lt;a href="https://github.com/emberwatch/ember-cli-typescript/issues/"&gt;come tell us&lt;/a&gt; on GitHub if you have thoughts or insights there!) And the fact that Microsoft has left this configurable is suggestive: different projects may have different preferences here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, for the &lt;strong&gt;tips&lt;/strong&gt;. Note that these are just a couple quick pointers; I’ll come back and talk about structuring your project and more sophisticated uses of TypeScript in the future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Don’t turn on &lt;code&gt;--strict&lt;/code&gt; or the corresponding individual flags on day 1. Unless you have an extremely unusual and disciplined Ember.js codebase, you’ll have an incredible set of errors to deal with.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Don’t set the the &lt;code&gt;noEmitOnError&lt;/code&gt; flag to &lt;code&gt;true&lt;/code&gt; in your &lt;code&gt;tsconfig.json&lt;/code&gt;, for much the same reason. Since the state of type declaration files for Ember is best described as &lt;em&gt;nascent&lt;/em&gt; at present, many of your files will have errors in them just from failed imports!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Don’t try to convert everything at once. Just pick the next feature or bug you’re working on, and start with the files you’re touching for that bug. Rename it to &lt;code&gt;.ts&lt;/code&gt;, fix any major issues it flags up that you can—but stick as locally as possible. You’re apt to find a &lt;em&gt;lot&lt;/em&gt; of small bugs as you start migrating, and some of them are things which are apt to affect your whole system because they touch central data types. It’s okay. You can come back to those later. For today, you can just be explicit about the weirdnesses.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;As part of that: get comfortable—really, really comfortable—with &lt;a href="http://www.typescriptlang.org/docs/handbook/advanced-types.html#union-types"&gt;union types&lt;/a&gt;. They’ll make it much easier to express the kind of code you’ve &lt;em&gt;actually&lt;/em&gt; written.&lt;a href="#fn1" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref1"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Don’t worry about adding explicit types to &lt;em&gt;everything.&lt;/em&gt; In fact, depending on how comfortable you are already with typed languages, you should probably take a pretty different tack with this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;If you’re just stepping into the world of typed programming languages, you might start adding types where they’re the &lt;em&gt;lowest risk&lt;/em&gt;: some place like your automated tests. That’ll help you start to see how to take advantage of them, while not impacting the way you write your app code until you have a better idea how best to employ the types.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;If you’re already really comfortable with typed programming languages, you might employ types where they’re &lt;em&gt;most helpful:&lt;/em&gt; start with some types in the hairiest or trickiest spots of your app.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is plenty more I could say, but I think that’s a good start for now. I’ll have lots more to add in later posts about the details of how specifically to get the most mileage out of types within an Ember.js app today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="/2017/typing-your-ember-part-1"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Previous:&lt;/strong&gt; Part 1 – Set your Ember.js project up to use TypeScript.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;section class="footnotes"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn1"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Also, I &lt;em&gt;strongly&lt;/em&gt; encourage you to write types in terms of unions of types rather than in terms of &lt;a href="http://www.typescriptlang.org/docs/handbook/interfaces.html#optional-properties"&gt;optional properties on types&lt;/a&gt;. That might be surprising; I’ll explain it in more detail in a future post.&lt;a href="#fnref1"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 08 May 2017 22:00:00 -0400</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2017-05-08:/2017/typing-your-ember-part-2.html</guid><category>typescript</category><category>emberjs</category><category>typing-your-ember</category></item><item><title>Typing Your Ember, Part 1</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2017/typing-your-ember-part-1.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;i class='series-overview'&gt;You write &lt;a href="https://emberjs.com"&gt;Ember.js&lt;/a&gt; apps. You think &lt;a href="http://www.typescriptlang.org"&gt;TypeScript&lt;/a&gt; would be helpful in building a more robust app as it increases in size or has more people working on it. But you have questions about how to make it work.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;i class='series-overview'&gt;This is the series for you! I’ll talk through everything: from the very basics of how to set up your Ember.js app to use TypeScript to how you can get the most out of TypeScript today—and I’ll be pretty clear about the current tradeoffs and limitations, too.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;i class='series-overview'&gt;&lt;a href="/typing-your-ember.html"&gt;(See the rest of the series. →)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this first post in the series, we’re going to keep things simple and easy: we’re going to get an Ember.js app configured to use TypeScript. Later posts will cover some of the other details.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because of the lovely &lt;a href="https://ember-cli.com"&gt;Ember CLI&lt;/a&gt; ecosystem, this is a pretty straightforward process. I’m going to start from &lt;em&gt;zero&lt;/em&gt; so that even if you’ve never written an Ember app before, you can get this up and running by following these instructions. These instructions have also been tested and confirmed to work across platforms—you can do this equally on Windows, macOS, or Linux.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol type="1"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Make sure you have Ember’s prerequisites installed. Get &lt;a href="https://nodejs.org/en/"&gt;Node&lt;/a&gt; for your platform. Optionally (but highly recommended) install &lt;a href="https://yarnpkg.com"&gt;Yarn&lt;/a&gt; to manage your Node packages.&lt;a href="#fn1" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref1"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Install the Ember command lines tools globally:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="sh"&gt;&lt;code&gt;yarn global add ember-cli&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;or&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="sh"&gt;&lt;code&gt;npm install --global ember-cli&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Create an Ember app.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="sh"&gt;&lt;code&gt;ember new my-ts-app --yarn&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(Using the &lt;code&gt;--yarn&lt;/code&gt; flag will make it so your app uses &lt;a href="https://yarnpkg.com"&gt;&lt;code&gt;yarn&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and creates a &lt;code&gt;yarn.lock&lt;/code&gt; file instead of using &lt;code&gt;npm&lt;/code&gt; when it installs its dependencies.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Now move to the root of the newly created app: this is where we’ll do everything else in the post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="sh"&gt;&lt;code&gt;cd my-ts-app&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Add the &lt;a href="https://emberobserver.com/addons/ember-cli-typescript"&gt;&lt;em&gt;ember-cli-typescript&lt;/em&gt; add-on&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="sh"&gt;&lt;code&gt;ember install ember-cli-typescript&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Generate your first UI component.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="sh"&gt;&lt;code&gt;ember generate component some-input&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Rename the files it generated from &lt;code&gt;.js&lt;/code&gt; to &lt;code&gt;.ts&lt;/code&gt;:
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;app/components/some-input.js&lt;/code&gt; → &lt;code&gt;app/components/some-input.ts&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;tests/integration/components/some-input-test.js&lt;/code&gt; → &lt;code&gt;tests/integration/components/some-input-test.ts&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(Eventually, we’ll make it so that you get TypeScript for all newly generated components when using &lt;em&gt;ember-cli-typescript&lt;/em&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Add some content to the files:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="handlebars"&gt;&lt;code&gt;{{!-- some-input.hbs --}}
{{input value=theValue change=(mut theValue)}}
{{theValue}}&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre class="typescript"&gt;&lt;code&gt;// some-input.ts
import Ember from &amp;#39;ember&amp;#39;;

export default Ember.Component.extend({
  theValue: &amp;#39;&amp;#39;,
});&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Update your &lt;code&gt;application.hbs&lt;/code&gt; file to remove the default &lt;code&gt;{{welcome}}&lt;/code&gt; template and replace it with &lt;code&gt;{{some-input}}&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Spin up the Ember application with Ember CLI’s development server:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="sh"&gt;&lt;code&gt;ember serve&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You’ll likely note some warnings: the TypeScript compiler won’t be able to find some of the modules imported in your files. I’ll have more to say about this in a future post. For now, suffice it to say: don’t worry, Ember CLI is still resolving and compiling your modules just fine.&lt;a href="#fn2" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref2"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Load the application by going to &lt;code&gt;localhost:4200&lt;/code&gt; in your browser. You should see a blank white screen with an input in it. Type in it, and see the input rendered to the page. Simple enough, but it’s using a TypeScript file compiled along the way!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And that’s it: we’re done setting up an Ember.js app to use TypeScript! In the next post, I’ll talk a bit about strategies for migrating an existing app to TypeScript—not just the mechanics of it, but also where and how to start actually integrating types into your code.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="/2017/typing-your-ember-part-2"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Next:&lt;/strong&gt; Part 2 – Adding TypeScript to an existing Ember.js project.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;section class="footnotes"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn1"&gt;&lt;p&gt;I strongly prefer to use &lt;code&gt;yarn&lt;/code&gt; over &lt;code&gt;npm&lt;/code&gt; because &lt;code&gt;yarn&lt;/code&gt; installs are predictable and repeatable, and if there’s one thing I don’t need to spend time on when developing our Ember.js app at Olo, it’s chasing problems with transitive dependencies that are different in the build server than in my local development environment. Yarn’s lockfiles mean what ends up built on the server is &lt;em&gt;exactly&lt;/em&gt; what ended up built on my machine.&lt;a href="#fnref1"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn2"&gt;&lt;p&gt;But if you’re curious, here’s a preview: we really need more &lt;a href="http://www.typescriptlang.org/docs/handbook/declaration-files/introduction.html"&gt;type definitions&lt;/a&gt; for the Ember ecosystem. I’ll be covering &lt;em&gt;how&lt;/em&gt; we build those in much more detail in a future installment.&lt;a href="#fnref2"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 05 May 2017 00:10:00 -0400</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2017-05-05:/2017/typing-your-ember-part-1.html</guid><category>typescript</category><category>emberjs</category><category>typing-your-ember</category></item><item><title></title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2016/11-22-1320.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Current status: Counter Culture coffee and &lt;a href="https://www.viderichocolatefactory.com"&gt;Videri Chocolate&lt;/a&gt; 70% dark chocolate and Ember.js for Olo. This is a good Tuesday afternoon.&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 22 Nov 2016 13:20:00 -0500</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2016-11-22:/2016/11-22-1320.html</guid><category>coffee</category><category>emberjs</category></item><item><title></title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2016/08-17-0825.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;I’m writing a talk on test-driven development with &lt;a href="http://emberjs.com"&gt;Ember.js&lt;/a&gt; for &lt;a href="http://www.olo.com"&gt;Olo&lt;/a&gt;’s in-house tech talks. How? By building a real feature and capturing the process!&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 17 Aug 2016 08:25:00 -0400</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2016-08-17:/2016/08-17-0825.html</guid><category>software development</category><category>testing</category><category>javascript</category><category>emberjs</category></item><item><title>Testing Ember.js Mixins (and Helpers) With a Container</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2016/testing-emberjs-mixins-with-a-container.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Updated to note that the same concerns apply to helpers. You can always see the full revision history of this item &lt;a href="https://github.com/chriskrycho/chriskrycho.com/commits/master/content/tech/ember-js-mixins-container.md"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today I was working on an Ember.js &lt;a href="http://emberjs.com/api/classes/Ember.Mixin.html#content"&gt;mixin&lt;/a&gt; for the new mobile web application we’re shipping at Olo, and I ran into an interesting problem when trying to test it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you’re testing mixins (or helpers), you’re generally not working with the normal Ember container.&lt;a href="#fn1" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref1"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; In fact, the default test setup for mixins doesn’t have &lt;em&gt;any&lt;/em&gt; container in play. It just looks like this (assuming you ran &lt;code&gt;ember generate mixin bar&lt;/code&gt; in an app named &lt;code&gt;foo&lt;/code&gt;):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="js"&gt;&lt;code&gt;import Ember from &amp;#39;ember&amp;#39;;
import BarMixin from &amp;#39;foo/mixins/bar&amp;#39;;
import { module, test } from &amp;#39;qunit&amp;#39;;

module(&amp;#39;Unit | Mixin | bar&amp;#39;);

// Replace this with your real tests.
test(&amp;#39;it works&amp;#39;, function(assert) {
  let BarObject = Ember.Object.extend(BarMixin);
  let subject = BarObject.create();
  assert.ok(subject);
});&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note two things:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol type="1"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It uses the basic Qunit &lt;code&gt;module&lt;/code&gt; setup, not the ember-qunit &lt;code&gt;moduleFor&lt;/code&gt; setup.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It assumes you’re generating a new object instance for every single test.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Both of those assumptions are fine, &lt;em&gt;if you don’t need to interact with the container&lt;/em&gt;. In many cases, that’s perfectly reasonable—I’d go so far as to say that most mixins and helpers probably &lt;em&gt;shouldn’t&lt;/em&gt; have any dependency on the container.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the specific case I was working on, however, the point of the mixin was to abstract some common behavior which included all the interactions with a &lt;a href="https://guides.emberjs.com/v2.6.0/applications/services/"&gt;service&lt;/a&gt;. This meant making sure the dependency injection worked in the unit test. This in turn meant dealing with the container. So let’s see what was involved in that. (You can generalize this approach to any place in the Ember ecosystem where you need to test something which doesn’t normally have the container set up.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We start by switching from the basic &lt;code&gt;qunit&lt;/code&gt; helpers to using the &lt;code&gt;ember-qunit&lt;/code&gt; helpers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="js"&gt;&lt;code&gt;// Replace this...
import { module, test } from &amp;#39;qunit&amp;#39;;
module(&amp;#39;Unit | Mixin | bar&amp;#39;);

// with this:
import { moduleFor, test } from &amp;#39;ember-qunit&amp;#39;;
moduleFor(&amp;#39;mixin:bar&amp;#39;, &amp;#39;Unit | Mixin | Bar&amp;#39;);&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;code&gt;moduleFor()&lt;/code&gt; helper has two things going for it—one of which we &lt;em&gt;need&lt;/em&gt;, and one of which isn’t strictly &lt;em&gt;necessary&lt;/em&gt;, but has some nice functionality. In any case, this will help when registering a container. Those two features:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol type="1"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It does support the use of the container. In fact, it’s declaring how this mixin relates to the container in the first argument to the helper function: &lt;code&gt;'mixin:foo'&lt;/code&gt; is the definition of the mixin for injection into the container.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Any functions we define on the options argument we can pass to the &lt;code&gt;moduleFor()&lt;/code&gt; helper are available on the &lt;code&gt;this&lt;/code&gt; of the test.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, in the first version of this, I had set up a common &lt;code&gt;Ember.Object&lt;/code&gt; which had mixed in the &lt;code&gt;BarMixin&lt;/code&gt;, so:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="js"&gt;&lt;code&gt;const BarObject = Ember.Object.extend(BarMixin);&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then, in each test, I created instances of this to use:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="js"&gt;&lt;code&gt;test(&amp;#39;test some feature or another&amp;#39;, function(assert) {
  const subject = BarObject.create();
  // ...do stuff and test it with `assert.ok()`, etc.
});&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The problem was that any of those tests which required a container injection always failed. Assume we have a service named &lt;code&gt;quux&lt;/code&gt;, and that it’s injected into the mixin like this in &lt;code&gt;foo/app/mixins/bar.js&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="js"&gt;&lt;code&gt;import Ember from &amp;#39;ember&amp;#39;;

export default Ember.Mixin.create({
  quux: Ember.inject.service()
});&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Any test which actually tried to &lt;em&gt;use&lt;/em&gt; &lt;code&gt;quux&lt;/code&gt; would simply fail because of the missing container (even if you specified in the test setup that you needed the service):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;test(&amp;#39;it uses quux somehow&amp;#39;, function(assert) {
  const subject = BarObject.create();
  const quux = subject.get(&amp;#39;quux&amp;#39;);  // throws Error
});&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Specifically, you will see &lt;code&gt;Attempting to lookup an injected property on an object without a container&lt;/code&gt; if you look in your console.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Taking advantage of the two &lt;code&gt;ember-qunit&lt;/code&gt; features, though, we can handle all of this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="js"&gt;&lt;code&gt;import Ember from &amp;#39;ember&amp;#39;;
import { moduleFor, test } from &amp;#39;ember-qunit&amp;#39;;

const { getOwner } = Ember;

moduleFor(&amp;#39;mixin:bar&amp;#39;, &amp;#39;Unit | Mixin | bar&amp;#39;, {
  // The `needs` property in the options argument tells the test
  // framework that it needs to go find and instantiate the `quux`
  // service. (Note that if `quux` depends on other injected
  // services, you have to specify that here as well.)
  needs: [&amp;#39;service:quux&amp;#39;],

  // Again: any object we create in this options object will be
  // available on the `this` of every `test` function below. Here,
  // we want to get a &amp;quot;test subject&amp;quot; which is attached to the
  // Ember container, so that the container is available to the
  // test subject itself for retrieving the dependencies injected
  // into it (and defined above in `needs`).
  subject() {
    BarObject = Ember.Object.extend(BarMixin);

    // This whole thing works because, since we&amp;#39;re in a
    // `moduleFor()`, `this` has the relevant method we need to
    // attach items to the container: `register()`.
    this.register(&amp;#39;test-container:bar-object&amp;#39;, BarObject);

    // `Ember.getOwner` is the public API for getting the
    // container to do this kind of lookup. You can use it in lots
    // of places, including but not limited to tests. Note that
    // that because of how the dependency injection works, what we
    // get back from the lookup is not `BarObject`, but an
    // instance of `BarObject`. That means that we don&amp;#39;t need to
    // do `BarObject.create()` when we use this below; Ember
    // already did that for us.
    return getOwner(this).lookup(&amp;#39;test-container:bar-object&amp;#39;);
  }
});

test(&amp;#39;the mixin+service does what it should&amp;#39;, function(assert) {
  // We start by running the subject function defined above. We
  // now have an instance of an `Ember.Object` which has
  // `BarMixin` applied.
  const subject = this.subject();

  // Now, because we used a test helper that made the container
  // available, declared the dependencies of the mixin in `needs`,
  // and registered the object we&amp;#39;re dealing with here, we don&amp;#39;t
  // get an error anymore.
  const quux = subject.get(&amp;#39;quux&amp;#39;);
});&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, in summary:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol type="1"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use the &lt;code&gt;ember-qunit&lt;/code&gt; helpers if you need the container.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Define whatever dependencies you have in &lt;code&gt;needs&lt;/code&gt;, just as you would in any other test.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Register the mixin-derived object (whether &lt;code&gt;Ember.Object&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;Ember.Route&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;Ember.Component&lt;/code&gt;, or whatever else) in a method on the options argument for &lt;code&gt;moduleFor()&lt;/code&gt;. Use that to get an instance of the object and you’re off to the races!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One final consideration: while in this case it made good sense to use this approach and make the service injection available for the test, there’s a reason that the tests generated by Ember CLI don’t use &lt;code&gt;moduleFor()&lt;/code&gt; by default. It’s a quiet but clear signal that you should reevaluate whether this &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; in fact the correct approach.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In general, mixins are best used for self-contained units of functionality. If you &lt;em&gt;need&lt;/em&gt; dependency injection for them, it may mean that you should think about structuring things in a different way. Can all the functionality live on the service itself? Can all of it live in the mixin instead of requiring a service? Can the service calls be delegated to whatever type is using the mixin?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But if not, and you &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt; need a mixin which injects a service, now you know how to do it!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Side note:&lt;/strong&gt; The documentation around testing mixins is relatively weak, and in general the testing docs are the weak bits in the Ember guides right now.&lt;a href="#fn2" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref2"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; After a conversation with &lt;a href="https://github.com/rwjblue"&gt;@rwjblue&lt;/a&gt; on the &lt;a href="https://ember-community-slackin.herokuapp.com"&gt;Ember Community Slack&lt;/a&gt;, though, I was able to get a handle on the issue, and here we are. Since it stumped me, I’m guessing I’m not the only one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When this happens, &lt;em&gt;write it up&lt;/em&gt;. I’ve been guilty of this too often in the past few months: learning something new that I couldn’t find anywhere online, and then leaving it stored in my own head. It doesn’t take a particularly long time to write a blog post like this, and if you’re stuck, chances are &lt;em&gt;very&lt;/em&gt; good someone else is too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section class="footnotes"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn1"&gt;&lt;p&gt;If you’re not familiar with the “container”, this is where all the various dependencies are registered, and where Ember looks them up to inject them when you use methods like &lt;code&gt;Ember.inject.service()&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;a href="#fnref1"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn2"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Something I intend to help address in the next week or two via a pull request, so if you’re my Ember.js documentation team friend and you’re reading this… it’s coming. 😉&lt;a href="#fnref2"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 09 Jun 2016 20:35:00 -0400</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2016-06-09:/2016/testing-emberjs-mixins-with-a-container.html</guid><category>emberjs</category><category>javascript</category><category>software development</category></item><item><title>Ember.js: "Introducing Subteams"</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2016/emberjs-introducing-subteams.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;In which one tech I really like (&lt;a href="http://emberjs.com"&gt;Ember.js&lt;/a&gt;) steals a great idea from another tech I really like (&lt;a href="https://www.rust-lang.org"&gt;Rust&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id="refs" class="references"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 24 May 2016 19:10:00 -0400</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2016-05-24:/2016/emberjs-introducing-subteams.html</guid><category>links</category><category>programming languages</category><category>emberjs</category><category>rust</category></item><item><title></title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2016/2016-05-06-1056.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;I just had one of thos beautiful moments when I realized I’d written a beautifully generic component I could reuse throughout the app, and it made me &lt;em&gt;so happy&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id="refs" class="references"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 06 May 2016 10:56:00 -0400</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2016-05-06:/2016/2016-05-06-1056.html</guid><category>software development</category><category>emberjs</category></item><item><title></title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2016/2016-04-19-1744.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;I still love EmberJS—but if I have one complaint, it’s that it’s &lt;em&gt;slightly&lt;/em&gt; too heavy on convention-based magic. I want it to be a little more explicit, so that I can have a little more insight into what it’s going. Yes, even if that means a little more boilerplate. Explicit is better than implicit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id="refs" class="references"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 19 Apr 2016 17:44:00 -0400</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2016-04-19:/2016/2016-04-19-1744.html</guid><category>javascript</category><category>emberjs</category><category>software development</category></item><item><title></title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2016/2016-03-12-1154.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Just registered for &lt;a href="https://wickedgoodember.com"&gt;Wicked Good Ember Conf&lt;/a&gt; 2016. Looking forward to chatting &lt;a href="http://emberjs.com"&gt;Ember.js&lt;/a&gt; in Boston in June!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id="refs" class="references"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 12 Mar 2016 11:54:00 -0500</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2016-03-12:/2016/2016-03-12-1154.html</guid><category>emberjs</category><category>conferences</category></item><item><title></title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2016/2016-03-09-1236.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Pro tip for tracking down oddities with &lt;a href="http://emberjs.com"&gt;Ember.js&lt;/a&gt; during testing: &lt;code&gt;ember test --serve --filter '&amp;lt;some pattern&amp;gt;'&lt;/code&gt; is &lt;em&gt;great&lt;/em&gt;. E.g. &lt;code&gt;ember t -s --filter 'Unit'&lt;/code&gt; for just unit tests.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id="refs" class="references"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 09 Mar 2016 12:36:00 -0500</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2016-03-09:/2016/2016-03-09-1236.html</guid><category>software development</category><category>javascript</category><category>emberjs</category></item><item><title>Unsurprisingly, In Flux</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2015/unsurprisingly-in-flux.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;i class="editorial"&gt;This started as a &lt;a href="https://alpha.app.net/chriskrycho/post/57102562"&gt;series of posts&lt;/a&gt; on App.net. I &lt;a href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2014/a-few-theses-on-blogging.html"&gt;resolved&lt;/a&gt; a while ago that if I was tempted to do that, I should just write a blog post instead. I failed at that resolution, but at a friend’s &lt;a href="https://alpha.app.net/jws/post/57108281"&gt;suggestion&lt;/a&gt;, am adapting it into a blog post anyway. You can see the posts that prompted it &lt;a href="https://alpha.app.net/keita/post/57096585"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://alpha.app.net/jws/post/57096838"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The state of JavaScript frameworks today is a scale, really, from not-at-all-monolithic to totally-monolithic, in roughly this order: Backbone – React &amp;amp; Angular – Ember – Meteor.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Backbone and related library Underscore are really collections of common JS tools and patterns you can use to write apps, but they’re not &lt;em&gt;frameworks&lt;/em&gt;, per se. You’ll write all your own boilerplate there.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;React and Angular supply much &lt;em&gt;more&lt;/em&gt; of the functionality, but Angular is a “meta-framework” that aims to do &lt;em&gt;some&lt;/em&gt; boilerplate but let you construct your own custom app framework.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Angular is very powerful, but it’s kind of like Git: wires are exposed; you have to understand a &lt;em&gt;lot&lt;/em&gt; about the internals to get it to do what you want. Its routing functionality is pretty limited out of the box, too—so much so that there’s a near-standard third-party router.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;React, as I understand it, supplies a paradigm and associated tools oriented primarily at view state management, though with capabilities via extensions for routing, etc. These tools are &lt;em&gt;extremely&lt;/em&gt; powerful for performance in particular. It’s not a full framework, and the docs expressly note that you can &lt;em&gt;just&lt;/em&gt; use React for the view layer with other tools if you want.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;In any case, Angular and React do &lt;em&gt;different&lt;/em&gt; things from each other, but both do substantially more than Backbone.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ember is a full framework, strongly emphasizing shared conventions (with a lot of common developers from Rails). It’s perhaps less adaptable than React or Angular, but is much more full-featured; you have very little boilerplate to do.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Meteor is like Ember, but does server-side Node as well as client-side stuff, with the goal being to minimize code duplication, sharing assets as much as possible.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Of all of those, Ember has easily (easily!) the best-explained roadmap, most articulate leadership, and best development path. They are also aggressively adopting the best features of other frameworks wherever it makes sense.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Angular is currently in flux, as Google has announced Angular 2.0 will be basically a completely different framework; there will be &lt;em&gt;no&lt;/em&gt; direct migration path for Angular 1.x apps to Angular 2.0+. Total rewrite required.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ember uses a steady 6-week release schedule with very careful regression testing and semantic versioning, with clear deprecation notices and upgrade paths, and is therefore both rapidly iterating &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; relatively stable for use.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;If you just need a set of tools for enhance functionality on otherwise relatively static pages, Backbone+Underscore is a great combo. If you already have a bunch of things in place but want a dedicated view layer, React is good.&lt;a href="#fn1" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref1"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;If you’re writing a new, full-on web &lt;em&gt;application&lt;/em&gt; (SPA, or organized in whatever other way), I think Ember is the very clear winner at this point. I have good confidence in their leadership and they’re firing on all cylinders.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Regarding Angular, &lt;a href="https://alpha.app.net/mikehoss"&gt;@mikehoss&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://alpha.app.net/mikehoss/post/57105656"&gt;posted&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the record they are doing that to make it more mobile-friendly. The Ang1 has abysmal performance on mobile. Besides a time machine, this maybe the best option. And Miško is a bit of a jerk.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I can’t speak to his comment about Miško (Miško Hevery, one of the leads on AngularJS), but I agree about Angular itself: the rewrite needs to happen. Angular 1.x is a mess—as are its docs. It’s just not a good time to be using 1.x for any new projects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ll add to these points that I’ve used Angular for the last 9 months on HolyBible.com development. As I noted: the documentation is pretty rough, and in a lot of cases you really do have to understand what the framework is doing and how before you can get it to do the things you want. This is, in one sense, exactly the &lt;em&gt;opposite&lt;/em&gt; of what I’m looking for in a framework—but it makes sense given Angular’s goal of being a meta-framework.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rather like Git, though, which was originally going to be infrastructure for version control systems which would have their own interface, but eventually just had a “good enough” interface that we’re all now stuck with, Angular is being used &lt;em&gt;as&lt;/em&gt; a framework, not just as a &lt;em&gt;meta-framework&lt;/em&gt;, and it’s unsurprisingly not great for that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;i class="editorial"&gt;Take this for what it’s worth: not the final word (by a long stretch) on JavaScript frameworks, but rather the perspective of one guy who notably &lt;em&gt;hasn’t used all of the frameworks&lt;/em&gt;, but has spent some time looking at them. Moreover, I haven’t particularly edited this; it’s more a summary in the kind of short-form posts that I originally created than a detailed analysis. The only things I’ve done are expand some of the notes on Angular and React, and add the footnote on React.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id="refs" class="references"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;section class="footnotes"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn1"&gt;&lt;p&gt;I &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; don’t know a ton about React, but I do think a lot of what I do know about it is cool from a programming perspective. From a designer perspective, however, it’s a bit of a pain: React’s “JSX” domain-specific language is &lt;em&gt;much&lt;/em&gt; less friendly to developers than standard HTML, and therefore than either Ember or Angular, both of which implement their templating via HTML templating languages. There’s a substantil tradeoff there: React’s model is interesting not only academically but in practice because of the performance results it produces. It’s worth note, though, that others have recognized this and are adopting it to varying degrees; notably, Ember is incorporating the idea of minimizing changes to the DOM by keeping track of state and updating only differences, rather than refreshing the whole tree, in the new rendering engine (HTMLBars) they’re rolling out over the past several and future several releases.&lt;a href="#fnref1"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 08 Apr 2015 16:05:00 -0400</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2015-04-08:/2015/unsurprisingly-in-flux.html</guid><category>software development</category><category>javascript</category><category>angularjs</category><category>emberjs</category><category>react</category></item></channel></rss>