<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Chris Krycho - ethics</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/</link><description></description><lastBuildDate>Mon, 04 Jun 2018 10:30:00 -0400</lastBuildDate><item><title>Good Arguments</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2018/good-arguments.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;I’m working my way slowly and carefully through Shannon Vallor’s &lt;cite&gt;Technology and the Virtues&lt;/cite&gt; and as I put it to my friend and partner-in-&lt;a href="https://winningslowly.org"&gt;Winning Slowly&lt;/a&gt; Stephen Carradini: I find that I &lt;em&gt;very often&lt;/em&gt; agree with Vallor on her conclusions while &lt;em&gt;equally often&lt;/em&gt; disagreeing with her on how she gets there. It makes for very interesting reading, certainly; and so far, at least, I can pretty heartily commend the book despite my disagreements.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And the reason why I can so heartily recommend it is what I’m more interested in at the moment. Vallor is a really excellent &lt;em&gt;conversation partner&lt;/em&gt;. Not all writers are. But &lt;cite&gt;Technology and the Virtues&lt;/cite&gt; is the kind of book that is sufficiently well-written and well-argued&lt;a href="#fn1" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref1"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; that the very act of disagreeing with it—if you take the time, anyway—produces light rather than merely heat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A good conversation partner prompts you to think hard about the differences between her position and your own. She pushes you to articulate &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt; you disagree, and whether your disagreements are well-founded, and if not to see if you &lt;em&gt;can&lt;/em&gt; provide a good foundation for them. Vallor has this and in spades. I have pages of notes both agreeing with many of her points and also articulating why—as a &lt;em&gt;Christian&lt;/em&gt; interested in virtue ethics—I differ sharply with her in certain areas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What makes all of this valuable is that these are &lt;em&gt;illuminating&lt;/em&gt; differences. I have a better sense of some of the gaps at least in my own education in Christian ethical systems.&lt;a href="#fn2" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref2"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; I have a better sense of the space in which Stephen and I are playing with Winning Slowly &lt;a href="https://winningslowly.org/season-6.html" title="Rejecting the Inevitable Future"&gt;Season 6&lt;/a&gt;. I have clarified my own view of the relationship of virtue and wisdom and law in meaningful ways in just the short time I’ve been working through this book—and I can feel the gears turning still in the background; there is a lot more sharpening to come from this.&lt;a href="#fn3" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref3"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When people talk about the benefits of reading those you disagree with, this is what they mean. The best interlocutors are those who push you like this—whether you agree or disagree, they make you work harder and think more sharply. Good arguments are invaluable for clear thinking and the pursuit of truth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One other thing this points at is that good thinking often begets good thinking. I actively &lt;em&gt;want&lt;/em&gt; to think well about these things, but I also am unable to do as well in a vacuum as I can with the help of others who are thinking hard and well about them—even, and sometimes &lt;em&gt;especially&lt;/em&gt;, when we disagree.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the reasons I blog is as an attempt to think well out loud. I cannot make others think well no matter how well I think; and I certainly do not presume that my own thinking &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; always thinking well. But the act of writing, and writing publicly, is an attempt to do the kind of work (on however small a scale) that I see people like Vallor and &lt;a href="http://blog.ayjay.org" title="Snakes and Ladders"&gt;Alan Jacobs&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://stratechery.com"&gt;Ben Thompson&lt;/a&gt; doing in their own spaces. If I can do even a fraction so well as they are in my own space, perhaps I too can help others think well. At the least, I know I am learning to think better along the way, and that is no small thing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section class="footnotes"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn1"&gt;&lt;p&gt;These are different! Complementary, but different.&lt;a href="#fnref1" class="footnote-back"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn2"&gt;&lt;p&gt;See &lt;a href="https://www.chriskrycho.com/2018/the-chinese-room-argument.html#fn2"&gt;footnote 2 on an earlier blog post&lt;/a&gt; for a comment on why I assume the problem is likely with &lt;em&gt;me&lt;/em&gt;. It’s probable that there &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; quite a bit of specifically Christian reflection on many of these ideas; I simply haven’t encountered it. This may also say some things about the specifics of my theological education; I think it does and may return to that in a later post, but that’s neither here nor there.&lt;a href="#fnref2" class="footnote-back"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn3"&gt;&lt;p&gt;A preview:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Vallor sees virtue ethics as incommensurable with deontological accounts of ethics; I think the two are meant to complement one another. The structure of Biblical ethics is both deontological and virtuous. In particular, my read of the Wisdom literature (as well as the New Testament account of righteous life which builds upon it) is that the Biblical account sees virtue (or righteousness) and wisdom as the fruit—and I choose that word intentionally—of life lived under God’s enduring law. The moral precepts do not change; their specific applications are plurifold, and the shape of Biblical ethical reflection itself is likewise wide-ranging. Put more simply: life lived under God’s law in his power &lt;em&gt;yields&lt;/em&gt; wisdom. This is not so different from Vallor’s picture of the virtue ethics of Aristotle, Confucius, or Buddha—save that wisdom in the Biblical account does not &lt;em&gt;supercede&lt;/em&gt; God’s law; it comes to rightly apprehend &lt;em&gt;how&lt;/em&gt; the God’s ways are rightly applied in every circumstance.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Vallor rejects the notion of any singular account of a human &lt;em&gt;telos&lt;/em&gt; or specific nature (other than what we have been given by evolution) that is capable of grounding the pursuit of virtue across all cultures. She aims for a kind of ethical pluralism that can account for the various cultural notions of human nature and &lt;em&gt;telos&lt;/em&gt; without falling into ethical relativism or absolutism. I don’t think her account can actually support this weight, though. By contrast, I think Christianity &lt;em&gt;does&lt;/em&gt; have the resources to support the kind of pluralism she rightly recognizes as necessary because its account of human naature and &lt;em&gt;telos&lt;/em&gt; are rich enough to embrace the goods of many cultures and contexts and wisdom traditions. (That Christianity has not perfectly or even very much at all lived up to this potential is, as Vallor herself notes of her own account of virtue ethics, by no means a defeater for the claim.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is much, &lt;em&gt;much&lt;/em&gt; more to say here, and I will—later!&lt;a href="#fnref3" class="footnote-back"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 04 Jun 2018 10:30:00 -0400</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2018-06-04:/2018/good-arguments.html</guid><category>writing</category><category>philosophy</category><category>ethics</category></item><item><title>The Chinese Room Argument</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2018/the-chinese-room-argument.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;I took a bunch of half days last week, because &lt;em&gt;goodness&lt;/em&gt; but I was tired. Too long running at full-throttle, and &lt;a href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2018/on-steam-specifically-running-out-of-it.html" title="On Steam (Specifically, Running Out Of It)"&gt;I’d been running out of steam&lt;/a&gt; as a result. And what did I do instead, that ended up being so effective in &lt;a href="https://www.chriskrycho.com/2018/vacation-as-recharging.html" title="Vacation as Recharging"&gt;recharging&lt;/a&gt;? Well, mostly… read literature reviews on interesting topics in philosophy, at least for the first few days. Dear reader, I am a nerd. But I thought I’d share a few of the thoughts I jotted down in my notebook from that reading.&lt;a href="#fn1" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref1"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;section id="the-chinese-room-argument" class="level2"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;“The Chinese Room Argument”&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was an argument whose &lt;em&gt;influence&lt;/em&gt; I’ve certainly encountered, but the actual content of which I was totally unfamiliar with.&lt;a href="#fn2" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref2"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The argument, in &lt;em&gt;exceedingly&lt;/em&gt; brief summary, is that “formal operations on symbols cannot produce thought”—that syntax is insufficient for conveying semantics. Searle made the argument by way of a thought experiment; a reference in a review on “Thought Experiments” I may post about later is how I found my way to the discussion. That thought experiment supposes a man being handed symbols (under a door, perhaps) which are questions in Chinese, who has a set of rules for constructing correct answers to those questions, also in Chinese—but the man himself, however much he gives every &lt;em&gt;appearance&lt;/em&gt; of knowing Chinese to the person passing in questions by way of the answers he gives, does not in fact know Chinese. He simply has a set of rules that allow him to give the appearance of knowledge. The Chinese Room argument, in other words, is a(n attempted) refutation of the &lt;a href="https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Turing_test"&gt;Turing Test&lt;/a&gt; as a metric for evaluating intelligence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The rejoinders to this are varied, of course, and I encourage you simply to follow the link above and read the summary—it’s good.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There were two particularly interesting points to me in reading this summary: the Churchland response, and the Other Minds response. To these I’ll add a quick note of my own.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section id="the-churchland-response" class="level3"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;1: The Churchland response&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Searle’s argument specifically addressed an approach to &lt;abbr title="artificial intelligence"&gt;AI&lt;/abbr&gt; (and especially so-called “strong &lt;abbr title="artificial intelligence"&gt;AI&lt;/abbr&gt;,” i.e. &lt;abbr title="artificial intelligence"&gt;AI&lt;/abbr&gt; that is genuinely intelligent) that was very much in vogue when he wrote the article in the 1980s, but which is very much &lt;em&gt;out&lt;/em&gt; of vogue now: rule-driven computation. One of the responses, which looks rather prescient in retrospect, was the Churchland reply that the brain is not a symbolic computation machine (i.e. a computer as we tend to think of it) but “a vector transformer”… which is a precise description of the “neural network”-based &lt;abbr title="artificial intelligence"&gt;AI&lt;/abbr&gt; that is now dominating research into e.g. self-driving cars and so on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The main point of interest here is not so much whether the Churchlands were correct in their description of the brain’s behavior, but in their point that any hypothesis about neural networks is &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; defeated by Searle’s thought experiment. Why not? Because neural networks are not performing symbolic computation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="the-other-minds-response" class="level3"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;2: The Other Minds response&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The other, and perhaps the most challenging response for Searle’s argument, is the “other minds” argument. Whether in other humans, or in intelligent aliens should we encounter them, or—and this is the key—in a genuinely intelligent machine, we attribute the existence other minds &lt;em&gt;intuitively&lt;/em&gt;. Nor do we (in general) doubt our initial conclusion that another mind exists merely because we come to have a greater understanding of the underlying neuro-mechanics. We understand far more about human brains and their relationship to the human mind than we did a hundred years ago; we do not therefore doubt the reality of a human mind. (Most of us, anyway! There are not many hard determinists of the sort who think consciousness is merely an illusion; and there are not many solipsists who think only their own minds exist.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the “other minds” objection runs into other intuitive problems all its own: supposing that we learned an apparently-conscious thing we interacted with were but a cleverly-arranged set of waterworks, we would certainly revise our opinion. Which intuition is to be trusted? Either, neither, or in some strange way both?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And this gets again at the difficulty of using thought experiments to reason to truth. What a thought experiment can genuinely be said to show is complicated at best. Yet their utility—at least in raising problems, but also in making genuine advances in understanding the world—seems clear.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="lowered-standards" class="level3"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Lowered standards&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The other thing I think is worth noting in all these discussions is a point I first saw Alan Jacobs raise a few years ago, but which was only &lt;em&gt;alluded&lt;/em&gt; to in this literature review. Jacobs &lt;a href="http://text-patterns.thenewatlantis.com/2010/08/advice-from-jaron-lanier.html"&gt;cites&lt;/a&gt; Jaron Lanier’s &lt;cite&gt;You Are Not A Gadget&lt;/cite&gt;. (I don’t have a copy of the book, so I’ll reproduce Jacobs’ quotation here.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the Turing test cuts both ways. You can’t tell if a machine has gotten smarter or if you’ve just lowered your own standards of intelligence to such a degree that the machine seems smart. If you can have a conversation with a simulated person presented by an AI program, can you tell how far you’ve let your sense of personhood degrade in order to make the illusion work for you?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is one of the essential points often left aside. Is the test itself useful? Is “ability to fool a human into think you’re human” &lt;em&gt;actually&lt;/em&gt; pointing at what it means to be intelligent? This is sort of the unspoken aspect of the “other minds” question. But it’s one we &lt;em&gt;ought&lt;/em&gt; to speak when we’re talking about intelligence!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section class="footnotes"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn1"&gt;&lt;p&gt;For those of you following along at home: I wrote all but the last 100 or so words of this a week ago and just hadn’t gotten around to publishing it. It’s not the even more absurd contradiction to yesterday’s post on writing plans than it seems. Really. I promise.&lt;a href="#fnref1" class="footnote-back"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn2"&gt;&lt;p&gt;It’s occasionally frustrating to find that there is &lt;em&gt;so&lt;/em&gt; much I’m unfamiliar with despite attempting to read broadly and, as best I can, deeply on subjects relevant to the things I’m talking about on Winning Slowly, in programming, etc. One of the great humility-drivers of the last few years is finding that, my best efforts to self-educate notwithstanding, I know &lt;em&gt;very little&lt;/em&gt; even in the fields I care most about.&lt;a href="#fnref2" class="footnote-back"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 19 May 2018 11:20:00 -0400</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2018-05-19:/2018/the-chinese-room-argument.html</guid><category>AI</category><category>ethics</category><category>philosophy</category></item><item><title>A Humanist Frame</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2018/a-humanist-frame.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;A few thoughts this morning on technologies, community, and the need for a positive (as well as a negative) vision of technology, cities, and indeed liberty—taking &lt;a href="https://tinyletter.com/lmsacasas/letters/the-convivial-society-no-4-community" title="No. 4: Community"&gt;the latest issue&lt;/a&gt; of Michael Sacasas’ newsletter &lt;a href="https://tinyletter.com/lmsacasas/archive"&gt;The Convivial Society&lt;/a&gt; as a jumping off point.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;aside&gt;
I don’t expect to link quite so often to the same writer, so don’t worry: this isn’t about to become a secondary feed for Sacasas’ writing. I do commend the newsletter, and especially this issue of it, to you. This essay, which I quote in brief, does something I hope to be able to do in a piece of writing someday: it &lt;em&gt;hangs together&lt;/em&gt; marvelously. There are standout paragraphs, but each one connects to those before and after it, and the essay is—in the best way—not excerpt-able. You should read the whole thing. If you have to choose, read that instead of this (seriously).
&lt;/aside&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Early in the newsletter, Sacasas offers this note on technological visionaries stretching back to the telegraph (at least):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It seems that none of these visionaries ever took into consideration the possibility that the moral frailties of human nature would only be amplified by their new technologies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He shortly thereafter suggests why that vision proved so alluring—the too-readily amplified frailties of human nature notwithstanding:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The rise of communication technologies from the mid-19th century through today has roughly coincided with the dissolution and degradation of the traditional communities, broken and often cruel though they may have been, that provided individuals with a relatively integrated experience of place and self. In 1953, the sociologist Robert Nisbett could write of the “quest for community” as the “dominant social tendency of the twentieth century.” Framing a new technology as a source of community, in other words, trades on an unfulfilled desire for community.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What strikes me as most interesting here is that Sacasas notes, even if only as an aside, one of the most important things that most critics of our current techno/cultural milieu seem entirely content to skip over: that the traditional communities &lt;em&gt;were&lt;/em&gt; “broken and often cruel.” One of the reasons that the social revolutions of the last 150 years have had such force is precisely this: that the traditional communities so casually valorized today (though not by Sacasas himself) may have helped people have “an integrated experience of place and self”—but that experience was, often as not, one of &lt;em&gt;abuse&lt;/em&gt;: of ethnic minorities, of women, of anyone outside the gentry…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sacasas’ description—“broken and often cruel”—is more right than is usually granted in these discussions. If we want to escape the shackles of atomistic individualism, we had best be thinking of something other than the glorious past, because the past was not glorious.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Third, and closely related to the above considerations: Sacasas closes the newsletter with a quote from Willa Cather’s &lt;em&gt;O Pioneers!&lt;/em&gt;, adding his own emphasis. I’ll reproduce the quotation in full here as he gave it (so: emphasis his) and then comment below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“You see,” he went on calmly, “measured by your standards here, I’m a failure. I couldn’t buy even one of your cornfields. I’ve enjoyed a great many things, but I’ve got nothing to show for it all.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“But you show for it yourself, Carl. I’d rather have had your freedom than my land.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Carl shook his head mournfully. “&lt;strong&gt;Freedom so often means that one isn’t needed anywhere.&lt;/strong&gt; Here you are an individual, you have a background of your own, you would be missed. But off there in the cities there are thousands of rolling stones like me. We are all alike; we have no ties, we know nobody, we own nothing. When one of us dies, they scarcely know where to bury him. Our landlady and the delicatessen man are our mourners, and we leave nothing behind us but a frock-coat and a fiddle, or an easel, or a typewriter, or whatever tool we got our living by. All we have ever managed to do is to pay our rent, the exorbitant rent that one has to pay for a few square feet of space near the heart of things. We have no house, no place, no people of our own. We live in the streets, in the parks, in the theaters. We sit in restaurants and concert halls and look about at the hundreds of our own kind and shudder.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alexandra was silent. She sat looking at the silver spot the moon made on the surface of the pond down in the pasture. He knew that she understood what he meant. At last she said slowly, “And yet I would rather have Emil grow up like that than like his two brothers. We pay a high rent, too, though we pay differently. We grow hard and heavy here. We don’t move lightly and easily as you do, and our minds get stiff. If the world were no wider than my cornfields, if there were not something beside this, I wouldn’t feel that it was much worth while to work. No, I would rather have Emil like you than like them. I felt that as soon as you came.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sacasas—with many others who are rightly critical of the social situation we have made for ourselves here in late modernity, including many of my friends over at &lt;a href="https://mereorthodoxy.com/book-review-liberalism-failed-patrick-deneen/" title="Example: Jake Meador&amp;#39;s sympathetic review of Deneen&amp;#39;s Why Liberalism Failed"&gt;Mere Orthodoxy&lt;/a&gt;—calls out the ways that our unrestrained freedom has come at a great cost to us. These critics are right to do so. But the bit that caught my attention as &lt;em&gt;equally&lt;/em&gt; worthy of notice in the section from Cather is Alexandra’s response (emphasis mine):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We pay a high rent, too, though we pay differently. We grow hard and heavy here. We don’t move lightly and easily as you do, and our minds get stiff. If the world were no wider than my cornfields, if there were not something beside this, I wouldn’t feel that it was much worth while to work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is something in this exchange of the tension between agrarianism and urbanism that seems to come up every time Wendell Berry is mentioned. It is true that cities (and late modernity!) often offer a kind of freedom that itself is slavery. But it is also true that the slavery of freedom is not the only kind of slavery.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It remains one of my chief concerns that few who &lt;em&gt;are&lt;/em&gt; taking seriously the problems we have made for ourselves in modernity seem interested in finding solutions that work &lt;em&gt;in cities&lt;/em&gt;. It is one thing to have a healthy suspicion of the kind of city-centrism and techno-centrism and indeed techno-fundamentalism that is largely the order of the day. It is something else entirely, however, to fail to imagine either city or technological milieu as &lt;em&gt;possibly good&lt;/em&gt;. (To be clear, this does not seem to be the tack that Sacasas is taking; and it is not so much that someone like my friend Jake Meador is &lt;em&gt;hostile&lt;/em&gt; to cities as that his own sympathies run more to rural life.) This is, I think, part of what &lt;a href="http://stephencarradini.com"&gt;Stephen Carradini&lt;/a&gt; has been getting at in his own more optimistic view in especially our &lt;a href="https://winningslowly.org/6.04/" title="6.04: Move Slowly and Fix Things"&gt;most recent Winning Slowly episode&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We must reject techno-utopianism; we must repent of our worship of technique. But we &lt;em&gt;must not&lt;/em&gt; make the usual conservative mistake and stop with the mere rejection of something bad. &lt;a href="http://bib.ly/luke11.24-26" title="Luke 11:24–26"&gt;That tends not to go so well.&lt;/a&gt; Instead, we need to consciously develop a frame that situates technology as properly subordinate to the humane, and which sets cities and farms and small towns and moon colonies not in opposition to each other but as complements.&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 01 May 2018 07:00:00 -0400</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2018-05-01:/2018/a-humanist-frame.html</guid><category>ethics</category><category>community</category></item><item><title>Stop Saying “What Capitalism Does”</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2018/stop-saying-what-capitalism-does.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;“What capitalism does,” or “what liberalism does,” or “what postmodernism does,” or “what fundamentalism does”: the phrase should die an unmourned death. It does us all a great disservice, not for what it says but for what it leaves unsaid and the ways it misleads us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I most recently ran into the &lt;em&gt;capitalism&lt;/em&gt; variant of the phrase in the influential 1995 essay “The Californian Ideology,” by Richard Barbrook and Andy Cameron. The text is littered with the phrase; if you took the essay at face value you would conclude that at least in the minds of Barbrook and Cameron capitalism had transformed from a system and structure into a demon, possessing and directing the culture they dislike.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am not opposed to &lt;a href="http://blogs.mereorthodoxy.com/matthewloftus/2017/04/27/new-gods-old-demons/" title="Matthew Loftus: “New Gods, Old Demons”"&gt;such readings of the world&lt;/a&gt; in principle; I think they may even &lt;a href="http://text-patterns.thenewatlantis.com/2017/04/principalities-powers-and-technical-boy.html" title="Alan Jacobs: “principalities, powers, and the technical boy”"&gt;get certain important things right&lt;/a&gt; that we too often overlook in our “disenchanted” modernity. If people want to talk of Capitalism and Marxism and Media and Liberalism and Technologism and The Beltway and The Kremlin and so on as capital-P Powers—if people want to think about the ways in which there may be real spiritual realities at work behind some of the things we take for granted—well, as the millennials say, &lt;em&gt;I am so here for that&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;a href="#fn1" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref1"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But that is not how Barbrook and Cameron meant it. Nor is it how most people mean the phrase when they toss it around.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What they mean, instead, is something like this: &lt;em&gt;People act differently in different systems and structures; the system and structure of capitalism [or liberalism or fundamentalism or…] leads people to act in [this way that I think is bad].&lt;/em&gt; It is, in other words, shorthand for an idea most of us can get behind.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That idea is important, too: people &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt; act differently in different systems and structures. What’s more, when a given structure is pervasive, it can be difficult to resist or reject, or even to consider that it should be resisted or rejected. This idea is so important that &lt;a href="http://stephencarradini.com"&gt;Stephen Carradini&lt;/a&gt; and I dedicated all of &lt;a href="https://www.winningslowly.org/season-5.html"&gt;Winning Slowly Season 5: Structure and Agency&lt;/a&gt; to the ins and outs of systems and structures, good and bad alike; the limits of individual action in the face of systemic pressure; and the ways we ought to leverage good systems and dismantle bad systems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But. As much as this shorthand captures something important, it also &lt;em&gt;obscures&lt;/em&gt; something important: it is &lt;em&gt;people&lt;/em&gt; who act differently under those different structures, and &lt;em&gt;people&lt;/em&gt; who set up systems in the first place and maintain them afterward. This is not to dismiss the tendency of systems to perpetuate themselves, or to ignore the reality of systems which harm everyone in them and go on existing anyway. (Self interest is complicated.) Rather, it is to remind us &lt;em&gt;how&lt;/em&gt; systems come to be (people created them because they seemed in some way good to them), &lt;em&gt;what&lt;/em&gt; they are made of (people continuing to do what seems in some way good to them), and &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt; they are hard to dismantle (because many people’s self-interest is aligned with maintaining existing institutions).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is possible to think and act as if individual agency is all that matters, and this is fallacious. People &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt; act differently in different systems and structures, for good and for ill. Capitalism, as a system and structure, serves as an environment in which enormous gains in productivity have been possible; but it also serves an environment where people reduce others (and themselves) to their productivity. “Liberalism,” as a system and structure, serves as an environment where many important gains in human liberties have grown up; but it also serves as an environment where the good of liberty has at times grown cancerous and indeed metastasized until the will of the individual is dangerously (and nonsensically) totalized. Contrast how people live and think and act in capitalist or liberal contexts with feudal or tribal contexts (to pick just two of the many contrasts we could) and you will see very, very different things. Systems matter; we cannot erase their impact on the individual.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But it is also possible to talk and act as if the structure, the system, is &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt;. This is the mistake the shorthand “what capitalism does” leads us to. Flip the emphasis in the previous paragraph: the environments of capitalism and liberalism matter, but &lt;em&gt;people&lt;/em&gt; continue to act in those environments. More than that, people continue to transform the structures and systems they inhabit, often in startling ways. Half a century ago, it would have been laughable to suggest that &lt;a href="https://www.apple.com" title="Apple"&gt;the most profitable corporation in the world&lt;/a&gt; would also be among those most assiduously pursuing environmental responsibility and stewardship. People’s continuous pressure, as well as the ascent to not only economic but also cultural leadership of people who care about this has changed capitalism in a good way. Social pressure on businesses has plenty of downsides, too, in our internet-rage-storm era; and there is much to critique about the ways that business leaders have come to dominate culture.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The point, though, is that systems and structures are more malleable than the shorthand credits them, and so we would do well to remember the limitations of the shorthand and indeed largely to abandon it unless we are often in the habit of qualifying it. It is too sloppy. Throw it out!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Or if not that (shorthands &lt;em&gt;are&lt;/em&gt; useful after all) then clarify often. Talk instead about structures, and systems, and people’s ability to change them—indeed to throw them out. Speak less often of “what capitalism does” and more often of what capitalism makes easy and what it makes hard, what avenues living in liberalism opens up and what it blinds us to, what virtues and what vices fundamentalism might inculcate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(And if you want to have a conversation about Powers, have at it.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section class="footnotes"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn1"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Yes, I am a millennial by age cohort. I mock these generational divides and characterizations because I think them mostly meaningless blather.&lt;a href="#fnref1" class="footnote-back"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 09 Mar 2018 07:00:00 -0500</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2018-03-09:/2018/stop-saying-what-capitalism-does.html</guid><category>ethics</category><category>technology</category></item><item><title>A Forgotten Blog Post Idea</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2018/a-forgotten-blog-post-idea.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;One of the most frustrating things as a writer is when you have a good idea and then &lt;em&gt;forget it&lt;/em&gt;. I had a thought this morning, and it was solid. But I was not in a spot where I could write it down (whether in a notebook or in &lt;a href="http://www.bear-writer.com"&gt;Bear&lt;/a&gt;). The frustration I feel at this is hard to express, but here I am trying.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is such a frustrating experience that I &lt;em&gt;keenly&lt;/em&gt; remember the experience happening to me once before—back in 2016, for a post I have not yet finished writing because I continually find it &lt;em&gt;beyond&lt;/em&gt; me. And since I cannot remember today’s good idea, and haven’t finished the last good idea, I’ll just share the notes I wrote down back in March 2016 about that idea in hopes that either I will actually run with them sooner rather than later, or that the act of putting it out there in this brief form will be enough to allow me to let it go:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;American conservatives point to previous eras as if our nation were less sinful, less blemished then. It was not. It was wretched in different ways—but no less wicked than now. Centuries of slavery, and of Jim Crow, &lt;em&gt;are not lesser sins than today’s sexual ills.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Conservatives have too often elided these essential questions: Whose “better” past? And in what sense “better”? It may have been less sexually perverse, but how is that “better” when it entailed at the same time massive oppression of whole groups of people—especially because that oppression was so often at the hands of people claiming the name of Christ?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is a great deal to unpack there, and I continue to find it more than I am really &lt;em&gt;able&lt;/em&gt; to unpack.&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 25 Feb 2018 16:00:00 -0500</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2018-02-25:/2018/a-forgotten-blog-post-idea.html</guid><category>writing</category><category>ethics</category><category>politics</category></item><item><title>A Strange Little Thought</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2018/a-strange-little-thought.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;I was, for some reason, thinking about the movie &lt;em&gt;Groundhog Day&lt;/em&gt; this morning, and thinking about what it would be like to be caught in a temporal loop of that sort. Plenty of interesting things have been said about the movie (which is &lt;em&gt;very&lt;/em&gt; good), but one I’ve not considered before is the extent to which the day Bill Murray’s character lives (and lives and lives and lives) is a product of choices he made the day before.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The loudest (though least important) of these earlier choices in the film is the alarm clock which wakes Murray’s character every day. He starts the day on the same radio station to the same vapid announcements because of choices he is powerless to affect in any way throughout the film: whatever he had done the night before.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The quieter (but much more important) versions of that are that the people in the town are who they are, and Murray’s own character is who and what he is, because of choices now out of all of their hands. The past is fixed to us, and in very real ways, we are who we are and live the lives we live now because of things we have already done (and things others have already done) and which we cannot change. That goes for it all: good, bad, and indifferent. And so the other side of the coin is that the choices we make &lt;em&gt;today&lt;/em&gt; similarly mark our courses for the future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nothing particularly profound or novel in any of that, of course. It was just something that was made a bit more striking in thinking about the predicament of a man caught in a time loop, living the exact same day over and over and therefore more particularly confronted with the choices that had led him to that specific day. &lt;em&gt;What&lt;/em&gt;, I wonder, &lt;em&gt;would I think of yesterday’s choices if I had to live today over and over again?&lt;/em&gt; And likewise: &lt;em&gt;What of tomorrow and the choices I make today?&lt;/em&gt;—even just at that simplest level of setting an alarm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just a strange little thought to start the day.&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 23 Feb 2018 07:15:00 -0500</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2018-02-23:/2018/a-strange-little-thought.html</guid><category>ethics</category><category>film</category></item><item><title>Against Doing What Comes Naturally.</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2018/against-doing-what-comes-naturally.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Twice, recently, I have found myself needing to start over—essentially from scratch—on something I had written. One was a tech talk for work, another my &lt;a href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2017/2017-in-review-my-goals.html" title="2017 In Review: My Goals"&gt;promised&lt;/a&gt; post on how we chose a new church after we moved across the country.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Both pieces suffered from an overabundance of combativeness. Or: I was kind of a jerk in the first drafts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thinking about them this morning, I noted that in both cases my tendency was to write in a posture that mixed defensiveness with hostility to an existing structure. In both cases, that hostility might actually be well-deserved—but there are times and places for everything, including polemic, and the more I (separately) chewed on both of these pieces, the more I realized that I didn’t want to have an argument. In these cases, at least, I don’t want to &lt;em&gt;punch&lt;/em&gt; the views I disagree with, so much as gently nudge them out of the way while showing a more excellent way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This runs up against one of my deepest-seated tendencies. I am passionate about teaching, about showing a better way, about correcting and fixing ills in the world. I also find a good argument wonderfully sharpening to the way I think—tracing out differences, finding the weaknesses in my own views and either tightening them up or abandoning them as appropriate, understanding other views more clearly… Those are good passions in many ways, but like all good passions they can go awry very easily. In my case, they can lead me to treat &lt;em&gt;everything&lt;/em&gt; like an argument, and to go after everything that seems amiss to me with the same kind of knock-it-down-with-a-battering-ram approach.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the last fifteen years, I have been learning &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; to verbally hammer at problems (whether in person or in writing). I have slowly learned to listen carefully and try to understand why someone holds the view they do, even when I still think their view is wrong. I have seen firsthand that people’s surface statements and their deepest-held beliefs alike often derive from experiences that are &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; obvious on the surface. Their struggles are not necessarily apparent. Their histories certainly are not.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have also slowly learned that a nudge here and a nudge there can often be both more effective and—more importantly—&lt;em&gt;kinder&lt;/em&gt; than trying to shove people where I think they ought to be. Even when I’m right about where they ought to be! And my judgments of such things, I have also too-slowly learned, are far less than perfect—which should temper the vigor with which I sally forth to do battle for those judgments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Make no mistake: there are times for rebuke. There are times to say, “This view you hold [about software development, or Christianity, or financial practices, or whatever else]? It’s &lt;em&gt;dead wrong&lt;/em&gt;.” But not all the time. Even though it’s what’s “natural” for me, even though it’s what feels right sometimes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sometimes, we have to fight our strongest instincts. No matter how natural something feels, it can be &lt;em&gt;wrong&lt;/em&gt;. That is certainly so for me when I get combative about something I’m passionate about. It’s the right response… &lt;em&gt;occasionally&lt;/em&gt;. Nearly all of the time, I need to be quieter, gentler, more patient, more understanding, and less interested in winning a fight.&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 22 Feb 2018 07:00:00 -0500</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2018-02-22:/2018/against-doing-what-comes-naturally.html</guid><category>ethics</category><category>writing</category></item><item><title>Good Work Takes Time</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2018/good-work-takes-time.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;It’s obvious enough when you say it aloud, of course, but it bears reiterating, and often: &lt;em&gt;Good work takes time, and most of the time and effort behind good projects remains forever invisible.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the things I did in 2017 that I’m most proud of (and which I get &lt;em&gt;enormous&lt;/em&gt; utility from every day at work) is building &lt;a href="https://github.com/chriskrycho/true-myth"&gt;True Myth&lt;/a&gt;, a library implementing &lt;code&gt;Maybe&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;Result&lt;/code&gt; types in TypeScript.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;aside&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note: if you’re about to tune out because this sounds technical, don’t. You can understand everything important in this post without understanding a thing about TypeScript or these particular types.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/aside&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There’s nothing &lt;em&gt;particularly&lt;/em&gt; special about that library compared to any of the others in the space which already do the same thing. It makes its own &lt;a href="https://github.com/chriskrycho/true-myth/blob/master/README.md#why-not" title="Comparisons with Folktale and Sanctuary"&gt;design tradeoffs&lt;/a&gt;, which are slightly &lt;em&gt;different&lt;/em&gt; from others, and it has what I think are &lt;a href="https://true-myth.js.org"&gt;best-in-class docs&lt;/a&gt;, but mostly it’s comparable to the others. Still, it’s &lt;em&gt;good&lt;/em&gt;, and it fits that particular niche in terms of design tradeoffs pretty well in my view.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you just saw the public work on that, you’d have first heard of it &lt;em&gt;at the earliest&lt;/em&gt; when I pushed the first commit to GitHub on September 21, 2017. But the roots go much, much further back.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For one thing, I just found a related bit of work dating all the way back to January 10, 2017: an early attempt to see if I could directly reimplement Rust’s Result and Option types in TypeScript, in the early days of my adoption of TypeScript.&lt;a href="#fn1" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref1"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; That initial spike didn’t work—and I mean that literally; I didn’t yet have enough of a handle on TypeScript’s type system to get it to actually compile! But it was the first of &lt;em&gt;multiple&lt;/em&gt; (mostly very brief) swings I took at it over the course of the year. The culmination of those repeated stabs at the problem was True Myth, with its polish, test coverage, and very considered design tradeoffs.&lt;a href="#fn2" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref2"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; But none of that would have happened without the better part of a year of experimenting along the way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What’s more: even that January spike wasn’t the real start of True Myth. I have code in our codebase (code we’re finally mostly done replacing with True Myth!) that was an early attempt to capture these same basic ideas in plain-old JavaScript—code that dates to March 2016!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So: do not be discouraged when your own work seems to take a long time, or when you see others produce what seem to be fully-formed projects all in a rush. Always, our best work stands on a foundation—of ideas simmering over time, of previous attempts that got partway, of previous outright &lt;em&gt;failures&lt;/em&gt;—and all of that is “underground,” out of sight.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section class="footnotes"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn1"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Somewhat amusingly to me in retrospect, I’d switched from Flow to TypeScript on our codebase at Olo as my final act of 2016.&lt;a href="#fnref1" class="footnote-back"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn2"&gt;&lt;p&gt;I remain convinced that we hit a &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; sweet spot with the design here: it works well as idiomatic JavaScript &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; supports nice functional idioms and I think it just feels nice to use &lt;em&gt;in JavaScript&lt;/em&gt;—not just as a port of ideas from Haskell, Scala, etc.&lt;a href="#fnref2" class="footnote-back"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 17 Feb 2018 18:00:00 -0500</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2018-02-17:/2018/good-work-takes-time.html</guid><category>software development</category><category>writing</category><category>ethics</category></item><item><title>A Meander</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2018/a-meander.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;This is a meander. I have a bunch of mostly-unformed thoughts, and I want to write, and the two come out here, together, in the next few minutes before I start my workday proper (because I stayed up late last night working on open source software and got up late accordingly, and so have a great deal less of &lt;a href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2017/knowing-your-rhythms.html" title="“Knowing Your Rhythms”"&gt;my normally-allocated writing time&lt;/a&gt; available today).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;section id="section" class="level2"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;1.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Open-source software is a very strange place, and the dynamics of it favor those of us who already have well-paying jobs and lots of flexibility in our schedule.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This isn’t &lt;em&gt;necessarily&lt;/em&gt; a bad thing. It means that anyone who wants to use open-source contribution as a gauge of someone’s fitness to work is making a pretty foolish decision, though: they’re inherently cutting off a whole sector—dare I say it, a whole &lt;em&gt;class&lt;/em&gt;—of people who simply do not (and, barring being given a pretty surprising break, will never) have that kind of stability and flexibility.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="section-1" class="level2"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;2.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Twitter is really, &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; bad for meaningful discussion. I follow both &lt;a href="https://mobile.twitter.com/noahpinion"&gt;Noah Smith (@noahpinion)&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://mobile.twitter.com/lymanstoneky"&gt;Lyman Stone (@lymanstoneky)&lt;/a&gt;, and they’re both extremely interesting follows, and they’re both clearly &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; smart and &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; well-informed, and in their off-Twitter writing they both do a good job of fairly representing others’ views and interacting with them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Twitter, their arguments are a disaster.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is not specific to Smith and Stone. This is Twitter in one pair of interlocutors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Seriously: stop tweeting and start blogging again, if you have an &lt;em&gt;argument&lt;/em&gt; to make rather than just a pithy, one-off observation or a link to share.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="section-2" class="level2"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;3.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can get a surprising amount of writing done in 5 minutes, if you’re willing to just word-vomit. (This whole post, start to finish, took me 12 minutes.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="section-3" class="level2"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;4.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I need to read more poetry; more rich, good fiction; more rich, good nonfiction. I’ve read a lot of nonfiction in the last five years, but I wouldn’t call most of it &lt;em&gt;rich&lt;/em&gt;. Most of it—most of my seminary reading, that is—was &lt;em&gt;just okay&lt;/em&gt;; very little of it engaged deeply with thought critical of its own perspective. (Major exceptions: David Koyzis’ really excellent &lt;em&gt;Political Visions and Illusions&lt;/em&gt;, Alvin Plantinga’s &lt;em&gt;Where the Conflict Really Lies&lt;/em&gt;, and of course St. Athanasius’ &lt;em&gt;On the Incarnation&lt;/em&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But I find that my own writing is far sharper, clearer, and better when I’m drawing &lt;em&gt;widely&lt;/em&gt; and from &lt;em&gt;deep wells&lt;/em&gt;. Widely, because I find that too much time in the same spot overly narrows my focus, whether that is apologetics or programming languages. From deep wells because, frankly, there is too much out there which warrants nothing more than a skim &lt;em&gt;at most&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And that is all!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 09 Feb 2018 07:00:00 -0500</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2018-02-09:/2018/a-meander.html</guid><category>writing</category><category>open-source software</category><category>ethics</category><category>reading</category><category>literature</category></item><item><title>Prayer Apps and Evaluating Technology</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2018/prayer-apps-and-evaluating-technology.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;I use technology a &lt;em&gt;lot&lt;/em&gt; to get after the goals I care about in my life. But over the last few years I’ve been thinking about, and I’m increasingly concerned about, the ways that we are shaped by our use of technology. We could generalize this discussion to all sorts of things, and I’m sure I will (though I’m also pretty sure you’d just be better off reading &lt;a href="https://thefrailestthing.com" title="The Frailest Thing"&gt;L. M. Sacasas&lt;/a&gt;, whom I’ve linked in this connection before). But for today, I want to just zoom in and think about this question specifically in the context of technologies we employ in the context of the Christian faith. (If you’re not a Christian, I suspect much of what I have to say here will still ring true, so don’t run off just yet.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ve been using apps to manage my list of tasks to get through for a long time: first &lt;a href="https://todoist.com"&gt;Todoist&lt;/a&gt;, then &lt;a href="https://www.omnigroup.com/omnifocus"&gt;OmniFocus&lt;/a&gt;, and now &lt;a href="https://culturedcode.com/things/"&gt;Things&lt;/a&gt;. So as I’ve been wanting to develop more rigor around my prayer life, and in particular to make sure I pray for certain people and the &lt;em&gt;very&lt;/em&gt; difficult circumstances they’re currently facing, it was natural to go looking for an app to manage that. And although “There’s an app for that” is no longer an Apple marketing campaign, is truer than ever it was when it &lt;em&gt;was&lt;/em&gt; an Apple marketing campaign. So there are a lot of prayer apps on the App Store.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I snagged an app both my wife and another woman I really respect have found helpful as a tool for &lt;em&gt;their&lt;/em&gt; prayer lives. And it’s been sitting there unused for a month. I launched the app once. I’ve had an item in Things for that whole time to populate it. But I haven’t.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The whole time the app has been sitting there on my homescreen, I’ve been stuck on this question: &lt;em&gt;How does this tool form me?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And this is the broader question that’s nagged at me for quite some time. How are we shaped and formed by our use of, and indeed our &lt;em&gt;dependence on&lt;/em&gt;, the tools we employ to remember things, to form habits, etc.? What happens if the tool goes away? Nick Carr has written fairly extensively&lt;a href="#fn1" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref1"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; about the effects on concentration and memory; but those merely point to a broader concern: what kind of people do we wish to form ourselves to be? And are our tools helping or hurting us in that aim? For our tools &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt; form us, no less than we form them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s not really about this (or any particular) prayer app. And I certainly don’t think it’s &lt;em&gt;inherently wrong&lt;/em&gt; to use a prayer app, or anything of the sort. But it nags at me. Will I truly learn to be disciplined about prayer, or will I simply learn to be further hooked on alerts from my pocket supercomputer? If I end up praying faithfully for people, but also end up more distracted, more reliant on this little slab of metal and glass, less engaged with my family, what is the net on that? It is, at a minimum, not a clear &lt;em&gt;win&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, none of these concerns are specific to prayer apps. I have been using a digital Bible for most of a decade now. I use a pomodoro timer to help my maintain my discipline and concentration throughout my work. I use &lt;a href="http://www.bear-writer.com"&gt;Bear&lt;/a&gt; for keeping a log of what I’ve done for work every day,&lt;a href="#fn2" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref2"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and for jotting down writing ideas. This very post started out that way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src="http://cdn.chriskrycho.com/images/bear-blog-idea.png" title="Bear app" alt="The note in Bear that was the germination of this blog post" /&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;The note in Bear that was the germination of this blog post&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using a digital notes app is not the same as disciplining myself to remember things. But the same concerns apply, of course, to &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; aids we employ. Using a digital notes app is not identical to using a physical notebook as a place for jotting down ideas—but they’re more similar to each other than they are to &lt;em&gt;not using a tool at all&lt;/em&gt;. Both have a cost in effective, &lt;em&gt;active&lt;/em&gt; memory of those ideas. On the other hand, they also have the benefit of helping us remember more ideas, and more clearly, than we would otherwise, and also of freeing us to think on and remember &lt;em&gt;other&lt;/em&gt; things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This also points to another of the fundamental challenges in evaluating the tools we use. We’re accustomed to thinking of many things—these days, mostly computers and computerized things—as technological and other things as sort of “natural” and “untechnological.” But of course, literally everything we do is unnatural and technological in many ways—too many to count; but for a start consider that clothing is not &lt;em&gt;natural&lt;/em&gt;; it is a technology! So are books. So are forks and cups and plates. So are journals, and pencils, and pens. And those technologies all shape and form us, too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Scribbling notes in a paper journal day after day will change your body and your mind; you will have calluses from holding the pen, and will know that your ideas are found in that journal. The loss of a journal filled with sketches of ideas might become a horrifying thought, because in writing down one’s ideas, one intentionally lets the paper do the work that one’s memory might have done otherwise. &lt;em&gt;Many&lt;/em&gt; of those things—though by no means all—are just the same whether using a digital journal or a paper one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At least in my own experience, some of the important differences include the way it feels mentally to think with a pen vs. to think with a keyboard. (I use the phrase “think with” here to emphasize what it is we’re doing either way: using the tool to help us think as well as to remember.) That difference is, so far as I can tell in considering my own thinking, not just one of &lt;em&gt;feel&lt;/em&gt;, either: I write different things, in different ways, with pen and paper than I do with a keyboard. I’m a much better poet with pen and paper, for example.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But those differences do not void the core they share: they are memory-replacements.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not for nothing have people worried about the effects of new technologies on memory for millennia. And it is worth note: those who thought the advent of each kind of new information technology would come with costs were not wrong. Literate cultures seem inevitably to lose the power of oral recall. Members of illiterate cultures can often accomplish feats of memory that astound members of literate cultures, because they do not have books to offload their stories and histories to. The only way to keep them—and we value stories, so we &lt;em&gt;always&lt;/em&gt; find a way to keep them—is to commit them to memory, and deeply. The tradeoff with books is real. The tradeoff with a physical journal is real. The tradeoff with the internet is real.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The question is not &lt;em&gt;whether&lt;/em&gt; but &lt;em&gt;how&lt;/em&gt; we will be formed by the technologies we employ—at least, unless you plan to go back to living naked, surviving off of whatever you can manage to collect with your bare hands and eat raw (fire, too, is technology, after all).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To narrow it further: the question is which specific shapings we find needful in our specific contexts. Perhaps, if there is a problem, it is not with a prayer app individually, or a todo app individually, or a notes app individually, but with offloading &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; of our mental tasks to a smartphone. No harm done in using a prayer app; but maybe write your to-do list on paper; and perhaps find something, anything at all, to simply &lt;em&gt;remember&lt;/em&gt; to do every day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section class="footnotes"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn1"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.roughtype.com/?p=8248"&gt;Here&lt;/a&gt;, on the smartphone, is just one of many times and places; his book &lt;em&gt;The Shallows&lt;/em&gt; is perhaps the best-known and longest treatment of it.&lt;a href="#fnref1" class="footnote-back"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn2"&gt;&lt;p&gt;For my own purposes; Olo doesn’t ask anything of the sort from me; but it helps me see what I actually get done over the course of a year, and that’s pretty neat.&lt;a href="#fnref2" class="footnote-back"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 26 Jan 2018 07:30:00 -0500</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2018-01-26:/2018/prayer-apps-and-evaluating-technology.html</guid><category>writing</category><category>ethics</category></item><item><title>Vexing Ironies</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2017/vexing-ironies.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;One of the most vexing problems in thinking and responding well to problems of ethics in &lt;em&gt;information technology&lt;/em&gt; specifically is the way that so much of thinking and responding about information technology takes place within the context of, well, information technology. Two examples of that challenge caught my attention this evening, ironies I noticed in reading the very same article.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a href="http://www.roughtype.com/?p=8248"&gt;“How smartphones hijack our minds”&lt;/a&gt;, Nick Carr explores much of the evidence for ways that use of smartphones can have seriously negative effects on our thinking in ways that are both pernicious (because we usually do not notice them consciously) and pervasive (in that they happen simply by dint of the &lt;em&gt;presence&lt;/em&gt; of the devices). It’s a good article, and I commend it you as a helpful summary of a lot of the most current research on attention, smartphones, and the like; you should read it and think about how you use your phone.&lt;a href="#fn1" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref1"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the first irony was that I read that article… on my smartphone. As indeed I read &lt;em&gt;many&lt;/em&gt; of Nick Carr’s articles. There’s something more than a little odd about considering the use of a smartphone by way of reading an article on a smartphone. But in a very real sense, there’s almost no way I &lt;em&gt;could&lt;/em&gt; have read Carr’s article otherwise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And accordingly, the second irony is that, although Carr, who has staked out a position as a popular-level writer tackling issues of how modern information technology affects us, &lt;a href="https://t.alibris.com/The-Shallows-What-the-Internet-Is-Doing-to-Our-Brains-Nicholas-Carr/book/11882057" title="The Shallows"&gt;certainly &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; published in hard copy&lt;/a&gt;, everything of his I’ve ever read has been in digital form. Indeed, although his books are important in their own ways, I think it’s fair to say that &lt;em&gt;most&lt;/em&gt; people’s interaction with his ideas, including his critiques of the ways we use and indeed rely on the internet, have all happened via and only because of the internet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m not entirely sure what to make of these observations. I don’t fault Carr for publishing a blog, exactly; and though I am increasingly chastened about my own at-times-unwise use of a smartphone, I don’t fault myself for having an RSS reader there. (Better than that a Twitter app, to be sure!) But there is something at a minimum &lt;em&gt;odd&lt;/em&gt; and perhaps even something &lt;em&gt;off&lt;/em&gt; about the ways that we tend to use the very tools we are critiquing as the medium for advancing our critiques. We implicate ourselves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But what is the alternative? On the one hand Carr’s message—which is important!—has likely been heard and even internalized by a far broader audience because he has transmitted it digitally than it would have been had he conscientiously limited it to books (and perhaps print media articles). The efficacy of the medium for distribution is the internet’s greatest strength. Likewise, I would never have run into Carr’s writing in the first place apart from articles in my RSS feed which linked it; and I do a great deal of my RSS feed reading on my iPhone and iPad, both of which are much better &lt;em&gt;reading&lt;/em&gt; environments than a laptop or a desktop computer. Indeed, much of what I find most helpful in my reading on technology and ethics I find my way to via articles in my RSS feed, and I often items for reading later by simply tapping a an interesting-looking link in an article I’m reading in that RSS feed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What do we make of this tension, these ironies? Especially when our concerns begin to rise to the level not merely of prudential judgments (though that level alone is perhaps sufficient reason to do more than we let ourselves) but deep ethical worries—do we abandon the smartphone altogether, cease blogging for fear of how it only contributes to the Google-ified and Facebook-ified age we live in?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don’t know.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section class="footnotes"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn1"&gt;&lt;p&gt;One of my concerns in my &lt;a href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2017/why-do-i-need-a-research-tool.html"&gt;ongoing project&lt;/a&gt; is to prompt people around me—friends and family, but perhaps also blog readers!—to consider how our use of technology &lt;em&gt;forms&lt;/em&gt; us. More on that in a future post.&lt;a href="#fnref1" class="footnote-back"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 17 Dec 2017 20:50:00 -0500</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2017-12-17:/2017/vexing-ironies.html</guid><category>ethics</category></item><item><title>Dear Tech CEOs: Yes, That Is Your Culture.</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2017/dear-tech-ceos-yes-that-is-your-culture.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;It is common, when stories break about horrible company cultures in —as &lt;a href="https://www.susanjfowler.com/blog/2017/2/19/reflecting-on-one-very-strange-year-at-uber"&gt;one did this week about Uber&lt;/a&gt;, and as &lt;a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2015/08/16/technology/inside-amazon-wrestling-big-ideas-in-a-bruising-workplace.html?_r=1"&gt;one did last year about Amazon&lt;/a&gt;—for the &lt;abbr&gt;CEO&lt;/abbr&gt;s to say things like:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What she describes is abhorrent and against everything Uber stands for and believes in. (Uber &lt;abbr&gt;CEO&lt;/abbr&gt; Travis Kalanick’s statement quoted at &lt;a href="http://www.recode.net/2017/2/19/14665076/ubers-travis-kalanick-susan-fowler-sexual-harassment-investigation"&gt;Recode&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Or:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The article doesn’t describe the Amazon I know or the caring Amazonians I work with every day. (Amazon &lt;abbr&gt;CEO&lt;/abbr&gt; Jeff Bezos’ statement quoted at &lt;a href="http://www.geekwire.com/2015/full-memo-jeff-bezos-responds-to-cutting-nyt-expose-says-tolerance-for-lack-of-empathy-needs-to-be-zero/"&gt;Geekwire&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The problem with this is simple. You can say all day that these events don’t represent your culture. But they &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt;. And if you’re not aware of it, that means you have two problems: the culture problem, and the fact that you’re so out of touch with what your company is actually like that you don’t know it has that culture problem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And you have one other, even bigger problem. If that’s the culture of the company you’ve built, it’s &lt;em&gt;your fault&lt;/em&gt;. You can’t foist it off on your underlings: you hired them. You can’t foist it off on the bureaucracy: you built it. You can’t foist it off on wrong priorities: you set those priorities. It’s on you.&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 21 Feb 2017 17:00:00 -0500</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2017-02-21:/2017/dear-tech-ceos-yes-that-is-your-culture.html</guid><category>ethics</category></item></channel></rss>