<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Chris Krycho - ethics</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/</link><description></description><lastBuildDate>Fri, 09 Feb 2018 07:00:00 -0500</lastBuildDate><item><title>A Meander</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2018/a-meander.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;This is a meander. I have a bunch of mostly-unformed thoughts, and I want to write, and the two come out here, together, in the next few minutes before I start my workday proper (because I stayed up late last night working on open source software and got up late accordingly, and so have a great deal less of &lt;a href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2017/knowing-your-rhythms.html" title="“Knowing Your Rhythms”"&gt;my normally-allocated writing time&lt;/a&gt; available today).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;*** &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section id="section" class="level2"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;1.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Open-source software is a very strange place, and the dynamics of it favor those of us who already have well-paying jobs and lots of flexibility in our schedule.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This isn’t &lt;em&gt;necessarily&lt;/em&gt; a bad thing. It means that anyone who wants to use open-source contribution as a gauge of someone’s fitness to work is making a pretty foolish decision, though: they’re inherently cutting off a whole sector—dare I say it, a whole &lt;em&gt;class&lt;/em&gt;—of people who simply do not (and, barring being given a pretty surprising break, will never) have that kind of stability and flexibility.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="section-1" class="level2"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;2.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Twitter is really, &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; bad for meaningful discussion. I follow both &lt;a href="https://mobile.twitter.com/noahpinion"&gt;Noah Smith (@noahpinion)&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://mobile.twitter.com/lymanstoneky"&gt;Lyman Stone (@lymanstoneky)&lt;/a&gt;, and they’re both extremely interesting follows, and they’re both clearly &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; smart and &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; well-informed, and in their off-Twitter writing they both do a good job of fairly representing others’ views and interacting with them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Twitter, their arguments are a disaster.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is not specific to Smith and Stone. This is Twitter in one pair of interlocutors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Seriously: stop tweeting and start blogging again, if you have an &lt;em&gt;argument&lt;/em&gt; to make rather than just a pithy, one-off observation or a link to share.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="section-2" class="level2"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;3.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can get a surprising amount of writing done in 5 minutes, if you’re willing to just word-vomit. (This whole post, start to finish, took me 12 minutes.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="section-3" class="level2"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;4.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I need to read more poetry; more rich, good fiction; more rich, good nonfiction. I’ve read a lot of nonfiction in the last five years, but I wouldn’t call most of it &lt;em&gt;rich&lt;/em&gt;. Most of it—most of my seminary reading, that is—was &lt;em&gt;just okay&lt;/em&gt;; very little of it engaged deeply with thought critical of its own perspective. (Major exceptions: David Koyzis’ really excellent_Political Visions and Illusions_, Alvin Plantinga’s_Where the Conflict Really Lies_, and of course St. Athanasius’ &lt;em&gt;On the Incarnation&lt;/em&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But I find that my own writing is far sharper, clearer, and better when I’m drawing &lt;em&gt;widely&lt;/em&gt; and from &lt;em&gt;deep wells&lt;/em&gt;. Widely, because I find that too much time in the same spot overly narrows my focus, whether that is apologetics or programming languages. From deep wells because, frankly, there is too much out there which warrants nothing more than a skim &lt;em&gt;at most&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And that is all!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 09 Feb 2018 07:00:00 -0500</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2018-02-09:/2018/a-meander.html</guid><category>writing</category><category>open-source software</category><category>ethics</category><category>reading</category><category>literature</category></item><item><title>Prayer Apps and Evaluating Technology</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2018/prayer-apps-and-evaluating-technology.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;I use technology a &lt;em&gt;lot&lt;/em&gt; to get after the goals I care about in my life. But over the last few years I’ve been thinking about, and I’m increasingly concerned about, the ways that we are shaped by our use of technology. We could generalize this discussion to all sorts of things, and I’m sure I will (though I’m also pretty sure you’d just be better off reading &lt;a href="https://thefrailestthing.com" title="The Frailest Thing"&gt;L. M. Sacasas&lt;/a&gt;, whom I’ve linked in this connection before). But for today, I want to just zoom in and think about this question specifically in the context of technologies we employ in the context of the Christian faith. (If you’re not a Christian, I suspect much of what I have to say here will still ring true, so don’t run off just yet.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ve been using apps to manage my list of tasks to get through for a long time: first &lt;a href="https://todoist.com"&gt;Todoist&lt;/a&gt;, then &lt;a href="https://www.omnigroup.com/omnifocus"&gt;OmniFocus&lt;/a&gt;, and now &lt;a href="https://culturedcode.com/things/"&gt;Things&lt;/a&gt;. So as I’ve been wanting to develop more rigor around my prayer life, and in particular to make sure I pray for certain people and the &lt;em&gt;very&lt;/em&gt; difficult circumstances they’re currently facing, it was natural to go looking for an app to manage that. And although “There’s an app for that” is no longer an Apple marketing campaign, is truer than ever it was when it &lt;em&gt;was&lt;/em&gt; an Apple marketing campaign. So there are a lot of prayer apps on the App Store.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I snagged an app both my wife and another woman I really respect have found helpful as a tool for &lt;em&gt;their&lt;/em&gt; prayer lives. And it’s been sitting there unused for a month. I launched the app once. I’ve had an item in Things for that whole time to populate it. But I haven’t.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The whole time the app has been sitting there on my homescreen, I’ve been stuck on this question: &lt;em&gt;How does this tool form me?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And this is the broader question that’s nagged at me for quite some time. How are we shaped and formed by our use of, and indeed our &lt;em&gt;dependence on&lt;/em&gt;, the tools we employ to remember things, to form habits, etc.? What happens if the tool goes away? Nick Carr has written fairly extensively&lt;a href="#fn1" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref1"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; about the effects on concentration and memory; but those merely point to a broader concern: what kind of people do we wish to form ourselves to be? And are our tools helping or hurting us in that aim? For our tools &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt; form us, no less than we form them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s not really about this (or any particular) prayer app. And I certainly don’t think it’s &lt;em&gt;inherently wrong&lt;/em&gt; to use a prayer app, or anything of the sort. But it nags at me. Will I truly learn to be disciplined about prayer, or will I simply learn to be further hooked on alerts from my pocket supercomputer? If I end up praying faithfully for people, but also end up more distracted, more reliant on this little slab of metal and glass, less engaged with my family, what is the net on that? It is, at a minimum, not a clear &lt;em&gt;win&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, none of these concerns are specific to prayer apps. I have been using a digital Bible for most of a decade now. I use a pomodoro timer to help my maintain my discipline and concentration throughout my work. I use &lt;a href="http://www.bear-writer.com"&gt;Bear&lt;/a&gt; for keeping a log of what I’ve done for work every day,&lt;a href="#fn2" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref2"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and for jotting down writing ideas. This very post started out that way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src="http://cdn.chriskrycho.com/images/bear-blog-idea.png" title="Bear app" alt="The note in Bear that was the germination of this blog post" /&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;The note in Bear that was the germination of this blog post&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using a digital notes app is not the same as disciplining myself to remember things. But the same concerns apply, of course, to &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; aids we employ. Using a digital notes app is not identical to using a physical notebook as a place for jotting down ideas—but they’re more similar to each other than they are to &lt;em&gt;not using a tool at all&lt;/em&gt;. Both have a cost in effective, &lt;em&gt;active&lt;/em&gt; memory of those ideas. On the other hand, they also have the benefit of helping us remember more ideas, and more clearly, than we would otherwise, and also of freeing us to think on and remember &lt;em&gt;other&lt;/em&gt; things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This also points to another of the fundamental challenges in evaluating the tools we use. We’re accustomed to thinking of many things—these days, mostly computers and computerized things—as technological and other things as sort of “natural” and “untechnological.” But of course, literally everything we do is unnatural and technological in many ways—too many to count; but for a start consider that clothing is not &lt;em&gt;natural&lt;/em&gt;; it is a technology! So are books. So are forks and cups and plates. So are journals, and pencils, and pens. And those technologies all shape and form us, too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Scribbling notes in a paper journal day after day will change your body and your mind; you will have calluses from holding the pen, and will know that your ideas are found in that journal. The loss of a journal filled with sketches of ideas might become a horrifying thought, because in writing down one’s ideas, one intentionally lets the paper do the work that one’s memory might have done otherwise. &lt;em&gt;Many&lt;/em&gt; of those things—though by no means all—are just the same whether using a digital journal or a paper one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At least in my own experience, some of the important differences include the way it feels mentally to think with a pen vs. to think with a keyboard. (I use the phrase “think with” here to emphasize what it is we’re doing either way: using the tool to help us think as well as to remember.) That difference is, so far as I can tell in considering my own thinking, not just one of &lt;em&gt;feel&lt;/em&gt;, either: I write different things, in different ways, with pen and paper than I do with a keyboard. I’m a much better poet with pen and paper, for example.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But those differences do not void the core they share: they are memory-replacements.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not for nothing have people worried about the effects of new technologies on memory for millennia. And it is worth note: those who thought the advent of each kind of new information technology would come with costs were not wrong. Literate cultures seem inevitably to lose the power of oral recall. Members of illiterate cultures can often accomplish feats of memory that astound members of literate cultures, because they do not have books to offload their stories and histories to. The only way to keep them—and we value stories, so we &lt;em&gt;always&lt;/em&gt; find a way to keep them—is to commit them to memory, and deeply. The tradeoff with books is real. The tradeoff with a physical journal is real. The tradeoff with the internet is real.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The question is not &lt;em&gt;whether&lt;/em&gt; but &lt;em&gt;how&lt;/em&gt; we will be formed by the technologies we employ—at least, unless you plan to go back to living naked, surviving off of whatever you can manage to collect with your bare hands and eat raw (fire, too, is technology, after all).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To narrow it further: the question is which specific shapings we find needful in our specific contexts. Perhaps, if there is a problem, it is not with a prayer app individually, or a todo app individually, or a notes app individually, but with offloading &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; of our mental tasks to a smartphone. No harm done in using a prayer app; but maybe write your to-do list on paper; and perhaps find something, anything at all, to simply &lt;em&gt;remember&lt;/em&gt; to do every day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section class="footnotes"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn1"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.roughtype.com/?p=8248"&gt;Here&lt;/a&gt;, on the smartphone, is just one of many times and places; his book &lt;em&gt;The Shallows&lt;/em&gt; is perhaps the best-known and longest treatment of it.&lt;a href="#fnref1" class="footnote-back"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn2"&gt;&lt;p&gt;For my own purposes; Olo doesn’t ask anything of the sort from me; but it helps me see what I actually get done over the course of a year, and that’s pretty neat.&lt;a href="#fnref2" class="footnote-back"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 26 Jan 2018 07:30:00 -0500</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2018-01-26:/2018/prayer-apps-and-evaluating-technology.html</guid><category>writing</category><category>ethics</category></item><item><title>Vexing Ironies</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2017/vexing-ironies.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;One of the most vexing problems in thinking and responding well to problems of ethics in &lt;em&gt;information technology&lt;/em&gt; specifically is the way that so much of thinking and responding about information technology takes place within the context of, well, information technology. Two examples of that challenge caught my attention this evening, ironies I noticed in reading the very same article.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a href="http://www.roughtype.com/?p=8248"&gt;“How smartphones hijack our minds”&lt;/a&gt;, Nick Carr explores much of the evidence for ways that use of smartphones can have seriously negative effects on our thinking in ways that are both pernicious (because we usually do not notice them consciously) and pervasive (in that they happen simply by dint of the &lt;em&gt;presence&lt;/em&gt; of the devices). It’s a good article, and I commend it you as a helpful summary of a lot of the most current research on attention, smartphones, and the like; you should read it and think about how you use your phone.&lt;a href="#fn1" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref1"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the first irony was that I read that article… on my smartphone. As indeed I read &lt;em&gt;many&lt;/em&gt; of Nick Carr’s articles. There’s something more than a little odd about considering the use of a smartphone by way of reading an article on a smartphone. But in a very real sense, there’s almost no way I &lt;em&gt;could&lt;/em&gt; have read Carr’s article otherwise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And accordingly, the second irony is that, although Carr, who has staked out a position as a popular-level writer tackling issues of how modern information technology affects us, &lt;a href="https://t.alibris.com/The-Shallows-What-the-Internet-Is-Doing-to-Our-Brains-Nicholas-Carr/book/11882057" title="The Shallows"&gt;certainly &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; published in hard copy&lt;/a&gt;, everything of his I’ve ever read has been in digital form. Indeed, although his books are important in their own ways, I think it’s fair to say that &lt;em&gt;most&lt;/em&gt; people’s interaction with his ideas, including his critiques of the ways we use and indeed rely on the internet, have all happened via and only because of the internet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m not entirely sure what to make of these observations. I don’t fault Carr for publishing a blog, exactly; and though I am increasingly chastened about my own at-times-unwise use of a smartphone, I don’t fault myself for having an RSS reader there. (Better than that a Twitter app, to be sure!) But there is something at a minimum &lt;em&gt;odd&lt;/em&gt; and perhaps even something &lt;em&gt;off&lt;/em&gt; about the ways that we tend to use the very tools we are critiquing as the medium for advancing our critiques. We implicate ourselves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But what is the alternative? On the one hand Carr’s message—which is important!—has likely been heard and even internalized by a far broader audience because he has transmitted it digitally than it would have been had he conscientiously limited it to books (and perhaps print media articles). The efficacy of the medium for distribution is the internet’s greatest strength. Likewise, I would never have run into Carr’s writing in the first place apart from articles in my RSS feed which linked it; and I do a great deal of my RSS feed reading on my iPhone and iPad, both of which are much better &lt;em&gt;reading&lt;/em&gt; environments than a laptop or a desktop computer. Indeed, much of what I find most helpful in my reading on technology and ethics I find my way to via articles in my RSS feed, and I often items for reading later by simply tapping a an interesting-looking link in an article I’m reading in that RSS feed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What do we make of this tension, these ironies? Especially when our concerns begin to rise to the level not merely of prudential judgments (though that level alone is perhaps sufficient reason to do more than we let ourselves) but deep ethical worries—do we abandon the smartphone altogether, cease blogging for fear of how it only contributes to the Google-ified and Facebook-ified age we live in?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don’t know.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section class="footnotes"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn1"&gt;&lt;p&gt;One of my concerns in my &lt;a href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2017/why-do-i-need-a-research-tool.html"&gt;ongoing project&lt;/a&gt; is to prompt people around me—friends and family, but perhaps also blog readers!—to consider how our use of technology &lt;em&gt;forms&lt;/em&gt; us. More on that in a future post.&lt;a href="#fnref1" class="footnote-back"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 17 Dec 2017 20:50:00 -0500</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2017-12-17:/2017/vexing-ironies.html</guid><category>ethics</category></item><item><title>Dear Tech CEOs: Yes, That Is Your Culture.</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2017/dear-tech-ceos-yes-that-is-your-culture.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;It is common, when stories break about horrible company cultures in —as &lt;a href="https://www.susanjfowler.com/blog/2017/2/19/reflecting-on-one-very-strange-year-at-uber"&gt;one did this week about Uber&lt;/a&gt;, and as &lt;a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2015/08/16/technology/inside-amazon-wrestling-big-ideas-in-a-bruising-workplace.html?_r=1"&gt;one did last year about Amazon&lt;/a&gt;—for the &lt;abbr&gt;CEO&lt;/abbr&gt;s to say things like:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What she describes is abhorrent and against everything Uber stands for and believes in. (Uber &lt;abbr&gt;CEO&lt;/abbr&gt; Travis Kalanick’s statement quoted at &lt;a href="http://www.recode.net/2017/2/19/14665076/ubers-travis-kalanick-susan-fowler-sexual-harassment-investigation"&gt;Recode&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Or:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The article doesn’t describe the Amazon I know or the caring Amazonians I work with every day. (Amazon &lt;abbr&gt;CEO&lt;/abbr&gt; Jeff Bezos’ statement quoted at &lt;a href="http://www.geekwire.com/2015/full-memo-jeff-bezos-responds-to-cutting-nyt-expose-says-tolerance-for-lack-of-empathy-needs-to-be-zero/"&gt;Geekwire&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The problem with this is simple. You can say all day that these events don’t represent your culture. But they &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt;. And if you’re not aware of it, that means you have two problems: the culture problem, and the fact that you’re so out of touch with what your company is actually like that you don’t know it has that culture problem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And you have one other, even bigger problem. If that’s the culture of the company you’ve built, it’s &lt;em&gt;your fault&lt;/em&gt;. You can’t foist it off on your underlings: you hired them. You can’t foist it off on the bureaucracy: you built it. You can’t foist it off on wrong priorities: you set those priorities. It’s on you.&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 21 Feb 2017 17:00:00 -0500</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2017-02-21:/2017/dear-tech-ceos-yes-that-is-your-culture.html</guid><category>ethics</category></item></channel></rss>