<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Chris Krycho</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/</link><description></description><atom:link href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/feeds/family.xml" rel="self"></atom:link><lastBuildDate>Sat, 08 Aug 2015 06:42:00 -0400</lastBuildDate><item><title>2015-08-08 06:42</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2015/2015-08-08-0642.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Ellie and Kate &lt;em&gt;consistently&lt;/em&gt; get up half an hour to an hour earlier on Saturday mornings than any other day of the week. Coincidentally—&lt;em&gt;or is it?&lt;/em&gt;—Saturday is also the only day we try to sleep in. It’s like they know, and plot against us!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="references"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 08 Aug 2015 06:42:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2015-08-08:2015/2015-08-08-0642.html</guid><category>family</category><category>kate</category><category>ellie</category></item><item><title>2015-08-04 18:55</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2015/2015-08-04-1855.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;A minute ago, Ellie asked me to play with her and Kate. I started to answer, “No, I need to finish publishing Winning Slowly.” Then I remembered: putting that first would be pretty much &lt;em&gt;exactly the opposite&lt;/em&gt; of &lt;a href="http://www.winningslowly.org/1.02" title="1.02: On Family"&gt;Winning Slowly&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="references"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 04 Aug 2015 18:55:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2015-08-04:2015/2015-08-04-1855.html</guid><category>family</category><category>ellie</category><category>kate</category><category>podcast</category></item><item><title>Faithfulness</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2015/faithfulness.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;It’s been a lot more than a month since the promised monthly update. I’ll blame it on a lack of self-discipline… or perhaps on the presence thereof.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Every day, we face choices about where to spend our time. In this particular season of life, that has often meant not writing, even things I &lt;em&gt;want&lt;/em&gt; to write. I have a family to care for, a church to serve, work to do, and schoolwork to accomplish. Family is a daily endeavor, work and school nearly so, and church regular if not quite daily. In the midst of that, I have to decide: &lt;em&gt;What will I do today?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our culture tends to put the question in terms of balance; my friend and pastor Ashok Nachnani suggested to me a while back that it is better to think in terms of &lt;em&gt;faithfulness&lt;/em&gt;. “Balance” suggests holding all these things in equal proportion, juggling them against each other. “Faithfulness” suggests fulfilling the responsibilities as best we can, with the time we are given. The actual day-to-day outcome may not look particularly different, but it is an important shift in the way we think nonetheless. To be faithful may mean letting some desireable things go, and it may mean doing some things in a different way or to a lesser degree than we might like.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Writing, for example.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I &lt;em&gt;love&lt;/em&gt; writing. I like keeping a public record for my friends and family to see how my life is. I enjoy stretching my mental muscles in the way that writing requires. I enjoy thinking through pen or keyboard. But faithfulness to the responsibilities God has given me right now means &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; trying to balance those desires against each other, and instead doing what is best for my family and my church. For the most part, right now that means not writing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I put it to Jaimie a while back, at this point in life I have time for one hobby—and only one. That hobby, at this point, is fitness. I run half marathons, and now I do triathlons (first one coming up in 10 days!). That takes up a non-trivial amount of time every week. It helps me in the other areas of my life, to be sure: it helps me be less physically tired, improves my focus in school and work, and serves to maintain my health. Nonetheless, it is hobby-like and it takes a substantial amount of time every day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So right now, I write a great deal less than I want, and a great deal less than I did in college or early in our marriage. I miss the days when I had time to work on poetry for hours at a stretch, or simply to muse for a few thousand words. But it is far more important for me to spend time with Ellie and Kate than it is to write poetry, or to compose music, right now. Lord willing, I have 55–60 years ahead of me. Of those years, they will be close only another 15–20, and they will be the age they are today &lt;em&gt;only for today&lt;/em&gt;. As much as writing and composing and hobby programming all look appealing to me, and as much as those really are good expressions of the ways God has gifted me, focusing on them would not be the most &lt;em&gt;faithful&lt;/em&gt; use of my time—not today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is not to say that writing and composing and developing interesting software are not important. Rather: they &lt;em&gt;are&lt;/em&gt; good and valuable things. But they are things to focus on at other times in life. As fast as this life goes, and I am increasingly aware that it goes quickly indeed, I can expect in the ordinary course of things to have &lt;em&gt;many&lt;/em&gt; years available for those things. I can exercise my gifts faithfully in the right time and season. Today, I can learn to love my little girls well, invest deeply in their lives, and savor moments that will never come back.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most of all, I must remind myself that teaching and shaping them is easily the most significant thing I will ever do. Should I write an essay that persuaded a thousand people to change their views on the arts, or to adopt a better view of the church, still my impact on two little lives would be more important. If I can point them faithfully to Christ and help them learn to walk faithfully with him as healthy members of his body, that will be a good life to have lived. Everything else is icing on the cake.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Icing is good, for the record. Sometimes, in these sorts of posts, we can mistake &lt;em&gt;relative importance&lt;/em&gt; for &lt;em&gt;absolute importance&lt;/em&gt;. I should, at various times in my life, make sure to exercise the good gifts God has given me in ways appropriate to that time and context. Right now, that means continuing to write, but less frequently. In the future, it will mean something else.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And all of this must stand in the context of resurrection hope. Too often, I live—too often, we &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; live—as though the next 60 years are all we may expect, the only time for writing and composing and so on. But it is not. I look forward to endless ages of creativity, exercising those gifts &lt;em&gt;more&lt;/em&gt; fully than I am able now. So: Lord Jesus, come soon. And in the meantime, may I be faithful in each season to do as well as I can.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="references"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 18 Jun 2015 17:00:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2015-06-18:2015/faithfulness.html</guid><category>family</category><category>writing</category></item><item><title>2015-06-15 05:35</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2015/2015-06-15-0535.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Our youngest has been sleeping through the night for a week now. Going to bed at 9:45 &amp;amp; getting up at 5:15 is suddenly doable again. Huzzah!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="references"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 15 Jun 2015 05:35:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2015-06-15:2015/2015-06-15-0535.html</guid><category>family</category><category>kate</category></item><item><title>The State of Our Family in Early 2015</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2015/early-2015-family.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;It has been a &lt;em&gt;long&lt;/em&gt; time since I wrote a family update here, and I skipped the Christmas letter this year because I was exhausted. I resolved at the beginning of the year to write at least one update every month, though. I want these updates here for &lt;em&gt;myself&lt;/em&gt;, if for no other reason. (Then, of course, I promptly missed January, but this is counting for that; there will be another post here at the end of the month.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What have we been up to, you ask? Well, quite a lot! Since the last time I wrote a blog post, we had a baby, who is now crawling around. (If you’re reading this, you probably already know that, of course.) Ellie is talking, constantly practicing saying things the right way and asking the names of things; Kate is scooting around the floor exploring everything and is increasingly verbal herself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They love playing together. Ellie and Kate are good friends—a while back Jaimie heard Ellie quietly talking to Katie in the back seat of the car, repeating, “You’re my best friend, Kate.” Sometimes when Ellie gives Kate a hug and a kiss goodnight every night, Kate goes into the most adorable squeals of delight. Indeed, no one elicits those squeals as much as Ellie. In addition to her scooting around the floor, Kate is happily eating solid foods—and the girl &lt;em&gt;loves&lt;/em&gt; her food. Today I put her in her high chair and she started laughing as I put the tray in front of her. She often thumps the tray, the table, or the floor to express her joy. And last but not least, this little gal is &lt;em&gt;strong&lt;/em&gt;. Her favorite time is getting in a bouncer and jumping for as long as we will let her.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src="/images/girls-games.jpg" title="My ladies playing Lego Star Wars"/&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;
My ladies playing &lt;i&gt;Lego Star Wars&lt;/i&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have been teaching Ellie a lot. Jaimie has slowly started working through the ABCs with her. She can count to 5, and she knows her way to 10, but sometimes gets sidetracked along the way. She is learning her colors and spent a while defaulting to calling everything “pink”… except for her favorite &lt;em&gt;purple&lt;/em&gt; dress. In the last month, she has started being able to identify the colors more reliably, along with lots of shapes. She loves cars and trucks and especially buses and fire trucks. She sings to herself and dances all the time. She loves building with blocks. She is learning to say “please” and “thank you”—learning, in this case, not because she doesn’t know how but because she has started &lt;em&gt;forgetting&lt;/em&gt;. She is learning to pray and to sing to God and learning the answer to simple questions like, “Who made you, Ellie?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jaimie has continued to write off and on, though the first many months we had Kate it was much spottier than it had been. She’s working on secret projects that are making her happy, and that makes me happy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As for why she didn’t get as much time, I was &lt;em&gt;busy&lt;/em&gt; last semester. I picked up a second contract, building the new &lt;a href="//holybible.com"&gt;HolyBible.com&lt;/a&gt;, and between that and my ongoing contract work and my one class, I pulled a lot of 50–60 hour weeks. That’s not particularly an experience we are keen to repeat, but it was the right call at the time: we were able to save up the money to fill up our six-month emergency fund and to pay for the rest of seminary. This semester is going a bit easier: I am taking Hebrew III and Baptist History and working ~30 hours a week instead of ~50–55. I &lt;em&gt;love&lt;/em&gt; my language classes; without a doubt Hebrew III and Greek III have been my very favorite classes since I started seminary.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I ran another half marathon in November, and set a PR at 1:25:37—a 6:32/mile pace. I was super happy with that outcome, and I plan to run the same race again for the third year in a row this coming fall, Lord willing. In the meantime, I have started swimming and cycling regularly with the aim of completing my first triathlon early this summer. (I’m going to stick to a short “sprint” tri to start, and work up from there.) While I love running, I would like to have the use of my joints in twenty (and forty, and sixty) years, and accordingly I need to make sure I do not keep putting over 1,000 miles a year on my legs. I have been going to a spinning class to get my legs in better cycling shape for the last month (and the last two weeks Jaimie has come with me!). We have also been doing a Pilates class weekly; my back needs to be a lot stronger and my legs a lot looser, and that is helping quite a bit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We continue to be extremely happy in our church here, FBC Durham. God has used our church to encourage and challenge us in a wide variety of ways—too many (and perhaps in many cases too subtle) even to summarize. We are excited to see what the years ahead hold for us there, as the church itself continues to flourish and grow and we seek opportunities to continue serving and building up this particular outpost of the body of Christ.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In short, life is &lt;em&gt;good&lt;/em&gt;. It is not perfect, of course; I long for Jesus’ return and the New Heavens and New Earth more and more all the time. But we see God’s faithfulness and goodness in the hard months no less than in the easy ones. We see the Spirit working in our hearts to make us more like Christ, and it is good.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I could go on, but a thousand words is enough. More again, and sooner than the last gap!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="references"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2015 20:30:00 -0500</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2015-02-10:2015/early-2015-family.html</guid><category>family</category><category>Ellie</category><category>Kate</category><category>Jaimie</category></item><item><title>Whiplash</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2014/whiplash.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;I have a pretty severe case of emotional whiplash&lt;a href="#fn1" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref1"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; at the moment. In the last eight hours, I have gone from jubilant to the most worried I have ever been to simple, utter exhaustion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This afternoon, I heard back from a then-potential and now-actual client who hired me and a friend to design and build a web application for them. They are going to pay us a substantial sum to do it. This is &lt;em&gt;fantastic&lt;/em&gt;. I have been hoping this particular opportunity would come through, because everything about it is appealing to me. It is an interesting application; I like the material it involves (a &lt;em&gt;lot&lt;/em&gt;); I will learn a bit along the way; I will get to stretch my front-end design chops again; I will make some seriously good money at it. I am, in a word, stoked.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fast forward four and a half hours. Jaimie and I are helping Ellie wrap up her evening activities and getting ready to take her upstairs and put her to bed. Kate is lying in a little sleep-rocker—her favorite spot to sleep during the day. She makes a bit of a coughing noise; we note it but think little of it (babies &lt;em&gt;often&lt;/em&gt; make that kind of noise). A few minutes later, Jaimie is walking by and glances at Kate. Our baby girl is bright red and turning purple. She grabs her. “Kate! Breathe! Breathe, little girl!” She isn’t breathing; she is getting upset but she isn’t crying. (Babies cry at the drop of a hat.) Little bubbles at her mouth. Jaimie is doing the baby variation of the Heimlich maneuver. I am nearly helpless; I keep using my finger to pull Kate’s mouth open; she finally latches onto the finger, starts sucking, and breathes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thank God.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We hold her. She breathes—&lt;em&gt;mostly&lt;/em&gt; normally. We keep paying close attention to her. The couple times I let her lay down on her back she starts seizing up and turning red again within a few minutes until I pick her up and pat her vigorously and she calms down again. We manage to get Ellie in bed. We call the doctor; she sends us to the hospital. A friend comes to watch Ellie and we run out the door. It is a 30-minute drive (and I am speeding, and Jaimie is holding Kate to make sure she keeps breathing).&lt;a href="#fn2" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref2"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; Kate wheezes off and on the whole way there. She still isn’t crying, and she should be. She hasn’t eaten in six hours; she should be hungry. Why isn’t she hungry?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They admit us. They get all her vitals. The doctor is a kind, soft-spoken man with the last name Saad; I like him. He asks dozens of good questions. He tells us, “95–99% of the time, this is just reflux. We just care about that other 1% of the time.” There is no reliable way to stop a baby from choking on milk she spits up because of reflux.&lt;a href="#fn3" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref3"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; They are going to do an EKG and chest X-rays just to make sure she is okay.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She seems to be okay. She is eating again—like a champ, like she normally does, like she should be.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I go home to relieve the wonderful friends who are sitting in our house to make sure Ellie is fine. Ellie is still sleeping. Good.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Breathe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whiplash. I am no less excited about that project. And my youngest daughter almost died tonight. Had she started choking while we were upstairs, or while we were all asleep tonight, God only knows what would have happened. We are grateful to God that we were feet away from Kate, that Jaimie “happened” to look at her just then. We are grateful, too, for the extra money coming in; it will help with the so-very-worth-it-but-not-easy-on-a-seminary-budget cost of an emergency room visit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ice cream.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think I’m going to sleep now. Hopefully tomorrow is less extreme.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="references"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;section class="footnotes"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn1"&gt;&lt;p&gt;So much so that I am having a hard time spelling “whiplash” correctly. I keep typing “whiplast”.&lt;a href="#fnref1"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn2"&gt;&lt;p&gt;If a police officer stops us, I will explain. He or she will understand. They will help us get to the hospital faster.&lt;a href="#fnref2"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn3"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Terrifying, just a bit? Yes.&lt;a href="#fnref3"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 14 Jul 2014 23:15:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2014-07-14:2014/whiplash.html</guid><category>family</category><category>Kate</category></item><item><title>The Long Race</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2014/the-long-race.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;It has been too long since I have written anything—too long not for my audience (small as it is), but for my soul. The last few weeks of class were of course even busier than the rest of the semester, courtesy of a couple major assignments I wrapped up and studying for and taking finals, all while doing my normal work as a software developer on the side. Writing simply fell by the wayside, alas. Even my devotions posts simply didn’t happen. And that is all right; there are seasons for all of these things, and it is not as if I didn’t write many thousands of words in late April and early May. They simply were not &lt;em&gt;blogging&lt;/em&gt; words.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So here I am tonight, writing simply to unwind. I spent much of the day working on various software projects—a pattern I expect to carry throughout the summer. In addition to my regular work for Quest Consultants Inc. back in Norman, I am picking up various web design and development jobs over the summer. God has been gracious in answering prayers for opportunities to pick up extra contracting work, and I have several really excellent opportunities to supplement my 20 hours a week for Quest with other work. That is nice not only financially, but also intellectually. The change of pace between different kinds of work helps me stay fresh on all of them. My own personal &lt;a href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2014/a-little-crazy.html"&gt;side projects&lt;/a&gt; are coming along slowly, but that is all right. Slow but steady is the best way to go about those kinds of projects anyway.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That lesson is one I have learned more and more from my ongoing and ever-increasing delight in running. So far in May I have run about 125 miles; I expect to run over 150 miles this month in total (though of course all such plans are always subject to revision, and never more so than when one’s wife is 37 weeks pregnant). I am now running easy, aerobic miles ten to fifteen seconds faster per mile than I could manage in my personal best half marathon time a few years ago. I run so (relatively) quickly now not because of any particular innate athleticism—quite the contrary, as anyone who has known me since high school can attest. I can run as far and fast as I do only because I have stuck with it and used a &lt;a href="http://markallenonline.com/maoArticles.aspx?AID=2" title="Working Your Heart"&gt;smart training plan&lt;/a&gt;. And really, as in most parts of life, it is that sticking-with-it that leads to getting somewhere. Of course, sticking with it is no guarantee that things will work out. It is usually a requisite step along the way, though—a necessary-though-insufficient condition. That is simply the way God built the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Little Ellie is quickly wrapping up her second year of life in this big world. She is saying lots of words (at last!), whining until she has driven Jaimie a bit crazy (in too-typical toddler fashion), and growing up in big ways and small. We are having a great deal of fun watching her start to be more socially aware and active, even if it is a little strange to have a daughter old enough that she has friends whom she loves and who love her in turn. She has also discovered a deep love of &lt;em&gt;Star Wars&lt;/em&gt;—no surprise for a daughter of ours, though the intensity of her delight in the movies, for a girl who is not yet two years old, did surprise both Jaimie and me a bit. You should hear her try to say “Darth Vader” or “Dark Side” or “Star Wars.” It is impossibly adorable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jaimie is, as noted above, some 37 weeks pregnant and quite ready to be done carrying our second little gal on the inside. She is still plugging away slowly at the &lt;a href="http://jaimiekrycho.com/shaking-epheria-pt-1/" title="Bloodlines: The Shaking of Epheria, Part I"&gt;second novella&lt;/a&gt; in her &lt;a href="http://www.amazon.com/Bloodlines-Epheria-The-Trilogy-ebook/dp/B00HY478QO/" title="Get Bloodlines of Epheria on Kindle!"&gt;Bloodlines&lt;/a&gt; fantasy trilogy. She manages to keep Ellie entertained—no small feat—and does a remarkable job taking care of things around the house so that I can focus on work and school. Her struggle with &lt;a href="http://2012-2013.chriskrycho.com/theology/marriage-depression/" title="Marriage and Depression"&gt;depression&lt;/a&gt; has not diminished, but God has given us grace to carry on and she and I have both learned to respond in better, healthier, more helpful ways when the slumps come.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As for the future, we really have no idea what the next several yeras will hold. I plan to finish my Master of Divinity—Lord willing, around December 2016. In the meantime, we will keep raising our little girls, I will keep writing software, and we will keep exploring and seeing what we want to do and how best to pursue those desires in a way that honors God. Who knows what those years will hold? God only, and certainly not us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="references"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 24 May 2014 00:07:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2014-05-24:2014/the-long-race.html</guid><category>software development</category><category>family</category><category>fitness</category></item><item><title>Spinning!</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2014/spinning.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;As she so often does, Ellie simply delighted me tonight, in two wonderful moments:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol type="1"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;As I was cleaning up the dishes and playing Max Richter’s &lt;a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/album/memoryhouse/id545010150"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Memoryhouse&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; album, I saw Ellie dancing, and encouraged her to keep going. After a moment, I looked over to see her spinning in circles. And spinning in circles. And spinning in circles. When she finally stopped, she started freaking out as she couldn’t get her balance. I swooped in and picked her up, laughing with her once she recovered.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;After she calmed down, she started tugging on my shirt. It took me a few seconds to realize what she wanted, but then it clicked: she was trying to turn me by twisting my shirt. “You want to spin?” I asked her. She nodded vigorously. “Is this a spinning song?” Again, the vigorous nod. So I started spinning around and around with her in my arms, and the sheer joy in the grin plastered across her face was something to behold. We spun first one way, then the other, all the way through &lt;a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=BfoSv8iWA_I"&gt;“The Twins (Prague)”&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moments like these are worth remembering.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="references"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 20 Mar 2014 19:10:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2014-03-20:2014/spinning.html</guid><category>family</category><category>Ellie</category></item></channel></rss>