<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Chris Krycho</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/</link><description></description><atom:link href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/feeds/fitness.xml" rel="self"></atom:link><lastBuildDate>Sat, 20 Feb 2016 15:50:00 -0500</lastBuildDate><item><title>2016-02-20 15:50</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2016/2016-02-20-1550.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;First day of true spring weather. Time to get the bike out and take a ride. Tri training season, here we come!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id="refs" class="references"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 20 Feb 2016 15:50:00 -0500</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2016-02-20:2016/2016-02-20-1550.html</guid><category>fitness</category></item><item><title>How I Became a (Relatively) Quick Runner</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2015/how-i-became-a-relatively-quick-runner.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;A few weeks ago, I ran the &lt;a href="http://cityofoaksmarathon.com"&gt;City of Oaks&lt;/a&gt; half marathon event for the third consecutive year. I finished at 1:24:58, which comes out to be about a 6:29/mile pace. I finished 20th overall, out of thousands of half-marathoners. If that seems fast to you, well, it seems fast to me, too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;People often ask me how I run so far and so quickly. I always laugh when they ask, because for my part, I haven’t thought of myself as particularly fast—the guys who finished first in my race this year ran over a minute per mile faster than me.&lt;a href="#fn1" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref1"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; The best half-marathoners in the world are running a 4:30/mile pace! But I grant that a 6:29/mile pace is, in the grand scheme of things, pretty quick.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That leads me to the &lt;em&gt;other&lt;/em&gt; reason I don’t tend to think of myself as fast: my training approach.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My half marathon times have always been pretty good,&lt;a href="#fn2" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref2"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; but it is &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; because I am particularly athletic. As I mentioned in &lt;a href="/2015/how-i-became-a-runner.html"&gt;my first post&lt;/a&gt; in this series: you can ask my high school football coaches. I was never particularly quick, and even now my best mile time is somewhere around 5:30. I knew people even in high school who were in the mid- to low-4:00 range. Still, going sub-6:30 for 13 miles is no joke, and if you had told me even five years ago—after I started running!—that someday I would run the race I did a few weeks ago, I’d have laughed in disbelief.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But it really is all in the training. I have two things going for me, and only two: I train &lt;em&gt;smart&lt;/em&gt;, and I train &lt;em&gt;consistently&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Consistency first: year-round, I am doing some sort of workout six days a week. Throughout the winter and spring, that will look like a mix of running, spin classes at the gym, and swimming as I prep for another triathlon. From now till the end of January or so, I’ll just do pretty much whatever I feel like in that mix, while keeping at it. From February till whatever point early next summer that my triathlon is, I’ll dedicate two workouts a week to each of the sports. Then I’ll slowly transition to nearly-all running. Through the fall, I will run 5–6 days a week, cycling for a commute when weather permits one of those days instead.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That right there is the single biggest factor in my performance. If &lt;em&gt;anyone&lt;/em&gt; did 30–45 minutes a day four days a week, an hour one day a week, and ninety minutes to two hours another day a week, he would get quicker rapidly. If he did that for five and a half years (as I have been), he would likely be in very similar shape to me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As for training smart, I basically just follow the &lt;a href="http://philmaffetone.com/what-is-the-maffetone-method/"&gt;Maffetone method&lt;/a&gt;. Most of my runs are easy, aerobic runs. Even at the height of my training for a half marathon, when I am running 45–50 miles each week, 80% of my miles are at a conversational pace. (I’ve carried on fifteen-minute-long phone conversations on runs before!) My long runs include a hard, roughly race-pace finish for the last three or four miles, and I do one hard run a week which is half aerobic and half pushing harder than race speed.&lt;a href="#fn3" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref3"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; But overall, I run a slow-for-me pace most of the time. I use a heart-rate monitor to help me stay in an easy, aerobic training zone, and I simply don’t go over that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That slow-run training pays off in a couple ways. First, it builds up my body’s ability to process energy aerobically (see &lt;a href="http://philmaffetone.com/what-is-the-maffetone-method/"&gt;the Maffetone method article&lt;/a&gt; for details). Second, it’s much easier on my body—I simply don’t have the joint problems or soreness that many runners do. Third, it is &lt;em&gt;much&lt;/em&gt; easier mentally, because I can enjoy my runs and not feel exhausted after them. That means it’s much easier to do them day after day, and that takes me back to the consistency point from above.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So if you want to run fast: run a lot, and usually run slow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id="refs" class="references"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;section class="footnotes"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn1"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The top finisher came in at 1:10:03 (to my 1:24:48)—a 5:21/mile pace. The record on the course—which isn’t a perfect match for what we ran today, but pretty similar—is 1:04:21, which is about a 4:55 pace. That’s &lt;em&gt;blisteringly&lt;/em&gt; fast.&lt;a href="#fnref1"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn2"&gt;&lt;p&gt;In my first, in December 2011, I ran a 1:36:32, which is about a 7:23 pace.&lt;a href="#fnref2"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn3"&gt;&lt;p&gt;I also occasionally through speed work days; this fall I did one day of hill repeats: a quarter mile pushing &lt;em&gt;hard&lt;/em&gt; up a hill, a quarter mile easy back down the hill, and a minute of rest. Five miles of that is tough; I’d like to do more in future years.&lt;a href="#fnref3"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 22 Nov 2015 11:00:00 -0500</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2015-11-22:2015/how-i-became-a-relatively-quick-runner.html</guid><category>fitness</category></item><item><title>How I Became a Runner</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2015/how-i-became-a-runner.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Sometime in the last few years, I became “that runner guy.” It is no longer strange for me to introduce myself to someone new in the area we live, and hear them say, “Have I seen you running?” I smile and nod: “Yep, that’s me.” And to be fair, I do run a lot: six days a week, most weeks, always at least half an hour. In three weeks, I’ll run my seventh half marathon,&lt;a href="#fn1" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref1"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and I finished my first triathlon last summer. So, yes, I do run a lot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But it’s still a little strange to me. I came to running late, and in a roundabout way. Many of my friends ran cross country in high school; I played football (and poorly at that) instead. I ran off and on in college in a (mostly failing) attempt to stay in shape and avoid college weight. The only running I did consistently was playing Ultimate on Fridays with some friends. For the first year I was out of college, my routine was much the same.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And then I got mono. I drank after a friend who carries around a particularly virulent strain of it, and was down for the count: a month in bed, and two months of recovery after that. I was, in theory, the captain of a church league Ultimate team that spring. I missed half the games, and even when I was able to attend some of them in the latter half of the season, it left me literally needing a nap just to stand and watch for an hour. In the hopes of being back in good enough shape to play the following fall, I started running as soon as I was cleared by the doctor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That first run on a treadmill in May 2010 was painfully slow. Even when I was furthest out of shape before that, running an 8-minute mile had been doable—painful, perhaps, but doable. That day I ran a 12-minute mile, and was done for the day. The same thing another day that week. And again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But slowly, over time, I built up my endurance. I managed to run two miles outside a few weeks later. By the time Ultimate season rolled around in late August, I could run five miles, and was doing three to five miles four times a week. I was in good enough shape to play Ultimate, and I enjoyed it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Still, I found running hard, and didn’t particularly enjoy it. I ran solely as a means to the end of playing Ultimate. More, five miles was my upper limit if I ran hard (as I always did). When I thought about people who ran half-marathons—still less the full—I simply could not understand how they did it. But I started to &lt;em&gt;want&lt;/em&gt; to understand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And then I had one simple conversation, which changed my entire approach to running. It set me on a course to this seventh half-marathon, and to being “that runner guy” around here. It led to my being the healthiest I’ve ever been. And, strangest of all, it ended up with my &lt;em&gt;loving&lt;/em&gt; to run—and not because I like pain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But more on that next time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id="references" class="references"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;section class="footnotes"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn1"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Dallas White Rock 2011, Oklahoma City 2012, Fort Worth 2012, one whose name I can’t remember in April 2013, City of Oaks 2013, City of Oaks 2014.&lt;a href="#fnref1"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 12 Oct 2015 20:00:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2015-10-12:2015/how-i-became-a-runner.html</guid><category>fitness</category></item><item><title>2015-09-13 19:20</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2015/2015-09-13-1920.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Ever since that &lt;a href="/2015/2015-09-13-1547.html"&gt;18-mile run&lt;/a&gt; earlier, I have been craving (and therefore drinking!) orange juice. Must be low on something or other.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="references"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 13 Sep 2015 19:20:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2015-09-13:2015/2015-09-13-1920.html</guid><category>fitness</category></item><item><title>2015-09-13 15:47</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2015/2015-09-13-1547.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;I took an 18-mile run today—the longest of my life so far. If you’d told me a half decade ago that I’d not only be doing this kind of thing but also feeling great afterward, I probably wouldn’t have believed you. But here we are.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="references"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 13 Sep 2015 15:47:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2015-09-13:2015/2015-09-13-1547.html</guid><category>fitness</category></item><item><title>fleet once more</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2015/fleet-once-more.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Every time I step out to take a run,&lt;br /&gt;
    it seems the clouds roll back,&lt;br /&gt;
    the sun begins to shine,&lt;br /&gt;
    intensifies its radiance and heat.&lt;br /&gt;
This makes for great discomfort, toil,&lt;br /&gt;
    as sweat rolls down my brow&lt;br /&gt;
    and heart rate climbs too quick,&lt;br /&gt;
    requires me to slow and sweat the more.&lt;br /&gt;
It frustrates, irritates, annoys me,&lt;br /&gt;
    that though I wish to speed,&lt;br /&gt;
    to cruise along, to glide,&lt;br /&gt;
    but quickly—not clodding in the heat.&lt;br /&gt;
Even so, I step out the door again:&lt;br /&gt;
    someday cooler airs, or cloudy skies,&lt;br /&gt;
    or both will come, and gladly&lt;br /&gt;
    I will find my feet are fleet once more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="references"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 10 Sep 2015 13:00:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2015-09-10:2015/fleet-once-more.html</guid><category>poetry</category><category>fitness</category></item><item><title>2015-09-08 15:39</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2015/2015-09-08-1539.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;A lovely rain storm started, so I thought I would take a run. Five minutes in, the rain stopped and then it was hot and sunny and muggy the rest of the time. Goodness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="references"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 08 Sep 2015 15:39:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2015-09-08:2015/2015-09-08-1539.html</guid><category>fitness</category></item><item><title>2015-09-06 13:21</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2015/2015-09-06-1321.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;I had forgotten both how good and how incredibly tired I feel after a hard fifteen mile run.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="references"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 06 Sep 2015 13:21:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2015-09-06:2015/2015-09-06-1321.html</guid><category>fitness</category></item><item><title>2015-09-02 16:24</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2015/2015-09-02-1624.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Tip for other runners out there: buy last year’s shoe model (on Ebay, Amazon, etc.). You’ll pay way less.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="references"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 02 Sep 2015 16:24:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2015-09-02:2015/2015-09-02-1624.html</guid><category>fitness</category></item><item><title>2015-08-11 09:09</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2015/2015-08-11-0909.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;My ASICS Gel-Lyte33s lasted me over a thousand miles. The Gel-Lyte33 3s I got to replace them lasted less than 450 miles (more in line with normal expectations for running shoes). I wonder what changed between the models?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="references"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 11 Aug 2015 09:09:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2015-08-11:2015/2015-08-11-0909.html</guid><category>fitness</category></item><item><title>2015-08-09 13:20</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2015/2015-08-09-1320.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;The uppers are coming off on both of my current pairs of ASICS running shoes. I guess it’s time to upgrade. &lt;span class="math inline"&gt;$$$&lt;/span&gt;…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="references"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 09 Aug 2015 13:20:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2015-08-09:2015/2015-08-09-1320.html</guid><category>fitness</category></item><item><title>2015-07-01 10:39</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2015/2015-07-01-1039.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Trying to decide whether the kind of “not good” I’m feeling today is the kind that will get better or worse with exercise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="references"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 01 Jul 2015 10:39:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2015-07-01:2015/2015-07-01-1039.html</guid><category>fitness</category></item><item><title>2015-06-03 11:44</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2015/2015-06-03-1144.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;I officially understand why people like triathlons. Cycling after running is just fine. Running after cycling is &lt;em&gt;amazing&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="references"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 03 Jun 2015 11:44:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2015-06-03:2015/2015-06-03-1144.html</guid><category>fitness</category></item><item><title>The Long Race</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2014/the-long-race.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;It has been too long since I have written anything—too long not for my audience (small as it is), but for my soul. The last few weeks of class were of course even busier than the rest of the semester, courtesy of a couple major assignments I wrapped up and studying for and taking finals, all while doing my normal work as a software developer on the side. Writing simply fell by the wayside, alas. Even my devotions posts simply didn’t happen. And that is all right; there are seasons for all of these things, and it is not as if I didn’t write many thousands of words in late April and early May. They simply were not &lt;em&gt;blogging&lt;/em&gt; words.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So here I am tonight, writing simply to unwind. I spent much of the day working on various software projects—a pattern I expect to carry throughout the summer. In addition to my regular work for Quest Consultants Inc. back in Norman, I am picking up various web design and development jobs over the summer. God has been gracious in answering prayers for opportunities to pick up extra contracting work, and I have several really excellent opportunities to supplement my 20 hours a week for Quest with other work. That is nice not only financially, but also intellectually. The change of pace between different kinds of work helps me stay fresh on all of them. My own personal &lt;a href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2014/a-little-crazy.html"&gt;side projects&lt;/a&gt; are coming along slowly, but that is all right. Slow but steady is the best way to go about those kinds of projects anyway.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That lesson is one I have learned more and more from my ongoing and ever-increasing delight in running. So far in May I have run about 125 miles; I expect to run over 150 miles this month in total (though of course all such plans are always subject to revision, and never more so than when one’s wife is 37 weeks pregnant). I am now running easy, aerobic miles ten to fifteen seconds faster per mile than I could manage in my personal best half marathon time a few years ago. I run so (relatively) quickly now not because of any particular innate athleticism—quite the contrary, as anyone who has known me since high school can attest. I can run as far and fast as I do only because I have stuck with it and used a &lt;a href="http://markallenonline.com/maoArticles.aspx?AID=2" title="Working Your Heart"&gt;smart training plan&lt;/a&gt;. And really, as in most parts of life, it is that sticking-with-it that leads to getting somewhere. Of course, sticking with it is no guarantee that things will work out. It is usually a requisite step along the way, though—a necessary-though-insufficient condition. That is simply the way God built the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Little Ellie is quickly wrapping up her second year of life in this big world. She is saying lots of words (at last!), whining until she has driven Jaimie a bit crazy (in too-typical toddler fashion), and growing up in big ways and small. We are having a great deal of fun watching her start to be more socially aware and active, even if it is a little strange to have a daughter old enough that she has friends whom she loves and who love her in turn. She has also discovered a deep love of &lt;em&gt;Star Wars&lt;/em&gt;—no surprise for a daughter of ours, though the intensity of her delight in the movies, for a girl who is not yet two years old, did surprise both Jaimie and me a bit. You should hear her try to say “Darth Vader” or “Dark Side” or “Star Wars.” It is impossibly adorable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jaimie is, as noted above, some 37 weeks pregnant and quite ready to be done carrying our second little gal on the inside. She is still plugging away slowly at the &lt;a href="http://jaimiekrycho.com/shaking-epheria-pt-1/" title="Bloodlines: The Shaking of Epheria, Part I"&gt;second novella&lt;/a&gt; in her &lt;a href="http://www.amazon.com/Bloodlines-Epheria-The-Trilogy-ebook/dp/B00HY478QO/" title="Get Bloodlines of Epheria on Kindle!"&gt;Bloodlines&lt;/a&gt; fantasy trilogy. She manages to keep Ellie entertained—no small feat—and does a remarkable job taking care of things around the house so that I can focus on work and school. Her struggle with &lt;a href="http://2012-2013.chriskrycho.com/theology/marriage-depression/" title="Marriage and Depression"&gt;depression&lt;/a&gt; has not diminished, but God has given us grace to carry on and she and I have both learned to respond in better, healthier, more helpful ways when the slumps come.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As for the future, we really have no idea what the next several yeras will hold. I plan to finish my Master of Divinity—Lord willing, around December 2016. In the meantime, we will keep raising our little girls, I will keep writing software, and we will keep exploring and seeing what we want to do and how best to pursue those desires in a way that honors God. Who knows what those years will hold? God only, and certainly not us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="references"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 24 May 2014 00:07:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2014-05-24:2014/the-long-race.html</guid><category>software development</category><category>family</category><category>fitness</category></item></channel></rss>