<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Chris Krycho</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/</link><description></description><atom:link href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/feeds/fitness.xml" rel="self"></atom:link><lastBuildDate>Wed, 18 Jun 2014 00:00:00 -0400</lastBuildDate><item><title>Choose Your Hobby</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2014/choose-your-hobby.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;We have hit a new phase of life, what with adorable little Kate in the house and
thus even more time devoted to child-rearing than before. It&amp;#8217;s what in my own
head I&amp;#8217;ve started calling the one-hobby&amp;nbsp;phase.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At earlier points in my life, I had time for many hobbies. I could work on
software, write at length, get in my fitness time, and still have a few hours
left over to watch a &lt;span class="caps"&gt;TV&lt;/span&gt; show or play video games with Jaimie. Not so much
anymore. These days, I get one hobby &lt;em&gt;on a consistent basis&lt;/em&gt;. I can indulge in
others from time to time, when we have breaks in our normal routine or schedule,
but in terms of regular activities outside of work, chores, and so on, I have
time to do only one thing&amp;nbsp;well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I made my choice without even really thinking about it. I &lt;em&gt;run&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The choice was easy for a lot of reasons. Running is a good change of pace for
me (no pun intended): whereas all my other work during the day tends to be
cerebral and physically static, it gets me moving and doesn&amp;#8217;t require a lot of
thought at all. Of course, being the nerd I am, I do plenty of thinking on my
runs, but that thinking is quite different from the thinking I do when writing
software or plowing through seminary coursework. Running decreases stress levels
and increases my energy. It gets me outside, breathing fresh air instead of
sitting inside staring at a computer screen or the pages of a book. It helps me
keep my weight at a healthy level and keeps my body in good condition in ways
that, Lord willing, will serve me well for the rest of my life. It lets me eat a
&lt;em&gt;lot&lt;/em&gt; of good food along the&amp;nbsp;way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I said: it wasn&amp;#8217;t even really a choice. It was instead something of a
realization. If I had to let go of every hobby but one, this one stayed. In
fact, it took me a while to realize that this &amp;#8220;hobby&amp;#8221; had stuck when all the
others had faded from prominence, because unlike my writing, composing, and
on-the-side software projects, running stopped being a hobby for me a long time
ago. It is just a non-negotiable part of my life. It is &lt;em&gt;flexible&lt;/em&gt;, but
non-negotiable: I take time off when I need it, or when Jaimie needs it, or when
Ellie or Kate need it. I give my body the rest it needs. I don&amp;#8217;t worry for a
moment if I don&amp;#8217;t get a run in that I had planned, or I had to go shorter than I
wanted, or &amp;#8220;lose&amp;#8221; a week because I get a nasty cold&amp;#8212;not least because I know
I&amp;#8217;ll be right back out there soon enough, knocking out the&amp;nbsp;miles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If I only get to have one regular hobby at this phase of life, running seems a
good one to have chosen. Who could argue with a hobby that lets you eat more ice&amp;nbsp;cream?&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 18 Jun 2014 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2014-06-18:2014/choose-your-hobby.html</guid><category>fitness</category></item><item><title>The Long Race</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2014/the-long-race.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;It has been too long since I have written anything&amp;#8212;too long not for my
audience (small as it is), but for my soul. The last few weeks of class were of
course even busier than the rest of the semester, courtesy of a couple major
assignments I wrapped up and studying for and taking finals, all while doing my
normal work as a software developer on the side. Writing simply fell by the
wayside, alas. Even my devotions posts simply didn&amp;#8217;t happen. And that is all
right; there are seasons for all of these things, and it is not as if I didn&amp;#8217;t
write many thousands of words in late April and early May. They simply were not
&lt;em&gt;blogging&lt;/em&gt;&amp;nbsp;words.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So here I am tonight, writing simply to unwind. I spent much of the day working
on various software projects&amp;#8212;a pattern I expect to carry throughout the
summer. In addition to my regular work for Quest Consultants Inc. back in
Norman, I am picking up various web design and development jobs over the
summer. God has been gracious in answering prayers for opportunities to pick up
extra contracting work, and I have several really excellent opportunities to
supplement my 20 hours a week for Quest with other work. That is nice not only
financially, but also intellectually. The change of pace between different
kinds of work helps me stay fresh on all of them. My own personal &lt;a href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2014/a-little-crazy.html"&gt;side
projects&lt;/a&gt; are coming along slowly, but that is all right. Slow but steady
is the best way to go about those kinds of projects&amp;nbsp;anyway.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That lesson is one I have learned more and more from my ongoing and
ever-increasing delight in running. So far in May I have run about 125 miles; I
expect to run over 150 miles this month in total (though of course all such
plans are always subject to revision, and never more so than when one&amp;#8217;s wife is
37 weeks pregnant). I am now running easy, aerobic miles ten to fifteen seconds
faster per mile than I could manage in my personal best half marathon time a
few years ago. I run so (relatively) quickly now not because of any particular
innate athleticism&amp;#8212;quite the contrary, as anyone who has known me since high
school can attest. I can run as far and fast as I do only because I have stuck
with it and used a &lt;a href="http://markallenonline.com/maoArticles.aspx?AID=2" title="Working Your Heart"&gt;smart training plan&lt;/a&gt;. And really, as in most
parts of life, it is that sticking-with-it that leads to getting somewhere. Of
course, sticking with it is no guarantee that things will work out. It is
usually a requisite step along the way, though&amp;#8212;a
necessary-though-insufficient condition. That is simply the way God built the&amp;nbsp;world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Little Ellie is quickly wrapping up her second year of life in this big world.
She is saying lots of words (at last!), whining until she has driven Jaimie a
bit crazy (in too-typical toddler fashion), and growing up in big ways and
small. We are having a great deal of fun watching her start to be more socially
aware and active, even if it is a little strange to have a daughter old enough
that she has friends whom she loves and who love her in turn. She has also
discovered a deep love of &lt;em&gt;Star Wars&lt;/em&gt;&amp;#8212;no surprise for a daughter of ours,
though the intensity of her delight in the movies, for a girl who is not yet
two years old, did surprise both Jaimie and me a bit. You should hear her try
to say &amp;#8220;Darth Vader&amp;#8221; or &amp;#8220;Dark Side&amp;#8221; or &amp;#8220;Star Wars.&amp;#8221; It is impossibly&amp;nbsp;adorable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jaimie is, as noted above, some 37 weeks pregnant and quite ready to be done
carrying our second little gal on the inside. She is still plugging away slowly
at the &lt;a href="http://jaimiekrycho.com/shaking-epheria-pt-1/" title="Bloodlines: The Shaking of Epheria, Part I"&gt;second novella&lt;/a&gt; in her &lt;a href="http://www.amazon.com/Bloodlines-Epheria-The-Trilogy-ebook/dp/B00HY478QO/" title="Get Bloodlines of Epheria on Kindle!"&gt;Bloodlines&lt;/a&gt; fantasy trilogy.
She manages to keep Ellie entertained&amp;#8212;no small feat&amp;#8212;and does a remarkable
job taking care of things around the house so that I can focus on work and
school. Her struggle with &lt;a href="http://2012-2013.chriskrycho.com/theology/marriage-depression/" title="Marriage and Depression"&gt;depression&lt;/a&gt; has not diminished, but
God has given us grace to carry on and she and I have both learned to respond
in better, healthier, more helpful ways when the slumps&amp;nbsp;come.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As for the future, we really have no idea what the next several yeras will
hold. I plan to finish my Master of Divinity&amp;#8212;Lord willing, around December
2016. In the meantime, we will keep raising our little girls, I will keep
writing software, and we will keep exploring and seeing what we want to do and
how best to pursue those desires in a way that honors God. Who knows what those
years will hold? God only, and certainly not&amp;nbsp;us.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 24 May 2014 00:07:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2014-05-24:2014/the-long-race.html</guid><category>software development</category><category>family</category><category>fitness</category></item></channel></rss>