<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Chris Krycho - from my sent folder</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/</link><description></description><lastBuildDate>Fri, 14 Jun 2019 08:30:00 -0400</lastBuildDate><item><title>From My Sent Folder: On Social Media Tradeoffs</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2019/from-my-sent-folder-on-social-media-tradeoffs.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.chriskrycho.com/2018/assumed-audiences.html"&gt;Assumed Audience&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/b&gt; anyone &lt;em&gt;willing&lt;/em&gt; to think hard about social media and its place in our lives.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;I got a particularly thoughtful email from a friend about his family’s use of Facebook in response to &lt;a href="https://www.chriskrycho.com/2019/breaking-up-with-social-media.html"&gt;yesterday’s essay&lt;/a&gt;. I’ve reproduced most of my response here because I think it’s a helpful extension on that essay.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I (a) totally hear where you’re coming from, and deeply sympathize; and (b) deeply disagree about the notion that they’re “just tools – not good or evil in themselves.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I agree in the strictest sense that the tools are not evil in and of themselves. But I think that particular framing is actually extremely misleading. Tools have &lt;em&gt;shapes&lt;/em&gt;, and those shapes form us in ways that may prove out to be particular bad. The usual example is: use a hammer for hours a day every day, and you’ll end up with calluses and quite possibly some hilariously out-of-proportion forearms if you don’t figure out how to be ambidextrous at least for hammering. That tools are not inherently moral does not mean they’re &lt;em&gt;neutral&lt;/em&gt;. (I also am not persuaded that tools are themselves always &lt;em&gt;morally&lt;/em&gt; neutral, but that’s another discussion and a subtler one.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the case of the social media tools, I &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt; think there are differences in both degree (the extent to which they shape us) and kind (the particular shapes they press us into as we use them). Thus my willingness to work for LinkedIn and my &lt;em&gt;un&lt;/em&gt;willingness to work for Twitter or Facebook! And with that in mind, I do agree that the tradeoffs around Facebook can look very different than those around Twitter today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What’s more, I’d go so far as to say that a service much like Facebook but retooled in certain very important ways could be a much-less-alloyed good in the world! (There are no unalloyed goods in our fallen reality, of course.) A service that was less interested in &lt;em&gt;driving user attention&lt;/em&gt; and therefore constantly working in ways that actively undermine people’s self-control and ability to disengage could have most (probably all!) the upsides Facebook offers you and your family today, with few of the horrid downsides we’re seeing with it at the macro scale and few (if any) of the downsides I have felt with it personally at the micro scale. It’s those vicious little loops driving me to check obsessively that I want out of—not the ability to have geographically distributed people able to stay in touch and indeed even to connect, of the sort you and I have benefited from so much.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;None of that is an argument for everyone to get off of Facebook. I certainly think you and your family have very &lt;em&gt;good&lt;/em&gt; reasons to be there. Rather, it’s more that the more of us who make the kinds of moves I’m making, the more it opens back up the &lt;em&gt;possibility&lt;/em&gt; that those communities could form in other spaces, and creates the &lt;em&gt;reminder&lt;/em&gt; for others that in fact many people are &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; in those spaces. It’s a very long play, for sure, but, you know: winning slowly and all that jazz.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In that regard it’s not so different from my rejection of Amazon: I’m under no misapprehension that I’m going to have any meaningful effect on the company itself, and in fact I have friends who I think are &lt;em&gt;very wise&lt;/em&gt; to continue using it because e.g. Prime eliminates needless frictions from their very challenging lives. It’s that my opting out allows me to support &lt;em&gt;other&lt;/em&gt;—healthier!—businesses and hopefully keep them going.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All of which is kind of a long way of saying: these are &lt;em&gt;wisdom&lt;/em&gt; questions, and I think that wisdom not only allows but indeed &lt;em&gt;dictates&lt;/em&gt; different courses for different people.&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 14 Jun 2019 08:30:00 -0400</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2019-06-14:/2019/from-my-sent-folder-on-social-media-tradeoffs.html</guid><category>social media</category><category>from my sent folder</category><category>ethics</category><category>wisdom</category></item><item><title>From My Sent Folder: On Mozilla and IRC</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2019/from-my-sent-folder-on-mozilla-and-irc.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.chriskrycho.com/2018/assumed-audiences.html"&gt;Assumed Audience&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/b&gt; anyone who cares about the success of free and open-source software.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;A New Rustacean listener sent me a note lamenting the way &lt;a href="https://blog.rust-lang.org/2019/04/26/Mozilla-IRC-Sunset-and-the-Rust-Channel.html"&gt;Mozilla’s transition from IRC to Discord&lt;/a&gt;—i.e., from an open protocol to a proprietary service. For many advocates of free software, this is a deeply unsettling move. The kind listener who sent me an email pointed to &lt;a href="https://matrix.org/blog/index"&gt;Matrix&lt;/a&gt;, an open-protocol service, and noted: “perhaps the default web interface is slightly less slick, but there’s not much in it, and it’s open source.” I sympathize with them, but also had a few &lt;em&gt;other&lt;/em&gt; thoughts. My reply is reproduced below.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yeah, it’s complicated for sure. The last time I looked, Matrix’s mobile clients were so bad as to be effectively unusable; I know that was one of the considerations for the Rust move to Discord.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It seems to me that a lot of folks committed to free and open-source have ended up wanting free-as-in-beer as well as free-as-in-speech, and the combo of that with the existing market dynamics means that good is rarely open/free-as-in-speech, and vice versa. It’s a Gordian knot I don’t see an easy way through.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The specific dynamic you highlight with docs is a prime example of the other cultural challenges I see, too: devs don’t like writing docs, they like writing code… but it turns out that docs and other “soft” things—including, yes, &lt;abbr&gt;UI&lt;/abbr&gt; polish!—are actually as or more important for adoption as things like protocols.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We’ll see this same cycle repeat until free and open source software advocates learn to prioritize the things users actually value as well as the things they (we!) believe they should value.&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 30 Apr 2019 08:25:00 -0400</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2019-04-30:/2019/from-my-sent-folder-on-mozilla-and-irc.html</guid><category>open-source software</category><category>free software</category><category>from my sent folder</category><category>UI</category></item></channel></rss>