<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Chris Krycho - getting things done</title><link>http://v4.chriskrycho.com/</link><description></description><lastBuildDate>Wed, 31 Jul 2019 18:30:00 -0400</lastBuildDate><item><title>A Healthier Calendar</title><link>http://v4.chriskrycho.com/2019/a-healthier-calendar.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;a href="https://v4.chriskrycho.com/2018/assumed-audiences.html"&gt;Assumed Audience&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/b&gt; people already persuaded of the value—at least to some extent—of “getting things done” strategies and having an idea of what you accomplished over the course of the year.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the things I’ve found over the last couple months is that my calendar is increasingly &lt;em&gt;full&lt;/em&gt;—full of meetings with this person or that team. This is not unexpected in an organization as large as LinkedIn, and I had a feeling I’d probably run into this as I transitioned from &lt;i&gt;new guy on the block&lt;/i&gt; to &lt;i&gt;someone whose expertise people want&lt;/i&gt;. That it’s happening means I’m doing my job: I am in a &lt;em&gt;leadership&lt;/em&gt; role, and my team’s customers are other developers! It’s important for me to be a resource to other people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, I am not a manager, and have no desire to be a manager. That means that it’s also important that I not &lt;em&gt;only&lt;/em&gt; be a resource to other people. I also need to continue doing technical work myself, and indeed &lt;em&gt;growing&lt;/em&gt; technically myself. It’s impossible to do that when each day is punctuated by anywhere between 2 and 8 meetings, often in no particular arrangement. Building software &lt;em&gt;well&lt;/em&gt;, like most other non-managerial work, requires time to think and sustained attention to a specific problem. Even for relatively straightforward programming tasks, half-hour blocks with meetings in between just won’t do it.&lt;a href="#fn1" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref1" role="doc-noteref"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;aside&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To be clear, some parts of managerial require that as well, but much of managerial work is &lt;em&gt;coordinative&lt;/em&gt;: that is, it is much more focused on connecting the right people and getting them the right information. That’s necessarily heavy on things which require talking with people and lighter on things which require sitting down and thinking about them uninterrupted for hours on end. What’s more: that work is &lt;em&gt;incredibly&lt;/em&gt; important, especially in larger companies and organizations. Engineers (like me!) who are interested in the technical problems can often be blind to the importance of non-technical solutions. In reality, good management &lt;em&gt;enables&lt;/em&gt; good engineering work, and good engineering work is responsive to the inputs communicated by good management! The two are complementary.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/aside&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This week was the tipping point for me. I’ve had multiple meetings every single day, and &lt;em&gt;no&lt;/em&gt; sustained blocks for working except in the early morning before any colleagues were working. My progress on a feature I’m implementing has been predictably slow as a result. While many of the meetings I have had were somewhat or even &lt;em&gt;very&lt;/em&gt; valuable, many others were in the dread urgent-but-not-important bucket.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My solution is one I’ve employed before when similarly starting to get over-busy: &lt;em&gt;book myself&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;a href="#fn2" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref2" role="doc-noteref"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; People check my calendar to see when I’m available for meetings, so I have simply blocked out large stretches of my time under the heading Getting Things Done. I left open a few hours each day for people to book meetings with me—remember: it’s part of my job to help others, too!—and of course I have recurring team and project meetings. But outside of those, I now have time allocated to do the hard technical work I was hired to do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When someone wants to book a meeting with me, there are times available to them. Importantly, they’re in times of day when I know from experience that I &lt;em&gt;won’t&lt;/em&gt; be effective on hard technical work anyway. And if someone ever complains that I’m not &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; busy in those slots I have booked, I’ll remind them that in fact I &lt;em&gt;am&lt;/em&gt; busy: busy doing the &lt;em&gt;other&lt;/em&gt; parts of the job for which I was hired!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I encourage you to do the same. Use your calendar’s tools to carve out time for things that are genuinely important—not just what others think is urgent. Make space for deep work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn1" role="doc-endnote"&gt;&lt;p&gt;You might be curious how that maps to &lt;a href="https://v4.chriskrycho.com/pomodoro/"&gt;my habit of doing pomodoro sessions&lt;/a&gt;. The difference is that 25 minutes of hard thinking with 5 minutes of mental rest and then diving back in for another session &lt;em&gt;enables&lt;/em&gt; deep thought for sustained periods. They allow me to keep pushing on a problem without hitting a mental wall. From experience, I can say that a 5-minute break—especially if I’m walking!—does not cause me to lose context, but in fact simply re-energizes me and often provides new insights into the problem. By contrast, 30-minute blocks interrupted by 30 minutes or more of &lt;em&gt;meetings&lt;/em&gt; mean I lose all my working memory and therefore context. 5 minutes is very different from 30, and a meeting is not a walk! What’s more: meetings are &lt;em&gt;very&lt;/em&gt; rarely generative of insights into problems I’m working on (unless they’re &lt;em&gt;about&lt;/em&gt; that problem).&lt;a href="#fnref1" class="footnote-back" role="doc-backlink"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn2" role="doc-endnote"&gt;&lt;p&gt;In a healthier culture, like the one the folks at Basecamp &lt;a href="https://m.signalvnoise.com/wait-other-people-can-take-your-time/"&gt;have built&lt;/a&gt;, this might not be quite as necessary. Certainly I think our culture could improve in the direction of defaulting to how Basecamp does things calendar-wise. But also: Basecamp has 50 employees; there are more engineers than that on the app my team supports! &lt;em&gt;Some&lt;/em&gt; of these dynamics are simply a matter of scale. If you want to argue that no company should ever be the size of LinkedIn, of course, that’s a possible solution. As much as I share a hostility to scale-for-scale’s sake, though, I also think there can be something &lt;em&gt;good&lt;/em&gt; in large groups of people collaborating to do something far bigger than a small group can accomplish. There are goods in &lt;em&gt;both&lt;/em&gt; of these approaches. There are also negatives. The key, in this broken world, is learning to encourage the goods and minimize the negatives.&lt;a href="#fnref2" class="footnote-back" role="doc-backlink"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 31 Jul 2019 18:30:00 -0400</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:v4.chriskrycho.com,2019-07-31:/2019/a-healthier-calendar.html</guid><category>getting things done</category><category>productivity</category></item><item><title>Update: Writing Down What I Do</title><link>http://v4.chriskrycho.com/2019/update-writing-down-what-i-do.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;a href="https://v4.chriskrycho.com/2018/assumed-audiences.html"&gt;Assumed Audience&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/b&gt; people already persuaded of the value—at least to some extent—of “getting things done” strategies and having an idea of what you accomplished over the course of the year.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A few months ago, I described &lt;a href="https://v4.chriskrycho.com/2018/just-write-down-what-you-do.html"&gt;my current workflow&lt;/a&gt; for tracking what I do every day, using &lt;a href="https://bear.app"&gt;Bear&lt;/a&gt;. I’m still doing that, but I’ve made one small tweak that makes for a &lt;em&gt;much&lt;/em&gt; nicer experience, and I figured I’d write that up for anyone else who’s thinking about using Bear in a similar way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The main pain point I’d had using Bear as a daily logging app is that I &lt;em&gt;also&lt;/em&gt; use it for &lt;a href="https://v4.chriskrycho.com/zettelkasten/"&gt;my general note-taking&lt;/a&gt;, and I increasingly found that my pomodoro logs ended up mostly being &lt;em&gt;clutter&lt;/em&gt; in my overall list of notes. I also realized that I don’t look at, say, my daily logs past the end of a week, weekly logs past the end of the month, and so on. However, I &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt; like keeping them around through at least the end of my performance review cycle in case I want to drill down into more details about a particular task or accomplishment. I wasn’t really sure how to enjoy both long-term access and shoretr-term eliminating of clutter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then I noticed that Bear has an Archive function:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src="https://cdn.chriskrycho.com/file/chriskrycho-com/images/archive-bear.png" alt="Archiving in Bear" /&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Archiving in Bear&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Archiving removes your notes from your normal list view and makes them non-editable. However, they remain searchable in your library and wiki-style navigation links, like &lt;code&gt;[[2019.07.21]]&lt;/code&gt;, still work. This is &lt;em&gt;exactly&lt;/em&gt; what I wanted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once I discovered this, I made one very small tweak to my previous flow: whenever I do the work of summarizing a given time-span, I simply archive all the notes at the level below that. So, for example, after copying the daily summaries into a week and summarizing that week, I simply archive all the day entries. Any given set of logs only ever has a handful of notes in it—at most 12, in the case of my year-level log. This made the already-great experience of using Bear for this kind of logging that much better. Again: I commend it to you!&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 29 Jul 2019 19:25:00 -0400</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:v4.chriskrycho.com,2019-07-29:/2019/update-writing-down-what-i-do.html</guid><category>productivity</category><category>pomodoro</category><category>getting things done</category></item><item><title>Just Write Down What You Do</title><link>http://v4.chriskrycho.com/2018/just-write-down-what-you-do.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;i class=editorial&gt;&lt;b&gt;Assumed audience:&lt;/b&gt; people already persuaded of the value—at least to some extent—of “getting things done” strategies and having an idea of what you accomplished over the course of the year.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the last few years, I’ve had a habit—not kept perfectly, but done more often than not, courtesy of my daily &lt;a href="https://v4.chriskrycho.com/pomodoro/"&gt;pomodoro&lt;/a&gt; discipline—of writing down what I do each day. Then, every week, I take a look at what I did each day, and turn that into a summary for the week. And every month, I look over my notes for weeks that made up that month, and write down what I did that month.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This has been &lt;em&gt;fantastic&lt;/em&gt; for me professionally. For one thing, it gives me a quick and easy way to see what I’ve done over the past however-long-between-performance-evaluations. The inevitable “What did you accomplish this year?” question has an an easy answer: I can look over my month-level summaries and summarize &lt;em&gt;those&lt;/em&gt;. (I’m inevitably frustrated by the months where I slacked off and don’t actually know what I did when do this exercise!)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Writing things down like this is also a helpful tool personally. I can look back at long stretches where I feel like I didn’t get a lot done and realize just many things I &lt;em&gt;did&lt;/em&gt; actually do. I have found this a helpful way of staving off the malaise that inevitably comes from months where there are just too many meetings, for example. What did I do? I &lt;i&gt;effected these changes&lt;/i&gt; (even if they weren’t in the form of code!).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I use &lt;a href="https://bear.app"&gt;Bear&lt;/a&gt; for this, but you could do it anywhere: a Word document or Google Doc, a notepad on your desk, in Emacs’ &lt;a href="https://orgmode.org"&gt;Org Mode&lt;/a&gt;, with &lt;a href="https://www.taskpaper.com"&gt;TaskPaper&lt;/a&gt;, or in &lt;a href="#"&gt;Trello&lt;/a&gt; (like my friend and colleague Ben Collins &lt;a href="https://benjamincollins.com/blog/using-trello-to-organize-my-daily-work/"&gt;does&lt;/a&gt;), or, well… whatever gets the job done.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The main thing is: write down what you did! Write it down at each of these scales, because it’s far easier to write down the larger scales if you wrote down the smaller scales. Once you start doing this regularly, you’ll probably find yourself frustrated at the times you failed to do it. (If you’re like me, those times will exist. It’s okay. Just start back up.) And again: make it fit you. But it’s one of the best tools I know of for personal and professional development, so I commend it to you!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;section id="bonus-my-bear-templates" class="level2"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Bonus: My Bear Templates&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In case you’re curious or want to copy my approach, here are the templates I use in Bear for each of my logs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section id="daily-log" class="level3"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Daily Log&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The daily log is the core of my entire productivity approach system, as well as the foundation of this specific logging strategy. These entries each includes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The date, which I format &lt;code&gt;YYYY.MM.DD&lt;/code&gt;—today would be &lt;code&gt;2018.11.13&lt;/code&gt;. A numeric year/month/day makes correctly sorting the notes easy. I use a period for the separator mostly because it looks nice in the font I use in Bear.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;A link to the parent week for the day, to make it easy to jump back and forth between individual day logs and a weekly log (as you’ll see below).&lt;a href="#fn1" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref1" role="doc-noteref"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;A set of goals. I set the goals either at the beginning of the day, at the end of the preceding work day, or a combination of the two. I usually limit myself to 3 goals, unless I &lt;em&gt;know&lt;/em&gt; I have a bunch of very small tasks.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;A list of pomodoro sessions. The pomodoro technique is &lt;em&gt;most&lt;/em&gt; effective for getting things done—both in my experience and as others describe it—when each block has both a discrete goal and what you actually got done. This helps me keep my focus during that session rather than getting sidetracked. I further break these down with &lt;strong&gt;Session 1&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;Break&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;Session 2&lt;/strong&gt;, etc. subheads—not because this makes me productive, but just because I like it.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;A summary of the day as a whole. At the end of the day, I look back over the sessions and my goals, and write a sentence or two about what I did. This is also often a good time for me to write up the next day’s overarching goals and first session goal: I have a much better idea what I should be doing next when I’m wrapping things up for the day than I will the next morning!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;A set of checkboxes for me to track whether I succeed in breaking my day into 15 discrete pomodoro sessions,&lt;a href="#fn2" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref2" role="doc-noteref"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and in standing at least 5 hours out of the day every day.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;pre class="md"&gt;&lt;code&gt;# &amp;lt;YYYY.MM.DD&amp;gt;

**Week:** [[]]

## Goals

- [ ] ::TODO::

---

## Details
### Session 1

1. **Goal:** ::TODO:: **Actual:** ::TODO::

---

## Summary

::TODO::

---

## Rhythm
### Pomodoro

- [ ] 1
- [ ] 2
- [ ] 3
- [ ] 4
- [ ] 5
- [ ] 6
- [ ] 7
- [ ] 8
- [ ] 9
- [ ] 10
- [ ] 11
- [ ] 12
- [ ] 13
- [ ] 14
- [ ] 15

### Stand

- [ ] 1
- [ ] 2
- [ ] 3
- [ ] 4
- [ ] 5
- [ ] 6
- [ ] 7
- [ ] 8
- [ ] 9
- [ ] 10&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="weekly-log" class="level3"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Weekly log&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The weekly log is just a place for me to be able to easily capture the results of my daily efforts. It links to the monthly log at the top just like the daily logs link to the month: for easy jumping back and forth. Each of the bullet points under &lt;strong&gt;Details&lt;/strong&gt; gets linked to a daily log entry, and the &lt;code&gt;::TODO::&lt;/code&gt; items get replaced with the &lt;strong&gt;Summary&lt;/strong&gt; from the daily log. At the end of the week, I write a summary of the whole week.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;Goals&lt;/strong&gt; heading here is new, something I only just started doing in the last couple of weeks, but so far it has proven helpful for me as I orient myself to what I want to get done on any given day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="md"&gt;&lt;code&gt;# &amp;lt;YYYY.MM.DD&amp;gt; – &amp;lt;YYYY.MM.DD&amp;gt;

**Month:** [[]]

## Goals

- [ ] ::TODO::

## Details

- [[]]: ::TODO::
- [[]]: ::TODO::
- [[]]: ::TODO::
- [[]]: ::TODO::
- [[]]: ::TODO::

## Summary

::TODO::&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="monthly-log" class="level3"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Monthly log&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The monthly log is exactly like the weekly log, but one level higher. It links back to individual weeks for easy jumping back and forth between the two views, and it newly has month-level goals. (As with weeks, I’m still experimenting with those!) The &lt;strong&gt;Details&lt;/strong&gt; bullets get filled in with links to weeks and the summary of each week copied over. At the end of the month, I take a few minutes to summarize those weeks. Unlike the lower-level summaries, I let that month-level summary expand out to a paragraph if need be. A lot tends to happen in a month!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="md"&gt;&lt;code&gt;# &amp;lt;YYYY.MM&amp;gt;

## Goals

- [ ] ::TODO::

## Details

- [[]]: ::TODO::
- [[]]: ::TODO::
- [[]]: ::TODO::
- [[]]: ::TODO::

## Summary

::TODO::&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn1" role="doc-endnote"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[[&amp;lt;some text&amp;gt;]]&lt;/code&gt; is Bear’s way of doing internal links to a note named &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;some text&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;a href="#fnref1" class="footnote-back" role="doc-backlink"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn2" role="doc-endnote"&gt;&lt;p&gt;15, not 16, because of the slop that ends up in most days. Most days, more than one session ends up being 35 minutes instead of 25. Over the course of the day, those come out to being the remaining half hour in the full 8 hours I make sure I give my employer. I know that from measuring consistently when I was working as a consultant: my &lt;a href="https://toggl.com"&gt;Toggl&lt;/a&gt; logs told the story clearly.&lt;a href="#fnref2" class="footnote-back" role="doc-backlink"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 13 Nov 2018 19:50:00 -0500</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:v4.chriskrycho.com,2018-11-13:/2018/just-write-down-what-you-do.html</guid><category>career</category><category>productivity</category><category>getting things done</category></item></channel></rss>