<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Chris Krycho - hardware</title><link>http://v4.chriskrycho.com/</link><description></description><lastBuildDate>Sun, 11 Nov 2018 21:20:00 -0500</lastBuildDate><item><title>The Apple Magic Keyboard</title><link>http://v4.chriskrycho.com/2018/the-apple-magic-keyboard.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Assumed audience: nerds who care about keyboards, most of whom will probably think I’m crazy for my views in this post.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was sitting at my kitchen counter this evening, doing a mishmash of things—from writing a little Rust, to sending some text messages to my family, to leaving a note on a programming forum. The whole time, I’ve just had this quiet sense of deep pleasure about the typing. I was slightly confused about why I was enjoying the feel of the &lt;em&gt;typing&lt;/em&gt; specifically… until I realized what exactly I was typing on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m sitting in front of a 2015 MacBook Pro… but I’m not typing on that keyboard. I’m typing on the &lt;a href="https://www.apple.com/shop/product/MLA22LL/A/magic-keyboard-us-english"&gt;Apple Magic Keyboard&lt;/a&gt; instead, which I brought upstairs from its normal perch on my desk and started using &lt;em&gt;everywhere&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;a href="#fn1" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref1" role="doc-noteref"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This keyboard is &lt;em&gt;perfect&lt;/em&gt; for me. It’s not what other people love, I know—people who prefer “mechanical keyboards” find it far too shallow. But there is something about the feeling of typing on this particular keyboard that I simply love. For me, it’s a perfect bit of industrial design, because it simultaneously &lt;i&gt;looks good&lt;/i&gt; and &lt;i&gt;works exactly the way I want it to&lt;/i&gt;, right down to the feeling of every keystroke.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mechanical keyboard lovers: you can keep your Cherry Blues. I’ll just stockpile Apple Magic Keyboards and be happy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;P.S. Apple should totally just figure out how to put &lt;em&gt;exactly&lt;/em&gt; this keyboard in their next-generation MacBook Pros. They won’t. But they should.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn1" role="doc-endnote"&gt;&lt;p&gt;What prompted it? I ordered a stand for it for all the times I’m not at my desk with its 5k monitor. And then just decided it was worth doing this way &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; the time.&lt;a href="#fnref1" class="footnote-back" role="doc-backlink"&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 11 Nov 2018 21:20:00 -0500</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:v4.chriskrycho.com,2018-11-11:/2018/the-apple-magic-keyboard.html</guid><category>design</category><category>hardware</category></item></channel></rss>