<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Chris Krycho</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/</link><description></description><atom:link href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/feeds/kate.xml" rel="self"></atom:link><lastBuildDate>Mon, 14 Jul 2014 23:15:00 -0400</lastBuildDate><item><title>Whiplash</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2014/whiplash.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;I have a pretty severe case of emotional whiplash&lt;sup id="fnref:1"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:1" rel="footnote"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; at the moment. In the last
eight hours, I have gone from jubilant to the most worried I have ever been to
simple, utter&amp;nbsp;exhaustion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This afternoon, I heard back from a then-potential and now-actual client who
hired me and a friend to design and build a web application for them. They are
going to pay us a substantial sum to do it. This is &lt;em&gt;fantastic&lt;/em&gt;. I have been
hoping this particular opportunity would come through, because everything about
it is appealing to me. It is an interesting application; I like the material it
involves (a &lt;em&gt;lot&lt;/em&gt;); I will learn a bit along the way; I will get to stretch my
front-end design chops again; I will make some seriously good money at it. I am,
in a word,&amp;nbsp;stoked.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fast forward four and a half hours. Jaimie and I are helping Ellie wrap up her
evening activities and getting ready to take her upstairs and put her to bed.
Kate is lying in a little sleep-rocker&amp;#8212;her favorite spot to sleep during the
day. She makes a bit of a coughing noise; we note it but think little of it
(babies &lt;em&gt;often&lt;/em&gt; make that kind of noise). A few minutes later, Jaimie is walking
by and glances at Kate. Our baby girl is bright red and turning purple. She
grabs her. &amp;#8220;Kate! Breathe! Breathe, little girl!&amp;#8221; She isn&amp;#8217;t breathing; she is
getting upset but she isn&amp;#8217;t crying. (Babies cry at the drop of a hat.) Little
bubbles at her mouth. Jaimie is doing the baby variation of the Heimlich
maneuver. I am nearly helpless; I keep using my finger to pull Kate&amp;#8217;s mouth
open; she finally latches onto the finger, starts sucking, and&amp;nbsp;breathes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thank&amp;nbsp;God.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We hold her. She breathes&amp;#8212;&lt;em&gt;mostly&lt;/em&gt; normally. We keep paying close attention to
her. The couple times I let her lay down on her back she starts seizing up and
turning red again within a few minutes until I pick her up and pat her
vigorously and she calms down again. We manage to get Ellie in bed. We call the
doctor; she sends us to the hospital. A friend comes to watch Ellie and we run
out the door. It is a 30-minute drive (and I am speeding, and Jaimie is holding
Kate to make sure she keeps breathing).&lt;sup id="fnref:2"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:2" rel="footnote"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Kate wheezes off and on the whole
way there. She still isn&amp;#8217;t crying, and she should be. She hasn&amp;#8217;t eaten in six
hours; she should be hungry. Why isn&amp;#8217;t she&amp;nbsp;hungry?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They admit us. They get all her vitals. The doctor is a kind, soft-spoken man
with the last name Saad; I like him. He asks dozens of good questions. He tells
us, &amp;#8220;95&amp;#8211;99% of the time, this is just reflux. We just care about that other 1%
of the time.&amp;#8221; There is no reliable way to stop a baby from choking on milk she
spits up because of reflux.&lt;sup id="fnref:3"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:3" rel="footnote"&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; They are going to do an &lt;span class="caps"&gt;EKG&lt;/span&gt; and chest X-rays
just to make sure she is&amp;nbsp;okay.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She seems to be okay. She is eating again&amp;#8212;like a champ, like she normally
does, like she should&amp;nbsp;be.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I go home to relieve the wonderful friends who are sitting in our house to make
sure Ellie is fine. Ellie is still sleeping.&amp;nbsp;Good.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Breathe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whiplash. I am no less excited about that project. And my youngest daughter
almost died tonight. Had she started choking while we were upstairs, or while we
were all asleep tonight, God only knows what would have happened. We are
grateful to God that we were feet away from Kate, that Jaimie &amp;#8220;happened&amp;#8221; to look
at her just then. We are grateful, too, for the extra money coming in; it will
help with the so-very-worth-it-but-not-easy-on-a-seminary-budget cost of an
emergency room&amp;nbsp;visit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ice&amp;nbsp;cream.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think I&amp;#8217;m going to sleep now. Hopefully tomorrow is less&amp;nbsp;extreme.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So much so that I am having a hard time spelling &amp;#8220;whiplash&amp;#8221; correctly. I
keep typing &amp;#8220;whiplast&amp;#8221;.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:2"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If a police officer stops us, I will explain. He or she will understand.
They will help us get to the hospital faster.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:2" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 2 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:3"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Terrifying, just a bit? Yes.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:3" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 3 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 14 Jul 2014 23:15:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2014-07-14:2014/whiplash.html</guid><category>family</category><category>Kate</category></item></channel></rss>