<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Chris Krycho</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/</link><description></description><atom:link href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/feeds/kate.xml" rel="self"></atom:link><lastBuildDate>Wed, 30 Sep 2015 06:29:00 -0400</lastBuildDate><item><title>2015-09-30 06:29</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2015/2015-09-30-0629.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;This week Kate learned to walk. Also, she decided to go on a goldfish-and-hotdogs-only food strike, and to wake up at 11pm and cry, shout, and scream for over an hour multiple nights this week. You win some, you lose some?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id="references" class="references"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 30 Sep 2015 06:29:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2015-09-30:2015/2015-09-30-0629.html</guid><category>family</category><category>kate</category></item><item><title>2015-09-01 19:19</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2015/2015-09-01-1919.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Observation: it is extremely difficult to compose when you have a(n adorable) one-year-old competing for the piano keys…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="references"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 01 Sep 2015 19:19:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2015-09-01:2015/2015-09-01-1919.html</guid><category>music</category><category>kate</category></item><item><title>2015-08-08 06:42</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2015/2015-08-08-0642.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Ellie and Kate &lt;em&gt;consistently&lt;/em&gt; get up half an hour to an hour earlier on Saturday mornings than any other day of the week. Coincidentally—&lt;em&gt;or is it?&lt;/em&gt;—Saturday is also the only day we try to sleep in. It’s like they know, and plot against us!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="references"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 08 Aug 2015 06:42:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2015-08-08:2015/2015-08-08-0642.html</guid><category>family</category><category>kate</category><category>ellie</category></item><item><title>2015-08-04 18:55</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2015/2015-08-04-1855.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;A minute ago, Ellie asked me to play with her and Kate. I started to answer, “No, I need to finish publishing Winning Slowly.” Then I remembered: putting that first would be pretty much &lt;em&gt;exactly the opposite&lt;/em&gt; of &lt;a href="http://www.winningslowly.org/1.02" title="1.02: On Family"&gt;Winning Slowly&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id="references" class="references"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 04 Aug 2015 18:55:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2015-08-04:2015/2015-08-04-1855.html</guid><category>family</category><category>ellie</category><category>kate</category><category>podcasting</category></item><item><title>2015-07-01 14:24</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2015/2015-07-01-1424.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;I want so much to grind some of this single-origin decaf coffee and drink it right now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But my 1-year-old is asleep downstairs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So: &lt;em&gt;nope&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="references"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 01 Jul 2015 14:24:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2015-07-01:2015/2015-07-01-1424.html</guid><category>coffee</category><category>kate</category></item><item><title>2015-06-17 05:36</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2015/2015-06-17-0536.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Kate kept us up late last night (no idea why). And we ran out of coffee yesterday. It’s going to be a long day…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="references"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 17 Jun 2015 05:36:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2015-06-17:2015/2015-06-17-0536.html</guid><category>coffee</category><category>Kate</category></item><item><title>2015-06-15 05:35</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2015/2015-06-15-0535.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Our youngest has been sleeping through the night for a week now. Going to bed at 9:45 &amp;amp; getting up at 5:15 is suddenly doable again. Huzzah!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="references"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 15 Jun 2015 05:35:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2015-06-15:2015/2015-06-15-0535.html</guid><category>family</category><category>kate</category></item><item><title>The State of Our Family in Early 2015</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2015/early-2015-family.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;It has been a &lt;em&gt;long&lt;/em&gt; time since I wrote a family update here, and I skipped the Christmas letter this year because I was exhausted. I resolved at the beginning of the year to write at least one update every month, though. I want these updates here for &lt;em&gt;myself&lt;/em&gt;, if for no other reason. (Then, of course, I promptly missed January, but this is counting for that; there will be another post here at the end of the month.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What have we been up to, you ask? Well, quite a lot! Since the last time I wrote a blog post, we had a baby, who is now crawling around. (If you’re reading this, you probably already know that, of course.) Ellie is talking, constantly practicing saying things the right way and asking the names of things; Kate is scooting around the floor exploring everything and is increasingly verbal herself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They love playing together. Ellie and Kate are good friends—a while back Jaimie heard Ellie quietly talking to Katie in the back seat of the car, repeating, “You’re my best friend, Kate.” Sometimes when Ellie gives Kate a hug and a kiss goodnight every night, Kate goes into the most adorable squeals of delight. Indeed, no one elicits those squeals as much as Ellie. In addition to her scooting around the floor, Kate is happily eating solid foods—and the girl &lt;em&gt;loves&lt;/em&gt; her food. Today I put her in her high chair and she started laughing as I put the tray in front of her. She often thumps the tray, the table, or the floor to express her joy. And last but not least, this little gal is &lt;em&gt;strong&lt;/em&gt;. Her favorite time is getting in a bouncer and jumping for as long as we will let her.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src="/images/girls-games.jpg" title="My ladies playing Lego Star Wars"/&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;
My ladies playing &lt;i&gt;Lego Star Wars&lt;/i&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have been teaching Ellie a lot. Jaimie has slowly started working through the ABCs with her. She can count to 5, and she knows her way to 10, but sometimes gets sidetracked along the way. She is learning her colors and spent a while defaulting to calling everything “pink”… except for her favorite &lt;em&gt;purple&lt;/em&gt; dress. In the last month, she has started being able to identify the colors more reliably, along with lots of shapes. She loves cars and trucks and especially buses and fire trucks. She sings to herself and dances all the time. She loves building with blocks. She is learning to say “please” and “thank you”—learning, in this case, not because she doesn’t know how but because she has started &lt;em&gt;forgetting&lt;/em&gt;. She is learning to pray and to sing to God and learning the answer to simple questions like, “Who made you, Ellie?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jaimie has continued to write off and on, though the first many months we had Kate it was much spottier than it had been. She’s working on secret projects that are making her happy, and that makes me happy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As for why she didn’t get as much time, I was &lt;em&gt;busy&lt;/em&gt; last semester. I picked up a second contract, building the new &lt;a href="//holybible.com"&gt;HolyBible.com&lt;/a&gt;, and between that and my ongoing contract work and my one class, I pulled a lot of 50–60 hour weeks. That’s not particularly an experience we are keen to repeat, but it was the right call at the time: we were able to save up the money to fill up our six-month emergency fund and to pay for the rest of seminary. This semester is going a bit easier: I am taking Hebrew III and Baptist History and working ~30 hours a week instead of ~50–55. I &lt;em&gt;love&lt;/em&gt; my language classes; without a doubt Hebrew III and Greek III have been my very favorite classes since I started seminary.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I ran another half marathon in November, and set a PR at 1:25:37—a 6:32/mile pace. I was super happy with that outcome, and I plan to run the same race again for the third year in a row this coming fall, Lord willing. In the meantime, I have started swimming and cycling regularly with the aim of completing my first triathlon early this summer. (I’m going to stick to a short “sprint” tri to start, and work up from there.) While I love running, I would like to have the use of my joints in twenty (and forty, and sixty) years, and accordingly I need to make sure I do not keep putting over 1,000 miles a year on my legs. I have been going to a spinning class to get my legs in better cycling shape for the last month (and the last two weeks Jaimie has come with me!). We have also been doing a Pilates class weekly; my back needs to be a lot stronger and my legs a lot looser, and that is helping quite a bit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We continue to be extremely happy in our church here, FBC Durham. God has used our church to encourage and challenge us in a wide variety of ways—too many (and perhaps in many cases too subtle) even to summarize. We are excited to see what the years ahead hold for us there, as the church itself continues to flourish and grow and we seek opportunities to continue serving and building up this particular outpost of the body of Christ.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In short, life is &lt;em&gt;good&lt;/em&gt;. It is not perfect, of course; I long for Jesus’ return and the New Heavens and New Earth more and more all the time. But we see God’s faithfulness and goodness in the hard months no less than in the easy ones. We see the Spirit working in our hearts to make us more like Christ, and it is good.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I could go on, but a thousand words is enough. More again, and sooner than the last gap!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="references"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2015 20:30:00 -0500</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2015-02-10:2015/early-2015-family.html</guid><category>family</category><category>Ellie</category><category>Kate</category><category>Jaimie</category></item><item><title>Whiplash</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2014/whiplash.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;I have a pretty severe case of emotional whiplash&lt;a href="#fn1" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref1"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; at the moment. In the last eight hours, I have gone from jubilant to the most worried I have ever been to simple, utter exhaustion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This afternoon, I heard back from a then-potential and now-actual client who hired me and a friend to design and build a web application for them. They are going to pay us a substantial sum to do it. This is &lt;em&gt;fantastic&lt;/em&gt;. I have been hoping this particular opportunity would come through, because everything about it is appealing to me. It is an interesting application; I like the material it involves (a &lt;em&gt;lot&lt;/em&gt;); I will learn a bit along the way; I will get to stretch my front-end design chops again; I will make some seriously good money at it. I am, in a word, stoked.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fast forward four and a half hours. Jaimie and I are helping Ellie wrap up her evening activities and getting ready to take her upstairs and put her to bed. Kate is lying in a little sleep-rocker—her favorite spot to sleep during the day. She makes a bit of a coughing noise; we note it but think little of it (babies &lt;em&gt;often&lt;/em&gt; make that kind of noise). A few minutes later, Jaimie is walking by and glances at Kate. Our baby girl is bright red and turning purple. She grabs her. “Kate! Breathe! Breathe, little girl!” She isn’t breathing; she is getting upset but she isn’t crying. (Babies cry at the drop of a hat.) Little bubbles at her mouth. Jaimie is doing the baby variation of the Heimlich maneuver. I am nearly helpless; I keep using my finger to pull Kate’s mouth open; she finally latches onto the finger, starts sucking, and breathes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thank God.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We hold her. She breathes—&lt;em&gt;mostly&lt;/em&gt; normally. We keep paying close attention to her. The couple times I let her lay down on her back she starts seizing up and turning red again within a few minutes until I pick her up and pat her vigorously and she calms down again. We manage to get Ellie in bed. We call the doctor; she sends us to the hospital. A friend comes to watch Ellie and we run out the door. It is a 30-minute drive (and I am speeding, and Jaimie is holding Kate to make sure she keeps breathing).&lt;a href="#fn2" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref2"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; Kate wheezes off and on the whole way there. She still isn’t crying, and she should be. She hasn’t eaten in six hours; she should be hungry. Why isn’t she hungry?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They admit us. They get all her vitals. The doctor is a kind, soft-spoken man with the last name Saad; I like him. He asks dozens of good questions. He tells us, “95–99% of the time, this is just reflux. We just care about that other 1% of the time.” There is no reliable way to stop a baby from choking on milk she spits up because of reflux.&lt;a href="#fn3" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref3"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; They are going to do an EKG and chest X-rays just to make sure she is okay.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She seems to be okay. She is eating again—like a champ, like she normally does, like she should be.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I go home to relieve the wonderful friends who are sitting in our house to make sure Ellie is fine. Ellie is still sleeping. Good.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Breathe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whiplash. I am no less excited about that project. And my youngest daughter almost died tonight. Had she started choking while we were upstairs, or while we were all asleep tonight, God only knows what would have happened. We are grateful to God that we were feet away from Kate, that Jaimie “happened” to look at her just then. We are grateful, too, for the extra money coming in; it will help with the so-very-worth-it-but-not-easy-on-a-seminary-budget cost of an emergency room visit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ice cream.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think I’m going to sleep now. Hopefully tomorrow is less extreme.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="references"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;section class="footnotes"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn1"&gt;&lt;p&gt;So much so that I am having a hard time spelling “whiplash” correctly. I keep typing “whiplast”.&lt;a href="#fnref1"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn2"&gt;&lt;p&gt;If a police officer stops us, I will explain. He or she will understand. They will help us get to the hospital faster.&lt;a href="#fnref2"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn3"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Terrifying, just a bit? Yes.&lt;a href="#fnref3"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 14 Jul 2014 23:15:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2014-07-14:2014/whiplash.html</guid><category>family</category><category>Kate</category></item></channel></rss>