<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Chris Krycho - learning</title><link>http://v4.chriskrycho.com/</link><description></description><lastBuildDate>Mon, 11 Nov 2019 20:55:00 -0500</lastBuildDate><item><title>Four Miscellanies</title><link>http://v4.chriskrycho.com/2019/four-miscellanies.html</link><description>&lt;section id="i.-another-thing-word-count-goals-are-bad-at" class="level2"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;I. Another thing word count goals are bad at&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="line-block"&gt;Poetry!&lt;br /&gt;
In some (important) sense&lt;br /&gt;
the core of the art is&lt;br /&gt;
brevity&lt;br /&gt;
so word count goals&lt;br /&gt;
best come inverted&lt;br /&gt;
if they come at all&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="ii.-an-answer-to-craig-mods-question" class="level2"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;II. An answer to Craig Mod’s question&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ve been reading Craig Mod’s fabulous &lt;a href="https://craigmod.com/ridgeline/"&gt;Ridgeline&lt;/a&gt; newsletter all year. It’s a letter about walking—kind of. That’s the jumping off-point, anyway. Mod asked a question, back at the beginning of the newsletter, and I kept thinking about answering it but never getting around to it, until in today’s issue he poked and prodded: “Just reply to this email with a sentence or two. Brevity is godliness. Don’t overthink!” So, I did:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wasn’t always a walker (though I grew up in a family that loved hiking and even backpacking). I got to running first, in fact. But I picked up the habit during my years in seminary: looooong days of reading and writing for school and programming for work, needing to somehow keep my brain moving—and finding that getting my body moving did the trick better than anything else. 25 minutes of work, 5 minutes of walk. Repeat. Circumlocute the little mall where the coffee shop is a few dozen times. Walk a few miles in a day. Body loose, mind still working, even 12 hours along. And it stuck—so you’ll still find me, even on a cold Colorado winter morning, bundling up and stepping out of the house and walking halfway down our street and back.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="iii.-keeping-learning" class="level2"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;III. Keeping learning&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My friend &lt;a href="https://benmakuh.com"&gt;Ben&lt;/a&gt;—look at that lovely new website! He just relaunched it—sent me &lt;a href="https://www.wix.engineering/post/breaking-chains-with-pipelines-in-modern-javascript"&gt;an interesting article&lt;/a&gt; tonight, and it was the straw that broke the camel’s back, where by “broke the camel’s back” I actually mean something much less… destructive? Something like “the pebble that started the avalanche,” but that too is destructive. Same goes for “tipped me over the edge.” (I didn’t mean for this paragraph to be a reflection on these destructive metaphors, but here we are.) The point is: the article got me digging into something I’ve been thinking about for a while,&lt;a href="#fn1" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref1" role="doc-noteref"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and now I want to dive so &lt;em&gt;very&lt;/em&gt; deep into that subject. I spent the better part of an hour tonight wrapping my head around it a bit more, starting to get the &lt;em&gt;feel&lt;/em&gt; of it by way of a bunch of examples.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I &lt;em&gt;love&lt;/em&gt; that feeling. My brain stretched a bit in a way that I love: like a set of muscles feeling a hint of pain, but a pain that means &lt;em&gt;progress&lt;/em&gt;. We were explaining this to our 7-year-old daughter recently, as she was learning something. “That feeling—that almost a pain, a special and strange kind of tiredness in your head—it means you’re learning!” We celebrated it with her, let her know that it is good and that we still feel it too: we hope she comes to love it the way we do. I hadn’t felt it quite like I did tonight in a while. It was good to dig in a bit, and it makes me want to do so all the more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="iv.-which-words-should-i-count" class="level2"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;IV. Which words should I count?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The point is to be writing. But which words count? The issue I wrote up on the TypeScript repository this evening? The answer I offered to a question on a forum about a software library? The notes scribbled in a notebook this morning, gestures toward the essays I would like to finish this year? The couple paragraphs of documentation I wrote for an open source project? The contents of this post? Would the words I sent to Craig Mod count if I dind’t include them in this post? I’m overthinking this. It is my way. It doesn’t really matter, of course. There’s just the silly part of me that wants to &lt;em&gt;know&lt;/em&gt; how much I have written when the month comes to a close. And so I have a spreadsheet! It tracks the daily average so far, has a little calculation for the expected number of words at the end of the month given that average. But spreadsheets demand specific numbers, and so I need to count my words, and that in turn makes me want to know: &lt;em&gt;which words?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Again: it does not matter. This whole project would work equally well if I opted &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; to track it this way. Somehow, though, I find it motivating to do so. And so here we are.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(Because I know at least one of you is dying to know, will be driven a little mad if I do not say: the contents of this post, and the documentation I wrote for that open source project—but not the words in the open source issue I opened or the answer I wrote up on a forum. Entirely arbitrary. That’s what seems right for this project, though.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn1" role="doc-endnote"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Web/JavaScript/Reference/Statements/function*"&gt;Generators&lt;/a&gt; in JavaScript, if you happen to care. The article was ostensibly about the proposed &lt;a href="https://github.com/tc39/proposal-pipeline-operator"&gt;pipeline operator&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href="#fnref1" class="footnote-back" role="doc-backlink"&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 11 Nov 2019 20:55:00 -0500</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:v4.chriskrycho.com,2019-11-11:/2019/four-miscellanies.html</guid><category>writing</category><category>walking</category><category>poetry</category><category>learning</category></item><item><title>Being an Amateur Again</title><link>http://v4.chriskrycho.com/2019/being-an-amateur-again.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;a href="https://v4.chriskrycho.com/2018/assumed-audiences.html"&gt;Assumed Audience&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/b&gt; Just about anyone… but I do assume a bit of familiarity with programming.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just a little note here, nothing long or fancy tonight.&lt;a href="#fn1" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref1" role="doc-noteref"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; I’ve just started working in earnest on my long-dreamt-of applications for research writing. This means I’m trying to figure out how to build some applications with native toolkits: UIKit and AppKit, specifically. And, for the first time in most of a decade, I have &lt;em&gt;no idea&lt;/em&gt; what I’m doing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I started doing web development in college, over a decade ago. I used a free Dreamweaver clone to build a simple portfolio website for my music when I was a sophomore. I was hacking on &lt;abbr&gt;XML&lt;/abbr&gt; templates for my old Blogger site as a junior. In the year after I finished college, I was building websites for friends, family, and my old church. I built multiple responsive web designs within months of Ethan Marcotte’s &lt;a href="https://alistapart.com/article/responsive-web-design"&gt;original article on the idea&lt;/a&gt;. I was writing loads of jQuery by mid-2011. I built my first single-page app in 2014 (and it’s still running!).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All of that is not to brag but to say: I am &lt;em&gt;deeply&lt;/em&gt; comfortable (and relatively expert) with web development. It is in many ways “old hat” to me. Pretty much any tool or framework that sits in that space, I can pick up very quickly, simply because I have deep experience in the space at this point.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And now: I am starting over in many ways. Native app development has a lot in common with web UI development in some ways… but in others, it could not be more foreign. While some of the patterns are the same, and if some of the terminology is curiously familiar&lt;a href="#fn2" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref2" role="doc-noteref"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; the actual details are all &lt;em&gt;wildly&lt;/em&gt; different.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The net of it all is discomfort.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am used to this feeling, so it does not bother me: I have made a point to be &lt;em&gt;learning&lt;/em&gt; constantly throughout my career. I will admit, though, that trying to dive in here is intimidating. I want to build apps that are distinguished in no small part by their quality and ease of use… and I am in over my head even to build things that work at &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; on these platforms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It helps that I have a five-year horizon for this project.&lt;a href="#fn3" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref3" role="doc-noteref"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; But it’s still strange to be diving into the deep end &lt;em&gt;without&lt;/em&gt; the comfort of all that existing knowledge. Every time I picked up a new thing in web development, I could layer it onto the things I already knew. Here, that is much less true. Yes, I have a reasonably good sense for how UIs work in many ways, and I have a great deal of general programming knowledge. But with iOS and macOS, at the end of the day, I’m still just a newb.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s both a bit intimidating and a little exhilarating. So: here we go!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn1" role="doc-endnote"&gt;&lt;p&gt;I’ve successfully been &lt;em&gt;not blogging&lt;/em&gt;, though not for exactly the reasons I hoped. One of the ways &lt;a href="https://v4.chriskrycho.com/burnout"&gt;the burnout&lt;/a&gt; lingers is that my bandwidth is lower than I might have hoped. Doing both &lt;a href="https://newrustacean.com"&gt;New Rustacean&lt;/a&gt; and my &lt;a href="https://emberconf.com/speakers.html#chris-krycho"&gt;EmberConf workshop&lt;/a&gt; was more than enough to keep me full for the first couple months of the year.&lt;a href="#fnref1" class="footnote-back" role="doc-backlink"&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn2" role="doc-endnote"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reading docs for UIKit and Swift is a lot like reading a weird mirror-universe version of Ember and TypeScript—you can still see Ember’s &lt;a href="https://sproutcore.com"&gt;SproutCore&lt;/a&gt; roots, and if you were reading the Ember docs back in the 1.x days, well… there’s a lot to recognize.&lt;a href="#fnref2" class="footnote-back" role="doc-backlink"&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn3" role="doc-endnote"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Being in your 30s has some advantages, it turns out! Comfort with longer time-scales is one of them.&lt;a href="#fnref3" class="footnote-back" role="doc-backlink"&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 05 Apr 2019 20:00:00 -0400</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:v4.chriskrycho.com,2019-04-05:/2019/being-an-amateur-again.html</guid><category>software development</category><category>learning</category></item></channel></rss>