<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Chris Krycho</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/</link><description></description><atom:link href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/feeds/links.xml" rel="self"></atom:link><lastBuildDate>Tue, 25 Mar 2014 08:00:00 -0400</lastBuildDate><item><title>God Become Man: Toward a Richer Theology of the Incarnation</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2014/god-become-man-toward-a-richer-theology-of-the-incarnation.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;My latest piece over at Mere Orthodoxy (and the first such in too&amp;nbsp;long):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It has been common these past few years to speak of &amp;#8220;incarnational theology&amp;#8221;
as a way of describing the Christian mission to the world: we ought to
&amp;#8220;incarnate&amp;#8221; Christ to the world as Christ &amp;#8220;incarnated&amp;#8221; the Godhead to us.
There is much to appreciate in this sentiment&amp;#8230;. Yet for all that, I think
that applying the language of incarnation to believers is a serious&amp;nbsp;mistake.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Incarnation matters, and it matters as more than a means of getting Jesus
to the cross so that he could die for our sins. We evangelicals too often
reduce everything to penal substitutionary atonement. Yes, the atonement is
incredible and amazing. It is one of the central affirmations and joys of the
Christian faith: our sins are paid for! Glory to God! But Jesus did more than
that, and he is worthy of yet more praise. He did not stop at paying the price
for our sins while leaving our bodies subject to corruption. He did not
content himself with performing a judicial act while leaving our wills broken,
certain to turn again to the same sin that led to our death in the first&amp;nbsp;place.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think &lt;a href="http://mereorthodoxy.com/god-become-man-richer-theology-incarnation/"&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; is the best thing I&amp;#8217;ve written so far this year; I hope you
find it&amp;nbsp;stimulating.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 25 Mar 2014 08:00:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2014-03-25:2014/god-become-man-toward-a-richer-theology-of-the-incarnation.html</guid><category>links</category><category>my writing elsewhere</category></item><item><title>North Korea Execution Fact Check</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2014/north-korea-execution-fact-check.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Christ and Pop Culture has some great follow-up on the link &lt;a href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2014/north-korea-set-to-execute-33-christians.html"&gt;I posted&lt;/a&gt; last&amp;nbsp;week:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you run in certain Facebook circles, you’ve likely already read that North
Korean leader Kim Jung-un has called for the execution of 33 North Korean
Christians. According to the widely circulated reports, these 33 people were
detained after it was discovered they had ties to Kim Jung-wook, a South
Korean missionary whose arrest for religious activity last year has made
international&amp;nbsp;headlines&amp;#8230;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But here’s the thing: No one can verify this call for executions actually took&amp;nbsp;place.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A great example of journalism done right, and of how Christians ought to carry
ourselves in the public square. It matters whether our facts are right or not&amp;#8212;
even when the &amp;#8220;message&amp;#8221; might be right either way. The &lt;a href="http://christandpopculture.com/33-christians-north-korea-really-execution/"&gt;whole thing&lt;/a&gt; is
worth your&amp;nbsp;time.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 19 Mar 2014 21:25:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2014-03-19:2014/north-korea-execution-fact-check.html</guid><category>links</category></item><item><title>Combatting Generational Poverty Through Early Childhood Intervention</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2014/combatting-generational-poverty-through-early-childhood-intervention.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Great piece here from Alan Noble, who is increasingly showing himself to be one
of the sharpest guys&amp;nbsp;around.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It seems inevitable that our country will try to combat generational poverty
and all its great harms by investing heavily in early childhood intervention.
We already see signs of the State moving towards such programs with President
Obama’s 2013 State of the Union address and Mayor de Blasio’s expanded pre-K.
Tragically and despite enormous costs, de Blasio’s pre-K initiative in New
York will most likely have very modest results, particularly since it begins
intervention at age four, so late in the child’s mental development. The
question for the church is, will we allow the state to take the initiative, or
will we take up this task and engender the kind of deep, redemptive healing
that the state can only dream&amp;nbsp;of?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You should (1) &lt;a href="http://www.canonandculture.com/combatting-generational-poverty-through-early-childhood-intervention/"&gt;read the rest of this piece&lt;/a&gt; and (2) read lots more by him
and other sharp guys at his homebase &lt;a href="http://christandpopculture.com"&gt;Christ and Pop Culture&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 16 Mar 2014 17:00:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2014-03-16:2014/combatting-generational-poverty-through-early-childhood-intervention.html</guid><category>links</category></item><item><title>North Korea Set to Execute 33 Christians</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2014/north-korea-set-to-execute-33-christians.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;The Washington Times&amp;nbsp;reports:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;North Korea tyrant Kim Jong-un has reportedly ordered that 33 Christians
believed to be working alongside South Korean Baptist missionary Kim Jung-wook
be put to&amp;nbsp;death.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;N.b. the source is Breitbart, which I usually take with a very large grain of
salt&amp;#8212;but this is not exactly surprising for Kim Jong-un or North Korea, so it
is deserving of further investigation and prayer in any&amp;nbsp;case.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 08 Mar 2014 22:20:00 -0500</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2014-03-08:2014/north-korea-set-to-execute-33-christians.html</guid><category>links</category></item><item><title>Why Is American Internet So Slow?</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2014/why-is-american-internet-so-slow.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Pretty damning of the current (lack of a) regulatory regime, if you ask&amp;nbsp;me:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;According to a recent study by Ookla Speedtest, the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;U.S.&lt;/span&gt; ranks a shocking 31st
in the world in terms of average download speeds. The leaders in the world are
Hong Kong at 72.49 Mbps and Singapore on 58.84 Mbps. And America? Averaging
speeds of 20.77 Mbps, it falls behind countries like Estonia, Hungary,
Slovakia, and&amp;nbsp;Uruguay.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 07 Mar 2014 19:55:00 -0500</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2014-03-07:2014/why-is-american-internet-so-slow.html</guid><category>links</category></item></channel></rss>