<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Chris Krycho</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/</link><description></description><atom:link href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/feeds/listicles.xml" rel="self"></atom:link><lastBuildDate>Fri, 02 Jan 2015 20:15:00 -0500</lastBuildDate><item><title>Public-ish Plans</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2015/public-ish-plans.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;I have not (yet) made a formal list of goals for 2015, though I think I may do
so on Sunday evening. While New Years&amp;#8217; resolutions can be silly and get us in
trouble (when we set unrealistic goals, or unhelpful goals), the turning of the
year can also be a helpful time to evaluate the way we spend our time and the
things we want to&amp;nbsp;accomplish.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What follows is a list of public-ish things I am &lt;em&gt;hoping&lt;/em&gt; to manage in 2015, in
no particular order. Come the end of the year, I will Lord willing look back and
see which of these I was able to pull&amp;nbsp;off!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Publish at least two seasons of &lt;a href="//www.winningslowly.org"&gt;Winning Slowly&lt;/a&gt; with &lt;a href="//stephencarradini.com"&gt;Stephen Carradini&lt;/a&gt;
    just as we did last year&amp;#8212;but&amp;nbsp;better.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Get the site for Winning Slowly updated so that it paginates between
    seasons! This means writing an extension for &lt;a href="//docs.getpelican.com/en/3.5.0/"&gt;Pelican&lt;/a&gt; that can paginate on
    something besides page count. An excuse to write Python? I call that
    winning.&lt;sup id="fnref:slowly"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:slowly" rel="footnote"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Migrate Jaimie&amp;#8217;s &lt;a href="//jaimiekrycho.com"&gt;Jaimie&amp;#8217;s professional writing website&lt;/a&gt; from WordPress to
    &lt;a href="//ghost.org"&gt;Ghost&lt;/a&gt;. (Maybe do something similar with her current &lt;a href="//jaimiedawn.blogspot.com"&gt;personal site&lt;/a&gt;, which
    runs on Blogger. Yuck.) I&amp;#8217;ve gotten a bit of a start on that already, and I
    hope to knock it out sooner rather than&amp;nbsp;later.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Get to a point where I&amp;#8217;m hosting all my own sites on my own DigitalOcean
    droplet (or similar). I&amp;#8217;ve been moving that direction slowly but steadily
    anyway&amp;#8212;whereas I started and ran for a long time on simple shared hosting,
    I&amp;#8217;ve been using &lt;a href="https://www.webfaction.com/?aid=67929"&gt;Webfaction&lt;/a&gt; for a good chunk of the past year, and now am
    pretty well ready to take the plunge this year into just running my own
    server. No skin off their backs; Webfaction has been great, as was
    &lt;a href="https://billing.stablehost.com/aff.php?aff=319"&gt;StableHost&lt;/a&gt; before them. I&amp;#8217;m just ready to be in control (even with the bit
    of extra maintenance that entails).&lt;sup id="fnref:affiliate"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:affiliate" rel="footnote"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Write at least three minutes of music, and post it to my &lt;a href="//soundcloud.com/chriskrycho"&gt;SoundCloud&lt;/a&gt;
    account. Preferably five minutes, but at least&amp;nbsp;three.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Write some&amp;nbsp;poetry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Write a substantive essay and post it at least once a&amp;nbsp;month.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Post at least a half dozen book reviews (which, among other things, means
    reading at least a half dozen books worth reviewing). These can be fiction
    or non-fiction. Personally, I&amp;#8217;d like to get everything from Dostoevsky to
    Schreiner in&amp;nbsp;there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Add a picture to my &lt;a href="/about"&gt;About&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;page!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Post a &lt;a href="/family"&gt;#family&lt;/a&gt; update at least once a month. It&amp;#8217;ll be good for &lt;em&gt;me&lt;/em&gt;, just
    to have a better way of tracking what&amp;#8217;s going on with our little gals, and I
    know my family would enjoy it,&amp;nbsp;too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In sum, I&amp;#8217;d like to be doing &lt;em&gt;something&lt;/em&gt; in nearly every public-facing category
in which I&amp;#8217;m interested. Maybe it won&amp;#8217;t be a lot, but keeping my musical skills
doing matters to me. Keeping my brain engaged on a wide variety of topics
matters to me. Keeping my writing skills sharp matters to me. I cannot &lt;em&gt;excel&lt;/em&gt;
at all of those things, certainly&amp;#8212;especially not if I wish to be a good
husband and father! But keeping them active means keeping them from further
atrophying, and that is something, at least. It will hopefully leave them more
available to me for times in the future when I am able to dedicate more time to&amp;nbsp;them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If 2014 and 2013 were both years in which I focused primarily on software&amp;#8212;and
all to the good!&amp;#8212;then I hope 2015 will be a year in which I am able to broaden
out again and focus on a wider variety of&amp;nbsp;things!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You&amp;#8217;ll note that there really aren&amp;#8217;t any purely personal goals on this list. Not
to worry: I have them, and I intend to formalize them in the next couple of
days. But one of the things I have learned over the many years I have been
blogging is that not everything needs to be public. Some things can be; indeed,
some &lt;em&gt;should&lt;/em&gt; be. Some things &lt;em&gt;may&lt;/em&gt; be public but &lt;em&gt;need&lt;/em&gt; not, and yet others
&lt;em&gt;should not&lt;/em&gt; be public. Right now, I am choosing to leave quite a few things in
the &amp;#8220;may be need not&amp;#8221; category private. (This direction, I can always change my
mind later. It&amp;#8217;s essentially impossible to do the opposite in the internet&amp;nbsp;era.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:slowly"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Slowly&lt;/em&gt;. Beat you to it.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:slowly" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:affiliate"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note: those are both affiliate links; they&amp;#8217;ll give me a slight
kickback. For StableHost, you should also use the code &lt;code&gt;krycho50percent&lt;/code&gt; to
get 50% off! I&amp;#8217;d love it if you used it if you decide to sign up for either
of them.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:affiliate" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 2 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 02 Jan 2015 20:15:00 -0500</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2015-01-02:2015/public-ish-plans.html</guid><category>listicles</category></item><item><title>A Few Theses on Blogging</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2014/a-few-theses-on-blogging.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;I am a habitually&amp;#8212;even chronically&amp;#8212;long-winded blogger. I always have been.
I sat down a few weeks ago to write up an explanation of my running approach,
and I haven&amp;#8217;t finished it yet&amp;#8230; because it is over 2,500 words long and growing
rapidly longer. But as I have considered my approach to blogging of late, and as
I have also been posting fairly regularly on App.net (my social media locale of
choice), it occurred to&amp;nbsp;me:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Blog posts do not have to be the lengthy things I usually make of&amp;nbsp;them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I often write up a series of thoughts&amp;#8212;not necessarily an &amp;#8220;argument&amp;#8221; or
    indeed anything more than a series of connected thoughts&amp;#8212;on App.net,
    connecting them via the &amp;#8216;reply&amp;#8217; mechanism and enumerating them. Rather like
    I am&amp;nbsp;here.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Doing so inevitably clutters up the streams of anyone following&amp;nbsp;me.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;That clutter may or may not be problematic: some folks may enjoy those
    connected thoughts. Others may&amp;nbsp;not.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For those that &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt; enjoy those connected thoughts, a blog post like this
    would probably serve just as&amp;nbsp;well.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For those who do &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; enjoy them&amp;#8230; well, this sort of thing would be a
    welcome way to clear their streams up without causing me any particular&amp;nbsp;difficulty.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Using lists does not automatically mean I have given in to the constant
    temptation to make my blogging about driving&amp;nbsp;views.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Seriously.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This blog will &lt;em&gt;never&lt;/em&gt; drive substantial amounts of traffic. That is fine by
    me. Indeed, I would probably feel a bit odd if it&amp;nbsp;did.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Therefore, when I have those sorts of thoughts-in-a-line in the future, I
    will do as I have done here. I will write a &amp;#8216;listicle&amp;#8217; (the shame!) and
    share it for others to partake of&amp;#8212;or not!&amp;#8212;as they&amp;nbsp;please.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Taking that approach will almost certainly free me up to blog more briefly
    when I feel like it, as well. That, too, can only be a good&amp;nbsp;thing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;After all: I am happier when I am writing.&lt;sup id="fnref:12"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:12" rel="footnote"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:12"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I have so often &lt;a href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2014/the-long-race.html"&gt;noted before&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#8230;&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:12" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 09 Jul 2014 21:15:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2014-07-09:2014/a-few-theses-on-blogging.html</guid><category>listicles</category></item></channel></rss>