<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Chris Krycho</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/</link><description></description><atom:link href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/feeds/listicles.xml" rel="self"></atom:link><lastBuildDate>Tue, 02 Jun 2015 22:43:00 -0400</lastBuildDate><item><title>Corporate and Government Surveillance</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2015/corporate-and-government-surveillance.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;i class="editorial"&gt;&lt;a href="https://witheredgrass.wordpress.com/"&gt;Brian Auten&lt;/a&gt; shared &lt;a href="http://www.lawfareblog.com/2015/06/why-americans-hate-government-surveillance-but-tolerate-corporate-data-aggregators/"&gt;this speech&lt;/a&gt; by Sen. Sheldon Whitehouse on Facebook, and I wrote up what follows in response.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol type="1"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I broadly agree with the critique of the libertarian/TP angle on government as essentially an appendage to business. I am &lt;em&gt;by no means&lt;/em&gt; hostile to the government in general or in principle, nor even to &lt;em&gt;spying&lt;/em&gt;, nor even to warranted (double entendre intended) use of data for law enforcement. The idea that all government is bad is woefully incorrect; it is better to speak of &lt;em&gt;abuses&lt;/em&gt;, either of government or of business or indeed of any sphere exceeding its right domain or acting inappropriately within its domain.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;There is a profound and important difference between corporate data collection and federal government data collection: one of them, people accede to directly (though see below); the other they accede to (at best!) indirectly through elected representatives, with whom they may profoundly disagree and against whom they have no recourse (unlike the case of, say, Google or Facebook—one &lt;em&gt;can&lt;/em&gt; simply stop dealing with them). Whatever information I have granted to a corporation, I have chosen to grant them, and I can stop doing so with future information at any time. I &lt;em&gt;cannot&lt;/em&gt; do so with the NSA, FBI, etc.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;That distinction may be relatively meaningless for most people in practice, given that the terms, means, and consequences of the data collection carried about by corporations are often obscure to the point of incomprehensibility.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;As such, a serious reformation ought to occur in the realm of business and the way that people’s information is handled. Treating information about customers as the primary point of transactional value has significantly deleterious costs on any number of things.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;For this reason, I consistently advocate for and (where possible) choose to use services which are supported by direct payment, rather than by advertising, and so on. This is not always possible, but where it is, we should consider taking that path.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Nonetheless, because of the government’s power of coercion—a power not held by corporations, though to be sure they can exercise significant force of a certain sort through legal machinery/chicanery—the collection of metadata by the government does pose a more potent and long-term threat to liberty than that by corporations.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;As such, people are &lt;em&gt;absolutely right&lt;/em&gt; to be more tolerant of corporate data collection than of federal data collection. That they ought to be less tolerant of corporate data collection by no means suggests that their hostility to unwarranted governmental data collection should be diminished: quite the contrary.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Therefore, while some of the criticism of the government’s data collection may well be driven by the sorts of corporate interests he suggests, and while much of the opposition from companies like Facebook and Google is indeed hypocritical, the criticism is still warranted. The NSA has clearly and repeatedly overstepped even the extremely wide bounds granted it by the Patriot Act, and the Patriot Act itself licensed behavior that should be horrifying to people concerned with the long-term effects of mass surveillance on governance.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 02 Jun 2015 22:43:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2015-06-02:2015/corporate-and-government-surveillance.html</guid><category>listicles</category></item><item><title>Public-ish Plans</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2015/public-ish-plans.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;I have not (yet) made a formal list of goals for 2015, though I think I may do so on Sunday evening. While New Years’ resolutions can be silly and get us in trouble (when we set unrealistic goals, or unhelpful goals), the turning of the year can also be a helpful time to evaluate the way we spend our time and the things we want to accomplish.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What follows is a list of public-ish things I am &lt;em&gt;hoping&lt;/em&gt; to manage in 2015, in no particular order. Come the end of the year, I will Lord willing look back and see which of these I was able to pull off!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Publish at least two seasons of &lt;a href="//www.winningslowly.org"&gt;Winning Slowly&lt;/a&gt; with &lt;a href="//stephencarradini.com"&gt;Stephen Carradini&lt;/a&gt; just as we did last year—but better.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Get the site for Winning Slowly updated so that it paginates between seasons! This means writing an extension for &lt;a href="//docs.getpelican.com/en/3.5.0/"&gt;Pelican&lt;/a&gt; that can paginate on something besides page count. An excuse to write Python? I call that winning.&lt;a href="#fn1" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref1"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Migrate Jaimie’s &lt;a href="//jaimiekrycho.com"&gt;Jaimie’s professional writing website&lt;/a&gt; from WordPress to &lt;a href="//ghost.org"&gt;Ghost&lt;/a&gt;. (Maybe do something similar with her current &lt;a href="//jaimiedawn.blogspot.com"&gt;personal site&lt;/a&gt;, which runs on Blogger. Yuck.) I’ve gotten a bit of a start on that already, and I hope to knock it out sooner rather than later.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Get to a point where I’m hosting all my own sites on my own DigitalOcean droplet (or similar). I’ve been moving that direction slowly but steadily anyway—whereas I started and ran for a long time on simple shared hosting, I’ve been using &lt;a href="https://www.webfaction.com/?aid=67929"&gt;Webfaction&lt;/a&gt; for a good chunk of the past year, and now am pretty well ready to take the plunge this year into just running my own server. No skin off their backs; Webfaction has been great, as was &lt;a href="https://billing.stablehost.com/aff.php?aff=319"&gt;StableHost&lt;/a&gt; before them. I’m just ready to be in control (even with the bit of extra maintenance that entails).&lt;a href="#fn2" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref2"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Write at least three minutes of music, and post it to my &lt;a href="//soundcloud.com/chriskrycho"&gt;SoundCloud&lt;/a&gt; account. Preferably five minutes, but at least three.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Write some poetry.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Write a substantive essay and post it at least once a month.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Post at least a half dozen book reviews (which, among other things, means reading at least a half dozen books worth reviewing). These can be fiction or non-fiction. Personally, I’d like to get everything from Dostoevsky to Schreiner in there.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Add a picture to my &lt;a href="/about"&gt;About&lt;/a&gt; page!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Post a &lt;a href="/family"&gt;#family&lt;/a&gt; update at least once a month. It’ll be good for &lt;em&gt;me&lt;/em&gt;, just to have a better way of tracking what’s going on with our little gals, and I know my family would enjoy it, too.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In sum, I’d like to be doing &lt;em&gt;something&lt;/em&gt; in nearly every public-facing category in which I’m interested. Maybe it won’t be a lot, but keeping my musical skills doing matters to me. Keeping my brain engaged on a wide variety of topics matters to me. Keeping my writing skills sharp matters to me. I cannot &lt;em&gt;excel&lt;/em&gt; at all of those things, certainly—especially not if I wish to be a good husband and father! But keeping them active means keeping them from further atrophying, and that is something, at least. It will hopefully leave them more available to me for times in the future when I am able to dedicate more time to them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If 2014 and 2013 were both years in which I focused primarily on software—and all to the good!—then I hope 2015 will be a year in which I am able to broaden out again and focus on a wider variety of things!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You’ll note that there really aren’t any purely personal goals on this list. Not to worry: I have them, and I intend to formalize them in the next couple of days. But one of the things I have learned over the many years I have been blogging is that not everything needs to be public. Some things can be; indeed, some &lt;em&gt;should&lt;/em&gt; be. Some things &lt;em&gt;may&lt;/em&gt; be public but &lt;em&gt;need&lt;/em&gt; not, and yet others &lt;em&gt;should not&lt;/em&gt; be public. Right now, I am choosing to leave quite a few things in the “may be need not” category private. (This direction, I can always change my mind later. It’s essentially impossible to do the opposite in the internet era.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section class="footnotes"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn1"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Slowly&lt;/em&gt;. Beat you to it.&lt;a href="#fnref1"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn2"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Note: those are both affiliate links; they’ll give me a slight kickback. For StableHost, you should also use the code &lt;code&gt;krycho50percent&lt;/code&gt; to get 50% off! I’d love it if you used it if you decide to sign up for either of them.&lt;a href="#fnref2"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 02 Jan 2015 20:15:00 -0500</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2015-01-02:2015/public-ish-plans.html</guid><category>listicles</category></item><item><title>A Few Theses on Blogging</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2014/a-few-theses-on-blogging.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;I am a habitually—even chronically—long-winded blogger. I always have been. I sat down a few weeks ago to write up an explanation of my running approach, and I haven’t finished it yet… because it is over 2,500 words long and growing rapidly longer. But as I have considered my approach to blogging of late, and as I have also been posting fairly regularly on App.net (my social media locale of choice), it occurred to me:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol type="1"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Blog posts do not have to be the lengthy things I usually make of them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I often write up a series of thoughts—not necessarily an “argument” or indeed anything more than a series of connected thoughts—on App.net, connecting them via the ‘reply’ mechanism and enumerating them. Rather like I am here.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Doing so inevitably clutters up the streams of anyone following me.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;That clutter may or may not be problematic: some folks may enjoy those connected thoughts. Others may not.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For those that &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt; enjoy those connected thoughts, a blog post like this would probably serve just as well.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For those who do &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; enjoy them… well, this sort of thing would be a welcome way to clear their streams up without causing me any particular difficulty.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Using lists does not automatically mean I have given in to the constant temptation to make my blogging about driving views.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Seriously.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This blog will &lt;em&gt;never&lt;/em&gt; drive substantial amounts of traffic. That is fine by me. Indeed, I would probably feel a bit odd if it did.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Therefore, when I have those sorts of thoughts-in-a-line in the future, I will do as I have done here. I will write a ‘listicle’ (the shame!) and share it for others to partake of—or not!—as they please.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Taking that approach will almost certainly free me up to blog more briefly when I feel like it, as well. That, too, can only be a good thing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;After all: I am happier when I am writing.&lt;a href="#fn1" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref1"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;section class="footnotes"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn1"&gt;&lt;p&gt;As I have so often &lt;a href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2014/the-long-race.html"&gt;noted before&lt;/a&gt;…&lt;a href="#fnref1"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 09 Jul 2014 21:15:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2014-07-09:2014/a-few-theses-on-blogging.html</guid><category>listicles</category></item></channel></rss>