<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Chris Krycho</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/</link><description></description><atom:link href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/feeds/m-div.xml" rel="self"></atom:link><lastBuildDate>Wed, 09 Apr 2014 09:00:00 -0400</lastBuildDate><item><title>The Spirit and Christian Formation</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2014/the-spirit-and-christian-formation.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Discussions of the person of the Holy Spirit in modern Christianity tend to
focus on the third person of the Trinity&amp;#8217;s obviously miraculous activity in the
world&amp;#8212;the &amp;#8220;gifts&amp;#8221; that characterize the charismatic movement and the
associated controversy. Though these gifts are certainly part of the recorded
history of the Spirit&amp;#8217;s work, the church&amp;#8217;s focus thereupon (whether positive or
negative) on the gifts has had the unfortunate side effect of hiding many of the
other, arguably more central and essential actions of the Spirit in the life of
the believer. Just as the Spirit is the person who mediates to us the work of
Christ in our salvation and brings about our conversion, the Spirit is the one
who leads us into greater participation in the renewed humanity the Son has
accomplished in his incarnation, life, death, resurrection, and ascension. The
Spirit is the one who progressively deepens our union with Christ and reshapes
us to be like Him who saved&amp;nbsp;us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Spirit accomplishes these ends in a variety of ways, all of which are
themselves worthy of further reflection. First of all, it was the Spirit who
superintended the writing of Scripture, the self-revelation of the Triune
Godhead for our salvation and sanctification. If Christian formation is in no
small measure a matter of growing to know our Creator&amp;#8212;if we are being restored
to active relationship with one who made us for that very relationship&amp;#8212;then
the ways in which our Creator has revealed himself are supremely important.
Without Scripture, we would know little of God; through it we enter in the deep
mysteries. The first part the Spirit plays in our formation, then, is in having
guided every hand from Moses&amp;#8217; to John&amp;#8217;s in the writing of the word of God. Upon
this foundation comes the Spirit&amp;#8217;s second work: opening our eyes to understand
that Scripture. The things of God are foolishness to unregenerate people, but
beautiful and savory to those who have been given spiritual life. The word of
God can seem dense and opaque to those who do not believe, but every believer in
Christ finds that more and more these mysteries unfold: this is the Spirit at&amp;nbsp;work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As we come to understand the person of God and the things he has commanded us in
his word, we find that we are still weak and struggle to do them. Here, too, the
Spirit is at work, for it is the Spirit who empowers our obedience. We know that
the same Spirit that raised Christ from the dead is at work in us&amp;#8212;and this is
the only hope we have of overcoming sin and growing in holiness. Part and parcel
of this, the Spirit empowers us to endure the suffering that God uses to make us
more dependent on him and more faithful to him. Likewise, when in the course of
our lives we are tempted to fall away, it is the Spirit who helps us continue to
hold fast to the faith. Moreover, the Spirit intercedes for us when we do not
know how to pray ourselves. When we are beset by temptation, when tempted to
fall away, when exhausted from the battle, when wearied of the pursuit of
holiness, the Spirit prays for us. Nor is the Spirit&amp;#8217;s work directed solely to
individuals. All of these realities are corporate, and in all of them we grow in
unity and kindness toward one another. The Spirit is our bond of&amp;nbsp;peace.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In summary, then, we have both the Spirit and the Son praying for us to the
Father who delights to answer those prayers, and the Spirit empowering us walk
in the Son&amp;#8217;s life with the&amp;nbsp;Father&amp;#8212;hallelujah!&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 09 Apr 2014 09:00:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2014-04-09:2014/the-spirit-and-christian-formation.html</guid><category>M. Div.</category><category>SEBTS</category></item><item><title>The Spirit and Conversion</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2014/the-spirit-and-conversion.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;The Holy Spirit is the member of the Triune Godhead who actively brings about
our conversion. It is the Spirit who regenerates a person, indwells him, and
seals him for the day of salvation. The spirit makes the gospel powerfully
effective for salvation so that those who hear it may believe and be saved. On
these points all are agreed, since they are backed by straightforward statements
in Scripture. The particulars, however, are a matter of some controversy, and so
bear further&amp;nbsp;consideration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are two broad views of the Spirit&amp;#8217;s work in regeneration. In the non-
Calvinist view (whether Arminian, Roman Catholic, or variations thereon in other
streams of Christian tradition), the Spirit does preparatory work in the hearts
of the unregenerate and provides God&amp;#8217;s grace to enable people to choose whether
to respond to the gospel or not. However it is articulated (most commonly as
&amp;#8220;prevenient grace&amp;#8221; in Baptist circles), this view emphasizes that the Spirit&amp;#8217;s
work is essential in making available the effects of Christ&amp;#8217;s work on the cross
to whomever will believe. Without the Spirit&amp;#8217;s work, regeneration through faith
is impossible, because no one will believe. With the Spirit&amp;#8217;s work, men are
enabled to choose freely whether to follow God or&amp;nbsp;no.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the Calvinist view, by contrast, the Spirit not only works in a preparatory
sense, but is also the active agent in bringing about conversion. People choose
as they will, and people dead in their trespasses always choose sin over
God&amp;#8212;this is the essence of our fallen nature. What is needed, in this view, is
not only the grace-given ability to choose (as in a prevenient grace view) but a
grace-changed heart so that we will freely choose God. No matter how free our
choice, unless the effects of original sin in us are undone, we continue freely
to choose sin and to reject God. The Spirit, then, takes away hearts of stone
and gives instead beating hearts of flesh that can respond to God. He gives eyes
to see the light he shines as well as the light&amp;nbsp;itself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The essential disagreement between the two views is to whom the Spirit gives
such eyes: to all men who hear the gospel, or only to the elect. Based on Paul&amp;#8217;s
arguments in 1 Corinthians, Ephesians, and elsewhere, I take it to be the
latter. If the Spirit opened everyone&amp;#8217;s eyes to see truly the goodness of God,
if he gave to everyone hearts of flesh rather than hearts of stone all would
believe. Regeneration logically precedes (but temporally coincides with) faith:
the unregenerate heart cannot and does not believe. So the Spirit gives hearts
that can and do believe, and in that very moment, we believe. The Spirit gives
us not only the opportunity to exercise faith, but also the faith that we&amp;nbsp;exercise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However the act of regeneration is accomplished, the Spirit is efficaciously at
work. In both views, the gospel &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; powerful for salvation&amp;#8212;whether by tilling
the soil or by actually causing the seed to sprout. People hear the gospel and
the Spirit uses that mightily. Then, once people have believed, the Holy Spirit
continues to work. He immediately indwells the believer, giving our mortal
bodies spiritual vitality. Thus Paul says that the same Spirit who raised Christ
from the dead is now at work in all believers. This indwelling seals our
conversion, ensuring we hold fast until we die or Christ returns. He
increasingly shapes our behaviors and attitudes to be more in line with those of
God, making us holy as God is&amp;nbsp;holy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In short, the Spirit is the one who makes Christ&amp;#8217;s work effective for salvation.
He enables and empowers the gospel to produce&amp;nbsp;conversion.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 03 Apr 2014 08:15:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2014-04-03:2014/the-spirit-and-conversion.html</guid><category>M. Div.</category><category>SEBTS</category></item><item><title>The Resurrection is Essential</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2014/the-resurrection-is-essential.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Paul tells us that if Jesus was not raised from the dead, then we are still dead
in our trespasses (1 Corinthians 15:17). This simple statement uncovers a great
deal about the necessity of Christ&amp;#8217;s resurrection as well as his death on our
behalf, as does much of the rest of the New Testament&amp;#8217;s view of the
resurrection. Paul tells us, for example, that Christ died for our trespasses
and was raised for our justification (Romans 4:25). Likewise, he notes Jesus&amp;#8217;
resurrection from the dead is intrinsically linked to our own life (e.g. Romans
8:11). Moreover, we know that if Jesus was not raised from the dead, then
neither will we be (1 Corinthians 15:16). We know that it was in the
resurrection that Jesus was shown to be the Son of God in power (Romans 1:4) and
thus the one who reigns over all things. Moreover, we note that the preaching of
the apostles as recorded in Acts refers to the resurrection of Christ as the
evidence that he is indeed the Jewish messiah and the judge of the earth&amp;#8212;
indeed, from Acts we see that the apostolic message &lt;em&gt;centered&lt;/em&gt; on the
resurrection of Christ. Likewise, the very shape of the gospels is such that
each in its own way climaxes not with Jesus&amp;#8217; death but with his resurrection, as
if to say that the central issue of our faith is not the death of Christ but his
being raised from the&amp;nbsp;dead.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As we put together all these pieces, it becomes clear that the resurrection is
integral in our salvation. It is not merely the &amp;#8220;seal&amp;#8221; upon the work Jesus did
at the cross, the evidence that the cross accomplished what it needed to. It is
part and parcel of our salvation, in and of itself. It is true that the
resurrection does indeed ratify the elements of the saving work of Christ that
were accomplished on the cross, but this is not all that it does. It seems clear
from the evidence of the New Testament that the resurrection itself is
efficacious in saving&amp;nbsp;us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If our mortal bodies are corrupted by sin, as we know they are, and if the
penalty of sin is death, as we know it is, then something more than payment for
sin must happen. Payment for sin is necessary, and so Jesus&amp;#8217; substitutionary
atonement in death on the cross is essential to our salvation. However, there is
more that is essential to our salvation. Reconciliation between God and man
began in the Incarnation, as in Jesus the Son of God united humanity and deity
in perfect fellowship once again, and it was accomplished (though not yet
finished) in the resurrection as Jesus took up a restored body in which the
power of sin and death were finally broken: an image of what our bodies will be
in the age to&amp;nbsp;come.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Likewise, we know that if we die as things were before the Resurrection, even
were our sins paid for, we remain mortal and would never rise again of our own
merits. In his resurrection, Jesus triumphed over death&amp;#8212;the last enemy&amp;#8212;and
we know that the same Spirit that raised him from the dead will raise us from
the dead. We know that Jesus&amp;#8217; resurrection is the means of our justification. He
paid for our sins in his atoning death, but he sets us right with God in his
triumphant new life. We know that his reign as the rightful heir of all things
was inaugurated in his resurrection, not in his&amp;nbsp;death.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In short, essential as was his death for our salvation, the resurrection of
Christ is no less important in our being restored to life with&amp;nbsp;God.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 18 Mar 2014 08:00:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2014-03-18:2014/the-resurrection-is-essential.html</guid><category>M. Div.</category><category>SEBTS</category></item><item><title>The Servant of God</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2014/the-servant-of-god.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;The Servant pictured in Isaiah is one of the most famous images in the Old
Testament for Christians. The language applied to him in Isaiah 53 in particular
has long been understood by Christians to point directly to Jesus as the atoning
savior. The role of the Servant in the book is somewhat more complex than a
simple prediction of Jesus as subtitutionary atonement however: it encompasses
that idea, but does much more as&amp;nbsp;well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The label of Servant is applied to two (or possibly three) different roles in
Isaiah: the nation of Israel, and one who suffers and works on behalf of Israel.
This latter role certainly contains messianic overtures, but may also include
poetic references to Isaiah&amp;#8217;s own suffering on behalf&amp;nbsp;Israel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The theme of the Servant first appears in chapter 40, and is immediately and
directly applied in reference to Israel/Jacob. The same is true of its
appearance in chapters 41 and 43, though the language used of the servant in
chapter 42 suggests an individual and not the nation, and should perhaps be
taken as pointing to a king who represents the nation given the national
context. Beginning in chapter 45 and moving forward, the Servant increasingly
appears as the individual who acts for Israel on Yahweh&amp;#8217;s&amp;nbsp;behalf.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whether the Servant-Israel or the Servant-for-Israel (as we might label them),
the Servant exists to be God&amp;#8217;s agent in bringing about the obedience of the
nations. The Servant-Israel experiences cleansing and purification to that end,
while the Servant-for-Israel experiences suffering in place of Israel, for her
sins and to save her from her unrighteous ways.&lt;sup id="fnref:1"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:1" rel="footnote"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; In both cases, the suffering
is part of God&amp;#8217;s plan to lead the nations out of their idolatry to participate
in his covenant with Israel. The shape of the role taken by the Servant differs,
though, and as the book progresses the need for the Servant-for-Israel becomes
more and more clear, because the Servant-Israel is simply not up to the task (as
was made clear by the first 39 chapters of the&amp;nbsp;book!).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thus, the Servant-for-Israel acts on behalf of Israel in the latter parts of
chapters 40&amp;#8211;55. He picks up kingly responsibilities of doing justice and
righteousness in the earth (a theme Isaiah seems to take up from the Psalms and
elaborate). He stands as Israel&amp;#8217;s representative in dealing with her sin. He
brings the nations in to participate in Israel&amp;#8217;s covenant life with God. In some
sense, the messianic king figure becomes True Israel on Israel&amp;#8217;s&amp;nbsp;behalf.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The transition between Servant-Israel and Servant-for-Israel not only picks up
messianic overtones, but also hints at autobiographical elements for Isaiah
himself. Lest Christian readers be skittish at this notion, wanting to preserve
the text&amp;#8217;s unique way of pointing to Jesus: it is hardly uncommon for figures in
the Old Testament to prefigure the messiah in various ways. Here it is Jesus&amp;#8217;
role as Prophet we see prefigured, just asthe entire Levitical system prefigured
him as Priest and David prefigured him as King. Isaiah&amp;#8217;s suffering on behalf of
Israel is a clear parallel to Jesus&amp;#8217; ministry, and Jesus himself makes this
clear in his teaching in the New Testament, where he emphasizes that he came in
part to close eyes and ears as well as open&amp;nbsp;them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The result of the progression is that the reader moves from seeing Israel as
God&amp;#8217;s servant to recognizing the need for a servant who will work as God&amp;#8217;s agent
on Israel&amp;#8217;s behalf, to seeing that even Isaiah was an incomplete picture of this
servant. The one of whom Isaiah prophesied would be not only Prophet but also
king and both priest and sacrifice on behalf of the people. He would not only
speak of the nations coming to participate in fellowship with God in the Zion of
Israel, he would bring it about&amp;nbsp;himself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Notably, the redemption pictured in Isaiah goes beyond subtitution for
sins, and includes restoration to a holy nature&amp;#8212;a theme that is picked up
clearly in the New Testament but too often overlooked by modern readers.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 11 Mar 2014 15:45:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2014-03-11:2014/the-servant-of-god.html</guid><category>M. Div.</category><category>SEBTS</category></item><item><title>Wisdom and Folly</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2014/wisdom-and-folly.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;The book of Proverbs opens with a lengthy introduction to the topic of wisdom,
expounding its virtues and necessity and contrasting them with the costs of
folly, before moving into the proverbs for which it is named. After a short
introductory statement, the book moves into a series of extended metaphors for
wisdom and folly to illustrate the point. These metaphors are those of the two
women, the two houses, and the two ways&amp;#8212;with the choices between the two
illustrated in each case by the simple youth who may choose one or the other and
become either wise or a&amp;nbsp;fool.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The two women of the book are the Ladies Wisdom and Folly. Throughout the first
nine chapters, the two stand in opposition to each other everywhere. Wisdom
calls out on the streets, by the gates, and in the highest point of the city.
She represents the first aspect of God&amp;#8217;s order in the world, that foundational
principle on which the world is built. She is an attribute of the creation God
made and a reflection of his desires and character. By contrast, the adulteress
(or &amp;#8220;foreign woman&amp;#8221;) who leads astray a simple youth and destroys him in chapter
7 is a picture not only of the particular follies of adultery but a
personification of all that is foolish: wherever wisdom stands and calls out, so
too does the adulteress&amp;#8212;Lady Folly in one of her most deceptive forms. She is
an image of what it means to go against the grain of God&amp;#8217;s created order, and
the consequence of going with her is death. No surprise, that: going against the
structure of God&amp;#8217;s reality has &lt;em&gt;always&lt;/em&gt; led to death, beginning in Genesis&amp;nbsp;3.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The two ways and two houses pick up this same motif and trace it out further.
One way leads to life, the other to death. One house is steadfast and sure,
while the other crumbles. One belongs to Wisdom, the other to Folly. These
images Jesus picks up again in his own teaaching in the New Testament: The way
that leads to life is narrow, and few find it, but the way that leads to
destruction is wide and many walk it. The wise man builds his house on the rock
that is Jesus&amp;#8217; word, but the foolish man builds his house on the sand that is
worldly wisdom. The naïve youth may answer Lady Wisdom&amp;#8217;s invitation and follow
her along the way of wisdom to the house of wisdom and so become wise, or he may
answer Lady Folly&amp;#8217;s call, walk down folly&amp;#8217;s road to the house of destruction and
so become a&amp;nbsp;fool.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The idea of the &amp;#8220;wise person&amp;#8221; and the &amp;#8220;fool&amp;#8221; then come up time and again
throughout the rest of the book. Whatever one decides has the enormous
consequences that the book traces out: fools become insolent, ignorant,
murderous rebels against God, while wise people become gracious, temperate,
gentle followers of&amp;nbsp;God.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 11 Mar 2014 15:00:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2014-03-11:2014/wisdom-and-folly.html</guid><category>M. Div.</category><category>SEBTS</category></item><item><title>Job—The Mourner</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2014/job-the-mourner.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;The book of Job has most commonly been read as theodicy, i.e. as a defense of
God&amp;#8217;s goodness in the face of human suffering and the existence of evil in the
world. This reading has a number of difficulties, not least in that though the
characters in the book raise this question, neither God in his appearance nor
the narrator offer an answer to it. Indeed, the final shape of the book is such
that the reader has some understanding of why &lt;em&gt;Job&lt;/em&gt; suffered as he did&amp;#8212;but
only some. God&amp;#8217;s reasons for acting in the particular ways he did remain hidden,
and (more importantly) the answers we see in Job&amp;#8217;s specific case are clearly not
applicable to every case of human&amp;nbsp;suffering.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One possible way out of this problem is to approach the text from a different
angle. Supposing that Job was not written as a theodicy, but as an exploration
of an entirely different need, how might we read the book more profitably? One
suggestion is that the central issue in the text is how Job might move from a
position of ritual mourning back into a position of ritual life&amp;#8212;and this
approach does indeed yield significant exegetical&amp;nbsp;fruit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All of Job&amp;#8217;s troubles experienced in the first two chapters of the book
warranted his entering a state of ritual mourning: he experienced calamity in
the loss of his possessions, the death of his sons and daughters, and the onset
of a skin disease. The Levitical law proscribed the kinds of mourning an
Israelite would undergo under each of these circumstances, and none were
trivial. Though Job as a non-Israelite would not have lived under the Levitical
law, he &lt;em&gt;did&lt;/em&gt; live in a culture that embraced that pattern of ritual mourning in
response to these problems, and the Israelite audience would have recognized his
behavior as such. Thus, in Job 1&amp;#8211;2, we see Job respond to his great calamity by
tearing his clothes, going out of the town and sitting on the trash heap, and
scraping his skin with a shard of pottery. These were not merely expressions of
his grief (though, to be sure, he was grieved) but symbolic statements that he
had entered a state of ritual death in a period of&amp;nbsp;mourning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Job now needed a way to move back to ritual life, the ordinary state of affairs.
Culturally, &amp;#8220;comforters&amp;#8221; were the means afforded him for this end, and this
explains the efforts of Eliphaz, Bildad, Zophar, and (eventually) Elihu. Each in
his way sought to help Job come to terms with his loss, become right with God,
and return to ordinary life. Since the three each embraced both the so-called
&amp;#8220;retribution principle&amp;#8221; and its corollary&amp;#8212;that God rewards the righteous and
punishes the wicked, and that accordingly prosperity and suffering are
indicators of righteousness and wickedness respectively&amp;#8212;they all tried to
convince Job that he ought to repent of his apparent&amp;nbsp;sin.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Notably, however, none could persuade Job of any sin warranting such suffering
as he endured, and moreover the book agrees with Job: the narrative prologue
first chapters tells us that Job was &amp;#8220;blameless and upright&amp;#8221; and that &amp;#8220;in all
this [his initial response to loss] he did not sin.&amp;#8221; Job&amp;#8217;s bitter response
midway through the book (&amp;#8220;Miserable comforters are you all!&amp;#8221;) makes perfect
sense in this context: they were not relieving him of his state of ritual death,
for their words offered no way forward. Thus, Job increasingly turns away from
answering his friends to pleading with God to appear and answer him, though as
Job acknowledges, no one can contend with God. Still: even against the largely
accurate answers Elihu provides in chapters 32&amp;#8211;36, Job was unmoved. He needed
something&amp;nbsp;else.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When God appears, he does not answer Job&amp;#8217;s questions, but neither does he accuse
him of sin. Rather, he shows Job his wisdom, and how greatly his wisdom exceeds
Job&amp;#8217;s understanding. This, it seems, &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; what Job needed in order to move from
mourning back to life. He is able to say, &amp;#8220;Before, I had heard of you, but now
my eyes have seen you,&amp;#8221; and &lt;em&gt;this&lt;/em&gt; is what triggers his return to normal life at
the end of the book. Moreover, his statement of repentance in Job 42 makes a
great deal more sense this way: he now turned away (&amp;#8220;repented&amp;#8221; in the bare
sense) &lt;em&gt;from&lt;/em&gt; dust and ashes&amp;#8212;not repenting of some unnamed sin &lt;em&gt;in&lt;/em&gt; dust and
ashes. Indeed, this (the common reading) would hardly make sense, given that Job
immediately puts off his dust and ashes and returns to his life. Job was able to
move from ritual death to ritual life because he had encountered God. As a
result, Job did return to all the ordinary parts of life. Whereas the mourner
was forbidden from feasting, worshipping, and sexual activity, Job participates
in all three in the conclusion of the book. His friends and family come and eat
with him. He offers sacrifice for his friends. He fathers more&amp;nbsp;children.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thus, taking Job in light of ancient near eastern mourning ritual helps us
understand the book&amp;#8217;s message and structure far more clearly than taking it as a
theodicy. The text does not seek to answer why God allows evil. Indeed, it
inverts the question: who are we to think we could understand? In Job we have
instead a recognition that the only thing that will really satisfy the soul of
one experiencing the deep suffering that life brings is an encounter with the
living God. The only thing that could move Job from ritual death to ritual life
is the only thing that can move us from spiritual death to spiritual life&amp;#8212;not
mere academic knowledge of facts about God, but encountering him as one who may
be&amp;nbsp;known.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 11 Mar 2014 14:30:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2014-03-11:2014/job-the-mourner.html</guid><category>M. Div.</category><category>SEBTS</category></item><item><title>What He Did Not Assume</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2014/what-he-did-not-assume.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;There have been many broken and flawed Christologies over the years, and in
truth many of them continue to crop up in mainstream evangelicalism. Nearly
every major heresy the church confronts (and no few of its littler skirmishes)
revolve around issues of the nature of the Incarnate Son of God. From the
earliest days of the church, there has been a tension between those emphasizing
Jesus&amp;#8217; humanity at the cost of his deity and those emphasizing his deity at the
cost of his humanity. The clear testimony of Scripture, however, is that Jesus
was everything that it is to be God and also everything that it is to be&amp;nbsp;human.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When we say, then, that in the Incarnation the Son of God &amp;#8216;took his flesh from
Mary&amp;#8217;, we are emphasizing that he inherited from her all that it means to be a
human being. Nothing was missing or absent. The Word who was from the
beginning, and through whom the Father created the world, and indeed for whom
the world exists, took upon himself human body and&amp;nbsp;soul/mind/spirit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He participated fully in all the weaknesses of human existence. He became
subject to common colds and the need to expel waste from his body. He
experienced teething pains, and he needed to eat and sleep. He experienced real
temptation to sin, more fully than has any other human because he resisted it
to the last. He bore the sorrows of life in a world filled with suffering and
war and death. He was in everything the word means &lt;em&gt;human&lt;/em&gt;. As the author of
Hebrews puts&amp;nbsp;it:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since therefore the children share in flesh and blood, he himself likewise
partook of the same things, that through death he might destroy the one who
has the power of death, that is, the devil, and deliver all those who through
fear of death were subject to lifelong slavery. For surely it is not angels
that he helps, but he helps the offspring of Abraham. Therefore he had to be
made like his brothers in every respect, so that he might become a merciful
and faithful high priest in the service of God, to make propitiation for the
sins of the people. For because he himself has suffered when tempted, he is
able to help those who are being tempted. (Hebrews&amp;nbsp;2:14&amp;#8211;18)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We share in flesh and blood; he shared in flesh and blood. He became like us in
every respect&amp;#8212;not partially, not in some respects, but in every respect. He
suffered when he was tempted; the lures and draws of the world did not simply
pass by him without any challenge whatsoever. He took from Mary &lt;em&gt;everything&lt;/em&gt;
about&amp;nbsp;humanity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This matters because, as the Fathers pointed out, what he has not assumed has
not been redeemed. Redemption is more than (though of course not less than)
propitiation for sins. It is the re-uniting of humanity with God, so that all
the myriad ways in which human nature has been broken may be set once again how
it ought to be. It is the restoration of &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; the things that were broken in
humanity by the Fall. There is no part of humanity that was not broken by the
Fall, no part that does not need restoration, no part that was not cut off from
fellowship with God. Thus, there is no part of humanity that is not in need of
redemption, and so anything the Son did not take up of our humanity when he
became Jesus the Christ is still&amp;nbsp;broken.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If Jesus had only the mind of God and not a human mind, then our minds are still
unredeemed. If Jesus&amp;#8217; body was not the Son&amp;#8217;s body but a drone-like extension of
his will, then our minds remain unredeemed. If Jesus&amp;#8217; will was not a human will
but purely and only a divine will, then our wills remain unredeemed. In each
case, if Jesus was not both God and man in his nature, we are lost. In this
sense, then, few things are of more theological import than the nature of the
incarnation. The cross and resurrection, powerful though they are, do not have
their intended effect of redeeming lost women and men unless the Incarnation was
the complete joining of God and man in Jesus. And so: praise be to God! For when
Jesus took his flesh from Mary, he took up humanity whole and entire, leaving
nothing out, and joined it with his deity whole and entire, leaving nothing out.
So now we through him participated in the divine nature (2 Peter 1:4), just as
he participated in human&amp;nbsp;nature.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 05 Mar 2014 15:30:00 -0500</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2014-03-05:2014/what-he-did-not-assume.html</guid><category>M. Div.</category><category>SEBTS</category></item><item><title>Adam’s Sin and Our Death</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2014/adams-sin-and-our-death.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;How exactly human beings&amp;#8217; guilt relates to Adam&amp;#8217;s guilt is a question of no
small theological import, and it has unsurprisingly been the topic of much
theological discussion&amp;#8212;not to say debate&amp;#8212;over the past many hundreds of
years. The central passage is Romans&amp;nbsp;5:12&amp;#8211;14:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Therefore, just as sin came into the world through one man, and death through
sin, and so death spread to all men because all sinned&amp;#8212;for sin indeed was in
the world before the law was given, but sin is not counted where there is no
law. Yet death reigned from Adam to Moses, even over those whose sinning was
not like the transgression of Adam, who was a type of the one who was to&amp;nbsp;come.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The basic historic, orthodox&lt;sup id="fnref:1"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:1" rel="footnote"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; views of this position may be summarized as&amp;nbsp;follows:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;All humans are guilty of Adam&amp;#8217;s sin because they were in his loins when he
  sinned, and so have not only been contaminated with his sinful nature but also
  actively sinned when he sinned, and so are guilty and under judgment of death
  from their very conception&amp;#8212;a position most famously and forcefully
  articulated by&amp;nbsp;Augustine.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;All humans are born guilty of Adam&amp;#8217;s sin because he acted as the federal head
  of the human race and so we are imputed guilty in him, just as when we
  partipate in the humanity of the new federal head of humanity&amp;#8212;Jesus
  Christ&amp;#8212;his righteousness is imputed to us. In this view, humans are born
  subject to the punishment of sin (including death) because all of us are
  &lt;em&gt;counted&lt;/em&gt; guilty in Adam, just as we experience the blessings of holiness
  when in Christ because we are &lt;em&gt;counted&lt;/em&gt; righteous in him (the historic
  Reformed&amp;nbsp;view).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;All humans are born innocent of Adam&amp;#8217;s guilt, but by dint of descent from him
  have the same corrupted sinful nature he did, and therefore all &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt; sin and
  incur guilt before a holy God. Furthermore, as Adam&amp;#8217;s descendants, all are
  born separated from God and therefore mortal. In this view, humans are born
  innocent of guilt but inevitably sin because of their fallen humanity and die
  because of their separation from God. This is the view articulated by the
  Baptist Faith and Message&amp;nbsp;2000.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most basic logic of the passage seems to run most closely in line with this
last articulation. Paul argues that &amp;#8220;sin came into the world through one man,
and death through sin, and so death spread to all men because all sinned&amp;#8221;. While
Augustine and the Reformers both took this latter phrase to mean &amp;#8220;all sinned &lt;em&gt;in
Adam&lt;/em&gt;&amp;#8221; it must be recognized that the idea that all sinned &amp;#8220;in Adam&amp;#8221; is foreign
to the text. Indeed, the sentence that follows immediately on the heels of this
first declaration suggest that it is individuals&amp;#8217; sins committed in their own
lives, and not Adam&amp;#8217;s sin, that is in view here. Otherwise, the distinction
between the sins that some committed before the law came and the sins that
others committed after the law came makes little sense. So likewise does the
distinction between Adam&amp;#8217;s sin and that of those who followed him, even those
whose sin was not like&amp;nbsp;his.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most significant textual challenge to this understanding comes in Paul&amp;#8217;s
statement that &amp;#8220;death spread to all men because all sinned&amp;#8221;&amp;#8212;a statement that
is hard to reconcile with the notion of the lack of conscious sin in infants or
the mentally handicapped. Certainly many humans die in infancy, and indeed many
die &lt;em&gt;in utero&lt;/em&gt; long before the cognitive ability to make any choice whatsoever
has developed. Thus, there is at least some sense in which Paul&amp;#8217;s argument
entails the death of human beings who have not yet come under condemnation for
their own sin because of Adam&amp;#8217;s&amp;nbsp;sin.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;None of the views outlined above resolve this tension perfectly. The Augustinian
view seems overly bound up in Augustine&amp;#8217;s views on sexual intercourse as the
means of the transmission of sin to human nature. The federal headship view
places more emphasis on the idea of imputation than this passage seems to
support, but deals forthrightly with the issue of death in the lives of those
who have committed no sins. The idea that humans are born innocent of specific
guilt but subject to a sin nature that leads inevitably to sin seems to do
justice to the basic flow of Paul&amp;#8217;s argument, but struggles with the
application of death to those who have not&amp;nbsp;sinned.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Integrating the latter two options seems the best solution. People die because
Adam corrupted human nature, and all participate in his corrupted human
nature&amp;#8212;a nature separated from the fellowship with God essential to human
immortality&amp;#8212;unless united to a &lt;em&gt;different&lt;/em&gt; human nature. People are guilty
for their own sins, not for Adam&amp;#8217;s, but they die because they share Adam&amp;#8217;s
basic nature, which came out of his guilt. In due time, they themselves sin
they &lt;em&gt;earn&lt;/em&gt; the death in which they already shared by dint of their broken
humanity. Even this solution, it must be admitted, remains somewhat messier
than we might like, but it is to be preferred as best dealing with all the
evidence before&amp;nbsp;us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I leave aside non-orthodox positions such as the Pelagian view that people
are born able to live perfectly righteous lives, with uncorrupted natures, which
runs against the clear teaching of Scripture that all sin and moreover that all
&lt;em&gt;inevitably&lt;/em&gt; sin because of the fallenness of our humanity.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 05 Mar 2014 15:00:00 -0500</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2014-03-05:2014/adams-sin-and-our-death.html</guid><category>M. Div.</category><category>SEBTS</category></item><item><title>The Name of Sin</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2014/the-name-of-sin.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Sin is described in various ways in the Old and New Testaments, and these various
descriptions and names tell us much about how the authors of the Bible
conceived of the power than enslaves us apart from&amp;nbsp;Christ.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Old Testament has several terms its authors often use to describe the broad
concept of sin:&lt;sup id="fnref:1"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:1" rel="footnote"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;span class="quo"&gt;&amp;lsquo;&lt;/span&gt;avah&lt;/em&gt;, meaning &amp;#8220;bent&amp;#8221; or&amp;nbsp;&amp;#8220;crooked&amp;#8221;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;span class="quo"&gt;&amp;lsquo;&lt;/span&gt;aval&lt;/em&gt;, which includes the idea of a lack of integrity, so is often
  given as&amp;nbsp;&amp;#8220;iniquity&amp;#8221;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;span class="quo"&gt;&amp;lsquo;&lt;/span&gt;avar&lt;/em&gt;, meaning &amp;#8220;to cross over&amp;#8221; or&amp;nbsp;&amp;#8220;transgress&amp;#8221;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;ra&amp;lsquo;&lt;/em&gt;, meaning &amp;#8220;the rule of&amp;nbsp;evil&amp;#8221;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;ma&amp;lsquo;al&lt;/em&gt;, meaning &amp;#8220;breach of&amp;nbsp;trust&amp;#8221;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;pasha&amp;lsquo;&lt;/em&gt;, meaning &amp;#8220;to revolt&amp;#8221; or &amp;#8220;refuse subjection to a rightful&amp;nbsp;authority&amp;#8221;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From these we see that humanity&amp;#8217;s brokenness before God in the Old Testament was
often conceived of in terms of doing things the wrong way, or in rejection of
the rightful authority, or a mix of the two. Rebellion against the creator and
his created order are essential ingredients of the concept of sin for the Old
Testament authors. To do evil is to be in rebellion against the right way God
established for things to be done, to reject his &lt;em&gt;shalom&lt;/em&gt; and replace it with
destruction and&amp;nbsp;disharmony.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most common term for sin in the Old Testament, however, and the one usually
translated into the English &amp;#8220;sin&amp;#8221; is &lt;em&gt;chatha&lt;/em&gt;, meaning &amp;#8220;to miss the mark&amp;#8221;.
Sinning was thus not necessarily always a matter of active, willful rejection
of God. It was also simply failing, by dint of corrupted human nature, to do as
God called humanity to do, in any and all spheres of life. Sin was thus a
pervasive and corrupting influence on &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; of human existence, not only on
those who were consciously rebelling against&amp;nbsp;God.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unsurprisingly, the New Testament picks up on many of these same ideas. Though
the specific terms used have different semantic ranges than those in the Old
Testament, as a group they cover much of the same&amp;nbsp;territory:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;parabasis&lt;/em&gt;, &amp;#8220;the transgression of a&amp;nbsp;boundary&amp;#8221;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;parakoe&lt;/em&gt;, &amp;#8220;disobedience to a&amp;nbsp;voice&amp;#8221;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;paraptoma&lt;/em&gt;, &amp;#8220;falling where one should have stood&amp;nbsp;upright&amp;#8221;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;agnoema&lt;/em&gt;, &amp;#8220;failing to know what one should have&amp;nbsp;known&amp;#8221;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;hettema&lt;/em&gt;, &amp;#8220;diminishing what should have been fully&amp;nbsp;rendered&amp;#8221;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;anomia&lt;/em&gt;, failing to observe a&amp;nbsp;law&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;plemmeleia&lt;/em&gt;, &amp;#8220;a discord in the harmonies of God&amp;#8217;s&amp;nbsp;universe&amp;#8221;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To the Old Testament range, they add this final notion of discord in the created
order&amp;#8212;a concept that was present in the Old Testament, to be sure, in the
notion of lost &lt;em&gt;shalom&lt;/em&gt;, but which was not so directly expressed. Again, as in
the Old Testament, these emphasize both failure to do and active rejection of
what is right. And, as in the Old Testament, the New Testament authors&amp;#8217; concept
of sin is most commonly expressed in a single word meaning &amp;#8220;missing the mark&amp;#8221;:
&lt;em&gt;hamartia&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This congruence between the Old and New Testament views of sin emphasizes the
fundamental unity between the various authors&amp;#8217; understanding of the issues at
stake. Sin is everything about humanity&amp;#8217;s failure to follow God&amp;#8217;s ways and live
in accord with his design for the universe. It encompasses the whole range of
human foibles, from  accidental failure and ignorance to the kind of rebellion
that shakes its fist at the heavens or boldly (and foolishly) proclaims that
there is no God. Sin is getting it wrong&amp;#8212;or, to put it another way that
better captures the breadth of Scriptural language on the issue, not getting it
&lt;em&gt;perfectly&lt;/em&gt; right, for whatever&amp;nbsp;reason.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;List drawn from Stanley Grenz, &lt;em&gt;Theology for the Community of God&lt;/em&gt;.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 05 Mar 2014 14:30:00 -0500</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2014-03-05:2014/the-name-of-sin.html</guid><category>M. Div.</category><category>SEBTS</category></item><item><title>In the Day That You Eat of It</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2014/in-the-day-that-you-eat-of-it.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;When God placed Adam in the Garden of Eden, he told him he could eat freely of
any fruit in the garden except one: the tree of the knowledge of good and evil.
If he ate from that tree, however, he would die the very day he ate of it
(Genesis 2:17). When, in Genesis 3, Adam and Eve ate the fruit of the tree of
the knowledge of good and evil, however, they did &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; die&amp;#8212;at least, not
physically. Indeed, Adam lived to be over nine hundred years&amp;nbsp;old.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What, then, did God mean when he told Adam that he would sure die the very day
he ate of the tree? Did he lie, or make a mistake, or change his mind after the
fact? Plainly put, no: none of these are true. Rather, all of them mistake the
nature of the death entailed in God&amp;#8217;s word to Adam. The death Adam immediately
experienced was not physical death but spiritual death. Physical death was a
consequence&amp;#8212;a symptom, as it were&amp;#8212;of his spiritual&amp;nbsp;death.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This spiritual death was multifold, and we see the various elements of it traced
out in the explanation of the fall given in Genesis 3. First of all came
separation from God. Rather than being in right relationship with the creator,
Adam now needed restoration. Whereas he had enjoyed fellowship and relationship
with his maker, now Adam experienced fear at the thought of encountering him,
so that he hid himself when God came walking in the garden in the cool of the
day. The rest of the Old Testament traces this theme out in great detail; it is
constantly asking the question, &amp;#8220;How may these unrighteous people come before a
holy&amp;nbsp;God?&amp;#8221;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Second, God removed Adam from the means of grace he had supplied to sustain his
mortal body. He had provided a tree of life from which Adam could eat so that
his body would go on living without fail. After the fall, Adam was removed from
this supply, and so his body began to fall apart. He began to experience the
first phase of physical death: aging and decay. He no longer had access to the
supernatural sustenance he required not to&amp;nbsp;die.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Third, he immediately experienced relational brokenness. The previously holy
and mutually delightful relationship he had experienced with his wife would now
be characterized by mutual blame and recriminations. Likewise, his sons would
not be loving brothers: one would kill the other. No more would he live in a
world characterized by peace and harmony, but one shaped by conflict and&amp;nbsp;war.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of all of these, though, it was the first that was most important and deepest.
Adam&amp;#8217;s separation from God was at the root of all the other problems he now
faced. It was the lack of God&amp;#8217;s spirit in him that led to his physical death.
It was the lack of God&amp;#8217;s presence in their midst, and the brokenness of his
image in them, that led men and women to be in conflict rather than mutually
supporting one another. With this separation came a warp in the character of
humanity that comprised the final part of Adam&amp;#8217;s immediate death: no more would
his will be ready to obey God. Instead, he (and all his descendants) would be quick
to turn aside to go against the grain of God&amp;#8217;s universe. Given the opportunity,
all would sin, and no one would turn away from sin without God&amp;#8217;s&amp;nbsp;intervention.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thus, Adam &lt;em&gt;did&lt;/em&gt; experience death the very day, indeed the very moment, that he
ate of the tree of the knowledge of good and evil. The death was more profound
and more horrifying than physical death alone would have been, though, because
it was a death that stretched to every point of his life, from his family and
the tasks with which God had entrusted him, to his very connection with God.
Everything became broken in him, and he no longer knew God. In gaining the
knowledge of good and evil, he lost the knowledge of the one of whom knowledge
matters&amp;nbsp;most.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 05 Mar 2014 14:00:00 -0500</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2014-03-05:2014/in-the-day-that-you-eat-of-it.html</guid><category>M. Div.</category><category>SEBTS</category></item><item><title>Sufficiency and Efficacy</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2014/sufficiency-and-efficacy.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;The extent of the atonement is one of the most debated topics in the history of
the church for centuries. Whether Jesus Christ&amp;#8217;s death provided substition for
the sins of all people or just some has been the cause of many dissensions and
denominational splits in the Protestant world ever since the Reformation. Most
famously, Arminius and his followers were expelled from the Calvinistic churches
over this very issue and the way they worked out their stance in other areas of&amp;nbsp;doctrine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the most part, though, what is at issue is not whether Jesus&amp;#8217; death was of
sufficient merit to save all people. Jesus the incarnate Son of God provided a
sacrifice of infinite worth, undoubtedly of sufficient worth to cover all the
sins of all mankind in all of history. Rather, the question is to whom the
atonement is applied and how&amp;#8212;or, to put it differently, to whom its benefits
are available. Thus, the phrases of &amp;#8220;limited atonement&amp;#8221; and &amp;#8220;unlimited
atonement&amp;#8221; are best understood as referring to the availability and effect of
the atonement, &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; to its&amp;nbsp;value.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Second, it must be recognized that all orthodox Christians affirm that the
effects of the atonement are limited in at least one important sense: not all
people are redeemed, and therefore not all people benefit from the atonement of
Christ. To put it as many have before, all orthodox believers affirm that the
atonement was &amp;#8220;sufficient for all, but efficient for some,&amp;#8221; for if it was
&amp;#8220;efficient&amp;#8221; for all, then all would be saved. (To affirm any lesser effect is to
diminish the atonement. This is not to say that there may not be other, broader
effects of Christ&amp;#8217;s death on the cross&amp;#8212;e.g. the notion of prevenient grace
enabling all to respond to the preached word&amp;#8212;only that the atonement itself is
not applied universally.) The question then is only who those &amp;#8220;some&amp;#8221; are and the
terms under which the atonement is available to&amp;nbsp;them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The simplest answer is simply to say, &amp;#8220;the elect!&amp;#8221; and have done, leaving aside
the tendentious question of who is elect&amp;#8212;but this question is precisely where
the rubber meets the road on the issue of the atonement. After all, everyone
agrees that the only the sins of those who believe are actually removed in
Christ, regardless of how election works out. Thus, when people speak of
&amp;#8220;limited&amp;#8221; or &amp;#8220;unlimited&amp;#8221; atonement, they are usually speaking of the issue of
general or specific election. Does the work of Christ mean that all are equally
able to hear and respond to the gospel, or does it mean that only the elect are
enabled to hear and&amp;nbsp;respond?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think the most faithful articulation of the matter is to speak of the
atonement in three ways. First, we affirm that Jesus&amp;#8217; death was sufficient to
atone for the sins of the world&amp;#8212;&lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; the world. Second, we offer the
atonement freely to everyone. Although the only the elect will be saved (however
we understand that to play out), the Scriptures clearly enjoin us to proclaim
Christ&amp;#8217;s subtitutionary death and justifying resurrection to sinners everywhere
and to urge everyone to repent and trust in him. Third, we affirm that the
saving work of the atonement is applied to the sins of those who confess Christ
as Savior and Lord and obey him. We need not perfectly understand or agree upon
the means by which people come to confess Christ as Lord to affirm that it is
only in that affirmation and obedience that one&amp;#8217;s sins are covered in the&amp;nbsp;atonement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is thus most appropriate to speak of Jesus&amp;#8217; atonement as unlimited in extent
but limited in&amp;nbsp;effect.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 25 Feb 2014 08:30:00 -0500</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2014-02-25:2014/sufficiency-and-efficacy.html</guid><category>M. Div.</category><category>SEBTS</category></item><item><title>Like His Brothers in Every Way</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2014/like-his-brothers-in-every-way.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Whether Jesus could have sinned or not is a question to tangle the mind. On the
one hand, we affirm that he was fully human, and this affirmation binds us to
affirm that he could indeed sin: all humans are capable of sinning, and apart
from Jesus, all humans &lt;em&gt;have&lt;/em&gt; sinned. The author of Hebrews reminds us
forcefully that Jesus was made like his brothers&amp;#8212;which is to say, &lt;em&gt;us&lt;/em&gt;&amp;#8212;in
every respect, being tempted like them, yet without sin. On the other hand, we
recognize that the Godhead is sinless and that, as James reminds us, he neither
tempts nor can be tempted with evil. As with many issues relating to the
Incarnation, we face the challenge of holding together both Jesus&amp;#8217; full deity
and his full humanity. When either is lost (or even simply diminished) in order
to emphasize or preserve the other, important aspects of our faith break in
serious&amp;nbsp;ways.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Difficult (mysterious even) the question may be, but the author of Hebrews
leaves little doubt. Jesus was tempted like us in &lt;em&gt;every&lt;/em&gt; way&amp;#8212;not only in some
ways, but in every way. This is an essential affirmation for the Christian
faith. If Jesus could not sin, then he was not fully human, and his perfect life
is unsurprising and not particularly meaningful. If he &lt;em&gt;could&lt;/em&gt; sin, then his
perfect life is extraordinary and especially&amp;nbsp;meaningful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the same time, we must integrate the things that Hebrews and James (and the
rest of the Scriptures) teach us. If the Godhead cannot be tempted by sin and
Jesus &lt;em&gt;was&lt;/em&gt; tempted by sin, does this make Jesus somehow &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; God? No, for this
misses the rest of the witness of the New Testament, including those selfsame
books. James himself calls Jesus Lord in terms that, set against a Jewish
background, can only be understood to refer to God himself (see especially James
5:11, perhaps the most direct quote of Exodus 34:6 in the whole New Testament
and an unmistakable reference to Yahweh God). Neither can we admit the notion
that James and Hebrews disagree with each other&amp;#8212;at least, not and maintain our
affirmation of the unity of Scripture, which is a non-negotiable from where I&amp;nbsp;stand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As with many things in the Trinity and the Incarnation, then, we are left making
a dual (and apparently conflicting affirmation). Jesus&amp;#8217; humanity was perfectly
capable of sinning, and his divinity was incapable of sinning. The Incarnation
holds the two together in a single person, and so we affirm that Jesus could
have sinned, but did not. We note, too, that he did not precisely because he did
as all humans are called to do (and what glorified humans &lt;em&gt;will&lt;/em&gt; do) and
perfectly trusted the Father by obeying the Holy Spirit. Jesus&amp;#8217; perfect life was
not the domination of his humanity by his divinity, but the submission of his
humanity to the divinity of the&amp;nbsp;Trinity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thus we affirm that Jesus&amp;#8217; not sinning on our behalf was a real moral victory,
not a hollow thing we can only look at bemusedly from afar. He lived as a real
second Adam, doing what the first Adam failed to do while beset by many more and
far greater temptations than the first Adam. He really did overcome the world&amp;#8212;
not only its powers, but its temptations. He really did demonstrate true and
perfect holiness that we might follow his example. He really did triumph over
every power of sin, that we might be transformed into his likeness. Though the
triune God is never tempted to sin, the triune God mysteriously partook of
everything it is to be human in the Incarnation, and that humanity &lt;em&gt;could&lt;/em&gt; be
tempted&amp;#8212;and he&amp;nbsp;overcame.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 11 Feb 2014 08:30:00 -0500</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2014-02-11:2014/like-his-brothers-in-every-way.html</guid><category>M. Div.</category><category>SEBTS</category></item><item><title>The Mother of God</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2014/the-mother-of-god.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Is it right to call Mary the Mother of God? The historic, orthodox answer is a
resounding &amp;#8220;yes&amp;#8221;&amp;#8212;though a clearly qualified and well articulated &amp;#8220;yes.&amp;#8221; This
is not just the historic, orthodox position; it is the &lt;em&gt;right&lt;/em&gt; position. Mary
was indeed the &amp;#8220;mother of God&amp;#8221;. She was the mother of Jesus. Jesus was (and is)
fully God &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; fully man, completely and truly, both at once without loss of
the full measure of either. He did not cease being totally divine upon his
incarnation, but he did assume full humanity. The argument is as simple as it
first seems: Mary is the mother of Jesus, and Jesus is God, therefore Mary is
the mother of&amp;nbsp;God.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Evangelicals tend to shy away from following the broader tradition and affirming
that Mary is the mother of God. There are many reasons for this, not least our
general discomfort with things having to do with Mary born of the over-
referencing of Mary in the Catholic tradition and the actual Mariolatry that is
too often evinced in Catholic lay practice throughout the world. However, our
response ought not be to reject this view, but to speak carefully and clearly
and reject what is mistaken while keeping what is&amp;nbsp;true.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is true that we must be nuanced in our handling of this issue. The word
&amp;#8220;mother&amp;#8221; brings with it implications that we must avoid, and we must remember
Jesus&amp;#8217; statements on what it meant to be his mother and brothers and sisters in
the gospels (i.e. that those who followed him were those really deserving of the
titles). However, simply to set aside the title is to lose important aspects of
the reality of the incarnation. If we say that Mary was &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; the mother of God,
we are really saying either that she was not truly the mother of Jesus, or that
Jesus was not fully God. Neither of these is a tolerable&amp;nbsp;option.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, to those qualifications. When we say that Mary is the mother of God, we are
not saying that God in any sense has his source in her. All of the humanity of
Jesus finds its source equally in Mary and in the Spirit&amp;#8217;s divine intervention
&amp;#8212;but Mary was created by the Son, rather than the Son originating in her. Mary
is the mother of God in Christ, but she is not to the Son exactly as ordinary
mothers are to ordinary sons, for Jesus was not an ordinary&amp;nbsp;son.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nor do we mean that Mary has special prerogatives because of her relationship to
Jesus. As noted above, Jesus made clear that he was concerned above all with
obedience to the will of God (see e.g. Matthew 12:46&amp;#8211;50). Thus, the devotions
offered to Mary by our Catholic and Eastern Orthodox brothers and sisters is
misplaced, as is the notion that her prayers are somehow more effective in
touching Jesus&amp;#8217; heart than are those of the ordinary saint who is seeking to
honor&amp;nbsp;God.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These qualifications notwithstanding, we must still be willing and ready to
affirm that Mary was in fact the Mother of God. To do otherwise is to reduce in
one way or another the mystery of the incarnation. It is not so much that &lt;em&gt;Mary&lt;/em&gt;
is important here as that affirming her motherhood of God helps us affirm the
important points to which we must hold fast in terms the full deity and full
humanity of &lt;em&gt;Christ&lt;/em&gt;. Mary is important because Jesus humanity came by means of
Mary&amp;#8217;s body. Everything that it is to be man, Jesus always was from conception,
and everything that it is to be God, Jesus always was from the moment of his&amp;nbsp;conception.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 04 Feb 2014 08:30:00 -0500</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2014-02-04:2014/the-mother-of-god.html</guid><category>M. Div.</category><category>SEBTS</category></item><item><title>Infant Guilt—Purest Speculation</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2014/infant-guilt-purest-speculation.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Whether people are born guilty of sin, or simply inherit a nature so predisposed
to sin that the actual act is inevitable has been a much debated topic for
generations. In my view, however, the question is impossible to answer. I do not
think Scripture speaks with sufficient clarity on the matter. We know on the one
hand that all are &amp;#8220;by nature children of wrath&amp;#8221; (Ephesians 2:3), and that &amp;#8220;all
have sinned and fall short of the glory of God&amp;#8221; (Romans 3:23). What neither of
these texts tell us, though, and what indeed &lt;em&gt;no&lt;/em&gt; text tells us, is whether
people are guilty at birth or whether they are simply sinful and become&amp;nbsp;guilty.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We could reason to a conclusion that accords with our other theological
commitments with little difficulty. We know that God is just, and punishes for
the wrongs we commit, but we have no evidence that he punishes wrongs we &lt;em&gt;might&lt;/em&gt;
commit, and therefore we might conclude that he would therefore not find guilty
any newly conceived or newly born person. On the other hand, we also must reckon
with the reality that the Scriptures treat questions of progeny far differently
than do individually-minded modern&amp;nbsp;Westerners.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Scripture points us to the God who &amp;#8220;will by no means clear the guilty, visiting
the iniquity of the fathers on the children and the children&amp;#8217;s children, to the
third and the fourth generation&amp;#8221; (Exodus 34:7) as well as the God who proclaims
that &amp;#8220;The soul who sins shall die. The son shall not suffer for the iniquity of
the father, nor the father suffer for the iniquity of the son&amp;#8221; (Ezekiel 18:20).
Paul did write that &amp;#8220;one trespass led to condemnation for all men,&amp;#8221; but he
immediately follows up this provocative statement by arguing that &amp;#8220;one act of
righteousness leads to justification and life for all men&amp;#8221; (Romans 5:18)&amp;#8212;yet
we know that Paul does not (and cannot) here mean that all men are saved, for we
know that he believes that those who do not repent and believe the gospel perish
in their sins under the expectation of&amp;nbsp;judgment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We cannot from the evidence that God has given us decide this question. We are
left without an answer. If we grant the sufficiency of Scripture, then we must
recognize that if there are questions God has in his wisdom opted not to answer,
it is for a reason, and we should cease with our speculations and be silent. We
may not know whether infants are &lt;em&gt;guilty&lt;/em&gt;, but we do know two other things that
are far more important than that: First, God is merciful and gracious and just.
We will not in the final reckoning find his justice lacking or his treatment of
(for example) those who died in infancy to be lacking. Second, all are born
under the dual curse of sin&amp;#8217;s hold and death&amp;#8217;s&amp;nbsp;certainty.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These truths give us clear and straightforward points of application. First, we
must preach the gospel clearly to people of every age and intellectual ability,
for even little children sin and death is awaiting us all. Whether or not we are
born guilty, we &lt;em&gt;become&lt;/em&gt; guilty very quickly. Second, much of the speculation on
this question&amp;#8212;and many churches practices such as infant baptism&amp;#8212;seems to be
rooted in worry about the fate of those who die young, without having made a
credible profession of faith. Yet even if we &lt;em&gt;did&lt;/em&gt; know the answer to the
question of their guilt, we still might not know God&amp;#8217;s response. Even did we
know the answer, still we would need learn to trust in the goodness and wisdom
of God in this&amp;nbsp;matter.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 01 Feb 2014 08:30:00 -0500</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2014-02-01:2014/infant-guilt-purest-speculation.html</guid><category>M. Div.</category><category>SEBTS</category></item><item><title>What Was Their Sin?</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2014/what-was-their-sin.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;As Christians, we all recognize that Adam and Eve&amp;#8217;s first sin in the garden of
Eden prompted the catastropic Fall of all humanity, and that their eating of the
fruit of the tree of the knowledge of good and evil was the &lt;em&gt;act&lt;/em&gt; of sin that
produced such horrific results in human history. What is perhaps less clear is
why that particular act was sinful. Was it disobedience? gaining knowledge?
pride? idolatry? The most straightforward reading of Genesis 3 makes it clear
that the act was sinful at the most basic level because it was disobedience, a
direct rejection of the stated will of God. God tells Adam that the consequences
he receives are because he ate of the tree from which he was commanded not to
eat&amp;nbsp;(3:17).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perhaps the more interesting question, then, is why disobedience to God is a
sin. As Christians, we acknowledge that the Bible teaches us this truth. Digging
deeper is helpful in understanding many things about God and the nature of both
humanity and the shape of the world we inhabit. To describe why disobedience is
sinful, though, requires that we first define what sin &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt;. Sin is, at the most
basic level, failure&amp;#8212;missing the mark, as the Greek word would have it. The
next question, then, is: &lt;em&gt;Failure at&amp;nbsp;what?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sin is failure to be what humans were (and still are) meant to be&amp;#8212;a mystery of
ages, to which we have the answer. Genesis tells us exactly who we humans are.
We are made in the image of God. We are to be small icons of divine glory. The
divinity we are meant to recapitulate in miniature exists in perfect harmony, is
completely wise and wholly good, and exercises utter sovereignty. Women and men
are meant likewise to exist in true harmony, to be wise in right measure and
truly good, and to exercise sovereignty in our appointed spheres. This is what
it &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; to be human: to do as God does in the ways he appoints in the world he&amp;nbsp;made.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thus, to &lt;em&gt;fail&lt;/em&gt; at that task is no small thing. It is to fail in the most
significant way possible. Worse still, to fail as Adam and Eve did (and as we
all have ever since) can only happen in a conscious act. Yes, our natures are
now so corrupted that we all sin incidentally, too. But we all of us sin on
purpose. Our first father and mother did not fail accidentally. They willfully
rejected the very reason for their existence and spat in the face of the author
of that existence. (Here is the source of the human struggle for existential
meaning and the dread of meaningless that plagues us.) They rejected both the
shape of reality and the one who made reality. They rebelled. They became
traitors against the universe&amp;#8217;s&amp;nbsp;God.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Their sin, then, was not only disobedience. There are times when disobedience
might be right: one &lt;em&gt;should&lt;/em&gt; reject unjust commands. This, however, was not such
a command. Their act of disobedience included both mistrust of most trustworthy
God and self-exaltation over and against the only exalted God. God does not only
demand our allegiance, he &lt;em&gt;deserves&lt;/em&gt; it. He requires our worship not because he
is vain, but because to worship anything else, however lovely, is to do injury
to the object of that worship, to ourselves, and to the Triune Godhead. Adam and
Eve&amp;#8217;s eating of the fruit of the tree of the knowledge of good represented
precisely that offense. They rejected God&amp;#8217;s sovereignty, his wisdom and
goodness, and even fellowship with him. They rejected their own sphere of
sovereignty, chose quick knowledge over wisdom, deceit over goodness, and
treachery over&amp;nbsp;communion.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 25 Jan 2014 08:00:00 -0500</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2014-01-25:2014/what-was-their-sin.html</guid><category>M. Div.</category><category>SEBTS</category></item></channel></rss>