<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Chris Krycho</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/</link><description></description><atom:link href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/feeds/mdiv.xml" rel="self"></atom:link><lastBuildDate>Tue, 11 Feb 2014 08:30:00 -0500</lastBuildDate><item><title>Like His Brothers in Every Way</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2014/like-his-brothers-in-every-way.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Whether Jesus could have sinned or not is a question to tangle the mind. On the
one hand, we affirm that he was fully human, and this affirmation binds us to
affirm that he could indeed sin: all humans are capable of sinning, and apart
from Jesus, all humans &lt;em&gt;have&lt;/em&gt; sinned. The author of Hebrews reminds us
forcefully that Jesus was made like his brothers&amp;#8212;which is to say, &lt;em&gt;us&lt;/em&gt;&amp;#8212;in
every respect, being tempted like them, yet without sin. On the other hand, we
recognize that the Godhead is sinless and that, as James reminds us, he neither
tempts nor can be tempted with evil. As with many issues relating to the
Incarnation, we face the challenge of holding together both Jesus&amp;#8217; full deity
and his full humanity. When either is lost (or even simply diminished) in order
to emphasize or preserve the other, important aspects of our faith break in
serious&amp;nbsp;ways.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Difficult (mysterious even) the question may be, but the author of Hebrews
leaves little doubt. Jesus was tempted like us in &lt;em&gt;every&lt;/em&gt; way&amp;#8212;not only in some
ways, but in every way. This is an essential affirmation for the Christian
faith. If Jesus could not sin, then he was not fully human, and his perfect life
is unsurprising and not particularly meaningful. If he &lt;em&gt;could&lt;/em&gt; sin, then his
perfect life is extraordinary and especially&amp;nbsp;meaningful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the same time, we must integrate the things that Hebrews and James (and the
rest of the Scriptures) teach us. If the Godhead cannot be tempted by sin and
Jesus &lt;em&gt;was&lt;/em&gt; tempted by sin, does this make Jesus somehow &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; God? No, for this
misses the rest of the witness of the New Testament, including those selfsame
books. James himself calls Jesus Lord in terms that, set against a Jewish
background, can only be understood to refer to God himself (see especially James
5:11, perhaps the most direct quote of Exodus 34:6 in the whole New Testament
and an unmistakable reference to Yahweh God). Neither can we admit the notion
that James and Hebrews disagree with each other&amp;#8212;at least, not and maintain our
affirmation of the unity of Scripture, which is a non-negotiable from where I&amp;nbsp;stand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As with many things in the Trinity and the Incarnation, then, we are left making
a dual (and apparently conflicting affirmation). Jesus&amp;#8217; humanity was perfectly
capable of sinning, and his divinity was incapable of sinning. The Incarnation
holds the two together in a single person, and so we affirm that Jesus could
have sinned, but did not. We note, too, that he did not precisely because he did
as all humans are called to do (and what glorified humans &lt;em&gt;will&lt;/em&gt; do) and
perfectly trusted the Father by obeying the Holy Spirit. Jesus&amp;#8217; perfect life was
not the domination of his humanity by his divinity, but the submission of his
humanity to the divinity of the&amp;nbsp;Trinity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thus we affirm that Jesus&amp;#8217; not sinning on our behalf was a real moral victory,
not a hollow thing we can only look at bemusedly from afar. He lived as a real
second Adam, doing what the first Adam failed to do while beset by many more and
far greater temptations than the first Adam. He really did overcome the world&amp;#8212;
not only its powers, but its temptations. He really did demonstrate true and
perfect holiness that we might follow his example. He really did triumph over
every power of sin, that we might be transformed into his likeness. Though the
triune God is never tempted to sin, the triune God mysteriously partook of
everything it is to be human in the Incarnation, and that humanity &lt;em&gt;could&lt;/em&gt; be
tempted&amp;#8212;and he&amp;nbsp;overcame.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 11 Feb 2014 08:30:00 -0500</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2014-02-11:2014/like-his-brothers-in-every-way.html</guid><category>M.&amp;hairsp;Div.</category></item><item><title>The Mother of God</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2014/the-mother-of-god.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Is it right to call Mary the Mother of God? The historic, orthodox answer is a
resounding &amp;#8220;yes&amp;#8221;&amp;#8212;though a clearly qualified and well articulated &amp;#8220;yes.&amp;#8221; This
is not just the historic, orthodox position; it is the &lt;em&gt;right&lt;/em&gt; position. Mary
was indeed the &amp;#8220;mother of God&amp;#8221;. She was the mother of Jesus. Jesus was (and is)
fully God &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; fully man, completely and truly, both at once without loss of
the full measure of either. He did not cease being totally divine upon his
incarnation, but he did assume full humanity. The argument is as simple as it
first seems: Mary is the mother of Jesus, and Jesus is God, therefore Mary is
the mother of&amp;nbsp;God.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Evangelicals tend to shy away from following the broader tradition and affirming
that Mary is the mother of God. There are many reasons for this, not least our
general discomfort with things having to do with Mary born of the over-
referencing of Mary in the Catholic tradition and the actual Mariolatry that is
too often evinced in Catholic lay practice throughout the world. However, our
response ought not be to reject this view, but to speak carefully and clearly
and reject what is mistaken while keeping what is&amp;nbsp;true.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is true that we must be nuanced in our handling of this issue. The word
&amp;#8220;mother&amp;#8221; brings with it implications that we must avoid, and we must remember
Jesus&amp;#8217; statements on what it meant to be his mother and brothers and sisters in
the gospels (i.e. that those who followed him were those really deserving of the
titles). However, simply to set aside the title is to lose important aspects of
the reality of the incarnation. If we say that Mary was &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; the mother of God,
we are really saying either that she was not truly the mother of Jesus, or that
Jesus was not fully God. Neither of these is a tolerable&amp;nbsp;option.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, to those qualifications. When we say that Mary is the mother of God, we are
not saying that God in any sense has his source in her. All of the humanity of
Jesus finds its source equally in Mary and in the Spirit&amp;#8217;s divine intervention
&amp;#8212;but Mary was created by the Son, rather than the Son originating in her. Mary
is the mother of God in Christ, but she is not to the Son exactly as ordinary
mothers are to ordinary sons, for Jesus was not an ordinary&amp;nbsp;son.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nor do we mean that Mary has special prerogatives because of her relationship to
Jesus. As noted above, Jesus made clear that he was concerned above all with
obedience to the will of God (see e.g. Matthew 12:46&amp;#8211;50). Thus, the devotions
offered to Mary by our Catholic and Eastern Orthodox brothers and sisters is
misplaced, as is the notion that her prayers are somehow more effective in
touching Jesus&amp;#8217; heart than are those of the ordinary saint who is seeking to
honor&amp;nbsp;God.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These qualifications notwithstanding, we must still be willing and ready to
affirm that Mary was in fact the Mother of God. To do otherwise is to reduce in
one way or another the mystery of the incarnation. It is not so much that &lt;em&gt;Mary&lt;/em&gt;
is important here as that affirming her motherhood of God helps us affirm the
important points to which we must hold fast in terms the full deity and full
humanity of &lt;em&gt;Christ&lt;/em&gt;. Mary is important because Jesus humanity came by means of
Mary&amp;#8217;s body. Everything that it is to be man, Jesus always was from conception,
and everything that it is to be God, Jesus always was from the moment of his&amp;nbsp;conception.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 04 Feb 2014 08:30:00 -0500</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2014-02-04:2014/the-mother-of-god.html</guid><category>M.&amp;hairsp;Div.</category></item><item><title>Infant Guilt—Purest Speculation</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2014/infant-guilt-purest-speculation.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Whether people are born guilty of sin, or simply inherit a nature so predisposed
to sin that the actual act is inevitable has been a much debated topic for
generations. In my view, however, the question is impossible to answer. I do not
think Scripture speaks with sufficient clarity on the matter. We know on the one
hand that all are &amp;#8220;by nature children of wrath&amp;#8221; (Ephesians 2:3), and that &amp;#8220;all
have sinned and fall short of the glory of God&amp;#8221; (Romans 3:23). What neither of
these texts tell us, though, and what indeed &lt;em&gt;no&lt;/em&gt; text tells us, is whether
people are guilty at birth or whether they are simply sinful and become&amp;nbsp;guilty.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We could reason to a conclusion that accords with our other theological
commitments with little difficulty. We know that God is just, and punishes for
the wrongs we commit, but we have no evidence that he punishes wrongs we &lt;em&gt;might&lt;/em&gt;
commit, and therefore we might conclude that he would therefore not find guilty
any newly conceived or newly born person. On the other hand, we also must reckon
with the reality that the Scriptures treat questions of progeny far differently
than do individually-minded modern&amp;nbsp;Westerners.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Scripture points us to the God who &amp;#8220;will by no means clear the guilty, visiting
the iniquity of the fathers on the children and the children&amp;#8217;s children, to the
third and the fourth generation&amp;#8221; (Exodus 34:7) as well as the God who proclaims
that &amp;#8220;The soul who sins shall die. The son shall not suffer for the iniquity of
the father, nor the father suffer for the iniquity of the son&amp;#8221; (Ezekiel 18:20).
Paul did write that &amp;#8220;one trespass led to condemnation for all men,&amp;#8221; but he
immediately follows up this provocative statement by arguing that &amp;#8220;one act of
righteousness leads to justification and life for all men&amp;#8221; (Romans 5:18)&amp;#8212;yet
we know that Paul does not (and cannot) here mean that all men are saved, for we
know that he believes that those who do not repent and believe the gospel perish
in their sins under the expectation of&amp;nbsp;judgment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We cannot from the evidence that God has given us decide this question. We are
left without an answer. If we grant the sufficiency of Scripture, then we must
recognize that if there are questions God has in his wisdom opted not to answer,
it is for a reason, and we should cease with our speculations and be silent. We
may not know whether infants are &lt;em&gt;guilty&lt;/em&gt;, but we do know two other things that
are far more important than that: First, God is merciful and gracious and just.
We will not in the final reckoning find his justice lacking or his treatment of
(for example) those who died in infancy to be lacking. Second, all are born
under the dual curse of sin&amp;#8217;s hold and death&amp;#8217;s&amp;nbsp;certainty.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These truths give us clear and straightforward points of application. First, we
must preach the gospel clearly to people of every age and intellectual ability,
for even little children sin and death is awaiting us all. Whether or not we are
born guilty, we &lt;em&gt;become&lt;/em&gt; guilty very quickly. Second, much of the speculation on
this question&amp;#8212;and many churches practices such as infant baptism&amp;#8212;seems to be
rooted in worry about the fate of those who die young, without having made a
credible profession of faith. Yet even if we &lt;em&gt;did&lt;/em&gt; know the answer to the
question of their guilt, we still might not know God&amp;#8217;s response. Even did we
know the answer, still we would need learn to trust in the goodness and wisdom
of God in this&amp;nbsp;matter.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 01 Feb 2014 08:30:00 -0500</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2014-02-01:2014/infant-guilt-purest-speculation.html</guid><category>M.&amp;hairsp;Div.</category></item><item><title>What Was Their Sin?</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2014/what-was-their-sin.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;As Christians, we all recognize that Adam and Eve&amp;#8217;s first sin in the garden of
Eden prompted the catastropic Fall of all humanity, and that their eating of the
fruit of the tree of the knowledge of good and evil was the &lt;em&gt;act&lt;/em&gt; of sin that
produced such horrific results in human history. What is perhaps less clear is
why that particular act was sinful. Was it disobedience? gaining knowledge?
pride? idolatry? The most straightforward reading of Genesis 3 makes it clear
that the act was sinful at the most basic level because it was disobedience, a
direct rejection of the stated will of God. God tells Adam that the consequences
he receives are because he ate of the tree from which he was commanded not to
eat&amp;nbsp;(3:17).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perhaps the more interesting question, then, is why disobedience to God is a
sin. As Christians, we acknowledge that the Bible teaches us this truth. Digging
deeper is helpful in understanding many things about God and the nature of both
humanity and the shape of the world we inhabit. To describe why disobedience is
sinful, though, requires that we first define what sin &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt;. Sin is, at the most
basic level, failure&amp;#8212;missing the mark, as the Greek word would have it. The
next question, then, is: &lt;em&gt;Failure at&amp;nbsp;what?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sin is failure to be what humans were (and still are) meant to be&amp;#8212;a mystery of
ages, to which we have the answer. Genesis tells us exactly who we humans are.
We are made in the image of God. We are to be small icons of divine glory. The
divinity we are meant to recapitulate in miniature exists in perfect harmony, is
completely wise and wholly good, and exercises utter sovereignty. Women and men
are meant likewise to exist in true harmony, to be wise in right measure and
truly good, and to exercise sovereignty in our appointed spheres. This is what
it &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; to be human: to do as God does in the ways he appoints in the world he&amp;nbsp;made.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thus, to &lt;em&gt;fail&lt;/em&gt; at that task is no small thing. It is to fail in the most
significant way possible. Worse still, to fail as Adam and Eve did (and as we
all have ever since) can only happen in a conscious act. Yes, our natures are
now so corrupted that we all sin incidentally, too. But we all of us sin on
purpose. Our first father and mother did not fail accidentally. They willfully
rejected the very reason for their existence and spat in the face of the author
of that existence. (Here is the source of the human struggle for existential
meaning and the dread of meaningless that plagues us.) They rejected both the
shape of reality and the one who made reality. They rebelled. They became
traitors against the universe&amp;#8217;s&amp;nbsp;God.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Their sin, then, was not only disobedience. There are times when disobedience
might be right: one &lt;em&gt;should&lt;/em&gt; reject unjust commands. This, however, was not such
a command. Their act of disobedience included both mistrust of most trustworthy
God and self-exaltation over and against the only exalted God. God does not only
demand our allegiance, he &lt;em&gt;deserves&lt;/em&gt; it. He requires our worship not because he
is vain, but because to worship anything else, however lovely, is to do injury
to the object of that worship, to ourselves, and to the Triune Godhead. Adam and
Eve&amp;#8217;s eating of the fruit of the tree of the knowledge of good represented
precisely that offense. They rejected God&amp;#8217;s sovereignty, his wisdom and
goodness, and even fellowship with him. They rejected their own sphere of
sovereignty, chose quick knowledge over wisdom, deceit over goodness, and
treachery over&amp;nbsp;communion.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 25 Jan 2014 08:00:00 -0500</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2014-01-25:2014/what-was-their-sin.html</guid><category>M.&amp;hairsp;Div.</category></item></channel></rss>