<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Chris Krycho</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/</link><description></description><atom:link href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/feeds/my-writing-elsewhere.xml" rel="self"></atom:link><lastBuildDate>Tue, 25 Mar 2014 08:00:00 -0400</lastBuildDate><item><title>God Become Man: Toward a Richer Theology of the Incarnation</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2014/god-become-man-toward-a-richer-theology-of-the-incarnation.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;My latest piece over at Mere Orthodoxy (and the first such in too long):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It has been common these past few years to speak of “incarnational theology” as a way of describing the Christian mission to the world: we ought to “incarnate” Christ to the world as Christ “incarnated” the Godhead to us. There is much to appreciate in this sentiment…. Yet for all that, I think that applying the language of incarnation to believers is a serious mistake.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Incarnation matters, and it matters as more than a means of getting Jesus to the cross so that he could die for our sins. We evangelicals too often reduce everything to penal substitutionary atonement. Yes, the atonement is incredible and amazing. It is one of the central affirmations and joys of the Christian faith: our sins are paid for! Glory to God! But Jesus did more than that, and he is worthy of yet more praise. He did not stop at paying the price for our sins while leaving our bodies subject to corruption. He did not content himself with performing a judicial act while leaving our wills broken, certain to turn again to the same sin that led to our death in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think &lt;a href="http://mereorthodoxy.com/god-become-man-richer-theology-incarnation/"&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; is the best thing I’ve written so far this year; I hope you find it stimulating.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="references"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 25 Mar 2014 08:00:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2014-03-25:2014/god-become-man-toward-a-richer-theology-of-the-incarnation.html</guid><category>links</category><category>my writing elsewhere</category></item></channel></rss>