<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Chris Krycho - note-taking</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/</link><description></description><lastBuildDate>Mon, 29 Apr 2019 20:00:00 -0400</lastBuildDate><item><title>What is a Zettelkasten?</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2019/what-is-a-zettelkasten.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.chriskrycho.com/2018/assumed-audiences.html"&gt;Assumed Audience&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/b&gt; People interested in note-taking, effective learning, or the idea of a Zettelkasten (which &lt;a href="https://www.chriskrycho.com/zettelkasten/"&gt;I’ve written about before&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A friend recently asked me: “What exactly &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; a Zettelkasten?” Unfortunately, there aren’t any (easy-to-find, anyway) answers in a single place online… hopefully until today!&lt;a href="#fn1" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref1" role="doc-noteref"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; The short answer is: a well-organized box (or group of boxes) of notecards. The word itself is just German for &lt;i&gt;an index card box&lt;/i&gt;. Given you likely landed here via an internet search, though, I expect you might want a bit more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A Zettelkasten as an idea dates to the work of the 20th century German sociologist &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Special:Search?search=Niklas%20Luhmann&amp;amp;go=Go"&gt;Niklas Luhmann&lt;/a&gt;, who used a large system of carefully labeled notecards (an index card is a &lt;i&gt;zettel&lt;/i&gt;) as a form of &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hypertext"&gt;hypertext&lt;/a&gt;. (The linked Wikipedia article notwithstanding, hypertext works perfectly well without any digital technologies: the real key to the idea is &lt;em&gt;links&lt;/em&gt; that you can easily follow.) In the system Luhmann devised, each notecard gets a unique identifier, which can then be used to reference it from other notecards, and which have a well-defined order of some sort.&lt;a href="#fn2" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref2" role="doc-noteref"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; They can also have keywords—tags—that group them into related sets of ideas. A full Zettelkasten also usually includes not just individual notes but also organizational notes. These serve as pointers and structure for whole other sets of notes—summaries of sets of knowledge you’ve built up over time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using this strategy transforms a &lt;em&gt;collection&lt;/em&gt; of notes into a &lt;em&gt;web&lt;/em&gt; of notes. If you build up that web carefully, you can follow the connections between notes in novel directions over time. This is great for memory, because it helps you cement those relationships in your own mind. Even more importantly, though, working with your notes as a network can produce brand new questions and ideas. Connections that were not immediately apparent can become so as you add more links and structures to the system. The Zettelkasten becomes a tool not merely for recollection but for &lt;em&gt;thought&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The beauty of this approach is its simplicity: A Zettelkasten is just a low-overhead, high-value way of creating, managing, and making use of a system of notes. It can use notecards, or &lt;a href="https://bear.app"&gt;any good note-taking app&lt;/a&gt;, or any combination of things that lets you easily “link” to and therefore navigate between notes. Its power is not in spite of but precisely because of that simplicity!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;aside&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As it turns out, I’ve tried a lot of different apps for this kind of thing—or &lt;em&gt;especially&lt;/em&gt; for research writing in general, of which note-taking is a huge part. Unfortunately, none of the existing apps quite hit the spot for me. So, being a good software developer… I’m building one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you’re interested, you can get updates on that project by subscribing to &lt;a href="https://buttondown.email/rewrite"&gt;the app newsletter&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;form action="https://buttondown.email/api/emails/embed-subscribe/rewrite" method="post" target="popupwindow" onsubmit="window.open(&amp;#39;https://buttondown.email/rewrite&amp;#39;, &amp;#39;popupwindow&amp;#39;)" class="embeddable-buttondown-form"&gt;
&lt;label for="bd-email"&gt;Enter your email:&lt;/label&gt; &lt;input type="email" name="email" id="bd-email"&gt; &lt;input type="hidden" value="1" name="embed"/&gt; &lt;input type="submit" value="Subscribe" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href="https://buttondown.email" target="_blank"&gt;Powered by Buttondown&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/form&gt;
&lt;/aside&gt;
&lt;section class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn1" role="doc-endnote"&gt;&lt;p&gt;I first learned about the idea &lt;a href="https://blog.ayjay.org/my-zettelkasten/"&gt;from Alan Jacobs&lt;/a&gt;, and then more from &lt;a href="https://zettelkasten.de"&gt;a dedicated site&lt;/a&gt;—but while Jacobs’ post gives a reasonably good summary, as does &lt;a href="https://zettelkasten.de/posts/zettelkasten-improves-thinking-writing/"&gt;this post&lt;/a&gt; on that dedicated site, neither has much search prominence.&lt;a href="#fnref1" class="footnote-back" role="doc-backlink"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn2" role="doc-endnote"&gt;&lt;p&gt;I’ve chosen to organize my own Zettelkasten by date, because &lt;a href="https://www.chriskrycho.com/2018/blog-as-note-taking-tool.html"&gt;I find&lt;/a&gt; that seeing what I was thinking at a particular time can be very helpful and very interesting, and it’s also often a &lt;a href="https://zettelkasten.de/posts/add-identity/"&gt;helpful way of remembering things&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;a href="#fnref2" class="footnote-back" role="doc-backlink"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 29 Apr 2019 20:00:00 -0400</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2019-04-29:/2019/what-is-a-zettelkasten.html</guid><category>writing</category><category>note-taking</category><category>zettelkasten</category></item><item><title>Don’t Forget Your Notebook</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2019/dont-forget-your-notebook.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.chriskrycho.com/2018/assumed-audiences.html"&gt;Assumed Audience&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/b&gt; people interested in research, note-taking, memory, and the like.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m sitting at a coffee shop enjoying a tasty drink and working on an app idea I’ve been slowly fleshing out over the last 3½ years… in a paper notebook.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ve been &lt;a href="https://www.chriskrycho.com/zettelkasten/" title="#zettelkasten on chriskrycho.com"&gt;writing a bit&lt;/a&gt; here over the last month or so about my experiment in building a &lt;a href="https://zettelkasten.de/posts/extend-your-mind-and-memory-with-a-zettelkasten/" title="Extend Your Mind and Memory With a Zettelkasten"&gt;Zettelkasten&lt;/a&gt;, and so far I’m quite pleased with it. It’s already proven helpful to me, and given my experiences so far I expect it to be much more so over the (hopefully many!) years ahead. I’ve &lt;a href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2018/starting-to-build-a-zettelkasten.html" title="Starting to Build a Zettelkasten"&gt;noted&lt;/a&gt; that &lt;a href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2018/zettelkasten-update-all-in-on-bear.html" title="Zettelkasten Update: All in on Bear"&gt;I’m putting all of my notes&lt;/a&gt; in &lt;a href="https://bear.app"&gt;Bear&lt;/a&gt;, as it’s a handy tool that &lt;em&gt;mostly&lt;/em&gt; maps to the way I think about note-taking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I’m sitting working on this app design, though, it strikes me how valuable I find a physical notebook to be. Plain old pen and paper remain my favorite tool for &lt;em&gt;thinking&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m not alone in this, &lt;a href="https://zettelkasten.de/posts/use-real-notebook/" title="Use a Real Notebook"&gt;even among the proponents of a Zettelkasten approach&lt;/a&gt;. Nor does this surprise me. I’ve long observed that I write—and, more importantly—&lt;em&gt;think&lt;/em&gt; differently with pen and paper than I do with keyboard and computer.&lt;a href="#fn1" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref1"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; That is true &lt;em&gt;especially&lt;/em&gt; true of poetry, but it’s still a factor even for something like app design—and not only, but certainly, as a factor of the tactility of it and for the sheer analogicity (if you’ll pardon the neologism) of it. Pen scratching on paper, with &lt;em&gt;genuinely&lt;/em&gt; immediate feedback, is different even than the best experience of stylus and laptop.&lt;a href="#fn2" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref2"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; Even for something like sketching out a particular &lt;abbr title="user interface"&gt;UI&lt;/abbr&gt; flow, a notebook affords different things than a tablet does. Perhaps doubly so because of the very analog nature of pen and paper: I am not tempted to make sure my lines are &lt;i&gt;just so&lt;/i&gt; on paper as I am on an iPad, where “undo” is a constant temptation, the very expression of the perfect being the enemy of the good.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The net of this is simple: even if you’re adopting something like &lt;a href="https://bear.app"&gt;Bear&lt;/a&gt; for your way of storing and searching your notes, it’s valuable to have paper and pen-or-pencil near to hand. You may spend a little more time copying and elaborating notes as you transfer them from your notebook than you would if you simply did everything digitally from the start, but you will also think different—and, at least in my experience, &lt;em&gt;better&lt;/em&gt;—thoughts using pen and paper than not.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s a truism in software development that we ought to use the right tool fo the job. The same goes for &lt;em&gt;learning&lt;/em&gt;, and we ought not facilely dismiss the old tools simply because the newer ones have their own strengths.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section class="footnotes"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn1"&gt;&lt;p&gt;I include iPads here, because the difference &lt;em&gt;seems&lt;/em&gt; to be typing into a screen. There are also real differences I perceive between writing with an iPad and keyboard than with a traditional computer, but those pale in comparison to the difference between computer and analog.&lt;a href="#fnref1" class="footnote-back"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn2"&gt;&lt;p&gt;I have an iPad Pro with an Apple Pencil. The responsiveness is astounding and outstanding; but it is not paper and pen.&lt;a href="#fnref2" class="footnote-back"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 03 Jan 2019 17:40:00 -0500</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2019-01-03:/2019/dont-forget-your-notebook.html</guid><category>writing</category><category>Zettelkasten</category><category>note-taking</category><category>research</category></item><item><title>Trying a New Book-Reading Strategy</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2018/trying-a-new-book-reading-strategy.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.chriskrycho.com/2018/assumed-audiences.html"&gt;Assumed Audience:&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/b&gt; people broadly interested in reading, writing, learning, and research systems.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today I started trying a new(-to-me!) approach to deeply reading books, with some relatively light reading (so that I can get the practice).&lt;a href="#fn1" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref1"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; I’m hoping to be able to grow this skill and use it effectively for learning deeply in 2019. The strategy is pretty simple:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol type="1"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Use very quick, light marks in the margins: &lt;code&gt;✓&lt;/code&gt; for agreement, &lt;code&gt;x&lt;/code&gt; for disagreement, &lt;code&gt;~&lt;/code&gt; for something that’s worth noting as halfway right but worth clarifying, and &lt;code&gt;*&lt;/code&gt; for key arguments. This is basically the tack I’ve taken for a long time, but I’ve dropped all underlining or bracketing from the process: they’re slow, and I’m not really persuaded they’re more helpful than just adding a quick mark, as the really helpful bits come later in my experience.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;On finishing reading each chapter (or major section):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pull in the quotes I want to keep from it. Interact with them as makes sense.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Create a note with a short summary of the argument of the chapter. Link from it to the quotes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The goal here is to have a quick view into the contents of the chapter, including the various quotes that were particularly salient from it.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;On finishing the book, summarize the argument of the book by using the quotes and summaries of the chapters along the way to guide me in formulating my own interpretation of the author’s arguments. Add in some explicit interaction with the argument-in-sum.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Along the way, I’ll also write up other thoughts and interactions with the text, linking them to the other notes as makes sense.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once I have these kinds of notes, I will have a lot of material available to put to whatever use. Most importantly, I will have done a lot more active thinking about the ideas I encountered, and will have quick access to those thoughts to build on later. But I will also be able to use both those quick references to the book and to my own thoughts as prompted by the book to generate writing prompts for blog posts, book reviews, teaching notes, and so on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You’ll notice that this is quite similar in a number of ways to &lt;a href="https://www.chriskrycho.com/2018/just-write-down-what-you-do.html"&gt;my approach to logging my work&lt;/a&gt;; that’s intentional. I have found that an extremely fruitful way to be able to quickly grasp what I have &lt;em&gt;done&lt;/em&gt; over a given span. It seems likely that this variant on it will be equally useful for quickly grasping what I have &lt;em&gt;read&lt;/em&gt; over a given span.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One other note: I will definitely not be doing this for &lt;em&gt;everything&lt;/em&gt; I read. That would be laborious indeed! I plan to do this for books which I find to be of particularly high value this way. Many books simply do not warrant it, and indeed warrant little more than a quick skim (or to be put aside entirely). I wrote a couple days ago about my intent to use my time more carefully in 2019; one part of that is carefully distinguishing in &lt;em&gt;how&lt;/em&gt; I read as well as &lt;em&gt;what&lt;/em&gt; I read.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section class="footnotes"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn1"&gt;&lt;p&gt;I’m reading &lt;cite&gt;The Shepherd Leader: Achieving Effective Shepherding in Your Church&lt;/cite&gt;, by Timothy Z. Witmer, as part of the elder training work at my church, as I have been nominated to and expect to stand for the office of elder in mid-2019. That might not seem like light reading to you, but I’ve read an awful lot of academic theology over the last decade and no few books in this same vein during my M. Div. work.&lt;a href="#fnref1" class="footnote-back"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 26 Dec 2018 09:10:00 -0500</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2018-12-26:/2018/trying-a-new-book-reading-strategy.html</guid><category>Zettelkasten</category><category>note-taking</category><category>research</category><category>reading</category></item></channel></rss>