<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Chris Krycho - notes</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/</link><description></description><lastBuildDate>Wed, 05 Dec 2018 08:30:00 -0500</lastBuildDate><item><title>Starting to Build a Zettelkasten</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2018/starting-to-build-a-zettelkasten.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.chriskrycho.com/2018/assumed-audiences.html"&gt;Assumed Audience:&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/b&gt; people broadly interested in reading, writing, learning, and research systems.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I’ve been slowly mulling on a number of things over the last few weeks, it became increasingly clear to me that I needed to invest a bit more in my research system. I’ve &lt;a href="https://www.chriskrycho.com/2017/how-do-you-manage-your-research-notes.html"&gt;asked before&lt;/a&gt; how people manage their own research, and I’ve noted how &lt;a href="https://www.chriskrycho.com/2018/blog-as-note-taking-tool.html"&gt;I use my blog as a note-taking tool of sorts&lt;/a&gt;. As I’ve started digging into a couple larger problems—one of which is likely going to take me a decade of work—I’ve come back to this question, and I find that I still don’t have great answers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Something like the &lt;a href="https://zettelkasten.de"&gt;Zettelkasten approach&lt;/a&gt; seems like it probably does what I need it to. So this week I’ve started organizing notes in &lt;a href="https://bear.app"&gt;Bear&lt;/a&gt; that way. I’m &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; taking the tack sometimes advocated of intentionally having no hierarchy whatsoever for my notes, though I’m eschewing any particularly deep hierarchies. I consistently find that I need some kind of project or “notebook” level of organization when I’m digging deep on something, and it’s always nice to hear that I’m not alone in that. &lt;a href="https://blog.ayjay.org/my-zettelkasten/"&gt;Alan Jacobs, on the same topic:&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, I thought, why not have a collection of Zettel that is based not on a lifetime of research but on a single project? So I tried that. And it worked wonderfully.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unlike Jacobs, the notecard system doesn’t work for me. I enjoy writing notes by hand, but in a lot of cases I’m writing down code snippets, which is very hard to do on notecards unless the code snippets are &lt;em&gt;very&lt;/em&gt; brief. Instead, I’m so far making heavy use of Bear’s ability to &lt;a href="https://bear.app/faq/Tags%20&amp;amp;%20Linking/How%20to%20link%20notes%20together/"&gt;link between notes&lt;/a&gt;, and even heavier use of Bear’s &lt;a href="https://bear.app/faq/Tags%20&amp;amp;%20Linking/Nested%20Tags/"&gt;tagging system&lt;/a&gt; for adding keywords to notes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In line with my comment about hierarchy, though, I’m only allowing myself one level of hierarchy: the “project” or “notebook.” Everything in that “notebook” is a single keyword/tag deep, structured like &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;notebook&amp;gt;/&amp;lt;keyword&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;—never &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;notebook&amp;gt;/&amp;lt;keyword&amp;gt;/&amp;lt;another keyword.&lt;/code&gt;. I am also freely including tags across these “notebooks”: something might be in &lt;code&gt;A/q&lt;/code&gt; and also &lt;code&gt;C/z&lt;/code&gt;. That gives me the best of both worlds: project-level organization, but also the ability to see associations that play out beyond an individual project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We’ll see how this plays out, but so far I’m liking it a lot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Amusingly, it’s forcing me to clean up my existing set of notes in Bear: things tagged “writing/ideas” are now getting pushed over into a corresponding bucket in &lt;a href="https://ulysses.app"&gt;Ulysses&lt;/a&gt;, which is my preferred application for actually &lt;em&gt;writing&lt;/em&gt;. Miscellaneous/non-project notes are currently going in a top level “notebook”—a top level tag in Bear—called &lt;code&gt;z&lt;/code&gt; (for Zettelkasten). Under it I have things like &lt;code&gt;z/pedagogy&lt;/code&gt;, but once again, I’m intentionally allowing myself only one level of nesting here. I am still &lt;a href="https://www.chriskrycho.com/2018/just-write-down-what-you-do.html"&gt;logging my work&lt;/a&gt; in a work tag. And I also have notebooks for things like food, gift ideas, etc., since Bear is currently my go-to notes app. (This is part of what forced me to the project/notebook mentality in the first place: having dozens of top-level tags in that sidebar was just going to break my brain.) But hopefully having all these notes around and in a just-structured-&lt;em&gt;enough&lt;/em&gt; form will be useful as I work on these larger projects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ll report more as I keep going with this!&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 05 Dec 2018 08:30:00 -0500</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2018-12-05:/2018/starting-to-build-a-zettelkasten.html</guid><category>writing</category><category>research</category><category>Zettelkasten</category><category>notes</category></item><item><title>Blog as Note-Taking Tool</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2018/blog-as-note-taking-tool.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;I have a habit that might not make sense to you. I reread my own blog posts fairly regularly. It’s not vanity—not some weird obsession with my own awesomeness in the form of my own writing or some such nonsense. It’s that in my blog posts over the last decade, I have a pretty serious backlog of &lt;em&gt;what I was thinking about at any given point in time.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s not exhaustive, by a long shot. It only includes things I actually decided to publish.&lt;a href="#fn1" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref1"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; There are, sadly, not many short thoughts in the mix. Nor is it well-tagged or organized in any internally-consistent way—even in any single version of the site, much less across versions. But nonetheless the history is still there, and I &lt;em&gt;can&lt;/em&gt; traverse the various lines through it, such as they are. (Sometimes, even, the changes in organization and structure are illuminating about how I was thinking about things at the time!) In any case, my habit of linking to previous references to ideas has proven invaluable for the times when I want to trawl back through old posts and consider those old thoughts again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reading old blog posts is a strange experience, of course. The person who wrote these things was recognizably myself; but I am not who I then I was, and I sometimes disagree with myself on the substance and often on the style. (I occasionally find an old gem and wonder how I ever managed to write so well.) That very strangeness, it turns out, is why I do this every so often, though. Thinking well is often a matter of forging connections between ideas that were previously not connected for us. We cannot consciously hold in our minds even a fraction of all the things we have thought about or even written something about over the years. We can, however, jog our memories, and let new connections form. And rereading one’s own blog post is a great way to do that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’d not heard specifically of the &lt;a href="https://zettelkasten.de"&gt;Zettelkasten method&lt;/a&gt; until Alan Jacobs linked it a while back, but it fits this model pretty perfectly, and maps as well to ways I’ve been &lt;em&gt;trying&lt;/em&gt; to structure my note-taking and thinking for the past few years. (I’m going to be consciously doing more of this in &lt;a href="http://www.bear-writer.com"&gt;Bear&lt;/a&gt;, my current notes app of choice. I’ll probably write up my experience that way once I’ve actually had some experience!) But this also ties into some of the things Jacobs has been &lt;a href="https://blog.ayjay.org/the-blog-garden/" title="The Blog Garden"&gt;musing out loud&lt;/a&gt; about in his own blog over the last week. It’s not just that a blog can serve as a place to do some of the fleshing-out of ideas. It’s not just that a blog can be a record of the development of ideas. It can also serve to jog new ideas if you read yourself again, displaced (both literally and temporally) from the original writing of the thing. A blog is kind of like a public notebook, and while it &lt;em&gt;may&lt;/em&gt; be useful for others to browse through it, is &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; useful for me to browse back through it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section class="footnotes"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn1"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Though: if you look at the archives, especially including those on my &lt;a href="http://blog.chriskrycho.com" title="Thoughts; A Flame"&gt;first real blog&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="http://2012-2013.chriskrycho.com"&gt;the previous iteration of this site&lt;/a&gt;, you’ll notice that I published a lot of posts about a lot of subjects, whether my thoughts were especially well-formed or not.&lt;a href="#fnref1" class="footnote-back"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 16 Jul 2018 07:00:00 -0400</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2018-07-16:/2018/blog-as-note-taking-tool.html</guid><category>Zettelkasten</category><category>notes</category><category>memory</category><category>writing</category><category>blogging</category></item></channel></rss>