<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Chris Krycho - patronage</title><link>http://v4.chriskrycho.com/</link><description></description><lastBuildDate>Tue, 01 Jan 2019 10:23:00 -0500</lastBuildDate><item><title>I Have a Patreon!</title><link>http://v4.chriskrycho.com/2019/i-have-a-patreon.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;a href="https://v4.chriskrycho.com/2018/assumed-audiences.html"&gt;Assumed Audience&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/b&gt; people who &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; like this website and like patronage or crowd-funding.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Happy 2019, readers! As I move into 2019, I wanted to publicize something that has &lt;em&gt;existed&lt;/em&gt; for most of the last year, but which I have not yet made much noise about: &lt;a href="https://patreon.com/chriskrycho"&gt;my Patreon&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this space, I write blog posts and essays on technology, theology, and art. I write about the process of building open-source software. I sometimes even write poetry and compose music and share those here! &lt;em&gt;I do all of those things no matter what.&lt;/em&gt; But if you wanted to support my various efforts in this space by helping me stay well-supplied with delicious coffee, I’d really appreciate it!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The benefits for patrons, as I’m publicly launching it:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;colgroup&gt;
&lt;col style="width: 14%" /&gt;
&lt;col style="width: 49%" /&gt;
&lt;col style="width: 36%" /&gt;
&lt;/colgroup&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr class="header"&gt;
&lt;th&gt;$1/month&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;$5/month&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;$25/month&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr class="odd"&gt;
&lt;td&gt;A shoutout on Twitter!&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;⃪ plus access to a private podcast about what I’m thinking about and working!&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;⃪ plus commentary and ancillary materials for my essays!&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don’t expect this kind of patronage ever to be a massive part of my income. I do think it’s a good thing to support the writers and thinkers whose work impacts us, and so it’s important to &lt;em&gt;let&lt;/em&gt; people support us if they’re interested in doing so! So if you’d like to support the work I do on this website, and especially if you’d like to see me do more of the important, careful essays that are the kinds of things I want to be doing, consider supporting me!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(Note that posts about this will not be a regular occurrence on the blog. I will probably integrate a link to the Patreon account into my RSS feed, but otherwise I will not mention it on the site more than once a year.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Regardless of whether you support my work on this site financially, thank you for reading!&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 01 Jan 2019 10:23:00 -0500</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:v4.chriskrycho.com,2019-01-01:/2019/i-have-a-patreon.html</guid><category>crowdfunding</category><category>patronage</category><category>writing</category></item></channel></rss>