<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Chris Krycho</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/</link><description></description><atom:link href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/feeds/philosophy.xml" rel="self"></atom:link><lastBuildDate>Mon, 16 May 2016 23:55:00 -0400</lastBuildDate><item><title>Realism and Antirealism</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2016/realism-and-antirealism.html</link><description>&lt;section id="part-i-argument-for-realism" class="level1"&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Part I: Argument for Realism&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;section id="introduction-definition-constraints" class="level2"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;1. Introduction, Definition, Constraints&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because these facts… are so striking, because there was no reason &lt;em&gt;a priori&lt;/em&gt; to expect man to be able to achieve such cognitive feats, because no undertaking can guarantee success &lt;em&gt;of this particular sort&lt;/em&gt;, we are confronted with a genuine problem: why is science so successful?&lt;span class="citation" data-cites="laudan:beyond-realism"&gt;&lt;a href="#fn1" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref1"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The success of science over the last four hundred years has produced a radical increase in effective prediction of natural phenomena across a wide array of domains. It has also yielded a striking ability to intervene successfully in the natural world in areas as diverse as biology and medicine on the one hand, and particle physics and the development of computing technology on the other. Yet, when scientists speak of electrons, quarks, dark matter, and so on—phenomena not directly accessible to ordinary human experience, but in many cases directly related to this empirical and technological success—it is an open question in philosophy of science whether such entities really exist, or are merely useful ways of solving problems and dealing with data. Scientific realism is the affirmation that the entities postulated by scientific theories actually do exist. This claim does not entail the success of all scientific theories, and is therefore not compromised by the failure and replacement of some scientific theories. Nor does it require that all theories be embraced equally firmly. It simply means the claims and practice of science do really, if only approximately, describe the world. This paper will argue that critical realism is the best explanation for science’s success, and that it correctly characterizes the relationship between scientific models and the world they describe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="reasons-for-accepting-realism" class="level2"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;2. Reasons for Accepting Realism&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;section id="a.-analogical-reasoning" class="level3"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;a. Analogical Reasoning&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the most straightforward arguments in favor of scientific realism is the intuition toward realism in general. When a detective examines a murder scene, she tends to assume the hypothesized criminal actually exists. Further analysis may or may not bear out the initial hypothesis about who committed a crime—perhaps it was a psychotic killer escaped from a mental ward, not an acquaintance of the deceased—but her normal faculties reliably point toward real entities in the world. Moreover, the process of analysis generally leads an (honest) investigator toward an increasingly accurate mental picture of the perpetrator. Missteps may occur in the analysis, but are amenable to critical reassessment, so that even when the revision from the original hypothesis is substantial, the trend-line of the mental model is toward increasing accuracy. The basic picture was refined, not destroyed: the victim was not after all killed by a wizard from Alpha Centauri (and even that would be a malicious, person-like agent).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Science, on a realist view, operates similarly. Initial hypotheses may prove to have more or less in common with the real world, and not only may but &lt;em&gt;must&lt;/em&gt; be subject to revision, even radical revision along the way. However, theories should be treated realistically, both ontologically (there really is something out there to know) and epistemically (science grants access to reality, albeit in approximate and limited fashion).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The primary argument against this analogy toward scientific realism is the idea of in-principle unobservables.&lt;a href="#fn2" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref2"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; The crime scene investigator has direct experience of things like criminals (other human persons, at least) as well as of the evidence itself. No one has direct experience of electrons. More than this, the postulates of quantum mechanics (are taken to) suggest that no one &lt;em&gt;can&lt;/em&gt; have such direct experience. Then, the antirealist argues, the scientific claim is at best unknowable: electrons may exist, but scientists have no way of knowing. They may observe a trail in a gas cloud, but whether the thing leaving the trail is really like an electron is unknowable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Any such attempt to distinguish in principle between observables and unobservables fails.&lt;a href="#fn3" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref3"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; First, antirealists use “unobservable” to mean anything not directly observable by human senses. However, declaring such objects in-principle unobservable is question-begging: the point under debate is just whether things detected indirectly are being observed or simply hypothesized. Antirealists must first establish such an in-principle distinction between indirect and direct observation. Realists note that indirect observation is rightly considered reliable in the realm of ordinary experience, and can rationally be extended analogically. It is reasonable to conclude that the wind is blowing from seeing its effects on trees even if sitting inside a closed room (with no direct experience of the wind). This would be so even for a person who had spent his entire life locked up inside and therefore had never had direct experiential access to wind or trees. Indirect observations still count as observations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="b.-whole-cloth-reasoning" class="level3"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;b. Whole-Cloth Reasoning&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moreover, human reasoning seems to be “whole cloth.” It is difficult (if not impossible) to find any particular line, even a blurry one, where this kind of inferential reasoning becomes suspect.&lt;a href="#fn4" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref4"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;4&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; Granted that electrons are quite different from anything of which humans have direct experience, this is not finally telling against reasoning about them. Humans are quite capable of making the requisite fine distinctions required for analogical reasoning to be valid; indeed, scientific models of electrons expressly include both similarities to and sharp discontinuities with human experience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Second, a realist view rightly makes sense of the way “observability” lies along a spectrum. On one end are those phenomena which can be detected through (normal, healthy) human senses such as hearing or vision. Moving down toward the not-directly-observable spectrum, scientists use telescopes and microscopes to enhance their ability to observe things inaccessible to ordinary human sight because of distance and size respectively. In both cases, however, there is no clear line distinguishing “observable” from “unobservable”—only a spectrum of more- or less-&lt;em&gt;directly&lt;/em&gt;-observable phenomena. Insects may be observed with the unaided human eye, bacteria with optical microscopes, individual molecules of materials with electron microscopes. In each case, the same principle is at work in the observation: light bouncing off an object and being received.&lt;span class="citation" data-cites="maxwell:theoretical-entities"&gt;&lt;a href="#fn5" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref5"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;5&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The anti-realist may object: the fact that the distinction between observables and unobservables is blurry does not mean it does not exist. As Samir Okasha notes, the line between “bald” and “hirsute” may be fuzzy (pun intended), but it is still possible to identify a bald man.&lt;span class="citation" data-cites="okasha:science-introduction"&gt;&lt;a href="#fn6" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref6"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;6&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt; Even granting the in-principle distinction between “observable” and “unobservable,” however, the objection fails to establish the strong claim made by antirealists. It does not establish that the items in question are in fact unobservable (especially when confronted with the realist argument for indirect observation). Nor does it establish that scientists would be in principle incapable of correctly modeling unobservables. At most, it establishes that unobservables &lt;em&gt;may&lt;/em&gt; exist.&lt;span class="citation" data-cites="okasha:science-introduction"&gt;&lt;a href="#fn7" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref7"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;7&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thus, it is reasonable to suppose that though current models of astronomical behavior, or of quantum mechanics, or gravity, or any other only-indirectly-observable phenomena may be incomplete or partial, they nonetheless represent something &lt;em&gt;actual&lt;/em&gt;. There really an electron leaving a trail in the gas chamber.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="c.-no-miracles" class="level3"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;c. No Miracles&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The substantial success of science in both predicting and providing coherent explanations for empirical phenomena, it seems &lt;em&gt;prima facie&lt;/em&gt; strange that the hypotheses in question would have nothing whatsoever to do with reality. It would be a miracle of sorts if a set of theories which do not directly rely on each other would all work effectively, and effectively &lt;em&gt;in conjunction&lt;/em&gt;, while not actually saying anything true about the world. These predictions are more than merely theoretically interesting; they have real-world application used every day: “laser technology is based on a theory about what happens when electrons in an atom go from higher to lower energy-states. And lasers work…”&lt;span class="citation" data-cites="okasha:science-introduction"&gt;&lt;a href="#fn8" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref8"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;8&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt; It seems reasonable that one reason scientific theories have been so successful is that they are approximately accurate, and increasingly so over time (if in fits and sometimes with false starts).&lt;span class="citation" data-cites="putnam:mathematics:1979"&gt;&lt;a href="#fn9" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref9"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;9&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many critics think the evidence of change in adoption of given theories, and varying degrees of empirical success over time, is hard evidence against the notion that scientific theories do generally refer in this way. Similarly, some theories once held to be &lt;em&gt;true&lt;/em&gt; are now thought to be neither approximately true, nor even subsets of what is true. Larry Laudan, citing a number of changes in this vein, sniffs: “The realist’s claim that we should expect referring theories to be empirically successful is simply false.”&lt;span class="citation" data-cites="laudan:confutation"&gt;&lt;a href="#fn10" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref10"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;10&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, the fact that science is an iterative and approximative process does not tell against the realism asserted. Any given theory may be substantially false. This does mean all theories are &lt;em&gt;likely&lt;/em&gt; not to refer, only that realists must be critical, aware of the possibility of failure, and willing to hold their claims tentatively, especially at first. No scientist with a knowledge of the history of the discipline should think otherwise. Electrons might not exist; but at least for the present, there is good reason to treat them not only as useful but as real. The longer the predictions of the model are (not dis)confirmed by the evidence, the more reason scientists have for holding the conclusion confidently. Likewise, as other theories developed without direct reference provide further corroboration, it is increasingly rational to affirm a theory as true, as well as empirically useful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Second, even if Laudan’s point is granted, it does not disprove realism. It simply proves naïve realism false—naïve, even. True: empirical success does not guarantee the truthlikeness of a theory, and vice versa. It does not follow that there is &lt;em&gt;no&lt;/em&gt; correspondence between the two. Laudan insists that the truthlikeness of a given theory has zero bearing on its empirical fruitfulness, but it is at least possible that it is instead a contributory facto.&lt;a href="#fn11" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref11"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;11&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, what about later theories which do &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; make special cases of the earlier theory? When Laudan, Kuhn, van Fraassen, and others examine e.g. the fluid and aether theories and compare them to the atomic theories now held by most physicists, they note that science has been empirically useful without being true in the past; the same may be true today. However, later views, currently held by realists to be accurate, can often explain the success of the earlier theory even without claiming it as a subset.&lt;span class="citation" data-cites="putnam:three-kinds-of-realism"&gt;&lt;a href="#fn12" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref12"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;12&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt; The atomic theory lets scientists explain the appearance of the aether. Newton’s mechanics can be applied to show why Ptolemy’s epicycles worked, even though they were false. The later theory not only has greater empirical success; its explanatory power also includes the now disconfirmed theory—whether as a special case or not. To be sure, the idea that all science proceeds linearly and that every theory is this kind of empirical superset of the former is incorrect.&lt;a href="#fn13" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref13"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;13&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; Still, the fact that later theories &lt;em&gt;often&lt;/em&gt; can do so is further evidence that truthlikeness is a contributory factor in the success of scientific theories.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="alternatives-to-realism" class="level2"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;3. Alternatives to Realism&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The two broad categories of antirealism, rational and non-rational, both deny the rationality of believing science truly describes the world.&lt;a href="#fn14" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref14"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;14&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; Larry Laudan’s instrumentalism, Bas C. van Fraassen’s constructive empiricism, and J. P. Moreland’s eclectic approach are &lt;em&gt;rational&lt;/em&gt; antirealisms. They all affirm the rationality of the scientific enterprise and reject conceptual relativism.&lt;span class="citation" data-cites="moreland:science:1989"&gt;&lt;a href="#fn15" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref15"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;15&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt; Non-rational antirealisms such as a strong Kuhnian approach deny the rationality of science and affirm conceptual relativism. Each fails as a critique of or alternative to critical realism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section id="a.-larry-laudans-instrumentalism" class="level3"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;a. Larry Laudan’s Instrumentalism&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instrumentalism takes the effectiveness of science as indicating only its effectiveness in delivering more reliable predictions.&lt;span class="citation" data-cites="laudan:beyond-realism"&gt;&lt;a href="#fn16" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref16"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;16&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt; Philosophers like Larry Laudan reject as both irrelevant and false the idea of “partial truth” or “verisimilitude” as incoherent: in a semantic model, statements are either true or false. This is partly fair: scientists claim their models have a semantic content correspondingly approximately to the world. Yet the critique fails to account for the way scientists use the notion of “approximate-ness.” Models may be incomplete, yet yield correct results &lt;em&gt;when the approximation is appropriate&lt;/em&gt;. There are thus three important distinctions to be made. The first is between accuracy (how near the &lt;em&gt;actual&lt;/em&gt; value a given experiment is) and precision (the repeatability of a measurement). An archer who consistently shoots four inches to the right of the bullseye is precise but not accurate; one who is always within two inches of the target but all around it is accurate, but not precise. The second is between accuracy and the philosophical binary of truth. A scientific model might in the strict sense be “false”—that is, even its predictions are not empirically &lt;em&gt;true&lt;/em&gt;, only &lt;em&gt;close to correct&lt;/em&gt;, while the model may be more accurate than any previous model. An arrow is either within the bullseye or not, but there is more to scoring an archery contest—and more to evaluating the accuracy of scientific claims.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The third distinction, and the most serious, is between models’ empirical content and their semantic content. A theory might be said to be “more true,” i.e. more &lt;em&gt;accurate&lt;/em&gt;, than any predecessor, if it is more consistent with the empirical data or capable of explaining a broader set of such data. However, the semantic claim is more likely to be binary. Either there are electrons, or there are not. If not, there may be nothing very much like electrons at all. Even so, this distinction is less sharp than Laudan supposes. Increasing approximation of reality is possible. Models may have more or less fidelity. A perfectly round globe may strictly be a false representation of the earth, which is slightly squashed due to its spin; but it is nearer correct than a piece of paper or a donut. The earth is much more like a sphere than a plane or a toroid. If reality is more like the Standard Model of quantum mechanics’ description of electrons and quarks than it is like a pre-atomic view of reality, the Standard Model is a better approximation to reality than the pre-atomic view. Voiding the distinction between accuracy and binary truth is simply a category mistake.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally Laudan shows how the scientific methodologies developed over the past several hundred years work, but not &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt;—especially in cases quite different from his example of double-blind clinical studies.&lt;span class="citation" data-cites="laudan:beyond-realism"&gt;&lt;a href="#fn17" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref17"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;17&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt; In scenarios where technological control over the environment is at stake, science clearly has an edge on other methods (so his critique of relativism stands).&lt;span class="citation" data-cites="vanfraassen:scientific-image"&gt;&lt;a href="#fn18" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref18"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;18&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt; It is less clear why drug trials should be amenable to this sort of testing if the human body and drug interactions are not &lt;em&gt;more like&lt;/em&gt; the scientific models than the non-scientific models. It was precisely the belief in the accuracy of such models which gave rise to the instrumentally effective methodology! One might posit, then, that &lt;em&gt;realism itself&lt;/em&gt; is instrumentally useful in the pursuit of these technological gains. The problem, of course, is that such an epistemic stance is difficult to maintain at best. It is one thing (and not a very controversial one) to say that the scientific method is instrumentally effective. It is another to say that belief in scientific realism is instrumentally effective and false, because no one can sustain a belief they think false.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="b.-bas-c.-van-fraassen-and-constructive-empiricism" class="level3"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;b. Bas C. van Fraassen and Constructive Empiricism&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Bas C. van Fraassen’s constructive empiricist model, science is (or at least should be) concerned solely with explaining the empirical data available to the human senses. Theories are useful but not true; they “do much besides answer the factual questions about regularities in the observable phenomena which, according to empiricism, are the scientist’s basic topic of concern.”&lt;span class="citation" data-cites="vanfraassen:scientific-image"&gt;&lt;a href="#fn19" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref19"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;19&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At least three major problems confront van Fraassen’s view. One is van Fraassen’s prior commitment to materialist empiricism. He asserts, for example, that criteria such as mathematical elegance, simplicity, scope, completion, unification, and explanatory “provide reasons for using a theory… and &lt;em&gt;cannot&lt;/em&gt; rationally guide our epistemic attitudes and decisions,”&lt;span class="citation" data-cites="vanfraassen:scientific-image"&gt;&lt;a href="#fn20" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref20"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;20&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt; Why? Because he has regards human observational powers as the sole grounds of knowledge. As such, he also rejects any critique of the limitations of “sense data” or problems with human perception as “armchair psychology” which can safely be ignored.&lt;span class="citation" data-cites="vanfraassen:scientific-image"&gt;&lt;a href="#fn21" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref21"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;21&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt; The &lt;em&gt;sole&lt;/em&gt; point of interest, for van Fraassen, is explaining those regularities in observable phenomena. As Grover Maxwell comments, though:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Surely the main concerns of, say, a theoretical physicist involve such things as the actual properties and varieties of subatomic particles rather than mere predictions about where and how intense a certain spectral line will be.&lt;span class="citation" data-cites="maxwell:theoretical-entities"&gt;&lt;a href="#fn22" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref22"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;22&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Indeed, theoretical physicists and chemists are concerned, even in conducting their ordinary research, with things they think actually exist. However much van Fraassen thinks science &lt;em&gt;should&lt;/em&gt; only concern itself with those regularities, realism seems basic to the scientific endeavor as actually practiced.&lt;a href="#fn23" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref23"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;23&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second problem for van Fraassen is closely related to the first: “empirical adequacy” is a necessary but insufficient condition for the acceptance of a scientific theory. Scientists do (and must) embrace those other conditions for accepting theories as true, and rightly so. Nothing about using those criteria to decide between theories is irrational in the least apart from van Fraassen’s prior commitment to empiricism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, van Fraassen simply reasserts the distinction between observable and unobservable entities. He begins with the idea of in-principle unobservability, but on encountering Maxwell’s argument from technological improvements, he moves the goalposts. He has in mind, he says, the limitations of human beings “&lt;em&gt;qua&lt;/em&gt; human beings;” technological aids actual or imaginable are irrelevant.&lt;span class="citation" data-cites="vanfraassen:scientific-image"&gt;&lt;a href="#fn24" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref24"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;24&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt; As shown above, though, the lack of any such clear distinction is the major problem for the antirealist interested in maintaining this distinction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="c.-morelands-selective-antirealism" class="level3"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;c. Moreland’s Selective Antirealism&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;J. P. Moreland suggests an alternative from within a Christian epistemology and ontology. He fully grants a generally realist epistemology and affirms a correspondence view of truth. However, he also approves a cautiously eclectic approach to &lt;em&gt;scientific&lt;/em&gt; realism.&lt;span class="citation" data-cites="moreland:science:1989"&gt;&lt;a href="#fn25" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref25"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;25&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt; He offers two major criteria for adopting antirealist stances. The first is “in those cases where the phenomena described by that theory lie outside the appropriate domain of science, or the scientific aspect of some phenomenon is inappropriately taken to be the whole phenomenon itself.”&lt;span class="citation" data-cites="moreland:science:1989"&gt;&lt;a href="#fn26" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref26"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;26&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt; For example: scientific explanations of mind currently tend toward reductive physicalism. But if there are good reasons to suspect that the mind is not reducible to the brain (say: the whole history of dualist arguments), any scientific theory which purports to explain mind solely in terms of material function should be treated antirealistically—as instrumentally useful, but not &lt;em&gt;true&lt;/em&gt;. But a critically realist claim about physical-mental state correlation does not entail physicalism. Rather, the physicalist claim is not scientific but philosophical. This should certain chasten the materialists, but it is not proof against realism—not generally, and not even in the case of this specific theory. It is proof only against unwarranted extension from the claim.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moreland also argues that “an antirealist stances should be taken toward some scientific theory in those cases where a realist view conflicts with a rationally well-established conceptual problem for that theory but an antirealist view does not.”&lt;span class="citation" data-cites="moreland:science:1989"&gt;&lt;a href="#fn27" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref27"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;27&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt; He suggests that the logically problematic claims of some interpretations of quantum mechanics suggest a non-realist interpretation: “the indeterminacy in nature is due to the uncertainty of our knowledge of nature or our inability to measure nature and is not a feature of nature itself.”&lt;span class="citation" data-cites="moreland:science:1989"&gt;&lt;a href="#fn28" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref28"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;28&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt; Similarly, if there are good philosophical reasons for rejecting infinite regress, one should be confident rejecting even an instrumentally-useful cosmological model of an infinite universe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In these latter examples, however, as well as in the further criteria he briefly mentions,&lt;a href="#fn29" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref29"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;29&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; Moreland lumps together two distinct phenomena under the same label of “anti-realism.” One is an in-principle denial that certain kinds of data are available to us; the other a denial that a &lt;em&gt;specific model&lt;/em&gt; comports with reality. One might think that all theories about electrons are permanently subject to antirealist critiques and that we can have no true knowledge of such allegedly unobservable entities. This is quite different from thinking that a given cosmological model is wrong. Both entail prior commitments, and the warrant in both cases arises outside science. They are nonetheless different kinds of claims: one about what is knowable, and one about what actually is. Even if Moreland’s criteria were granted, this is very different from van Fraassen’s empiricism or Laudan’s instrumentalism. Rejecting a given theory is quite different from rejecting the possibility of a theory being true.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="d.-non-rational-antirealism" class="level3"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;d. Non-Rational Antirealism&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The strongest form of Thomas Kuhn’s description of scientific history emphasizes that the theories on either side of a scientific revolution are totally incommensurable, actually operating in “different worlds.”&lt;span class="citation" data-cites="kuhn:revolutions:2012"&gt;&lt;a href="#fn30" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref30"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;30&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt; The shift away from Aristotelian is one where Galileo &lt;em&gt;saw differently&lt;/em&gt; than he had before.&lt;a href="#fn31" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref31"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;31&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; Kuhn’s protests that he understands the problem with the phrase notwithstanding, he regularly reverts to the idea that scientists before and after revolutions lived in different worlds.&lt;span class="citation" data-cites="kuhn:revolutions:2012"&gt;&lt;a href="#fn32" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref32"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;32&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt; This cannot be right: even if the theories are distinct in important ways, and even if are not totally commensurable, there are certainly data on which they can agree. Even if what the planets were seen &lt;em&gt;as&lt;/em&gt; shifted between the Ptolemaic and the Keplerian eras, the basic observational data were agreeable to both, for example. Likewise, though mass has different semantic content in the Newtonian and Einsteinian conceptions, both agree on many of the empirical values—including problematic measurements which prompted to the transition between them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Taken as a chastening of overconfident or naïve realism Kuhn’s historical critique is to be appreciated. His view of scientific revolutions leads him (or at least many of his readers) further, though—to conclude that observation is so theory-laden that, though the objective world is “out there” to describe, humans have no true access to it. The data itself is always subject to the flux of another revolution. Such a view, whatever its attractions, is first of all suspect simply on the reality that scientific approaches &lt;em&gt;have&lt;/em&gt; accomplished goals (like predicting and controlling floods) which cut across scientific and non-scientific cultures.&lt;span class="citation" data-cites="laudan:beyond-realism"&gt;&lt;a href="#fn33" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref33"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;33&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt; Second, any such non-rational antirealism stands clearly opposed to the Biblical idea that truth is knowable and that both moral and empirical data may be true or not—that the final standard is not human knowledge but the God-created reality outside the human knower. Third, such a view is self-defeating, as it claims objective knowledge about scientific theories while purporting that no such objective knowledge is possible.&lt;span class="citation" data-cites="moreland:science:1989"&gt;&lt;a href="#fn34" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref34"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;34&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="conclusion-the-best-option" class="level2"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;4. Conclusion: The Best Option&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Scientific realism, then, is the best option. It has its limitations, and specific theories may well not be finally accurate descriptions of reality. Phlogiston, after all, is not real; it may turn out that quarks are not either. But neither radical skepticism nor even hard agnosticism are therefore warranted. Rather, a critical realism which acknowledges the limitations and possibility for inaccuracy in any given model is far more appropriate. This model best accounts for both science’s instrumental effectiveness as a standalone discipline and its applicability to other disciplines. It best makes sense of the philosophical issues around epistemology and ontology. It best explains how scientific theories advance over time, not necessarily linearly but such that later models to tend to be capable of treating earlier models either as special cases or as comprehensible misunderstandings. Not least, it best comports with the Biblical view of truth and knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="part-ii-excursusrealism-and-creationism" class="level1"&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Part II: Excursus—Realism and Creationism&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Antirealism holds an undeniable appeal to many young-earth creationists. If science is meaningful only in a pragmatic sense, then the creationist may happily accept the utility of science for technological innovation, while still rejecting scientific claims about the age of the earth and common descent of living organisms without any serious conflict. As Moreland comments, “After all, if one does not assume that evolutionary theory is approximately true or objectively rational, then why bother to argue against it or to integrate Christian theological claims about the history of life with evolutionary theory?”&lt;span class="citation" data-cites="moreland:science:1989"&gt;&lt;a href="#fn35" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref35"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;35&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt; The more traditional (and admittedly more straightforward) reading of the Genesis narrative may be maintained, and the propositions of secular science safely sidelined as merely useful models which say nothing about the actual world. More, the off-putting claim often associated with scientific realism, “that science or the scientific method represents the &lt;em&gt;only&lt;/em&gt; (or, more weakly, the &lt;em&gt;most&lt;/em&gt;) effective instrument for discovering truths about the world”&lt;span class="citation" data-cites="laudan:beyond-realism"&gt;&lt;a href="#fn36" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref36"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;36&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt; may be safely rejected.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This excursus aims to show that, whatever the appeals of an antirealist stance for young-earth creationism, such a view is deeply mistaken. First, as seen above in Part I, there are good reasons to embrace realism in general, and to reject the major alternatives on offer. Second, even if one embraces an eclectic stance, &lt;em&gt;a la&lt;/em&gt; J. P. Moreland, the relevant criteria do not apply to the creation-science debate specifically. Third, in order for the antirealist objection to prove useful in the creation-science debate, it must go far beyond those criteria anyway—it must treat nearly &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; modern science antirealistically. It smuggles in a radical skepticism not especially congenial to Christian thought. It proves too much.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section id="the-argument-applied" class="level2"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;1. The Argument Applied&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The constructive empiricist program has severe problems for the Christian. As van Fraassen freely admits in the introduction to “The Scientific Image”:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By empiricism I mean the philosophical position that experience is our source of information about the world, &lt;em&gt;and our only source.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;span class="citation" data-cites="vanfraassen:scientific-image"&gt;&lt;a href="#fn37" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref37"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;37&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The motivation for a constructive empiricist view of science, then, is expressly the defense of empiricism. But empiricism as a worldview is antithetical to Christianity. Grover Maxwell searingly points out the underlying philosophical commitment: “the conviction that there are very few ontologically legitimate kinds of entities, perhaps only one.”&lt;span class="citation" data-cites="maxwell:theoretical-entities"&gt;&lt;a href="#fn38" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref38"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;38&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt; Empiricism as an all-encompassing &lt;em&gt;gestalt&lt;/em&gt; must be distinguished from the employment of empirical methods within other paradigms, of course: the Christian believes that the God-given senses are broadly trustworthy as a means of acquiring knowledge. However, Christians do (and must) affirm that non-empirical sources of data provide real warrant for belief: particularly divine revelation. Constructive empiricism is plainly antithetical to Christian theism—and certainly no friend to a claim about the age of the earth driven entirely by special revelatory considerations!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thus, the two kinds of anti-realism regularly embraced by young-earth creationists are instrumentalism and J. P. Moreland’s eclectic antirealism. Instrumentalism is at least at first blush much more appealing an option for Christians than empiricism. It allows the believer to affirm that science produces enormously helpful insights for technological advancement and control of the world.&lt;a href="#fn39" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref39"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;39&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; Beyond the basic critiques of instrumentalism noted in Part I, however, there are further problems for the young-earth creationist considering instrumentalism as an “out.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, one might reject scientific approaches for measuring the age of fossils or the earth itself. Current isotope decay rates explain some observations, and are technologically applicable to e.g. managing nuclear reactors—but they are merely useful, not true. As such, they are certainly not applicable to the past. Therefore, any claims about their past behavior should thereby be ruled out of bounds. Granted that the past is strictly inaccessible to scientists, this should still give the young-earth antirealist some pause. Dating a manuscript or a particular piece of pottery is not terribly dissimilar to dating a fossil. Taking this stance equally rules out much of the archaeological support mustered for the antiquity of the Bible. For that matter, how can one know that paper did not transmute words in the past? Claiming that documents changed their meaning would seem patently silly, but there is no more and no less evidence for it than that isotope decay rates have changed. Historical investigation of any sort, but especially archaeology, depends on the accessibility of the past much as geology does. It is not at all clear that reasoning about the earth suddenly becomes out of bounds at some arbitrary point far enough back in the past, or that radiometric isotopes should be assumed to be reliable up to a given point but no further.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Worse, while astronomy and geology seem at least partly to follows Laudan’s model of problem-solving—the practice of the disciplines results in more empirically-adequate explanations over time&lt;a href="#fn40" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref40"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;40&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;—his pragmatic approach asserts that science never approaches the truth whatsoever. Science solves empirical problems and helps humans accomplish certain technical tasks, but it reveals nothing of the world itself. Like van Fraassen’s constructive empiricism, it is thus contrary to the biblical view of the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="morelands-criteria" class="level2"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;2. Moreland’s Criteria&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Notably, many young-earth creationists such as Ken Ham take an explicitly realist stance toward science overall, arguing for something like the eclectic realism of J. P. Moreland, rather than a true instrumentalism or empiricism. This makes sense: it seems that one or more of J. P. Moreland’s criteria for eclectic antirealism might give warrant for taking an antirealist stance toward some of the relevant theories. However, even if Moreland is right that “We should not automatically assume that if science and theology conflict… the scientific theory should be read in realist terms and attacked accordingly,”&lt;span class="citation" data-cites="moreland:science:1989"&gt;&lt;a href="#fn41" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref41"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;41&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt; there remain two major problems with applying Moreland’s criteria in this way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, even if Moreland’s criteria for skepticism are valid, they are not applicable to the majority of the data under consideration in creationist arguments about e.g. the age of the earth. His first criterion certainly does not apply: the investigation of questions like the age of the earth or the life-cycle of stars or even the relationship between various kinds of life on earth all seem to be well within the legitimate territory of scientific explanation. His second criterion, having “a rationally well-established conceptual problem for that theory [which] an antirealist view does not,”&lt;span class="citation" data-cites="moreland:science:1989"&gt;&lt;a href="#fn42" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref42"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;42&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt; seems more applicable. Surely a well-established history of young-earth exegesis counts as a “rationally well-established conceptual problem”? Indeed, this is the strongest argument in favor Moreland’s eclectic empiricism applied to the issue. But of course, interpretations of the early chapters of Genesis have varied widely throughout the history of the church. This suggests at the least that the problem is less well-established that its proponents might think or hope. Moreover, it is relatively straightforward to propose readings of the creation narratives which accord with both the rest of Scripture &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; with science—far more straightforward than to propose entirely new, mutually compatible systems of physics, geology, biology, etc. The shoe seems to be on the other foot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What about Moreland’s other suggested criteria?&lt;span class="citation" data-cites="moreland:science:1989"&gt;&lt;a href="#fn43" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref43"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;43&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt; Most of the fields are &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; especially young.&lt;a href="#fn44" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref44"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;44&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; Few of them (especially the cornerstone fields of astronomy, geology, and particle physics) have experienced a large proportion of theory replacement over refinement of existing theories. None of the fields are in a period of Kuhnian crisis. One stronger contender is that “non rational, sociological factors account for much of the theory’s acceptance by the scientific community.”&lt;span class="citation" data-cites="moreland:science:1989"&gt;&lt;a href="#fn45" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref45"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;45&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt; This certainly looks to be the case in some ways, and it is fair to critique the scientific community on those terms. However, the same could equally be said of the young-earth creationist stance itself: it has at times been difficult even to get a job in conservative evangelical institutions while denying young-earth creationism.&lt;a href="#fn46" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref46"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;46&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; Moreover, although the critique stands for some of the fields, it is certainly not applicable to all of them; there is no particular sociological pressure on findings about isotope decay rates relevant to the discussion, for example. Finally, one might claim of evolutionary biology that “the main virtue… is its empirical adequacy, and its more metaphysical, theoretical aspects can be understood as unnecessary, excess baggage”&lt;span class="citation" data-cites="moreland:science:1989"&gt;&lt;a href="#fn47" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref47"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;47&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;—but again, the same can hardly be said of isotope decay or stellar life-cycle theories, neither of which has particularly strong metaphysical implications here!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second, related problem—conflating two distinct phenomena into a single label of “antirealism”—was noted above but warrants further discussion.&lt;span class="citation" data-cites="moreland:science:1989"&gt;&lt;a href="#fn48" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref48"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;48&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt; Again: one (strict instrumentalism or van Fraassen’s constructive empiricism) is an in-principle denial that certain kinds of data are available to us; the other a denial that a specific model is correct. So for example, one might think that all theories about electrons are permanently subject to antirealist critiques and that we can have no true knowledge of such allegedly unobservable entities; we can never know whether our theories about these things are in fact &lt;em&gt;true&lt;/em&gt;. Regardless of whether this claim is correct, it is quite different from thinking that a given cosmological model is wrong, while another one is correct (and demonstrably so if certain key assumptions were to be revisited). Both of these entail prior philosophical commitments, and in both cases the warrant for critiquing the realist claim arises outside of science itself, e.g. from a commitment to empiricism, or from a specific reading of Scripture. But they are nonetheless different kinds of claims: one about what is knowable, and one about what actually is the case.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One can of course imagine an antirealist critique of the former sort being levied against some cosmological model or another, but this is not what young-earth creationists who adopt an antirealist stance toward cosmology (Moreland included) seem to be proposing. Moreover, precisely because these are different kinds of claims, the kinds of warrant for skepticism that are in play for scientific knowledge about electrons or quarks are quite different both in principle and practice from the relevant factors for cosmology, geology, and so on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Taking an anti-realist stance toward these phenomena, then, requires a radical degree of skepticism—more radical than Moreland’s criteria warrant, and as it turns out with rather sharp consequences for other domains.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="severe-and-undesirable-consequences" class="level2"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;3. Severe and Undesirable Consequences&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is not sufficient to grant a certain suspicion about unobserved or indirectly observed phenomena.&lt;a href="#fn49" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref49"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;49&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; Rather, the would-be &lt;em&gt;creationist&lt;/em&gt; antirealist must commit to rejecting the realist validity of some or all the claims of: nuclear physics, geology, and paleontology (with serious repercussions to archaeology); general relativity; evolutionary biology; and observational astronomy (with direct application to cosmology). The consequences are no less devastating for the Christian worldview than for the physicalist,&lt;a href="#fn50" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref50"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;50&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; albeit for different reasons.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First of all, the no-miracles argument applies not only to the question of realism in general but also to the age of the earth and universe specifically. It is profoundly unlikely that one could derive an empirically adequate scientific model of something like fundamental particles without any correspondence to reality. It is at least as unlikely that findings from a variety of unrelated fields should all agree, while also all being totally wrong. Though some young-earth creationists chalk up this outcome to conspiratorial forces in the sciences (so Henry Morris) or to the presuppositions held by non-Christian scientists (so many disciples of Van Til), the claim both strains credulity and also—more to the point—is simply inaccurate both historically and in the present. The history of scientific estimates of the age of the earth is particularly illuminating; committed Christian Lord Kelvin’s early and foundational work already pointed to an age in the millions of years at a minimum. Likewise, many working Christian scientists today find the evidence for the antiquity of the earth and the universe quite reasonable, and they would be neither member of a Morrisian conspiracy nor, as regenerate believers, subject to precisely the same Van Tillian noetic defects as their non-Christian colleagues.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Independent lines of evidence for the antiquity of the universe and the earth include: astronomical observation and theories of star formation; cosmological development models and the prediction and discovery of the Big Bang background radiation in line with those models; geological and paleontological observations and associated data from decay rates which derive from fundamental physics. Many of these lines of data arose independently but have since been found to confirm one another. For example, isotopic decay rates are both predicted by particle physics and well-verified, and provide an independent line of evidence for the age of the earth in line with the ways of estimating that age: from patterns of stratification, to tree ring samples, to similar measurements of the age of other objects in the solar system. Models built up from the plate-tectonic theory of geology corroborates paleontological evidence of geographic colocation of certain species in the past. Radiometric dating of the age of the earth also accords with analyses of the age of the universe based on current models of star life-cycles and the formation of heavy elements, which in turn accord with models of cosmological development. These astronomical observations and analyses depend on both general and special relativity as well. Moreover, the evidence for these individual claims appears quite defensible to many confessing evangelical Christians. That &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; these independent lines of evidence, leaning on nearly every major area of physics, earth science, and biology should coincide at all—much less so neatly—while being entirely false is just the kind of miracle subject to the critique levied above.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moreover, this kind of strong antirealism leads to a radical skepticism that seems very out of keeping with Scriptural teaching on the role of nature. Surely passages such as Psalm 19 and Romans 1 indicate clearly that the world has a kind of revelatory content, which points to the nature of the one who created it. But imagine the young-earth creationist adopts an antirealist stance toward astronomical observation as a way of rejecting the apparent age of the universe. This requires asserting all of the following: No star has gone supernova before the last 10,000 years, and thus the heavy elements were all created “in situ” and are not, as currently believed, the product of supernovae. Indeed, any kind of apparent stellar life-cycle is an illusion (or at least: has never actually been experienced by any star). The evidence of background radiation is merely coincidence, and is in fact unrelated to the apparent expansion of the universe indicated by the red-shift of stars further from the earth. The apparent expansion of the universe is just that: apparent only; it has only ever been fractionally different than it is. Whatever the apparent evidence, the light seen is not in fact from the stars apparently observed: given the apparent distance to most stars, and the best models of how stars work, many of the stars in the night sky would have ceased to be visible, whether by exploding into supernovae or by burning down to white dwarfs, long before they were actually created. In other words, there is literally nothing true revealed by observing the stars—not even the brute fact of their existence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Much the same could be said for the other sciences. The earth shows apparent geological history including incredible catastrophes—ice ages, impacts from meteors, and so on—which in point of fact &lt;em&gt;never happened&lt;/em&gt;. This is far more radical than instrumentalism, and stronger even than van Fraassen’s empiricism. It even goes beyond the kinds of claims advanced by the conceptual relativists. There is no possible evidence which could countervail against it. It is sheer fideism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="conclusion" class="level2"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;4. Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Antirealism, particularly of the instrumental or eclectic varieties, may seem appealing to Christians troubled by the claims advanced by modern science. Whether the concern is with a kind of materialist “scientism” which strongly asserts a monadic view of human consciousness, or the apparent contradictions between Scripture and claims about the age of the universe, treating science as useful but not necessarily &lt;em&gt;true&lt;/em&gt; seems a helpful escape-hatch. However, adopting such a stance brings along so many other, and such severe, problems that whatever gains appears in this area seem not to be worth the cost—especially if there are other means of reconciling a realist view of science with Scripture’s teaching. Note that this does not mean that young-earth creationism is wrong. There may be other good reasons, including scientific reasons, to think that the earth is young.&lt;a href="#fn51" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref51"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;51&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; Programs of research oriented this direction may be fully realist while not affirming the veracity of any particular model. The distinction between principled antirealism and the rejection of a given theory is helpful and important.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Scientists at times maintain their views in the face of contrary evidence, or because of presuppositions they refuse to relinquish. But so may exegetes. If there is good reason to be a realist about science generally (and there is), and seemingly good evidence for the age of the earth (and there is), it behooves Christians at the least to hold their young-earth views tentatively. The strength of the claim that the earth is young, given all the evidence, warrants some humility.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="bibliography" class="level1 unnumbered"&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Bibliography&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;div id="refs" class="references"&gt;
&lt;div id="ref-diegues-lucena:laudan:2006"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Diéguez-Lucena, Antonio. “Why Does Laudan’s Confutation of Convergent Realism Fail?” &lt;em&gt;Journal for General Philosophy of Science&lt;/em&gt; 37, no. 2 (2006): 393–403.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="ref-vanfraassen:scientific-image"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fraassen, Bas C. van. &lt;em&gt;The Scientific Image.&lt;/em&gt; Clarendon Library of Logic and Philosophy. OUP Premium, 1980.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="ref-kuhn:revolutions:2012"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kuhn, Thomas S. &lt;em&gt;The Structure of Scientific Revolutions&lt;/em&gt;. 50th Anniversary Edition. 1962. Reprint, The University of Chicago Press, 2012.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="ref-laudan:confutation"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Laudan, Larry. “A Confutation of Convergent Realism.” &lt;em&gt;Philosophy of Science&lt;/em&gt; 48, no. 1 (March 1981): 19–49.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="ref-laudan:beyond-realism"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;———. “Explaining the Success of Science: Beyond Epistemic Realism and Relativism.” In &lt;em&gt;Science and Reality: Recent Work in the Philosophy of Science&lt;/em&gt;, edited by J. T. Cushing, C. F. Delaney, and G. Gutting, 83–105. Notre Dame: University of Notre Dame Press, 1984.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="ref-maxwell:theoretical-entities"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Maxwell, Grover. “The Ontological Status of Theoretical Entities.” In &lt;em&gt;Scientific Explanation, Space &amp;amp; Time&lt;/em&gt;, edited by Herbert Feigl and Grover Maxwell, III:3–27. Minnesota Studies in Philosophy of Science. University of Minnesota Press, 1962.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="ref-moreland:science:1989"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moreland, J. P. &lt;em&gt;Christianity and the Nature of Science: A Philosophical Investigation&lt;/em&gt;. Grand Rapids, Michigan: Baker Book House, 1989.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="ref-okasha:science-introduction"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Okasha, Samir. &lt;em&gt;Philosophy of Science: A Very Short Introduction&lt;/em&gt;. Very Short Introductions. New York: Oxford University Press, 2002.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="ref-putnam:mathematics:1979"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Putnam, Hilary. “Mathematics, Matter and Method,” Second edition., 1:60–78. Philosophical Papers. Cambridge University Press, 1979.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="ref-putnam:three-kinds-of-realism"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;———. “Three Kinds of Scientific Realism.” &lt;em&gt;Philosophical Quarterly&lt;/em&gt; 32, no. 128 (1982): 195–200.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="ref-rosenberg:philosophy-of-science:2012"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rosenberg, Alex. &lt;em&gt;Philosophy of Science: A Contemporary Introduction&lt;/em&gt;. Edited by Paul K. Moser. Third edition. Routledge Contemporary Introductions to Philosophy. 2000. Reprint, New York: Routledge, 2012.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="ref-torrance:reality-scientific-theology:1985"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Torrance, Thomas F. &lt;em&gt;Reality and Scientific Theology&lt;/em&gt;. Edited by T. F. Torrance. Theology and Science at the Frontiers of Knowledge. Edinburgh: Scottish Academic Press, 1985.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section class="footnotes"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn1"&gt;&lt;p&gt;“Explaining the Success of Science: Beyond Epistemic Realism and Relativism,” in &lt;em&gt;Science and Reality: Recent Work in the Philosophy of Science&lt;/em&gt;, ed. J. T. Cushing, C. F. Delaney, and G. Gutting (Notre Dame: University of Notre Dame Press, 1984), 89. &lt;a href="#fnref1"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn2"&gt;&lt;p&gt;See also the discussion of Bas C. van Fraassen’s constructive empiricism below.&lt;a href="#fnref2"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn3"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The following material is adapted from a short essay written for Dr. Welty’s PHI7650 midterm.&lt;a href="#fnref3"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn4"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The general problem of induction is left aside and the basic validity of inductive reasoning is assumed for the sake of argument; this is obviously contentious in its own right, and orthogonal to this issue. Perhaps all inferential reasoning is suspect, but if so that tells against empirical and instrumental accounts of science as well.&lt;a href="#fnref4"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn5"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Grover Maxwell, “The Ontological Status of Theoretical Entities,” in &lt;em&gt;Scientific Explanation, Space &amp;amp; Time&lt;/em&gt;, ed. Herbert Feigl and Grover Maxwell, vol. III, Minnesota Studies in Philosophy of Science (University of Minnesota Press, 1962), 4–11. &lt;a href="#fnref5"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn6"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Philosophy of Science: A Very Short Introduction&lt;/em&gt;, Very Short Introductions (New York: Oxford University Press, 2002), 69–70. &lt;a href="#fnref6"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn7"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ibid., 70. &lt;a href="#fnref7"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn8"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ibid. &lt;a href="#fnref8"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;So Hilary Putnam, “Mathematics, Matter and Method,” Second edition, vol. 1, Philosophical Papers (Cambridge University Press, 1979), 72–73, and &lt;em&gt;contra&lt;/em&gt; &lt;span class="citation" data-cites="vanfraassen:scientific-image"&gt;Bas C. van Fraassen, &lt;em&gt;The Scientific Image.&lt;/em&gt;, Clarendon Library of Logic and Philosophy (OUP Premium, 1980)&lt;/span&gt; 39. &lt;a href="#fnref9"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn10"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Larry Laudan, “A Confutation of Convergent Realism,” &lt;em&gt;Philosophy of Science&lt;/em&gt; 48, no. 1 (March 1981): 24. &lt;a href="#fnref10"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn11"&gt;&lt;p&gt;See the discussion and analysis in pp. 398–399 of &lt;span class="citation" data-cites="diegues-lucena:laudan:2006"&gt;Antonio Diéguez-Lucena, “Why Does Laudan’s Confutation of Convergent Realism Fail?” &lt;em&gt;Journal for General Philosophy of Science&lt;/em&gt; 37, no. 2 (2006): 393–403&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;a href="#fnref11"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn12"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Cf. Hilary Putnam, “Three Kinds of Scientific Realism,” &lt;em&gt;Philosophical Quarterly&lt;/em&gt; 32, no. 128 (1982): 197–99. &lt;a href="#fnref12"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn13"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Kuhn’s discussion of Galileo’s measurements vs. those conducted today is enlightening (see &lt;span class="citation" data-cites="kuhn:revolutions:2012"&gt;Thomas S. Kuhn, &lt;em&gt;The Structure of Scientific Revolutions&lt;/em&gt;, 50th Anniversary Edition (1962; repr., The University of Chicago Press, 2012)&lt;/span&gt; 119ff). Note, however, that though Galileo’s measurements are not reproducible today, reasons may readily be adduced for the measurements he took from within the context of later theories—the accuracy of the measuring apparatus available to him, for example. Kuhn’s objection is weaker than he thinks.&lt;a href="#fnref13"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn14"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Categorization from &lt;span class="citation" data-cites="moreland:science:1989"&gt;J. P. Moreland, &lt;em&gt;Christianity and the Nature of Science: A Philosophical Investigation&lt;/em&gt; (Grand Rapids, Michigan: Baker Book House, 1989)&lt;/span&gt; 140–141. For a more detailed discussion of the strengths and weaknesses of these views, see &lt;span class="citation" data-cites="moreland:science:1989"&gt;ibid., &lt;/span&gt; ch. 5, though he is perhaps overly sympathetic to antirealist critiques (especially of theoretical physics), on which see below.&lt;a href="#fnref14"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn15"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ibid., 194. &lt;a href="#fnref15"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn16"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Laudan, “Explaining the Success of Science,” 91. &lt;a href="#fnref16"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn17"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ibid., 98–100. &lt;a href="#fnref17"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn18"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Cf. Fraassen, &lt;em&gt;The Scientific Image.&lt;/em&gt;, 40. &lt;a href="#fnref18"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn19"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ibid., 70. &lt;a href="#fnref19"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn20"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ibid., 87. &lt;a href="#fnref20"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn21"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ibid., 72. &lt;a href="#fnref21"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn22"&gt;&lt;p&gt;“The Ontological Status of Theoretical Entities,” 19–20. &lt;a href="#fnref22"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn23"&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the idea of embracing realism instrumentally, see above in §2a, and cf. &lt;span class="citation" data-cites="rosenberg:philosophy-of-science:2012"&gt;Alex Rosenberg, &lt;em&gt;Philosophy of Science: A Contemporary Introduction&lt;/em&gt;, ed. Paul K. Moser, Third edition, Routledge Contemporary Introductions to Philosophy (2000; repr., New York: Routledge, 2012)&lt;/span&gt; 211-214.&lt;a href="#fnref23"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn24"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Fraassen, &lt;em&gt;The Scientific Image.&lt;/em&gt;, 18. &lt;a href="#fnref24"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn25"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Moreland, &lt;em&gt;Christianity and the Nature of Science&lt;/em&gt;, 193–41. &lt;a href="#fnref25"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn26"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ibid., 206. &lt;a href="#fnref26"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn27"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ibid., 210. &lt;a href="#fnref27"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn28"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ibid., 210. &lt;a href="#fnref28"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn29"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="citation" data-cites="moreland:science:1989"&gt;ibid., &lt;/span&gt; 211; and see discussion in Part II below.&lt;a href="#fnref29"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn30"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Kuhn, &lt;em&gt;The Structure of Scientific Revolutions&lt;/em&gt;, 111. &lt;a href="#fnref30"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn31"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="citation" data-cites="kuhn:revolutions:2012"&gt;ibid., &lt;/span&gt; 119; see pp. 118–124 on this transition specifically and ch. 10 on paradigm-shifts more generally.&lt;a href="#fnref31"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn32"&gt;&lt;p&gt;E.g. his discussion of chemistry in ibid., 133. &lt;a href="#fnref32"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn33"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Laudan, “Explaining the Success of Science,” 94–95. &lt;a href="#fnref33"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn34"&gt;&lt;p&gt;So, rightly, Moreland, &lt;em&gt;Christianity and the Nature of Science&lt;/em&gt;, 201–2. &lt;a href="#fnref34"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn35"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ibid., 142. &lt;a href="#fnref35"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn36"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Laudan, “Explaining the Success of Science,” 85. &lt;a href="#fnref36"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn37"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Fraassen, &lt;em&gt;The Scientific Image.&lt;/em&gt;, 8, emphasis mine. &lt;a href="#fnref37"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn38"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Maxwell, “The Ontological Status of Theoretical Entities,” 27. &lt;a href="#fnref38"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn39"&gt;&lt;p&gt;In this author’s experience, instrumentalism is far more common among Christians trained in engineering than to those trained in the sciences—perhaps (and this is merely speculation) because the engineering disciplines &lt;em&gt;already&lt;/em&gt; instrumentalize science. Cf. &lt;span class="citation" data-cites="torrance:reality-scientific-theology:1985"&gt;Thomas F. Torrance, &lt;em&gt;Reality and Scientific Theology&lt;/em&gt;, ed. T. F. Torrance, Theology and Science at the Frontiers of Knowledge (Edinburgh: Scottish Academic Press, 1985)&lt;/span&gt; 22.&lt;a href="#fnref39"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn40"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Cf. &lt;span class="citation" data-cites="laudan:beyond-realism"&gt;Laudan, “Explaining the Success of Science.”&lt;/span&gt;. Interestingly, Laudan’s view comports in this area with van Fraassen’s constructive empiricism.&lt;a href="#fnref40"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn41"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Moreland, &lt;em&gt;Christianity and the Nature of Science&lt;/em&gt;, 211. &lt;a href="#fnref41"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn42"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ibid., 210. &lt;a href="#fnref42"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn43"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ibid., 211. &lt;a href="#fnref43"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn44"&gt;&lt;p&gt;To be sure, there are related fields which are quite young and, in this author’s view, quite suspect, e.g. evolutionary psychology. But the field’s findings are irrelevant to the age of the earth, and thus to the question at hand.&lt;a href="#fnref44"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn45"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ibid., 211. &lt;a href="#fnref45"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn46"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Nor is this limited to creationism; for much of the last century, many evangelical institutions demanded fealty to dispensationalism!&lt;a href="#fnref46"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn47"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ibid., 211. &lt;a href="#fnref47"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn48"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Cf. ibid., 206–11. &lt;a href="#fnref48"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn49"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;a la&lt;/em&gt; &lt;span class="citation" data-cites="moreland:science:1989"&gt;ibid., &lt;/span&gt; 210–211.&lt;a href="#fnref49"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn50"&gt;&lt;p&gt;See Part I § 2a and 2b above.&lt;a href="#fnref50"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn51"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This author tends to think the earth is as old as it appears, and that young-earth views hinge on hermeneutical and philosophical commitments which are unnecessary and incorrect—but this is beside the point.&lt;a href="#fnref51"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 16 May 2016 23:55:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2016-05-16:2016/realism-and-antirealism.html</guid><category>SEBTS</category><category>M. Div.</category><category>papers</category><category>philosophy</category><category>science</category></item><item><title>2016-05-16 18:33</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2016/2016-05-16-1833.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Finished writing &lt;em&gt;enough words&lt;/em&gt;. Going to take a two hour break to go hack on a potential solution to a problem that has been vexing us at work for months and which I think I know how to solve. Then come back, edit, and submit this thing!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id="refs" class="references"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 16 May 2016 18:33:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2016-05-16:2016/2016-05-16-1833.html</guid><category>writing</category><category>SEBTS</category><category>papers</category><category>M. Div.</category><category>philosophy</category></item><item><title>2016-05-16 16:45</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2016/2016-05-16-1645.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;500 words and some editing and 75 minutes to go. Put on some Ellie Goulding. Head down. Let’s do this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id="refs" class="references"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 16 May 2016 16:45:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2016-05-16:2016/2016-05-16-1645.html</guid><category>music</category><category>writing</category><category>SEBTS</category><category>M. Div.</category><category>philosophy</category><category>papers</category></item><item><title>2016-05-15 16:36</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2016/2016-05-15-1636.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;~5600 words down. ~1800 to go. Yes, I underestimated yesterday by about 1500 words. &lt;em&gt;Whoops.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id="refs" class="references"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 15 May 2016 16:36:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2016-05-15:2016/2016-05-15-1636.html</guid><category>SEBTS</category><category>writing</category><category>papers</category><category>philosophy</category><category>m. div.</category></item><item><title>2016-05-14 15:56</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2016/2016-05-14-1556.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;~3500 words down, ~2500 to go. Steady on!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id="refs" class="references"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 14 May 2016 15:56:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2016-05-14:2016/2016-05-14-1556.html</guid><category>sebts</category><category>papers</category><category>writing</category><category>philosophy</category><category>M. Div.</category></item><item><title>2016-05-14 09:15</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2016/2016-05-14-0915.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;That feeling when you’re researching a paper and a philosopher cherry-picks all his examples and ignores every countervailing examples.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id="refs" class="references"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 14 May 2016 09:15:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2016-05-14:2016/2016-05-14-0915.html</guid><category>philosophy</category></item><item><title>Full-On Question-Begging</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2016/full-on-question-begging.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;i class="editorial"&gt;The following was prepared as a one-page, single-spaced short response to a question from the readings for this class.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Scientific naturalism, as a worldview (not an instrumental technique applied in certain circumstances) is certainly question-begging. First, the claim that “the physical world is the only thing which exists” is fundamentally a philosophical and not a scientific claim. That is, if science is a broadly experimental approach to discovering truth about the physical world, it is incapable of determining whether a non-physical world exists, and it is not even asking—still less answering!—metaphysical questions about the nature of reality. The basic issues of epistemology, ontology, and ethics are themselves not subject to empirical analysis. Evidence from the natural world may certainly be useful and even helpful in considering these domains, but by definition cannot be finally determinative. For example: if the physical world is &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; the only thing which exists, what sort of purely physical test could demonstrate that? Likewise, if humans have cognitive access to spiritual realities, because they are dualist and not purely physical beings, they might have genuine non-physical experiential knowledge. No ontological, epistemological, or teleological claim is finally resolvable through merely physical testing; claims in such areas are finally philosophical and theological.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Second, the efficacy of science in the domain of explaining the physical world is in no sense evidence that it is a particularly effective way of describing &lt;em&gt;all things&lt;/em&gt;. This is akin to suggesting that because musical notation is particularly effective for representing notes to be played, it is the only form of notation required; all written words should immediately be discarded, as should all computer programs. That is, the utility of one form of description or program of study for a given domain does not make it immediately applicable to or indeed at all relevant for other domains. Even with the context of scientific efforts, this is obvious: different techniques are used in observational astronomy than in ecological analysis, and different methods of analysis in assessing the claims of theoretical physics than in analyzing data from a given paleontological dig.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Third, and perhaps most importantly for current debates, the efficacy of science in describing the physical world provides no evidence whatsoever that the physical world is the only thing which exists. To suggest otherwise is simply to commit a basic logical fallacy. This is obvious if the premises and conclusion are laid out explicitly: The argument might be laid out so: “(P1) Science describes the physical world effectively. (P2) Science does not and cannot describe the non-physical world. (C) Therefore, the physical world is the only thing which exists.” But the conclusion clearly does not follow from the premises, even inductively. The argument might be modified into an inductive form: “(P1) Science describes the physical world effectively. (P2) Science has provided increased effectiveness in describing an ever-wider variety of phenomena over time. (P3) In so doing, science has found physical explanations of phenomena which at one time seemed intractable to such explanations. (C1) Therefore, science will at some point in the future find physical explanations for all phenomena. (C2) Therefore, there are no non-physical phenomena.” Even so strengthened, there are two major problems with the argument. First, C1 is an incredibly strong claim, and the purported evidence toward it in this form’s P3 is itself disputed. Moreover, even if C1 were granted, it would offer some evidence for C2 but &lt;em&gt;would not prove it&lt;/em&gt;. There still might be reason to think that physical phenomena and their corresponding explanations were expressions of the will of a wise divine being, for example. Moreover, while claims for non-physical purposes for or fundamental explanations of physical mechanisms might then be on shakier ground in virtue of being apparently less simple, the physicalist would need to make a (philosophical) argument for the apparent scientific virtue of simplicity! There is no escape from claims which are themselves not even capable of being tested empirically.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id="refs" class="references"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 12 May 2016 21:09:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2016-05-12:2016/full-on-question-begging.html</guid><category>M. Div.</category><category>SEBTS</category><category>philosophy</category><category>science</category></item><item><title>Empirical Equivalence, Real Semantic Difference</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2016/empirical-equivalence-real-semantic-difference.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;i class="editorial"&gt;The following was prepared as a one-page, single-spaced short response to a question from the readings for this class.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When two theories make contradictory claims, even were they to have empirically equivalent outcomes, the contradiction in their claims is not merely terminological or semantic. It is fairly easy to conceive of claims are &lt;em&gt;merely&lt;/em&gt; semantically different, but which have the same basic content: “That is a chair” and the Spanish equivalent “ésa es una silla” both have the same basic referents, and even intend broadly the same meaning. Their variance is terminological, by dint of being in two distinct languages. It is far more difficult to find two claims which are in opposition to each other, but their opposition is merely terminological.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is not just the case in science. To make a claim, scientific or otherwise, is to assert something about the world as it actually is. Thus, “The sky is blue” and “The sky is green but appears to us as blue because all our eyes are defective in a way we cannot measure” would have the same base empirical content, but make very different claims about the nature of human sight and the sky. This particular claim is trivially testable in some other way; but different claims in fundamental physics—empirically equivalent string theories, for example—might not be trivially testable, or testable at all: they might be empirically equivalent in principle as well as in practice. But the trivial example serves to highlight the reality that empirical equivalence does not entail semantic equality. The blueness or greenness of the sky is not merely a matter of human descriptions of things. Rather, even though they are meaningful only because of their semantics, their semantics carry force that is not merely different ways of saying the same thing: that is one of the basic necessities for language to function. If different semantics did not actually entail different claims, communication would be impossible. Less pragmatically, if one affirms that the referents in question are in some sense “out there” and not merely the contents of human speech or human sense data—that is, if one embraces a correspondence theory of truth and a basically, albeit critically, realist view of human knowledge including scientific knowledge—then the notion that two claims are merely terminological variants even though their semantics stand in contrast is clearly false.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To take an example particularly appropriate to a science-and-religion course: it is quite conceivable that a disinterested god (quite different from the one we worship) and a pantheon of disinterested gods and a universe which came out purely by chance would all be empirically equivalent. Yet “there is one bored god out there” and “there is no god out there” and “there are many bored gods out there” are clearly and obviously not terminological variants of each other, even if there is no empirical way to tell them apart. A similar thing would hold of two string theories, one which postulated 12 and the other 28 hidden dimensions. Even if both yielded the same empirical predictions (which were verified) and were in-principle incapable of any further test, they would nonetheless be claims with semantic content about the nature of reality which is &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; reducible merely to a terminological variant. The fact that the truth or falsity of a claim may not be knowable does not tell against its distinctive semantic content, only against its pragmatic utility. If one of the two string theories suggested above were true, it might not make any practical difference which one it was. After all, if the contents are permanently inaccessible to humans, and the theoretical consequences identical, then either may be used in the pursuit of other knowledge. However, by dint of the fact that they make distinct and countervailing claims to one another, at least one must be false. And truth is no small matter!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id="refs" class="references"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 12 May 2016 21:08:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2016-05-12:2016/empirical-equivalence-real-semantic-difference.html</guid><category>M. Div.</category><category>SEBTS</category><category>philosophy</category><category>science</category></item><item><title>Realism, Generality, and Precision—In Tension?</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2016/realism-generality-and-precision-in-tension.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;i class="editorial"&gt;The following was prepared as a one-page, single-spaced short response to a question from the readings for this class.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The tension between realism, generality, and precision posited in biology is a function not of those constraints in general, but of the specific constraints on biology and other sciences dealing with what is often described as having “emergent” phenomena. The closer the science is to physical first principles, the less these terms stand in contrast. For example, in chemistry, a realist description of the chemicals in question is actually &lt;em&gt;helpful&lt;/em&gt; in dealing precisely with the terms in question. The behavior of the chemicals at large scales can be modeled more effectively precisely because the underlying principles are relatively well understood and the phenomenon describable not merely as a representative abstraction but in terms corresponding to what seem to be the &lt;em&gt;actual&lt;/em&gt; characteristics of the system in view. The same is true of much of physics. For example, the idea of general relativity is (as its name suggests) extremely general, covering the behavior of all macroscopic systems at least; is sufficiently precise in its predictions to enable extraordinary feats of timekeeping and geolocation; and is understood by the majority of working physicists to be a &lt;em&gt;true&lt;/em&gt; and not merely a &lt;em&gt;useful&lt;/em&gt; description of how space-time behaves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The question arises then: assuming the claim is correct for biology, why is this so? The answer seems to be that biological systems are not subject (at least so far as they are understood so far) to be capable of reduction to the same kinds of general theorems as the more purely physical sciences. Though biological is concerned of physical subjects, those subjects seem not to merely the expression of mechanistic phenomena (though of course this point is debated by some physicalist philosophers and scientists). Rather, their behavior emerges atop the underlying physical system, and then diverges in unpredictable ways from individual subject to individual subject. As a result, descriptions of the trends that occur in a given &lt;em&gt;population&lt;/em&gt; may be general, but do not do justice to the behavior of any one member of that population, and so are not &lt;em&gt;precise&lt;/em&gt;. Thus, ecologies are functions of &lt;em&gt;aggregate&lt;/em&gt; behavior, but that aggregation is something like the “average American family”: it is a description of no individual element within the system, but of the combined output of the whole system. Moreover, under even trivially different conditions (a lightning strike occurring in one place rather than another, for example, and changing the behavior of the animals in that area), the specific outcome of the system might have been meaningfully different—even if still able to be modeled under the same general descriptions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Indeed, most effective general models of behavior in biological systems are neither realistic nor precise. Attempts to model the function of neurons are often precise, but intentionally non-realist and non-general, not least because in most organisms, neurons are non-generalizable: only the simplest creatures have non-differentiated neurons. But in each of these cases, these are functions of the kind of increasingly complex systems, which are not apparently describable purely in terms of their underlying components. The brain, for example, is composed not just of an extraordinarily large number of neurons, but of a great variety of kinds of neurons as well, and the neurons all have the same basic chemical makeup and the same basic genetic structure, but develop in different ways because of specific driving factors in their environment, signals from chemicals driven by other parts of the body, and so on. Any description of any part of this system will necessarily be subject to the constraints the biologist describes simply because there is no single underlying principle driving the system; rather, it is a complex system where each part informs the others. The same is true (and even more so) of systems made up of biological actors, such as communities and ecologies; it is unsurprisingly also a common feature of systems which include actors with agency (such as economics).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id="refs" class="references"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 12 May 2016 21:07:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2016-05-12:2016/realism-generality-and-precision-in-tension.html</guid><category>M. Div.</category><category>SEBTS</category><category>philosophy</category><category>science</category></item><item><title>Aristotle, Newton, and Progress</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2016/aristotle-newton-and-progress.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;i class="editorial"&gt;The following was prepared as a one-page, single-spaced short response to a question from the readings for this class.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Aristotle’s impetus theory provided an effective and predictively accurate (and indeed, &lt;em&gt;scientific&lt;/em&gt;) model of the behavior of objects in terrestrial contexts. Though it was later superseded by Newton’s model, which had no impetuses at all, Aristotle’s method was a perfectly defensible model because it accounted for the &lt;em&gt;known&lt;/em&gt; phenomena well. The method worked because a number of constraints in the systems observed were not yet themselves understood. In a limited sense, Aristotle’s view could be construed as a &lt;em&gt;for-certain-conditions&lt;/em&gt; subset of Newton’s laws (though, strictly speaking, this is inaccurate). That is, in the conditions in which Aristotle made his observations, and failing to account for some of the phenomena for which Newton’s approach &lt;em&gt;did&lt;/em&gt; account, the impetus model for motion was valid.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In systems where there is resistance—e.g., all terrestrial systems—objects do not remain in motion without some other object providing an impetus to them, and objects of different masses but the same basic size do not fall at the same rate. Newton’s revolution was not in denying this but in recognizing that the grounding assumptions were incorrect: terrestrial systems are a &lt;em&gt;subset&lt;/em&gt; of a broader possible systems. Because this is so, there exists a more general set of laws which govern the behavior of objects in both terrestrial and non-terrestrial systems. This in turn led to the recognition that Aristotle had made a false generalization from the observed (terrestrial) data: the idea that objects require impetuses to remain in motion was empirically sound, but incomplete. Thus, a feather and a similarly-weighted needle fall at different rates because their different densities and surface areas relative to their masses result in different degrees of resistance. A bowling ball eventually comes to rest because of the resistive forces it experiences due to friction. These are not the general case, but subsets of the broader laws Newton derived; but Aristotle’s formulation can readily be seen just as that subset, under certain conditions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is not an unusual pattern in the history of science, and in fact is similarly applicable to Newton’s own system of mechanics, since superseded by both quantum mechanics and general relativity. As the constraints under which a given law operates become better-understood, it is sometimes possible (at least in the case of physical laws) to derive deeper generalizations about the systems in question, generalizations of which the currently-held set of laws are recognized to be a subset. Granted that at times, the new laws do not supersede but wholly replace the old model, and that both the Aristotle-Newton and Newton-Einstein/QM transitions contain some degree of this latter, it is still the case that newer theories ofttimes succeed because they demonstrate themselves capable of solving the same set of problems as the preceding theory, while also addressing many of the unresolved issues in it. So: Newton was able to derive more, and more accurate, predictions than was the Aristotelian model, and to provide more thorough explanations of the systems in question; and likewise Einstein than Newton. In both cases, however, the original model had the utility it did (and the empirical success it did) precisely because it was in some way a &lt;em&gt;for-certain-conditions&lt;/em&gt; subset of the more general theory.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A rather more interesting contrast, then, is between theories where the earlier theory is not even construable as a for-certain-conditions subset of the later, as in the phlogiston theory of combustion, since replaced by an oxidizing view. The idea had substantial explanatory power and harmonized quite well with the data, but was ultimately overthrown by the alternative (and now current, albeit revised) view of oxidation. Such cases, unlike the Aristotelian-Newtonian or Newtonian-Einsteinian/quantum mechanical transitions, are much harder to reconcile with a progressive view of the development of scientific theory, or with realist accounts of scientific explanation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id="refs" class="references"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 12 May 2016 21:06:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2016-05-12:2016/aristotle-newton-and-progress.html</guid><category>M. Div.</category><category>SEBTS</category><category>philosophy</category><category>science</category></item><item><title>Statistical Regularities and Explanation</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2016/statistical-regularities-and-explanation.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;i class="editorial"&gt;The following was prepared as a one-page, single-spaced short response to a question from the readings for this class.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is easy to mistake &lt;em&gt;exactness&lt;/em&gt; for &lt;em&gt;explanatory power&lt;/em&gt; in the realm of explanation. Thus, it might be tempting to suppose that precise and consistent statistical regularities have greater explanatory power than inexact laws which have an attendant set of constraints and conditions specifying when and how they apply. However, the inverse is true.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Statistical regularity has &lt;em&gt;no&lt;/em&gt; explanatory power. It has enormous utility, in that it allows effective prediction. However, it provides no insight into the reason why the regularity is captures occurs. Explanation is at core a matter of determining the reasons why something occurs, not simply observing &lt;em&gt;that&lt;/em&gt; it occurs. If on every first, second, and third Tuesday of the month for three hours early in the afternoon small black marks are rendered onto a mostly white LED display, and the range of marks is tightly bounded, and the marks are known to form meaningful words and sentences and even stories, and there can therefore be strong statistical confidence that &lt;em&gt;next&lt;/em&gt; Tuesday the same pattern will occur again, this does nothing to &lt;em&gt;explain&lt;/em&gt; the marks. What suffices as an explanation is a person using a typewriter to compose the draft of a novel on those Tuesdays when she has a babysitter for her children. This is certainly not even a &lt;em&gt;ceteris paribus&lt;/em&gt; law, and yet it has substantially greater explanatory power than does the statistical observation, regardless of the degree of statistical precision available.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By contrast, even inexact laws subject to restrictions and limitations are capable of offering meaningful explanations, because they can offer insight into the causal mechanisms which drive the processes. Though such statements of causality are inherently circumscribed to a certain degree—the &lt;em&gt;ceteris paribus&lt;/em&gt; clauses are necessary—they retain the explanatory power that inheres in causal reasoning. It is both legitimate and explanatory to reason that “all other things being equal, Superman will win in a fistfight with Batman because he has superhuman strength and is functionally invincible to human weaponry.” Granted that all other things may &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; be equal (as in the famous 1980s story from which recent cinema drew more or less inspiration) and that Batman may, if he has access to Kryptonite, bring about a different outcome, in no way diminishes the explanatory power of the original statement. In fact, it may strengthen it by suggesting what kinds of things must be equal for the statement to hold, and suggesting other kinds of causal factors in the system. Since the system that is the universe—even Batman and Superman’s universe—is very large, it is unsurprising that causal relations can only be described with these kinds of constraints. After all, only God could know the total set of forces acting on a system and therefore could deliver a non-&lt;em&gt;ceteris paribus&lt;/em&gt; statement of causal factors exhaustively.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This does not mean that statistical regularity is useless for explanation. In fact, it is a powerful tool for reasoning about the state of the world as part of deriving &lt;em&gt;ceteris paribus&lt;/em&gt;-constrained causal statements. To derive such causal statements, one must (usually) first derive sufficient data on which to base an analysis at all. Thus, knowing that Superman has been completely invulnerable to all human weapons of whatever magnitude in the past, and that Batman is an ordinary human, is important in being able to state that Superman will win in an ordinary fistfight between the two. The statistical data drives an inference to the best &lt;em&gt;explanation&lt;/em&gt; that he is in fact invulnerable to ordinary human weapons (an explanation which we as outside readers know in fact to be true), and grounds the “all other things being equal” statement. If other factors are introduced, so that other things are &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; equal, the inference from that statistical data set will still hold; but now other causal elements are in play and new statistical data would need to be gathered, for the sake of further reasoning &lt;em&gt;to explanation&lt;/em&gt;. The two go hand in hand, in other words.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id="refs" class="references"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 12 May 2016 21:04:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2016-05-12:2016/statistical-regularities-and-explanation.html</guid><category>M. Div.</category><category>SEBTS</category><category>philosophy</category><category>science</category></item><item><title>Counterfactuals and Supervenience</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2016/counterfactuals-and-supervenience.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;i class="editorial"&gt;The following was prepared as a one-page, single-spaced short response to a question from the readings for this class.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The natural sciences all claim to use the same basic model of knowledge, and claim to aim for the same kind of explanatory power: the &lt;em&gt;law&lt;/em&gt;. However, clearly the kinds of laws which have such force in chemistry and especially physics are at least much less common in the other sciences; they may be entirely absent. Biology serves as a prime example of an unquestionably “hard” science in which laws are much harder to come by. Whereas physics includes both descriptive laws (&lt;em&gt;PV = nRT&lt;/em&gt;) and explanatory laws (general relativity), biology seems entirely limited to the former. That is, there are e.g. laws describing &lt;em&gt;how&lt;/em&gt; populations behave in an ecosystem, but there are no systematizing principles which are thought to offer the same degree of broad explanatory and predictive power as, say, the Standard Model of quantum mechanics. The closest example is a broadly Darwinian model of evolution, but even leaving aside questions about the accuracy of the model, it differs substantially from physical or chemical laws. It offers far less in the way of precise predictions, for one. For another, althought it serves as an explanation, the &lt;em&gt;kind&lt;/em&gt; of explanation it offers is distinct in that it does not seem to have the kind of (nomic) necessity possessed by physical laws: even if Darwinian evolution is the means by which life arose on the planet, it by no means requires that life arose &lt;em&gt;as it did&lt;/em&gt;; Certainly it is possible that life could have taken other forms even under the same selective pressures, given some other mutation—or have failed to succeed at all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Biological systems (and yet-higher-level systems like ecologists or economies) demonstrate phenomena that &lt;em&gt;supervene&lt;/em&gt; on the underlying physical realities. Unlike physics or chemistry, these phenomena seem, perhaps permanently, resistant to reductive and unifying explanations. This is precisely because of their lack of nomic or causal necessity: counterfactuals are easy to imagine in biology; much less economics. In the most abstract sciences—behavioral psychology, sociology, and economics, for example–it seems that human agency plays a major part in the actual outcomes in the world. Physicalist/materialist claims notwithstanding, it seems quite unlikely that such agency can be reduced to the &lt;em&gt;results&lt;/em&gt; of chemical and electrical activity in the brain.&lt;a href="#fn1" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref1"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; Even at the level of microbes, however, the so-called “emergent behavior” of biological systems is not reducible to mere physical &lt;em&gt;properties&lt;/em&gt; as is the case in physics and chemistry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Again, counterfactuals play one significant part in this: biological systems could be other than what they are. But another significant factor is the purposive nature of organisms. Even the simplest living things&lt;a href="#fn2" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref2"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; have a teleological bent. Even if they were not designed, they themselves carry out certain patterns of &lt;em&gt;directed&lt;/em&gt; behavior. They take in energy (eat). They reproduce. Even if this behavior is entirely deterministic, arising purely from the physical states of the organism, it remains irreducible to principles with broad explanatory force. “All living things consume from their environment for energy” is not an explanation; it is a description. “Objects’ motion as described by ‘gravity’ derives from the curvature of space-time’ is an explanation and not merely a description. Biological systems, still less conglomeration of such systems (especially those with minds!) both exist and behave in trivially counterfactuals ways, and therefore not only do not but probably &lt;em&gt;cannot&lt;/em&gt; have the kind of nomic necessity present in non-emergent systems. If such a system does exist, it must consist of properties well outside our current sphere of knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id="refs" class="references"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;section class="footnotes"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn1"&gt;&lt;p&gt;That the physical state of the brain is closely related to and indeed affects mental state is unsurprising; that they would be the sole cause of mental states (and that there is no influence running the other direction) is a much stronger, and much less well-justified claim.&lt;a href="#fnref1"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn2"&gt;&lt;p&gt;and, arguably, strange edge cases and hangers-on like viruses or prions&lt;a href="#fnref2"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 12 May 2016 21:03:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2016-05-12:2016/counterfactuals-and-supervenience.html</guid><category>M. Div.</category><category>SEBTS</category><category>philosophy</category><category>science</category></item><item><title>Science and Pseudo-Science</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2016/science-and-pseudo-science.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;i class="editorial"&gt;The following was prepared as a one-page, single-spaced short response to a question from the readings for this class.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many differences do not admit of clear or hard distinctions. The difference between science and pseudo-science is just such a difference. There is a clear and intuitively obvious difference between astronomy and astrology, between medical research and homeopathic remedies, between chemistry and alchemy. This is so even though it is difficult (if not impossible) to specify exactly what set of criteria are both necessary and sufficient to constitute one thing as a pseudo-science and another as actual science. This is not a difficulty specific to this differentiation; few categories are truly binary. Instead, humans normally and rationally distinguish between kinds of things on the basis of sets of criteria. So, as the well-known example from discussions of realism and anti-realism makes clear: humans can tell a bald man from a man with a full-head of hair, even though there is no single point at which one stops being hirsute and starts being bald. Likewise, we can recognize a sunny day from a cloudy day, even though there is a spectrum ranging from &lt;em&gt;not a cloud in the sky&lt;/em&gt; to &lt;em&gt;clouds so thick and dark it seems like twilight at midday&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the case of science and pseudo-science, there are a broad set of criteria which form a sort of diagnostic battery. Different (though overlapping) sets of tests are applicable in different fields. There is one set of discriminants between astronomy and astrology. There is another set between chemistry and alchemy, and another between pharmaceutical research and homeopathy. All share commonalities, but are not identical. For example, astronomy and astrology both rely on observation of the same celestial phenomena; pharmaceutical research and homeopathy both aim to treat physical ills by way of some external treatment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the astronomy/astrology divide, the major distinction is &lt;em&gt;applicability&lt;/em&gt;. Astronomy applies the observed data to understanding the subject under observation: stars, galaxies, and so on. Astrology applies the observed data to &lt;em&gt;other&lt;/em&gt; subjects (namely human lives). The applicability of observations about stars to analysis of stars is straightforward and obvious. The applicability of those observations to predicting human affairs involves a substantial leap from the observation to a non-(physically-)associated subject. The latter is not logically inconceivable: even in a purely physical system of causation, it is possible that the stars’ positions were designed by some creative force to provide just such indicators. However, the claim advanced is much stronger relative to the relationship between the data and the purported effect; the applicability much less obvious; and (last but not least) the claim as usually advanced is &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; physical but mystical. Again: this does not in and of itself mean astrology is not &lt;em&gt;true&lt;/em&gt;. It does mean that it advances claims that are both outside the means by which science is conducted (which, when prediction is involved, usually involve some degree of falsifiability), and also outside the normal &lt;em&gt;application&lt;/em&gt; of observations within science.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The pharmaceutical research and homeopathy distinction shares some but not all of these difference-markers. There is certainly an element of repeatability and falsifiability in play, for one. (How effective this actually is, given recent studies in repeatability in pharmaceutical work especially but the sciences in general, is an important related question, but not ultimately final.) However, they do not share the applicability issue in the astronomy/astrology divide. The subject—sick humans—is the same. So is the treatment pattern. Nor is there generally an appeal to non-physical realities. The distinction here seems to be &lt;em&gt;only&lt;/em&gt; one of methodology and empiricism. The differences between chemistry and alchemy are of a similar nature. But other science/pseudo-science distinctions will look different.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The problem, then, is not that it is &lt;em&gt;impossible&lt;/em&gt; to distinguish between science and pseudo-science, but that there are a broad set of criteria involved in making those distinctions, and the criteria are overlapping but not identical in different fields.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id="refs" class="references"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 12 May 2016 21:01:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2016-05-12:2016/science-and-pseudo-science.html</guid><category>M. Div.</category><category>SEBTS</category><category>philosophy</category><category>science</category></item><item><title>Corpuscularianism and Atomism</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2016/corpuscularianism-and-atomism.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;i class="editorial"&gt;The following was prepared as a one-page, single-spaced short response to a question from the readings for this class.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One possible point of difference between philosophy and science is the way they proceed toward answering questions and understanding the world. For example, “Corpuscularianism was mere philosophy. Atomism is science,” suggests an important difference: between reasoning from first principles and reasoning from observed phenomena in the world. The idea is that the corpuscularian idea derived not from observations about the world external to the thinker, but from abstract reasoning about the world—that is, not from &lt;em&gt;data&lt;/em&gt; but from &lt;em&gt;first principles&lt;/em&gt;. This distinction, while initially appealing, has several problems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, it simply does not square with the actual history of science. A number of significant advances have come from reasoning about the world. Einstein’s analyses, across all fields (including some related to atomistic views of the world) were famously the product of initial thought experiments &lt;em&gt;followed&lt;/em&gt; rather than &lt;em&gt;preceded&lt;/em&gt; by mathematical derivation and finally observational data. To be sure, there are many times when scientific understandings change because of data. But this is not the only way scientific interpretations shift. Rather, changes in epistemology, metaphysics, and other prior commitments may lead to substantial reinterpretations of the same data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moreover, those reevaluations may themselves produce further scientific work. One thinks of the way quantum mechanics developed over the twentieth century—including the substantial resistance to it from those enamored of more classical and determinist models, Einstein among them; and the multiple interpretive schemes for dealing philosophically with the implications of quantum mechanics’ findings. These are themselves conditioned by the evidence—but do &lt;em&gt;and must&lt;/em&gt; supersede it in explanatory power and scope. The various interpretations of quantum mechanics are interpretations not only of the data but the world in which the data lives. A radical indeterminism view, an observer-affected data view, a hidden variable view, and so on all offer up points of view which inform the work done by the scientists themselves in an inherent feedback loop. Philosophy and science are not the same, but they are inextricable from each other; one’s prior commitments inevitably shape the answers one will find to some degree or another.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As such, this view fails to deal with the way that those philosophical commitments drove scientific exploration. The belief in a corpuscularian was part and parcel of the discovery of atomism. That there were philosophical reasons for accepting the view prior to observational evidence for it actually serves to reinforce rather than undercut the view. Indeed, the phrasing of the proposition itself is suspect. “Mere” philosophizing, as noted above, necessarily underlies all scientific research programs. At the most basic level: a commitment to the existence of an external world to be interacted with and discovered, the reliability of experience as a kind of evidence, and the generalizability of data via induction and inference to the best explanation are all necessary for the practice of science.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moreover, if one entirely rejected in an &lt;em&gt;a priori&lt;/em&gt; sense that it was possible to discover anything not directly observable (say, because one rejected any sort of corpuscularianism, or because one was a strict anti-realist, or for any number of other reasons), one would simply not look for evidence in that direction. Whatever experiments revealed, an individual with those commitments would not go looking for atoms or evidence of them. The evidence might, over time, suggest a revision of the worldview, and this sort of empirical refutation of the paradigm is of course the point of the proposition. Unfortunately for the proposition, this is not a distinction between philosophy and science, but between unrelenting dogmatism and critical realism. Science may be deeply dogmatic, and philosophy may readily revise its conclusions in the face of new evidence. Such evidence may differ in kind: it might be a a logical proof rather than physical data, as Gödel’s incompleteness theorem forced a revision in logical positivism. It does not, however, lead to an in-principle difference in method.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id="refs" class="references"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 12 May 2016 20:58:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2016-05-12:2016/corpuscularianism-and-atomism.html</guid><category>M. Div.</category><category>SEBTS</category><category>philosophy</category><category>science</category></item><item><title>Realism and Anti-Realism in Science</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2016/realism-and-anti-realism-in-science.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Adjudicating the realism/anti-realism debate in science often involves discussion of ‘miracles,’ the ‘observable/unobservable distinction,’ and ‘underdetermination’. Pick one of these three areas and develop an argument for realism or anti-realism in terms of it. Don’t forget to assess the argument.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The realism/anti-realism debate in science often hinges on the nature of and relationship between observables and unobservables. Anti-realists argue that scientists can have no actual knowledge of unobservables, and therefore should treat theories about unobservables agnostically: however useful the models may be, they should not be considered to correspond to &lt;em&gt;truth&lt;/em&gt; about reality. For example, anti-realists argue that hypotheses about the nature of fundamental particles such as quarks and electrons should not be taken as if quarks and electrons actually exist, but only as pragmatically useful, with no way even in principle of determining whether such things actually exist.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In fact, any attempt to consider the relationship between observables and unobservables ultimately points instead toward a (critical) realist account of science. Any attempt to distinguish sharply or clearly in principle between observables and unobservables fails, for two reasons: first, the claim that “unobservables” as such exist in a strict sense; and second, that, the relationship between “observable” and “unobservable” falls along a spectrum.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the first case, anti-realists use “unobservable” to mean anything not &lt;em&gt;directly&lt;/em&gt; observable by human senses. However, to declare such objects in principle unobservable is to beg the question, since the point under debate is precisely whether things detected indirectly—electron traces in a gas cloud, for example—are being observed or simply hypothesized. Anti-realists must first establish in an in-principle sense a sharp distinction between that which is indirectly observed and that which is directly observed. Realists, by contrast, note that indirect observation is rightly considered reliable in the realm of ordinary experience. It is reasonable to conclude that the wind is blowing from seeing its effects on trees even if sitting inside a closed room with no direct experience of the wind. Indirect observations still count as observations, and are clear signals of the real presence of a thing being observed. Whether it is observed directly or indirectly does not determine whether it is observed at all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This also extends into the second case: a realist view rightly makes sense of the way things are more or less directly observable. On one end are those phenomena which can be detected through (normal, healthy) human senses such as hearing or vision. Moving down toward the not-directly-observable spectrum, scientists use various sorts of equipment to enhance their ability to observe: telescopes, when looking at things inaccessible to ordinary human sight because of distance; and microscopes, when examining things inaccessible to ordinary human sight because of size. In both cases, however, there is no clear line distinguishing the “observable” and the “unobservable”—only a spectrum of more- or less-directly-observable phenomena. Insects may be observed with the unaided human eye, bacteria with optical microscopes, individual molecules of materials with electron microscopes. In each case, the same principle is at work in the observation: light bouncing off an object and being received.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The anti-realist may object that this is not so: the fact that the distinction between observables and unobservables is blurry does not mean it does not exist. To borrow an example from Okasha: the line between “bald” and “hirsute” may be fuzzy (pun intended), but it is still possible to identify a bald man. Even granting the in-principle distinction between “observable” and “unobservable,” however, the objection fails to establish the strong claim made by anti-realists. It does not establish that the items in question are in fact unobservable (especially when confronted with the realist argument for indirect observation). Nor does it establish that scientists would be in principle incapable of correctly modeling unobservables. At most, it establishes that unobservables may exist.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thus, it is reasonable to suppose that though current models of astronomical behavior, or of quantum mechanics, or gravity, or any other only-indirectly-observable phenomena may be incomplete or partial, they nonetheless represent something &lt;em&gt;actual&lt;/em&gt;. The wind really is blowing. There really an electron leaving a trail in the gas chamber.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id="refs" class="references"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 15 Mar 2016 12:30:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2016-03-15:2016/realism-and-anti-realism-in-science.html</guid><category>M. Div.</category><category>SEBTS</category><category>philosophy</category><category>science</category></item><item><title>The 'Covering Law' Model</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2016/the-covering-law-model.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;What is the ‘covering law’ model of scientific explanation and what are two reasons it seems to be defective? How do these defects point to a better model of scientific explanation?&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The ‘covering law’ model of scientific explanation is the view that scientific explanations consist of three elements: &lt;em&gt;deductive&lt;/em&gt; arguments, with &lt;em&gt;sound&lt;/em&gt; premises, which make referent to (at least) one natural law. That is, for an explanation to count as “scientific,” it must first of all be in the from of an argument, “If A is true then B is the case; A is true, therefore B is the case.” Second, the premises of the argument must be valid. In other words, “If A and B are both true, then C is the case; A and B are true, therefore C is the case” is deductively valid, but if either of the premises A or B are false, the argument is not sound and it does not serve as a scientific explanation. Finally, the explanation must refer to one or more general laws in the course of its argument. That is, in the same formulation, “If A and B are both true, then C is the case; A and B are true, therefore C is the case,” the explanation may be both deductive and sound but &lt;em&gt;unscientific&lt;/em&gt; if neither A nor B are natural laws of some sort.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One classic example of this sort of explanation is answering why a given plant died. Given that scientists know a great many things about the necessary conditions for plants to remain alive, it is possible to construct an explanation that fits the covering law model. Such an argument might proceed as follows:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol type="1"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;All living must metabolize sources of energy to stay alive [general law GL-A].&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Plants are living things [observation O-A].&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Plants metabolize energy via photosynthesis [general law GL-B].&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This plant was kept in the dark [an observation O-B].&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Therefore, this plant could not metabolize energy via photosynthesis [conclusion C-A following from GL-B and O-B].&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Therefore, this plant died [conclusion following from C-A, O-A, and GL-A].&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It would equally be possible in the absence of observations (O-A and O-B) to formulate a &lt;em&gt;prediction&lt;/em&gt;: in place of O-B and the conclusions which follow it, we could supply this form:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start="4" type="1"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If a plant is kept in the dark, it will not be able to metabolize energy via photosynthesis [P].&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Therefore, a plant which is kept in the dark will die. [C-C]&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note that the two forms are symmetric, because of the rules of deductive logic. Any explanation formulated under the covering law model could also be couched as a prediction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although the covering law model is initially attractive, there are two serious problems with it. The first is this very point of symmetry. Explanations, it turns out, are rarely symmetric with predictions. To borrow an example from Okasha, given the rules of trigonometry, if one knows any two of the angle of the sun in the sky, the height of a flagpole, or the length of the shadow cast by the flagpole, one can &lt;em&gt;predict&lt;/em&gt; the third element. For example, having only the length of the shadow and the height of the flagpole, one can calculate the angle of the sun in the sky. Clearly, however, the length of the shadow and the height of the flagpole have no causal relation to the position of the sun in the sky. They do not &lt;em&gt;explain&lt;/em&gt; it, though they may be used to predict it. By contrast, the intent of the person fashioning the flagpole, and a combination of facts about the sun’s emanation of light as part of the process of fusion and the earth’s orbit around the sun do suffice to explain the length of the shadow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is not merely a hypothetical concern; it is precisely the distinction between ancient Babylonian and ancient Greek methods of astronomy, as J.P. Moreland comments. The Babylonian astronomers were able to &lt;em&gt;predict&lt;/em&gt; the positions of stars in the sky, relying on careful observation and detailed tables. They did not offer any &lt;em&gt;explanation&lt;/em&gt; of those positions, however; the Greeks did. Though the Ptolemaic model the Greeks embraced is now rejected, it was an explanatory, and therefore &lt;em&gt;scientific&lt;/em&gt;, model. Predictions are not the same as explanations, precisely because explanations indicate the underlying causes that things are as they are.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Second, it is possible to offer explanations which satisfy the covering law model, but in which the premises are &lt;em&gt;irrelevant to the conclusion&lt;/em&gt;. In Okasha’s example, a doctor explains why a man does not become pregnant in terms of the observation that people who regularly take oral contraceptives do not become pregnant, and the man is taking oral contraceptives. Leaving aside the question of why a man would be taking oral contraceptives, the actual explanation is quite different: the man does not become pregnant because men are biologically incapable of pregnancy. Though the argument is deductively valid, and its premises are at least potentially sound, the law actually fails as an explanation. In this case, its predictive power is actually deceptive, because the prediction is totally uncoupled from the cause.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Both of these failings share in common the same core issue: ignoring the role of causality. Scientific explanations—to be differentiated from scientific &lt;em&gt;observations&lt;/em&gt; such as “water is two molecules of hydrogen and one of oxygen”—traffic in &lt;em&gt;causes&lt;/em&gt; and not merely &lt;em&gt;predictions&lt;/em&gt;. Any model of how scientific explanation actually works must therefore include the arrow of causality.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id="refs" class="references"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 15 Mar 2016 12:30:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2016-03-15:2016/the-covering-law-model.html</guid><category>M. Div.</category><category>SEBTS</category><category>philosophy</category><category>science</category></item><item><title>The Problem of Induction</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2016/the-problem-of-induction.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;What is the problem of induction? Discuss two proposed solutions to this problem, and explain why (in your view) they are adequate solutions or defective ones.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The problem of induction is the question: &lt;em&gt;Is induction a trustworthy means of obtaining knowledge?&lt;/em&gt; The majority of scientific reasoning necessarily leans heavily on induction—it is, after all, impossible to observe every star in the universe, or every duck on Earth, or the psychological patterns of all humans, for example. Thus, any scientific reasoning which purports to rise to the level of a universal explanation or law must rely on induction to arrive at its conclusion: “We have observed things to obey rules X, Y, and Z in all known instances. Given the regularity of the universe, it follows that things obey rules X, Y, and Z everywhere.” The question is whether the leap between the premises and the conclusion is warranted: is it reasonable to suppose that things scientists have &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; observed (whether because they are out of observational range, or because they are in the future) behave the same way as those they &lt;em&gt;have&lt;/em&gt; observed?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mark Lange helpfully summarizes the problem in the form of a simple argument: since all arguments are either deductive or inductive, the middle link in the argument for the reliability of induction must be either deductive or inductive. But it cannot be an inductive argument; that would simply be a circular argument: “If inductive reasoning holds, it is valid to use inductive reasoning, and inductive reasoning has always worked in the past, so we induce that it will continue to work in the future, ergo it is valid to use inductive reasoning.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, the argument may also not be &lt;em&gt;deductive&lt;/em&gt;. There is an infinite number of &lt;em&gt;logically&lt;/em&gt; possible explanations for the apparent success of induction to date. For example, it is logically possible that all objects believed to be green—and which inductive reasoning would therefore suggest will be green tomorrow as well—are in fact the mysterious and previous unobserved color “grue”: a color which appears green until an unspecified date, after which it is blue. This is just as logically consistent with all observations as the idea that induction holds. Thus, no deductive argument can demonstrate the validity of induction, for there is no &lt;em&gt;deductive&lt;/em&gt; manner of choosing between such possibilities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One proposed solutions is a pragmatic argument. &lt;em&gt;If the universe behaves uniformly, then induction will work; if the universe does &lt;strong&gt;not&lt;/strong&gt; behave uniformly, then no method will work. Therefore, scientists are justified in acting as though induction works.&lt;/em&gt; Unfortunately, this argument at best establishes a matter of reasonable policy for scientists, without providing warrant for belief. That is, however reasonable and even necessary it may be for scientists to proceed as though induction holds and is valid, the argument provides no evidence that induction &lt;em&gt;does&lt;/em&gt; in fact hold.&lt;a href="#fn1" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref1"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another solution is the argument from Christian theism: &lt;em&gt;given God’s creation covenant to maintain order (Genesis 9), the goodness and providence of God (derived from statements to that effect throughout Scripture), and the claim to efficacy of the Proverbs, it is theologically necessary that the universe continue to work as it has in the past.&lt;/em&gt; In its favor, this suggestion has the form of an argument, and is not directly reliant on the evidence of past uniformity as a basis for future uniformity. However, this sort of reasoning from Scripture is itself inductive. It takes a specific interpretation of the texts under consideration, and a belief that things are at a certain point in cosmological/theological history (i.e. the eschaton has not yet arrived) and extrapolates to the notion that God will continue upholding the previous pattern of laws of nature. Moreover, even if the argument were to hold, it would not be a &lt;em&gt;scientific&lt;/em&gt; but a &lt;em&gt;philosophical-theological&lt;/em&gt; argument. (This is, perhaps, unsurprising given that though the problem of induction is especially applicable to the practice of science, it is a far more general problem.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id="refs" class="references"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;section class="footnotes"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn1"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Interestingly, however, if the validity of induction is taken as an &lt;em&gt;a priori&lt;/em&gt; assumption, its historical efficacy may be taken as good evidence for the consistency of nature as a reasonable inference to the best explanation in the realism/anti-realism debate.&lt;a href="#fnref1"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 15 Mar 2016 12:30:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2016-03-15:2016/the-problem-of-induction.html</guid><category>M. Div.</category><category>SEBTS</category><category>philosophy</category><category>science</category></item></channel></rss>