<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Chris Krycho</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/</link><description></description><atom:link href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/feeds/philosophy.xml" rel="self"></atom:link><lastBuildDate>Sun, 15 May 2016 16:36:00 -0400</lastBuildDate><item><title>2016-05-15 16:36</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2016/2016-05-15-1636.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;~5600 words down. ~1800 to go. Yes, I underestimated yesterday by about 1500 words. &lt;em&gt;Whoops.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id="refs" class="references"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 15 May 2016 16:36:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2016-05-15:2016/2016-05-15-1636.html</guid><category>SEBTS</category><category>writing</category><category>papers</category><category>philosophy</category></item><item><title>2016-05-14 15:56</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2016/2016-05-14-1556.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;~3500 words down, ~2500 to go. Steady on!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id="refs" class="references"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 14 May 2016 15:56:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2016-05-14:2016/2016-05-14-1556.html</guid><category>sebts</category><category>papers</category><category>writing</category><category>philosophy</category><category>M. Div.</category></item><item><title>2016-05-14 09:15</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2016/2016-05-14-0915.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;That feeling when you’re researching a paper and a philosopher cherry-picks all his examples and ignores every countervailing examples.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id="refs" class="references"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 14 May 2016 09:15:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2016-05-14:2016/2016-05-14-0915.html</guid><category>philosophy</category></item><item><title>Full-On Question-Begging</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2016/full-on-question-begging.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;i class="editorial"&gt;The following was prepared as a one-page, single-spaced short response to a question from the readings for this class.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Scientific naturalism, as a worldview (not an instrumental technique applied in certain circumstances) is certainly question-begging. First, the claim that “the physical world is the only thing which exists” is fundamentally a philosophical and not a scientific claim. That is, if science is a broadly experimental approach to discovering truth about the physical world, it is incapable of determining whether a non-physical world exists, and it is not even asking—still less answering!—metaphysical questions about the nature of reality. The basic issues of epistemology, ontology, and ethics are themselves not subject to empirical analysis. Evidence from the natural world may certainly be useful and even helpful in considering these domains, but by definition cannot be finally determinative. For example: if the physical world is &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; the only thing which exists, what sort of purely physical test could demonstrate that? Likewise, if humans have cognitive access to spiritual realities, because they are dualist and not purely physical beings, they might have genuine non-physical experiential knowledge. No ontological, epistemological, or teleological claim is finally resolvable through merely physical testing; claims in such areas are finally philosophical and theological.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Second, the efficacy of science in the domain of explaining the physical world is in no sense evidence that it is a particularly effective way of describing &lt;em&gt;all things&lt;/em&gt;. This is akin to suggesting that because musical notation is particularly effective for representing notes to be played, it is the only form of notation required; all written words should immediately be discarded, as should all computer programs. That is, the utility of one form of description or program of study for a given domain does not make it immediately applicable to or indeed at all relevant for other domains. Even with the context of scientific efforts, this is obvious: different techniques are used in observational astronomy than in ecological analysis, and different methods of analysis in assessing the claims of theoretical physics than in analyzing data from a given paleontological dig.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Third, and perhaps most importantly for current debates, the efficacy of science in describing the physical world provides no evidence whatsoever that the physical world is the only thing which exists. To suggest otherwise is simply to commit a basic logical fallacy. This is obvious if the premises and conclusion are laid out explicitly: The argument might be laid out so: “(P1) Science describes the physical world effectively. (P2) Science does not and cannot describe the non-physical world. (C) Therefore, the physical world is the only thing which exists.” But the conclusion clearly does not follow from the premises, even inductively. The argument might be modified into an inductive form: “(P1) Science describes the physical world effectively. (P2) Science has provided increased effectiveness in describing an ever-wider variety of phenomena over time. (P3) In so doing, science has found physical explanations of phenomena which at one time seemed intractable to such explanations. (C1) Therefore, science will at some point in the future find physical explanations for all phenomena. (C2) Therefore, there are no non-physical phenomena.” Even so strengthened, there are two major problems with the argument. First, C1 is an incredibly strong claim, and the purported evidence toward it in this form’s P3 is itself disputed. Moreover, even if C1 were granted, it would offer some evidence for C2 but &lt;em&gt;would not prove it&lt;/em&gt;. There still might be reason to think that physical phenomena and their corresponding explanations were expressions of the will of a wise divine being, for example. Moreover, while claims for non-physical purposes for or fundamental explanations of physical mechanisms might then be on shakier ground in virtue of being apparently less simple, the physicalist would need to make a (philosophical) argument for the apparent scientific virtue of simplicity! There is no escape from claims which are themselves not even capable of being tested empirically.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id="refs" class="references"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 12 May 2016 21:09:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2016-05-12:2016/full-on-question-begging.html</guid><category>M. Div.</category><category>SEBTS</category><category>philosophy</category><category>science</category></item><item><title>Empirical Equivalence, Real Semantic Difference</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2016/empirical-equivalence-real-semantic-difference.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;i class="editorial"&gt;The following was prepared as a one-page, single-spaced short response to a question from the readings for this class.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When two theories make contradictory claims, even were they to have empirically equivalent outcomes, the contradiction in their claims is not merely terminological or semantic. It is fairly easy to conceive of claims are &lt;em&gt;merely&lt;/em&gt; semantically different, but which have the same basic content: “That is a chair” and the Spanish equivalent “ésa es una silla” both have the same basic referents, and even intend broadly the same meaning. Their variance is terminological, by dint of being in two distinct languages. It is far more difficult to find two claims which are in opposition to each other, but their opposition is merely terminological.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is not just the case in science. To make a claim, scientific or otherwise, is to assert something about the world as it actually is. Thus, “The sky is blue” and “The sky is green but appears to us as blue because all our eyes are defective in a way we cannot measure” would have the same base empirical content, but make very different claims about the nature of human sight and the sky. This particular claim is trivially testable in some other way; but different claims in fundamental physics—empirically equivalent string theories, for example—might not be trivially testable, or testable at all: they might be empirically equivalent in principle as well as in practice. But the trivial example serves to highlight the reality that empirical equivalence does not entail semantic equality. The blueness or greenness of the sky is not merely a matter of human descriptions of things. Rather, even though they are meaningful only because of their semantics, their semantics carry force that is not merely different ways of saying the same thing: that is one of the basic necessities for language to function. If different semantics did not actually entail different claims, communication would be impossible. Less pragmatically, if one affirms that the referents in question are in some sense “out there” and not merely the contents of human speech or human sense data—that is, if one embraces a correspondence theory of truth and a basically, albeit critically, realist view of human knowledge including scientific knowledge—then the notion that two claims are merely terminological variants even though their semantics stand in contrast is clearly false.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To take an example particularly appropriate to a science-and-religion course: it is quite conceivable that a disinterested god (quite different from the one we worship) and a pantheon of disinterested gods and a universe which came out purely by chance would all be empirically equivalent. Yet “there is one bored god out there” and “there is no god out there” and “there are many bored gods out there” are clearly and obviously not terminological variants of each other, even if there is no empirical way to tell them apart. A similar thing would hold of two string theories, one which postulated 12 and the other 28 hidden dimensions. Even if both yielded the same empirical predictions (which were verified) and were in-principle incapable of any further test, they would nonetheless be claims with semantic content about the nature of reality which is &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; reducible merely to a terminological variant. The fact that the truth or falsity of a claim may not be knowable does not tell against its distinctive semantic content, only against its pragmatic utility. If one of the two string theories suggested above were true, it might not make any practical difference which one it was. After all, if the contents are permanently inaccessible to humans, and the theoretical consequences identical, then either may be used in the pursuit of other knowledge. However, by dint of the fact that they make distinct and countervailing claims to one another, at least one must be false. And truth is no small matter!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id="refs" class="references"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 12 May 2016 21:08:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2016-05-12:2016/empirical-equivalence-real-semantic-difference.html</guid><category>M. Div.</category><category>SEBTS</category><category>philosophy</category><category>science</category></item><item><title>Realism, Generality, and Precision—In Tension?</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2016/realism-generality-and-precision-in-tension.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;i class="editorial"&gt;The following was prepared as a one-page, single-spaced short response to a question from the readings for this class.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The tension between realism, generality, and precision posited in biology is a function not of those constraints in general, but of the specific constraints on biology and other sciences dealing with what is often described as having “emergent” phenomena. The closer the science is to physical first principles, the less these terms stand in contrast. For example, in chemistry, a realist description of the chemicals in question is actually &lt;em&gt;helpful&lt;/em&gt; in dealing precisely with the terms in question. The behavior of the chemicals at large scales can be modeled more effectively precisely because the underlying principles are relatively well understood and the phenomenon describable not merely as a representative abstraction but in terms corresponding to what seem to be the &lt;em&gt;actual&lt;/em&gt; characteristics of the system in view. The same is true of much of physics. For example, the idea of general relativity is (as its name suggests) extremely general, covering the behavior of all macroscopic systems at least; is sufficiently precise in its predictions to enable extraordinary feats of timekeeping and geolocation; and is understood by the majority of working physicists to be a &lt;em&gt;true&lt;/em&gt; and not merely a &lt;em&gt;useful&lt;/em&gt; description of how space-time behaves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The question arises then: assuming the claim is correct for biology, why is this so? The answer seems to be that biological systems are not subject (at least so far as they are understood so far) to be capable of reduction to the same kinds of general theorems as the more purely physical sciences. Though biological is concerned of physical subjects, those subjects seem not to merely the expression of mechanistic phenomena (though of course this point is debated by some physicalist philosophers and scientists). Rather, their behavior emerges atop the underlying physical system, and then diverges in unpredictable ways from individual subject to individual subject. As a result, descriptions of the trends that occur in a given &lt;em&gt;population&lt;/em&gt; may be general, but do not do justice to the behavior of any one member of that population, and so are not &lt;em&gt;precise&lt;/em&gt;. Thus, ecologies are functions of &lt;em&gt;aggregate&lt;/em&gt; behavior, but that aggregation is something like the “average American family”: it is a description of no individual element within the system, but of the combined output of the whole system. Moreover, under even trivially different conditions (a lightning strike occurring in one place rather than another, for example, and changing the behavior of the animals in that area), the specific outcome of the system might have been meaningfully different—even if still able to be modeled under the same general descriptions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Indeed, most effective general models of behavior in biological systems are neither realistic nor precise. Attempts to model the function of neurons are often precise, but intentionally non-realist and non-general, not least because in most organisms, neurons are non-generalizable: only the simplest creatures have non-differentiated neurons. But in each of these cases, these are functions of the kind of increasingly complex systems, which are not apparently describable purely in terms of their underlying components. The brain, for example, is composed not just of an extraordinarily large number of neurons, but of a great variety of kinds of neurons as well, and the neurons all have the same basic chemical makeup and the same basic genetic structure, but develop in different ways because of specific driving factors in their environment, signals from chemicals driven by other parts of the body, and so on. Any description of any part of this system will necessarily be subject to the constraints the biologist describes simply because there is no single underlying principle driving the system; rather, it is a complex system where each part informs the others. The same is true (and even more so) of systems made up of biological actors, such as communities and ecologies; it is unsurprisingly also a common feature of systems which include actors with agency (such as economics).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id="refs" class="references"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 12 May 2016 21:07:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2016-05-12:2016/realism-generality-and-precision-in-tension.html</guid><category>M. Div.</category><category>SEBTS</category><category>philosophy</category><category>science</category></item><item><title>Aristotle, Newton, and Progress</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2016/aristotle-newton-and-progress.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;i class="editorial"&gt;The following was prepared as a one-page, single-spaced short response to a question from the readings for this class.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Aristotle’s impetus theory provided an effective and predictively accurate (and indeed, &lt;em&gt;scientific&lt;/em&gt;) model of the behavior of objects in terrestrial contexts. Though it was later superseded by Newton’s model, which had no impetuses at all, Aristotle’s method was a perfectly defensible model because it accounted for the &lt;em&gt;known&lt;/em&gt; phenomena well. The method worked because a number of constraints in the systems observed were not yet themselves understood. In a limited sense, Aristotle’s view could be construed as a &lt;em&gt;for-certain-conditions&lt;/em&gt; subset of Newton’s laws (though, strictly speaking, this is inaccurate). That is, in the conditions in which Aristotle made his observations, and failing to account for some of the phenomena for which Newton’s approach &lt;em&gt;did&lt;/em&gt; account, the impetus model for motion was valid.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In systems where there is resistance—e.g., all terrestrial systems—objects do not remain in motion without some other object providing an impetus to them, and objects of different masses but the same basic size do not fall at the same rate. Newton’s revolution was not in denying this but in recognizing that the grounding assumptions were incorrect: terrestrial systems are a &lt;em&gt;subset&lt;/em&gt; of a broader possible systems. Because this is so, there exists a more general set of laws which govern the behavior of objects in both terrestrial and non-terrestrial systems. This in turn led to the recognition that Aristotle had made a false generalization from the observed (terrestrial) data: the idea that objects require impetuses to remain in motion was empirically sound, but incomplete. Thus, a feather and a similarly-weighted needle fall at different rates because their different densities and surface areas relative to their masses result in different degrees of resistance. A bowling ball eventually comes to rest because of the resistive forces it experiences due to friction. These are not the general case, but subsets of the broader laws Newton derived; but Aristotle’s formulation can readily be seen just as that subset, under certain conditions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is not an unusual pattern in the history of science, and in fact is similarly applicable to Newton’s own system of mechanics, since superseded by both quantum mechanics and general relativity. As the constraints under which a given law operates become better-understood, it is sometimes possible (at least in the case of physical laws) to derive deeper generalizations about the systems in question, generalizations of which the currently-held set of laws are recognized to be a subset. Granted that at times, the new laws do not supersede but wholly replace the old model, and that both the Aristotle-Newton and Newton-Einstein/QM transitions contain some degree of this latter, it is still the case that newer theories ofttimes succeed because they demonstrate themselves capable of solving the same set of problems as the preceding theory, while also addressing many of the unresolved issues in it. So: Newton was able to derive more, and more accurate, predictions than was the Aristotelian model, and to provide more thorough explanations of the systems in question; and likewise Einstein than Newton. In both cases, however, the original model had the utility it did (and the empirical success it did) precisely because it was in some way a &lt;em&gt;for-certain-conditions&lt;/em&gt; subset of the more general theory.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A rather more interesting contrast, then, is between theories where the earlier theory is not even construable as a for-certain-conditions subset of the later, as in the phlogiston theory of combustion, since replaced by an oxidizing view. The idea had substantial explanatory power and harmonized quite well with the data, but was ultimately overthrown by the alternative (and now current, albeit revised) view of oxidation. Such cases, unlike the Aristotelian-Newtonian or Newtonian-Einsteinian/quantum mechanical transitions, are much harder to reconcile with a progressive view of the development of scientific theory, or with realist accounts of scientific explanation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id="refs" class="references"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 12 May 2016 21:06:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2016-05-12:2016/aristotle-newton-and-progress.html</guid><category>M. Div.</category><category>SEBTS</category><category>philosophy</category><category>science</category></item><item><title>Statistical Regularities and Explanation</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2016/statistical-regularities-and-explanation.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;i class="editorial"&gt;The following was prepared as a one-page, single-spaced short response to a question from the readings for this class.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is easy to mistake &lt;em&gt;exactness&lt;/em&gt; for &lt;em&gt;explanatory power&lt;/em&gt; in the realm of explanation. Thus, it might be tempting to suppose that precise and consistent statistical regularities have greater explanatory power than inexact laws which have an attendant set of constraints and conditions specifying when and how they apply. However, the inverse is true.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Statistical regularity has &lt;em&gt;no&lt;/em&gt; explanatory power. It has enormous utility, in that it allows effective prediction. However, it provides no insight into the reason why the regularity is captures occurs. Explanation is at core a matter of determining the reasons why something occurs, not simply observing &lt;em&gt;that&lt;/em&gt; it occurs. If on every first, second, and third Tuesday of the month for three hours early in the afternoon small black marks are rendered onto a mostly white LED display, and the range of marks is tightly bounded, and the marks are known to form meaningful words and sentences and even stories, and there can therefore be strong statistical confidence that &lt;em&gt;next&lt;/em&gt; Tuesday the same pattern will occur again, this does nothing to &lt;em&gt;explain&lt;/em&gt; the marks. What suffices as an explanation is a person using a typewriter to compose the draft of a novel on those Tuesdays when she has a babysitter for her children. This is certainly not even a &lt;em&gt;ceteris paribus&lt;/em&gt; law, and yet it has substantially greater explanatory power than does the statistical observation, regardless of the degree of statistical precision available.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By contrast, even inexact laws subject to restrictions and limitations are capable of offering meaningful explanations, because they can offer insight into the causal mechanisms which drive the processes. Though such statements of causality are inherently circumscribed to a certain degree—the &lt;em&gt;ceteris paribus&lt;/em&gt; clauses are necessary—they retain the explanatory power that inheres in causal reasoning. It is both legitimate and explanatory to reason that “all other things being equal, Superman will win in a fistfight with Batman because he has superhuman strength and is functionally invincible to human weaponry.” Granted that all other things may &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; be equal (as in the famous 1980s story from which recent cinema drew more or less inspiration) and that Batman may, if he has access to Kryptonite, bring about a different outcome, in no way diminishes the explanatory power of the original statement. In fact, it may strengthen it by suggesting what kinds of things must be equal for the statement to hold, and suggesting other kinds of causal factors in the system. Since the system that is the universe—even Batman and Superman’s universe—is very large, it is unsurprising that causal relations can only be described with these kinds of constraints. After all, only God could know the total set of forces acting on a system and therefore could deliver a non-&lt;em&gt;ceteris paribus&lt;/em&gt; statement of causal factors exhaustively.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This does not mean that statistical regularity is useless for explanation. In fact, it is a powerful tool for reasoning about the state of the world as part of deriving &lt;em&gt;ceteris paribus&lt;/em&gt;-constrained causal statements. To derive such causal statements, one must (usually) first derive sufficient data on which to base an analysis at all. Thus, knowing that Superman has been completely invulnerable to all human weapons of whatever magnitude in the past, and that Batman is an ordinary human, is important in being able to state that Superman will win in an ordinary fistfight between the two. The statistical data drives an inference to the best &lt;em&gt;explanation&lt;/em&gt; that he is in fact invulnerable to ordinary human weapons (an explanation which we as outside readers know in fact to be true), and grounds the “all other things being equal” statement. If other factors are introduced, so that other things are &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; equal, the inference from that statistical data set will still hold; but now other causal elements are in play and new statistical data would need to be gathered, for the sake of further reasoning &lt;em&gt;to explanation&lt;/em&gt;. The two go hand in hand, in other words.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id="refs" class="references"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 12 May 2016 21:04:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2016-05-12:2016/statistical-regularities-and-explanation.html</guid><category>M. Div.</category><category>SEBTS</category><category>philosophy</category><category>science</category></item><item><title>Counterfactuals and Supervenience</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2016/counterfactuals-and-supervenience.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;i class="editorial"&gt;The following was prepared as a one-page, single-spaced short response to a question from the readings for this class.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The natural sciences all claim to use the same basic model of knowledge, and claim to aim for the same kind of explanatory power: the &lt;em&gt;law&lt;/em&gt;. However, clearly the kinds of laws which have such force in chemistry and especially physics are at least much less common in the other sciences; they may be entirely absent. Biology serves as a prime example of an unquestionably “hard” science in which laws are much harder to come by. Whereas physics includes both descriptive laws (&lt;em&gt;PV = nRT&lt;/em&gt;) and explanatory laws (general relativity), biology seems entirely limited to the former. That is, there are e.g. laws describing &lt;em&gt;how&lt;/em&gt; populations behave in an ecosystem, but there are no systematizing principles which are thought to offer the same degree of broad explanatory and predictive power as, say, the Standard Model of quantum mechanics. The closest example is a broadly Darwinian model of evolution, but even leaving aside questions about the accuracy of the model, it differs substantially from physical or chemical laws. It offers far less in the way of precise predictions, for one. For another, althought it serves as an explanation, the &lt;em&gt;kind&lt;/em&gt; of explanation it offers is distinct in that it does not seem to have the kind of (nomic) necessity possessed by physical laws: even if Darwinian evolution is the means by which life arose on the planet, it by no means requires that life arose &lt;em&gt;as it did&lt;/em&gt;; Certainly it is possible that life could have taken other forms even under the same selective pressures, given some other mutation—or have failed to succeed at all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Biological systems (and yet-higher-level systems like ecologists or economies) demonstrate phenomena that &lt;em&gt;supervene&lt;/em&gt; on the underlying physical realities. Unlike physics or chemistry, these phenomena seem, perhaps permanently, resistant to reductive and unifying explanations. This is precisely because of their lack of nomic or causal necessity: counterfactuals are easy to imagine in biology; much less economics. In the most abstract sciences—behavioral psychology, sociology, and economics, for example–it seems that human agency plays a major part in the actual outcomes in the world. Physicalist/materialist claims notwithstanding, it seems quite unlikely that such agency can be reduced to the &lt;em&gt;results&lt;/em&gt; of chemical and electrical activity in the brain.&lt;a href="#fn1" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref1"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; Even at the level of microbes, however, the so-called “emergent behavior” of biological systems is not reducible to mere physical &lt;em&gt;properties&lt;/em&gt; as is the case in physics and chemistry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Again, counterfactuals play one significant part in this: biological systems could be other than what they are. But another significant factor is the purposive nature of organisms. Even the simplest living things&lt;a href="#fn2" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref2"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; have a teleological bent. Even if they were not designed, they themselves carry out certain patterns of &lt;em&gt;directed&lt;/em&gt; behavior. They take in energy (eat). They reproduce. Even if this behavior is entirely deterministic, arising purely from the physical states of the organism, it remains irreducible to principles with broad explanatory force. “All living things consume from their environment for energy” is not an explanation; it is a description. “Objects’ motion as described by ‘gravity’ derives from the curvature of space-time’ is an explanation and not merely a description. Biological systems, still less conglomeration of such systems (especially those with minds!) both exist and behave in trivially counterfactuals ways, and therefore not only do not but probably &lt;em&gt;cannot&lt;/em&gt; have the kind of nomic necessity present in non-emergent systems. If such a system does exist, it must consist of properties well outside our current sphere of knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id="refs" class="references"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;section class="footnotes"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn1"&gt;&lt;p&gt;That the physical state of the brain is closely related to and indeed affects mental state is unsurprising; that they would be the sole cause of mental states (and that there is no influence running the other direction) is a much stronger, and much less well-justified claim.&lt;a href="#fnref1"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn2"&gt;&lt;p&gt;and, arguably, strange edge cases and hangers-on like viruses or prions&lt;a href="#fnref2"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 12 May 2016 21:03:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2016-05-12:2016/counterfactuals-and-supervenience.html</guid><category>M. Div.</category><category>SEBTS</category><category>philosophy</category><category>science</category></item><item><title>Science and Pseudo-Science</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2016/science-and-pseudo-science.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;i class="editorial"&gt;The following was prepared as a one-page, single-spaced short response to a question from the readings for this class.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many differences do not admit of clear or hard distinctions. The difference between science and pseudo-science is just such a difference. There is a clear and intuitively obvious difference between astronomy and astrology, between medical research and homeopathic remedies, between chemistry and alchemy. This is so even though it is difficult (if not impossible) to specify exactly what set of criteria are both necessary and sufficient to constitute one thing as a pseudo-science and another as actual science. This is not a difficulty specific to this differentiation; few categories are truly binary. Instead, humans normally and rationally distinguish between kinds of things on the basis of sets of criteria. So, as the well-known example from discussions of realism and anti-realism makes clear: humans can tell a bald man from a man with a full-head of hair, even though there is no single point at which one stops being hirsute and starts being bald. Likewise, we can recognize a sunny day from a cloudy day, even though there is a spectrum ranging from &lt;em&gt;not a cloud in the sky&lt;/em&gt; to &lt;em&gt;clouds so thick and dark it seems like twilight at midday&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the case of science and pseudo-science, there are a broad set of criteria which form a sort of diagnostic battery. Different (though overlapping) sets of tests are applicable in different fields. There is one set of discriminants between astronomy and astrology. There is another set between chemistry and alchemy, and another between pharmaceutical research and homeopathy. All share commonalities, but are not identical. For example, astronomy and astrology both rely on observation of the same celestial phenomena; pharmaceutical research and homeopathy both aim to treat physical ills by way of some external treatment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the astronomy/astrology divide, the major distinction is &lt;em&gt;applicability&lt;/em&gt;. Astronomy applies the observed data to understanding the subject under observation: stars, galaxies, and so on. Astrology applies the observed data to &lt;em&gt;other&lt;/em&gt; subjects (namely human lives). The applicability of observations about stars to analysis of stars is straightforward and obvious. The applicability of those observations to predicting human affairs involves a substantial leap from the observation to a non-(physically-)associated subject. The latter is not logically inconceivable: even in a purely physical system of causation, it is possible that the stars’ positions were designed by some creative force to provide just such indicators. However, the claim advanced is much stronger relative to the relationship between the data and the purported effect; the applicability much less obvious; and (last but not least) the claim as usually advanced is &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; physical but mystical. Again: this does not in and of itself mean astrology is not &lt;em&gt;true&lt;/em&gt;. It does mean that it advances claims that are both outside the means by which science is conducted (which, when prediction is involved, usually involve some degree of falsifiability), and also outside the normal &lt;em&gt;application&lt;/em&gt; of observations within science.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The pharmaceutical research and homeopathy distinction shares some but not all of these difference-markers. There is certainly an element of repeatability and falsifiability in play, for one. (How effective this actually is, given recent studies in repeatability in pharmaceutical work especially but the sciences in general, is an important related question, but not ultimately final.) However, they do not share the applicability issue in the astronomy/astrology divide. The subject—sick humans—is the same. So is the treatment pattern. Nor is there generally an appeal to non-physical realities. The distinction here seems to be &lt;em&gt;only&lt;/em&gt; one of methodology and empiricism. The differences between chemistry and alchemy are of a similar nature. But other science/pseudo-science distinctions will look different.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The problem, then, is not that it is &lt;em&gt;impossible&lt;/em&gt; to distinguish between science and pseudo-science, but that there are a broad set of criteria involved in making those distinctions, and the criteria are overlapping but not identical in different fields.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id="refs" class="references"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 12 May 2016 21:01:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2016-05-12:2016/science-and-pseudo-science.html</guid><category>M. Div.</category><category>SEBTS</category><category>philosophy</category><category>science</category></item><item><title>Corpuscularianism and Atomism</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2016/corpuscularianism-and-atomism.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;i class="editorial"&gt;The following was prepared as a one-page, single-spaced short response to a question from the readings for this class.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One possible point of difference between philosophy and science is the way they proceed toward answering questions and understanding the world. For example, “Corpuscularianism was mere philosophy. Atomism is science,” suggests an important difference: between reasoning from first principles and reasoning from observed phenomena in the world. The idea is that the corpuscularian idea derived not from observations about the world external to the thinker, but from abstract reasoning about the world—that is, not from &lt;em&gt;data&lt;/em&gt; but from &lt;em&gt;first principles&lt;/em&gt;. This distinction, while initially appealing, has several problems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, it simply does not square with the actual history of science. A number of significant advances have come from reasoning about the world. Einstein’s analyses, across all fields (including some related to atomistic views of the world) were famously the product of initial thought experiments &lt;em&gt;followed&lt;/em&gt; rather than &lt;em&gt;preceded&lt;/em&gt; by mathematical derivation and finally observational data. To be sure, there are many times when scientific understandings change because of data. But this is not the only way scientific interpretations shift. Rather, changes in epistemology, metaphysics, and other prior commitments may lead to substantial reinterpretations of the same data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moreover, those reevaluations may themselves produce further scientific work. One thinks of the way quantum mechanics developed over the twentieth century—including the substantial resistance to it from those enamored of more classical and determinist models, Einstein among them; and the multiple interpretive schemes for dealing philosophically with the implications of quantum mechanics’ findings. These are themselves conditioned by the evidence—but do &lt;em&gt;and must&lt;/em&gt; supersede it in explanatory power and scope. The various interpretations of quantum mechanics are interpretations not only of the data but the world in which the data lives. A radical indeterminism view, an observer-affected data view, a hidden variable view, and so on all offer up points of view which inform the work done by the scientists themselves in an inherent feedback loop. Philosophy and science are not the same, but they are inextricable from each other; one’s prior commitments inevitably shape the answers one will find to some degree or another.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As such, this view fails to deal with the way that those philosophical commitments drove scientific exploration. The belief in a corpuscularian was part and parcel of the discovery of atomism. That there were philosophical reasons for accepting the view prior to observational evidence for it actually serves to reinforce rather than undercut the view. Indeed, the phrasing of the proposition itself is suspect. “Mere” philosophizing, as noted above, necessarily underlies all scientific research programs. At the most basic level: a commitment to the existence of an external world to be interacted with and discovered, the reliability of experience as a kind of evidence, and the generalizability of data via induction and inference to the best explanation are all necessary for the practice of science.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moreover, if one entirely rejected in an &lt;em&gt;a priori&lt;/em&gt; sense that it was possible to discover anything not directly observable (say, because one rejected any sort of corpuscularianism, or because one was a strict anti-realist, or for any number of other reasons), one would simply not look for evidence in that direction. Whatever experiments revealed, an individual with those commitments would not go looking for atoms or evidence of them. The evidence might, over time, suggest a revision of the worldview, and this sort of empirical refutation of the paradigm is of course the point of the proposition. Unfortunately for the proposition, this is not a distinction between philosophy and science, but between unrelenting dogmatism and critical realism. Science may be deeply dogmatic, and philosophy may readily revise its conclusions in the face of new evidence. Such evidence may differ in kind: it might be a a logical proof rather than physical data, as Gödel’s incompleteness theorem forced a revision in logical positivism. It does not, however, lead to an in-principle difference in method.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id="refs" class="references"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 12 May 2016 20:58:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2016-05-12:2016/corpuscularianism-and-atomism.html</guid><category>M. Div.</category><category>SEBTS</category><category>philosophy</category><category>science</category></item><item><title>Realism and Anti-Realism in Science</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2016/realism-and-anti-realism-in-science.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Adjudicating the realism/anti-realism debate in science often involves discussion of ‘miracles,’ the ‘observable/unobservable distinction,’ and ‘underdetermination’. Pick one of these three areas and develop an argument for realism or anti-realism in terms of it. Don’t forget to assess the argument.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The realism/anti-realism debate in science often hinges on the nature of and relationship between observables and unobservables. Anti-realists argue that scientists can have no actual knowledge of unobservables, and therefore should treat theories about unobservables agnostically: however useful the models may be, they should not be considered to correspond to &lt;em&gt;truth&lt;/em&gt; about reality. For example, anti-realists argue that hypotheses about the nature of fundamental particles such as quarks and electrons should not be taken as if quarks and electrons actually exist, but only as pragmatically useful, with no way even in principle of determining whether such things actually exist.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In fact, any attempt to consider the relationship between observables and unobservables ultimately points instead toward a (critical) realist account of science. Any attempt to distinguish sharply or clearly in principle between observables and unobservables fails, for two reasons: first, the claim that “unobservables” as such exist in a strict sense; and second, that, the relationship between “observable” and “unobservable” falls along a spectrum.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the first case, anti-realists use “unobservable” to mean anything not &lt;em&gt;directly&lt;/em&gt; observable by human senses. However, to declare such objects in principle unobservable is to beg the question, since the point under debate is precisely whether things detected indirectly—electron traces in a gas cloud, for example—are being observed or simply hypothesized. Anti-realists must first establish in an in-principle sense a sharp distinction between that which is indirectly observed and that which is directly observed. Realists, by contrast, note that indirect observation is rightly considered reliable in the realm of ordinary experience. It is reasonable to conclude that the wind is blowing from seeing its effects on trees even if sitting inside a closed room with no direct experience of the wind. Indirect observations still count as observations, and are clear signals of the real presence of a thing being observed. Whether it is observed directly or indirectly does not determine whether it is observed at all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This also extends into the second case: a realist view rightly makes sense of the way things are more or less directly observable. On one end are those phenomena which can be detected through (normal, healthy) human senses such as hearing or vision. Moving down toward the not-directly-observable spectrum, scientists use various sorts of equipment to enhance their ability to observe: telescopes, when looking at things inaccessible to ordinary human sight because of distance; and microscopes, when examining things inaccessible to ordinary human sight because of size. In both cases, however, there is no clear line distinguishing the “observable” and the “unobservable”—only a spectrum of more- or less-directly-observable phenomena. Insects may be observed with the unaided human eye, bacteria with optical microscopes, individual molecules of materials with electron microscopes. In each case, the same principle is at work in the observation: light bouncing off an object and being received.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The anti-realist may object that this is not so: the fact that the distinction between observables and unobservables is blurry does not mean it does not exist. To borrow an example from Okasha: the line between “bald” and “hirsute” may be fuzzy (pun intended), but it is still possible to identify a bald man. Even granting the in-principle distinction between “observable” and “unobservable,” however, the objection fails to establish the strong claim made by anti-realists. It does not establish that the items in question are in fact unobservable (especially when confronted with the realist argument for indirect observation). Nor does it establish that scientists would be in principle incapable of correctly modeling unobservables. At most, it establishes that unobservables may exist.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thus, it is reasonable to suppose that though current models of astronomical behavior, or of quantum mechanics, or gravity, or any other only-indirectly-observable phenomena may be incomplete or partial, they nonetheless represent something &lt;em&gt;actual&lt;/em&gt;. The wind really is blowing. There really an electron leaving a trail in the gas chamber.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id="refs" class="references"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 15 Mar 2016 12:30:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2016-03-15:2016/realism-and-anti-realism-in-science.html</guid><category>M. Div.</category><category>SEBTS</category><category>philosophy</category><category>science</category></item><item><title>The 'Covering Law' Model</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2016/the-covering-law-model.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;What is the ‘covering law’ model of scientific explanation and what are two reasons it seems to be defective? How do these defects point to a better model of scientific explanation?&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The ‘covering law’ model of scientific explanation is the view that scientific explanations consist of three elements: &lt;em&gt;deductive&lt;/em&gt; arguments, with &lt;em&gt;sound&lt;/em&gt; premises, which make referent to (at least) one natural law. That is, for an explanation to count as “scientific,” it must first of all be in the from of an argument, “If A is true then B is the case; A is true, therefore B is the case.” Second, the premises of the argument must be valid. In other words, “If A and B are both true, then C is the case; A and B are true, therefore C is the case” is deductively valid, but if either of the premises A or B are false, the argument is not sound and it does not serve as a scientific explanation. Finally, the explanation must refer to one or more general laws in the course of its argument. That is, in the same formulation, “If A and B are both true, then C is the case; A and B are true, therefore C is the case,” the explanation may be both deductive and sound but &lt;em&gt;unscientific&lt;/em&gt; if neither A nor B are natural laws of some sort.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One classic example of this sort of explanation is answering why a given plant died. Given that scientists know a great many things about the necessary conditions for plants to remain alive, it is possible to construct an explanation that fits the covering law model. Such an argument might proceed as follows:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol type="1"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;All living must metabolize sources of energy to stay alive [general law GL-A].&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Plants are living things [observation O-A].&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Plants metabolize energy via photosynthesis [general law GL-B].&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This plant was kept in the dark [an observation O-B].&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Therefore, this plant could not metabolize energy via photosynthesis [conclusion C-A following from GL-B and O-B].&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Therefore, this plant died [conclusion following from C-A, O-A, and GL-A].&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It would equally be possible in the absence of observations (O-A and O-B) to formulate a &lt;em&gt;prediction&lt;/em&gt;: in place of O-B and the conclusions which follow it, we could supply this form:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start="4" type="1"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If a plant is kept in the dark, it will not be able to metabolize energy via photosynthesis [P].&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Therefore, a plant which is kept in the dark will die. [C-C]&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note that the two forms are symmetric, because of the rules of deductive logic. Any explanation formulated under the covering law model could also be couched as a prediction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although the covering law model is initially attractive, there are two serious problems with it. The first is this very point of symmetry. Explanations, it turns out, are rarely symmetric with predictions. To borrow an example from Okasha, given the rules of trigonometry, if one knows any two of the angle of the sun in the sky, the height of a flagpole, or the length of the shadow cast by the flagpole, one can &lt;em&gt;predict&lt;/em&gt; the third element. For example, having only the length of the shadow and the height of the flagpole, one can calculate the angle of the sun in the sky. Clearly, however, the length of the shadow and the height of the flagpole have no causal relation to the position of the sun in the sky. They do not &lt;em&gt;explain&lt;/em&gt; it, though they may be used to predict it. By contrast, the intent of the person fashioning the flagpole, and a combination of facts about the sun’s emanation of light as part of the process of fusion and the earth’s orbit around the sun do suffice to explain the length of the shadow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is not merely a hypothetical concern; it is precisely the distinction between ancient Babylonian and ancient Greek methods of astronomy, as J.P. Moreland comments. The Babylonian astronomers were able to &lt;em&gt;predict&lt;/em&gt; the positions of stars in the sky, relying on careful observation and detailed tables. They did not offer any &lt;em&gt;explanation&lt;/em&gt; of those positions, however; the Greeks did. Though the Ptolemaic model the Greeks embraced is now rejected, it was an explanatory, and therefore &lt;em&gt;scientific&lt;/em&gt;, model. Predictions are not the same as explanations, precisely because explanations indicate the underlying causes that things are as they are.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Second, it is possible to offer explanations which satisfy the covering law model, but in which the premises are &lt;em&gt;irrelevant to the conclusion&lt;/em&gt;. In Okasha’s example, a doctor explains why a man does not become pregnant in terms of the observation that people who regularly take oral contraceptives do not become pregnant, and the man is taking oral contraceptives. Leaving aside the question of why a man would be taking oral contraceptives, the actual explanation is quite different: the man does not become pregnant because men are biologically incapable of pregnancy. Though the argument is deductively valid, and its premises are at least potentially sound, the law actually fails as an explanation. In this case, its predictive power is actually deceptive, because the prediction is totally uncoupled from the cause.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Both of these failings share in common the same core issue: ignoring the role of causality. Scientific explanations—to be differentiated from scientific &lt;em&gt;observations&lt;/em&gt; such as “water is two molecules of hydrogen and one of oxygen”—traffic in &lt;em&gt;causes&lt;/em&gt; and not merely &lt;em&gt;predictions&lt;/em&gt;. Any model of how scientific explanation actually works must therefore include the arrow of causality.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id="refs" class="references"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 15 Mar 2016 12:30:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2016-03-15:2016/the-covering-law-model.html</guid><category>M. Div.</category><category>SEBTS</category><category>philosophy</category><category>science</category></item><item><title>The Problem of Induction</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2016/the-problem-of-induction.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;What is the problem of induction? Discuss two proposed solutions to this problem, and explain why (in your view) they are adequate solutions or defective ones.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The problem of induction is the question: &lt;em&gt;Is induction a trustworthy means of obtaining knowledge?&lt;/em&gt; The majority of scientific reasoning necessarily leans heavily on induction—it is, after all, impossible to observe every star in the universe, or every duck on Earth, or the psychological patterns of all humans, for example. Thus, any scientific reasoning which purports to rise to the level of a universal explanation or law must rely on induction to arrive at its conclusion: “We have observed things to obey rules X, Y, and Z in all known instances. Given the regularity of the universe, it follows that things obey rules X, Y, and Z everywhere.” The question is whether the leap between the premises and the conclusion is warranted: is it reasonable to suppose that things scientists have &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; observed (whether because they are out of observational range, or because they are in the future) behave the same way as those they &lt;em&gt;have&lt;/em&gt; observed?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mark Lange helpfully summarizes the problem in the form of a simple argument: since all arguments are either deductive or inductive, the middle link in the argument for the reliability of induction must be either deductive or inductive. But it cannot be an inductive argument; that would simply be a circular argument: “If inductive reasoning holds, it is valid to use inductive reasoning, and inductive reasoning has always worked in the past, so we induce that it will continue to work in the future, ergo it is valid to use inductive reasoning.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, the argument may also not be &lt;em&gt;deductive&lt;/em&gt;. There is an infinite number of &lt;em&gt;logically&lt;/em&gt; possible explanations for the apparent success of induction to date. For example, it is logically possible that all objects believed to be green—and which inductive reasoning would therefore suggest will be green tomorrow as well—are in fact the mysterious and previous unobserved color “grue”: a color which appears green until an unspecified date, after which it is blue. This is just as logically consistent with all observations as the idea that induction holds. Thus, no deductive argument can demonstrate the validity of induction, for there is no &lt;em&gt;deductive&lt;/em&gt; manner of choosing between such possibilities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One proposed solutions is a pragmatic argument. &lt;em&gt;If the universe behaves uniformly, then induction will work; if the universe does &lt;strong&gt;not&lt;/strong&gt; behave uniformly, then no method will work. Therefore, scientists are justified in acting as though induction works.&lt;/em&gt; Unfortunately, this argument at best establishes a matter of reasonable policy for scientists, without providing warrant for belief. That is, however reasonable and even necessary it may be for scientists to proceed as though induction holds and is valid, the argument provides no evidence that induction &lt;em&gt;does&lt;/em&gt; in fact hold.&lt;a href="#fn1" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref1"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another solution is the argument from Christian theism: &lt;em&gt;given God’s creation covenant to maintain order (Genesis 9), the goodness and providence of God (derived from statements to that effect throughout Scripture), and the claim to efficacy of the Proverbs, it is theologically necessary that the universe continue to work as it has in the past.&lt;/em&gt; In its favor, this suggestion has the form of an argument, and is not directly reliant on the evidence of past uniformity as a basis for future uniformity. However, this sort of reasoning from Scripture is itself inductive. It takes a specific interpretation of the texts under consideration, and a belief that things are at a certain point in cosmological/theological history (i.e. the eschaton has not yet arrived) and extrapolates to the notion that God will continue upholding the previous pattern of laws of nature. Moreover, even if the argument were to hold, it would not be a &lt;em&gt;scientific&lt;/em&gt; but a &lt;em&gt;philosophical-theological&lt;/em&gt; argument. (This is, perhaps, unsurprising given that though the problem of induction is especially applicable to the practice of science, it is a far more general problem.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id="refs" class="references"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;section class="footnotes"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn1"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Interestingly, however, if the validity of induction is taken as an &lt;em&gt;a priori&lt;/em&gt; assumption, its historical efficacy may be taken as good evidence for the consistency of nature as a reasonable inference to the best explanation in the realism/anti-realism debate.&lt;a href="#fnref1"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 15 Mar 2016 12:30:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2016-03-15:2016/the-problem-of-induction.html</guid><category>M. Div.</category><category>SEBTS</category><category>philosophy</category><category>science</category></item></channel></rss>