<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Chris Krycho - photography</title><link>http://v4.chriskrycho.com/</link><description></description><lastBuildDate>Sun, 03 Nov 2019 17:25:00 -0500</lastBuildDate><item><title>Photography-ing Again!</title><link>http://v4.chriskrycho.com/2019/photography-ing-again.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;a href="https://v4.chriskrycho.com/2018/assumed-audiences.html"&gt;Assumed Audience&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/b&gt; people who find photography and/or personal biography interesting.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the past few months, I have been picking back up my long-dormant interest in photography. I started trying to learn how to take good photographs back during college—first with an inexpensive point-and-shoot with a decent built-in zoom lens, then with an inexpensive Canon &lt;abbr title="digital single lens reflex"&gt;DSLR&lt;/abbr&gt; that was my college graduation present. I spent a decent amount of time on the hobby over those years, including doing some family and engagement photos for friends. (They were serviceable, not good; but I was learning a ton and it was a lot of fun… and my friends didn’t have to pay for them.) I was just starting to develop a more serious interest in the technical aspects of the art… when we moved to North Carolina and I started seminary.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the next five years, I took essentially zero photos with a camera not attached to my smartphone. It was not that I was no longer interested; it was that I simply could not keep up that hobby &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; everything else I was doing. I was doing a &lt;em&gt;lot&lt;/em&gt;—&lt;a href="https://v4.chriskrycho.com/burnout"&gt;probably too much.&lt;/a&gt; This summer, though, I found myself wanting to pick it back up in earnest. I was making good use of my phone camera, and I dug out my old &lt;abbr&gt;DSLR&lt;/abbr&gt; and bought new batteries for it and started taking it with me on a regular basis. I knew the old camera had some serious limitations, but I wanted to see if I enjoyed and was able to make good practice out of shooting with it anyway. No point in buying a new camera if I wasn’t actually enjoying using the old one, if the hobby didn’t stick.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It stuck. This time, all the interest in technical aspects came back with a vengeance, so I have spent a not-inconsiderable amount of time wrapping my head around the physics of lenses. The limitations of the lenses I had for the old camera were very apparent every time I tried to take any kind of low-light shot, and its auto-focus performance was, well not bad for an inexpensive &lt;abbr&gt;DSLR&lt;/abbr&gt; from a decade ago—if you take my meaning. Having gotten a much better handle on the physics involved, though, I initially thought that I might be able to get away with just keeping the old camera and investing in good lenses for it. Unfortunately, as I started poking around, I concluded that I basically &lt;em&gt;couldn’t&lt;/em&gt; get some of the lenses I would want for it in the long term: wide primes with low 𝑓 numbers. Canon makes lenses in this bucket, but once you account for the &lt;a href="https://www.bhphotovideo.com/explora/photography/tips-and-solutions/understanding-crop-factor"&gt;crop factor&lt;/a&gt; of an &lt;abbr title="Advanced Photo System type-C"&gt;APS-C&lt;/abbr&gt; camera like my old &lt;abbr&gt;DSLR&lt;/abbr&gt;, your options for actually wide lenses are pretty limited.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A lot of my time over the last few months has gone to reading—a &lt;em&gt;lot&lt;/em&gt;—about my options in the space. I discovered the &lt;a href="https://www.digitaltrends.com/photography/what-is-a-mirrorless-camera/"&gt;mirrorless&lt;/a&gt; revolution (most of a decade late), along with the dizzying array of lens options for full-frame cameras. Curious about how this worked in practice, I &lt;a href="https://share.lensrentals.com/x/tIxLHl" title="LensRentals"&gt;rented&lt;/a&gt; one of Sony’s &lt;a href="https://www.bhphotovideo.com/explora/photography/tips-and-solutions/understanding-crop-factor"&gt;full-frame&lt;/a&gt; cameras for our family’s recent trip to North Carolina, and fell in love. (That’s an affiliate link for LensRentals: we both get $25 off a rental if you use it.) My own copy of the camera I had rented came this week, and I may have driven poor Jaimie slightly up the wall with all the pictures I’ve been taking since.&lt;a href="#fn1" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref1" role="doc-noteref"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once upon a time, I &lt;a href="https://2012-2013.chriskrycho.com/art/category/photo/"&gt;tried&lt;/a&gt; to include some photos in my blogging. I never got very far with it—in part because of the same lens limitations I ran into once I picked the hobby back up, but also because my old blog flow never really supported it well. (Sorry, 2012-era WordPress, but it’s true.) As I’m getting back into it, I want to find a way to make that flow work. This is yet another requirement for my much-delayed website redesign. I don’t think I’m going to have a solution I’m happy with in place by the time I ship (more on that soon, I hope!), but it’s something I &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt; want to get in place before too long.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This also has me wishing there were better options for social sharing around photos. Indie blogging of the sort I so value is wonderful, but at the moment it doesn’t lend itself well to &lt;em&gt;interaction&lt;/em&gt; around items like photography. I have a &lt;em&gt;lot&lt;/em&gt; of thoughts on things like &lt;a href="https://indieweb.org/Webmention"&gt;Webmention&lt;/a&gt;, including how I plan to use it on my upcoming site redesign… but those are for another day. For today: thanks for reading!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src="https://cdn.chriskrycho.com/file/chriskrycho-com/images/Black%20%26%20White%20thumb.jpg" title="thumbnail of a photograph of a coffee shop" alt="" /&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Black &amp;amp; White Coffee, Wake Forest, NC – Sony FE 35mm F1.8 – 𝑓/2.2, ISO 400, ¹⁄₁₂₅s (&lt;a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/chriskrycho/49009951457/"&gt;see full size&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;section class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn1" role="doc-endnote"&gt;&lt;p&gt;If you’re curious: a &lt;a href="https://www.bhphotovideo.com/c/product/1494679-REG/sony_ilce7rm4_b_alpha_a7r_iv_mirrorless.html"&gt;Sony α7R IV&lt;/a&gt;. It’s kind of ridiculously pricey… but I expect to get at &lt;em&gt;least&lt;/em&gt; the next decade of shooting out of it, and the resolution is just bonkers, and the &lt;em&gt;feel&lt;/em&gt; of the thing is absolutely delightful to me. If I were making a recommendation for an entry into the Sony mirrorless space, I’d point you instead to the &lt;a href="https://www.bhphotovideo.com/c/product/1394217-REG/sony_ilce_7m3_alpha_a7_iii_mirrorless.html"&gt;Sony α7 III&lt;/a&gt;, which is itself a phenomenal camera, and I almost got it instead.&lt;a href="#fnref1" class="footnote-back" role="doc-backlink"&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 03 Nov 2019 17:25:00 -0500</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:v4.chriskrycho.com,2019-11-03:/2019/photography-ing-again.html</guid><category>photography</category></item></channel></rss>