<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Chris Krycho - podcasting</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/</link><description></description><lastBuildDate>Sun, 23 Dec 2018 14:35:00 -0500</lastBuildDate><item><title>"2018: Some Closing Thoughts"</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2018/some-closing-thoughts.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.chriskrycho.com/2018/assumed-audiences.html"&gt;Assumed Audience:&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/b&gt; mostly my future self!—but you’re welcome to read along and see my thoughts on how 2018 went for me and what I hope 2019 will look like.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As has long been my tradition&lt;a href="#fn1" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref1"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; I’m wrapping up the year by looking back at what happened in it and thinking about what I’d like to do in the year ahead. I say little here about family or church, but that should not be taken as an indicator of importance: in fact, my commitments in those two spheres deeply inform everything else!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section id="section" class="level2"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;2018&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;2018 was not the year I hoped or expected it might be. It was difficult in a great many ways, and the more so as the year went on. It was not the single hardest year I’ve had—that title goes without question to 2016—but it’s up there. There’s still a lot of good in the mix, but it was hard.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section id="podcasting" class="level3"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Podcasting&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had intended to publish about twice as many episode of New Rustacean this year as I was ultimately able to release. My goal was actually to be releasing 3–4 episodes each month, and to cover most of the rest of the language! As it turned out, I was able to release only 1–2 episodes per month. I’m nonetheless very happy with the episodes I &lt;em&gt;did&lt;/em&gt; release this year. And my episode on burnout may end up being one of the most important things to come out of the show, from the email responses I’ve received about it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We launched a new design of the &lt;a href="https://winningslowly.org"&gt;Winning Slowly website&lt;/a&gt; and we were able to record and publish about three quarters of the episodes we had planned for Season 6 before the burnout tanked me. There’s a wrap-up episode we recorded and which should be out in a few days (after I edit it!). We also released our 100th episode, which was fun! It was frustrating not to be able to finish everything we had planned, but I remain proud of the work we’ve done there over the last five years, and this season had a couple really important episodes in it. If you didn’t listen to anything else, I’d commend &lt;a href="https://winningslowly.org/6.04/"&gt;6.04: Move Slowly and Fix Things&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://winningslowly.org/6.06/"&gt;6.06: A Kind of Blindness&lt;/a&gt;. The latter, on “big data” and the difference between information and wisdom, is one of my single favorite episodes of the show.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="reading-and-writing" class="level3"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Reading and writing&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also set out this year to read a lot of books—I had a list of a 14 pieces of nonfiction on the list—and in the end I finished &lt;em&gt;none&lt;/em&gt; of them. I participated in a reading group which covered much of &lt;cite&gt;Domain Modeling Made Functional&lt;/cite&gt;, and I made it through the first fifth or so of St. Augustine’s &lt;cite&gt;City of God&lt;/cite&gt;, but I didn’t even manage to finish a few books I had started &lt;em&gt;last&lt;/em&gt; year! The only things I managed to finish were novels:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I finished rereading &lt;cite&gt;The Wheel of Time&lt;/cite&gt; and enjoyed some new-to-me “popcorn” in the form of &lt;a href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2018/agent-of-change.html"&gt;&lt;cite&gt;Agent of Change&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I devoured Mary Robinette Kowal’s &lt;a href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2018/the-calculating-stars.html"&gt;&lt;cite&gt;The Calculating Stars&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2018/review-the-fated-sky.html"&gt;&lt;cite&gt;The Fated Sky&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I read a couple Hugo and Nebula award winners: Larry Niven’s &lt;a href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2018/ringworld-review.html"&gt;&lt;cite&gt;Ringworld&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and N.K. Jemisin’s &lt;cite&gt;The Fifth Season&lt;/cite&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While those novels were basically the only thing I read, I very much like the habit of writing very short reviews I started with those novels. I expect to keep that habit, and it should be useful as I dig back into nonfiction in the future!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Speaking of writing: for all that this year felt like it was unproductive in some ways, I still ended up blogging to the tune of somewhere north of 70,000 words across about 95 posts.&lt;a href="#fn2" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref2"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; That’s a solid showing for a year full of burnout (even if burnout itself &lt;a href="https://www.chriskrycho.com/burnout"&gt;ended up being the subject of no few of those&lt;/a&gt;: about 6,000 words). But one of my goals for the year was to publish a few longer-form essays, possibly even getting paid for them. That certainly did not happen; I did not manage to publish even a single essay at Mere Orthodoxy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="health" class="level3"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Health&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I ran a fair bit, and am slowly adjusting to living at roughly 7,000 feet above sea level instead of about 400 feet above sea level. But for the third year in a row, I did &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; manage to run a race. I can still feel, and the more so at this altitude, the lingering effects of the mild case of walking pneumonia I came down with in the summer of 2016. The one thing I did manage in terms of exercise and health was a &lt;em&gt;lot&lt;/em&gt; of cycling. Despite my dad’s being in the midst of ongoing monthly chemo treatments for a brain tumor, he and I rode 80 miles in two days together for the &lt;a href="http://www.childrenscoloradofoundation.org/courage-classic"&gt;Courage Classic&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="work" class="level3"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Work&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Work has been a mixed bag. On the one hand, I accomplished a lot this year. Despite a number of large roadblocks that were entirely outside my control (and several of which I argued strenuously against), I lead a very important effort to hit several meaningful milestones. I also kept pushing the state of our tooling forward, including some important open-source work, and at the end of November gave a “tech talk” on technical costs which seems to have made a real (if, so far, still small!) impact on the entire organization.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, work directly triggered the burnout I experienced. To be sure, I had plenty of existing stressors from moving across and walking through my dad’s fight with cancer with the rest of my family. But the things that pushed me over the edge from &lt;i&gt;tired and worn down&lt;/i&gt; to &lt;i&gt;burnout&lt;/i&gt; were challenges at work. There were the aforementioned roadblocks. There were some high-stress projects. But most of all, there is a lack of alignment between my engineering and business philosophies and those in play at Olo. Those aren’t &lt;em&gt;moral&lt;/em&gt;, but prudential and strategic, kinds of differences—but that does not make them unimportant! More on this below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="in-sum" class="level3"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;In sum&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In spite of the burnout, and notwithstanding all the things I did not get done, I’m grateful for this year. My dad has so far not only survived his battle with a brain tumor but is thriving overall. I managed to come through my experience of burnout mostly okay. Our new church has been a great blessing to us, and we’ve been able to step into serving in many ways already.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="section-1" class="level2"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;2019&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So looking forward into 2019, my hopes (I dare not call them plans anymore):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section id="podcasting-1" class="level3"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Podcasting&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I want to publish the dozen more episodes of &lt;a href="https://newrustacean.com"&gt;New Rustacean&lt;/a&gt; that I had planned for 2018! At my current rate of about two a month, that’ll take me the first six months or so of the year. Once I’m through that list, I’ll have covered the entirety of the language and quite a few of the most important crates in the ecosystem. But there are always new things happening, so I’ll have some interesting decisions to make about where to take the show.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m also going to keep producing &lt;a href="https://winningslowly.org"&gt;Winning Slowly&lt;/a&gt; with Stephen Carradini. We have not yet nailed down what Season 7 will focus on or look like yet, but we’re far from done. The issue is not finding something to talk about, but narrowing it down to which specific things we want to zoom in on! We also have an interview lined up in January (which will come out as an inter-season standalone episode) which we’re &lt;em&gt;very&lt;/em&gt; excited about. It’ll be quite different from the other interviews we’ve done, and represents an important step forward for the show.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="reading-and-writing-1" class="level3"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Reading and Writing&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My reading and writing goals for the year ahead are intentionally modest. I’ve consistently failed to achieve my more ambitious goals over the past few years, and I’m rather chastened by that. I also have to remind myself fairly often that I will, Lord willing, have many decades of life when I &lt;em&gt;don’t&lt;/em&gt; have my kids around. That means both that there is plenty of time to spend on reading and writing later and that there is &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; very much time to spend with my daughters later. Insofar as I want to continue reading and writing in important ways, then—and I do!—I need to make my reading and writing time count by approaching them in more focused and targeted ways.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have people ask me quite regularly for recommendations on various topics, and I simply can’t give them! That needs to change, so I want to read at least four popular level books on theology or culture—about one a quarter. My plan is to review them in this space, but also (more importantly!) to be able to point people in my church toward or away from them. In the long-term, I would love to take up a role (official or not) as a custodian of our church’s library.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also want to keep my mind sharp and growing on theology, culture, politics, art, etc. I’ve very much felt the lack of engagement on that over the last few years (and have said so here more than once). In that connection, I aim to work through two academic works on theology, and two on some other aspect of culture. I have yet to decide what those will be. Most likely I’ll start by finishing the volumes I already started, but I also expect to spend a bit of time on Patristic Christology, as I’m teaching a class on the person and nature of Jesus in August for our church.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Writing-wise, I know that I’ll continue blogging here. However, I actually hope to blog &lt;em&gt;less&lt;/em&gt; overall. The time I spent writing 70,000 words this year was time well-spent, but as I note &lt;a href="https://www.chriskrycho.com/2018/intentional-cyclicality.html" title="Intentional Cyclicality (March)"&gt;time&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://www.chriskrycho.com/2018/writing-plans-for-the-rest-of-2018.html" title="Writing Plans for the Rest of 2018 (May)"&gt;again&lt;/a&gt;, I have a hard time &lt;a href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2018/cant-stop-wont-stop.html" title="Can’t Stop, Won’t Stop (September)"&gt;&lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; blogging&lt;/a&gt;. I plan to work on that in a couple ways.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, I’m going to try to evaluate, with each idea I have, whether it should be a blog post or just go in my &lt;a href="https://www.chriskrycho.com/zettelkasten/"&gt;Zettelkasten&lt;/a&gt;. So much of my writing over the last decade has been a kind of &lt;a href="https://www.chriskrycho.com/2018/blog-as-note-taking-tool.html"&gt;public thinking-out-loud&lt;/a&gt;. That’s good, but I also feel much more need to polish something if I’m going to publish it than if it’s a private note. The way I polish a blog post is nothing like the way I polish essays, of course, but I do spend some time clarifying and adding nuance. Even when &lt;a href="https://www.chriskrycho.com/2018/assumed-audiences.html"&gt;specifying an assumed audience&lt;/a&gt;, I need to be more careful if I am writing for others than if I am working something out by writing about it for myself. As a result, I expect a lot of things which might have ended up on the blog in the past to just go in &lt;a href="https://bear.app"&gt;Bear&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Second, I plan (and we’ll see how this goes), I’m going to try &lt;em&gt;very&lt;/em&gt; hard to write fewer blog posts in favor of more well-developed essays. About a month ago, I started drafting an essay which seems like it might be legitimately important. Unfortunately, even though it is certainly more worth my time than the things I &lt;em&gt;have&lt;/em&gt; written since then (&lt;a href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2018/internal-and-external-parameter-names-in-javascript-and-typescript.html"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2018/starting-to-build-a-zettelkasten.html"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2018/zettelkasten-update-all-in-on-bear.html"&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2018/stewarding-my-reserves.html"&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2018/hey-siri-record-a-zettel.html"&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2018/javascript-is-c.html"&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;), I have not made progress since the day I started it. It’s not that my notes on research and note-taking are worthless. Rather, it’s that there is a cost to spending my limited time on writing those instead of more important writing efforts.&lt;a href="#fn3" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref3"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; At a minimum, I intend to do even &lt;em&gt;less&lt;/em&gt; polish on those posts than I have to date, when I let myself write them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="health-1" class="level3"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Health&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have a handful of goals for this year in terms of physical health:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I want to lose about 10 pounds. I’m at a healthy weight currently, but I felt and performed at my best a few years ago when I was down in my target weight range. This is going to require tweaking the &lt;em&gt;content&lt;/em&gt;, rather than the &lt;em&gt;quantity&lt;/em&gt;, of what I eat, and introduce more variation into the kinds of exercise I’m doing. I can tell both that my metabolism has shifted as I’ve hit my 30’s, and that I’ve acclimated to the workout load that I’ve more-or-less consistently held over the last eight years. It’s annoying, honestly!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I plan to participate in the &lt;a href="http://www.childrenscoloradofoundation.org/courage-classic"&gt;Courage Classic&lt;/a&gt; again with my dad, and I’d like to do the 80-mile route at least one of the days. Maybe both days, if he and I are both trained for it! Unfortunately, this probably means investing in a new bike. The one I have currently is almost twenty years old, and it’s a good bike… but it’s increasingly going to need parts replaced. So: CraigsList here I come.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I’d like to complete another half marathon, probably in May. I don’t particularly care what my pace ends up being: I just want to get back in the rhythm and routine of training and completing the event. I went through a similar push after we moved to North Carolina, and 30 months later I ran the best race of my life. Now, I know that &lt;a href="https://runkeeper.com/user/chriskrycho/activity/684713960"&gt;the sub-1:25 time I ran back in 2015&lt;/a&gt; is not something I’m apt to see again, especially at altitude, but I’d like to get back to that kind of consistency and discipline (and I’ll see where it gets me!).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Given that I’m currently planning two events in late spring and summer, I also need to find something to do in the fall and winter next year, just to keep up my fitness level &lt;em&gt;for&lt;/em&gt; something. Previous years, I had the same issue for the spring, and the year I was in my very best shape, I played Ultimate in the spring and fall &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; did a super sprint triathlon in the summer. So: something like that again, perhaps.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="work-1" class="level3"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Work&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I close in on the end of the first decade of my career, I’m &lt;a href="https://www.chriskrycho.com/2018/career-trajectory.html"&gt;thinking a lot&lt;/a&gt; about what I want the next decade of my career to look like. I don’t expect to be able to figure it all out ahead of time, of course. At the same time, I’m resolved to find opportunities that align more with my values and the general aims for my career I’ve started developing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One part of that is that I intend to push forward on a few things I’ve been plotting for a few years now. I started learning Rust back in the summer of 2015 for a &lt;em&gt;reason&lt;/em&gt;, and I’m coming back to that reason this year. I don’t in the least regret the detour that I’ve gone on in the meantime: New Rustacean remains one of my favorite things I’ve done, and is certainly a more important contribution than any code I could have written in that time. But the project that got this all started has my attention again, and I will be spending some of my personal time on it this year.&lt;a href="#fn4" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref4"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;4&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; It’s the kind of thing that I rather hope &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; my career a few years down the line—but there’s a boatload of work to do to get there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another part is looking at a much longer horizon even. Over the past three years, I’ve become increasingly interested in programming language theory and practice. I have some ideas and insights I think are genuinely valuable and &lt;em&gt;relatively&lt;/em&gt; unique (at a minimum they’re not currently in use in industry anywhere, and I’ve yet to find any papers touching on them) and I would like to see them land at some point. Getting there is a long game; I am not exaggerating when I say that if I ever really make this happen, I expect it to be in my 40s. Probably my &lt;em&gt;late&lt;/em&gt; 40s. But that gives me time to learn in the meantime: to build small languages and see what that process is like, to find ways to collaborate on existing language projects, to learn a wide array of existing languages in more detail, and so on. If the ideas I have are ever to come to fruition, all of those things are necessary precursors for my efforts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here in late 2018, I have &lt;em&gt;just&lt;/em&gt; started on much of that: I am reading a book on programming language development and taking an awful lots of notes along the way. I will be completing the exercises in the book, and I will also be trying to learn enough to build my own little toy languages along the way. I am getting some practice in the pragmatics of it by collaborating with Dave Herman on &lt;a href="https://github.com/tc39/proposal-do-expressions"&gt;the &lt;code&gt;do&lt;/code&gt; expressions JavaScript proposal&lt;/a&gt;, which we hope to make substantial progress on in 2019. These kinds of programming language ideas will &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; be the emphasis in 2019, but they will be a piece, in the interest of laying the foundations I will need later.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="in-sum-1" class="level3"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;In sum&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hope 2019 is a less difficult year than 2018 was. I am also aiming to be more effective in accomplishing the things I care about, in part by setting more modest goals for myself. Keep podcasting. Read a few books of a few specific sorts. Write some essays, at the expense of some blog posts. Start on some new projects, but not in a hurry or a rush. Love my family and love my church.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section class="footnotes"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn1"&gt;&lt;p&gt;I’ve been doing this since 2007, but I’m not linking you to the blog post I wrote that year. There’s nothing quite like reading things I wrote halfway through college to make me cringe. There is some good stuff there, but also: 20-year-old Chris Krycho was, uhh… &lt;em&gt;very&lt;/em&gt; emotional. And the way I approach my faith has shifted a lot since then.&lt;a href="#fnref1" class="footnote-back"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn2"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Running &lt;code&gt;wc -w&lt;/code&gt; on the posts I wrote in 2018 reports 76,768 words, but that number includes all the post metadata. Assuming an average of 65 words of metadata per post, across the 94 posts I wrote, that comes out to around 6,100 words. So: about 70,000, for an average of about 750 words per post. Not too shabby!&lt;a href="#fnref2" class="footnote-back"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn3"&gt;&lt;p&gt;So: what of this kind of year-end review, which is itself not exactly one of those more important writing projects? Good point. I find his exercise helpful, though, and I’d almost certainly be doing it privately in nearly identical terms. I have found this practice helpful over the years, despite never coming near accomplishing the specific goals I’ve set myself, so I expect to keep up this habit.&lt;a href="#fnref3" class="footnote-back"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn4"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is another reason for the emphasis on focusing my writing time on high-value projects. Time I spend writing random blog posts is time I am &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; spending on these programming efforts.&lt;a href="#fnref4" class="footnote-back"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 23 Dec 2018 14:35:00 -0500</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2018-12-23:/2018/some-closing-thoughts.html</guid><category>writing</category><category>reading</category><category>podcasting</category><category>burnout</category><category>fitness</category><category>health</category><category>career</category></item><item><title>Burnout (New Rustacean)</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2018/burnout-new-rustacean.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Insofar as I have a platform and a voice on this blog and &lt;a href="https://www.chriskrycho.com/podcasts.html"&gt;my podcasts&lt;/a&gt;, I hope to use it to help &lt;em&gt;others&lt;/em&gt; who experience burnout as well. So, the only episode I’ve managed to release of New Rustacean so far in September is &lt;a href="https://newrustacean.com/show_notes/bonus/burnout/"&gt;this one, on burnout&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 22 Sep 2018 21:30:00 -0400</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2018-09-22:/2018/burnout-new-rustacean.html</guid><category>burnout</category><category>links</category><category>podcasting</category></item><item><title>Building Things</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2018/building-things.html</link><description>&lt;section id="i." class="level2"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;I.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For almost three years, now, I have been more or less steadily—sometimes more, sometimes less!—putting out episodes of New Rustacean. It’s fairly popular. I’ve had really smart people tell me how helpful it was in getting them up to speed with the language. I have had the surprising and slightly weird (if also somewhat gratifying) experience of walking into a room and seeing people respond in recognition of my voice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m grateful for the impact the podcast has had, and as I tell people often: this is far and away the most significant thing I could have done in the Rust ecosystem in the last three years. There are a lot of people better-equipped than I to write top-notch libraries and applications in the ecosystem. People well-equipped for podcasting by dint of already being active in the space, and well-equipped for teaching specifically by dint of background and training? There are a lot fewer of those. I don’t think there is anywhere at all I could have made a bigger dent in the same time for Rust.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And yet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If I went and applied for a job today, where actual Rust &lt;em&gt;experience&lt;/em&gt; was desired, the vast majority of my show’s listeners would have substantially more to show than me. A command line tool here, a little experiment there. My &lt;a href="https://github.com/chriskrycho/lightning-rs" title="lightning (lx)"&gt;one real project&lt;/a&gt; has been on hold almost since I started it. Another project, my original inspiration for learning Rust at all, I’ve never even started. My actual lines of Rust code written in the last three years top out somewhere under 3,000. It’s a pittance. As well as I know the language’s &lt;em&gt;ideas&lt;/em&gt;, and indeed as well as I can explain them… I actually haven’t gotten to &lt;em&gt;build&lt;/em&gt; much of anything with it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="ii." class="level2"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;II.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The last few months at work, I’ve spent a lot of my time—and an increasingly large proportion of it—on mentoring, code reviews, and leading the team and effort I’m on. This is genuinely wonderful in a lot of ways. I &lt;em&gt;love&lt;/em&gt; teaching, and it’s a pleasure to help shape the overall direction of a project and a codebase.&lt;a href="#fn1" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref1"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; In many ways, I’m right in line with the goals I set explicitly with my manager at the beginning of the year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That’s really good, and really important. I recently saw someone tweet the pithy remark that the &lt;em&gt;definition&lt;/em&gt; of a senior engineer is that they are mentoring a more junior engineer. I don’t think that’s quite right—there is a lot of room for really outstanding technical contributors who don’t have the gift of teaching, but whose technical chops mean they genuinely &lt;em&gt;are&lt;/em&gt; senior people on the team.&lt;a href="#fn2" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref2"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; But the reasonable insight under the hyperbole is that enabling others can often be far more effective than merely doing work yourself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And yet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over the last several months, the amount of code I have written myself has dropped substantially. Not to nothing, of course; I’m still doing the actual work of designing and implementing pieces of the application I work on a majority of the time. But I’m not sure how much more than 50% of my time it is on any given week at this point. As much as I’ve enjoyed helping drive this particular project forward,&lt;a href="#fn3" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref3"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; I haven’t actually gotten to &lt;em&gt;build&lt;/em&gt; as much during this phase of it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="iii." class="level2"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;III.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These two things have a great deal in common, for all their superficial differences. Both are places where my most valuable contributions are not what I can build myself, but what I can enable &lt;em&gt;others&lt;/em&gt; to build.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thousands and thousands of people have listened to New Rustacean. For some non-trivial number of them, the podcast was an important part of their wrapping their heads around the language. I know this because they tell me, in emails and conversations and tweets that are genuinely my favorite parts of doing the show! I have done far, far more with the podcast than I possibly could have by building another library in Rust.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Similarly, albeit on a much smaller scale, my role in my team at Olo matters. I’ve been able to help set the overall technical direction of a number of our front-end initiatives at the company in important ways. I’ve been able to help more junior developers ramp up their skills. I have done far more in this kind of role than I could possibly have done by just quietly shipping features.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And yet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Being a “force multiplier” (what a terrible phrase!) isn’t always what it’s cracked up to be. It can be both &lt;em&gt;worth it&lt;/em&gt; and also &lt;em&gt;profoundly frustrating and boring&lt;/em&gt; at times. I was drawn to software in no small part because of the joy of being able to make things—to start with nothing but an idea or a sketch and a few hours later have something people can interact with, that solves a problem for them. I still love that side of it, and it’s clear to me if nothing else that (for the foreseeable future, anyway) I have no desire whatsoever to go into management roles, “force multiplier” or not.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There’s a real trick here, because it’s not that I’m &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; building things in these roles. It’s just that building a team or a community is not quite the same thing—it does not scratch the same itch—as building a really elegant user interface component with an elegant and communicative animation. They’re both good; and they’re very, very different from each other.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section class="footnotes"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn1"&gt;&lt;p&gt;I separate those on purpose: a project and a codebase are &lt;em&gt;related&lt;/em&gt;, but they’re far from identical. A project can succeed—at least in the short term—with a terrible codebase; an excellent codebase is no guarantee of project success. Getting them aligned is rare, difficult, and rewarding.&lt;a href="#fnref1" class="footnote-back"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn2"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This seems like a typical overcorrection: against the idea that teaching is &lt;em&gt;unimportant&lt;/em&gt;, it now comes into vogue to say that teaching is the &lt;em&gt;most&lt;/em&gt; important. Imagine if we simply noted that teaching is some people’s gift and vocation, and not others; and that we can complement one another’s strengths by sharing our own—that it is not a zero-sum game but one in which &lt;a href="https://www.esv.org/1+Corinthians+12+12/" title="1 Corinthians 12:12 and following"&gt;we are like hands and feet and elbows and ears, each one needing the other, none able to do without the others&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;a href="#fnref2" class="footnote-back"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn3"&gt;&lt;p&gt;much of the time anyway; the &lt;a href="https://www.chriskrycho.com/2018/some-mild-burnout.html" title="Some Mild Burnout"&gt;burnout&lt;/a&gt; I’m experiencing is related to some of the dynamics of this particular project&lt;a href="#fnref3" class="footnote-back"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 06 Aug 2018 21:15:00 -0400</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2018-08-06:/2018/building-things.html</guid><category>software development</category><category>leadership</category><category>podcasting</category><category>New Rustacean</category></item><item><title>2017 in Review: Looking Forward</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2017/2017-in-review-looking-forward.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;As I do every year, I’ve been making some goals for myself for 2018. I’m breaking these down into three big categories this year, having learned from the experience of summarizing my goals for last year:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Standing aims&lt;/strong&gt;: things that I can’t exactly check off as &lt;em&gt;done&lt;/em&gt;, but which are extremely important to me.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Goals&lt;/strong&gt;: things I &lt;em&gt;can&lt;/em&gt; mark as done.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Primary:&lt;/strong&gt; the most important of my goals—the ones I’ll count myself as having failed in some way if I don’t accomplish them over the course of the year (barring &lt;em&gt;major&lt;/em&gt; unforeseen goings-on, which are, well… impossible to foresee).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Flexible&lt;/strong&gt;: other goals, which I’d &lt;em&gt;like&lt;/em&gt; to get to, but which it won’t bother me if I don’t get to them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;section id="standing-aims" class="level2"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Standing aims&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Integrate well into our new church—including finding specific ways and places to serve regularly, joining a small group, and making some good friends.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Spend more, better, and more consistent time with my family.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Work hard at Olo.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="goals" class="level2"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Goals&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;section id="primary" class="level3"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Primary&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Podcasting:
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ship a minimum of 3 episodes of New Rustacean per month January—October.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Publish Winning Slowly Season 6.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Writing:
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Publish at least 4 medium-length (2,000–3,500 words) at Mere Orthodoxy.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Software:
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Get ember-cli-typescript “finished”—i.e. with full support for addons and fast incremental builds.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ship a &lt;a href="https://alistapart.com/article/responsive-web-design"&gt;responsive&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/Apps/Progressive"&gt;progressive&lt;/a&gt; version of a major application I work on.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Read, or finish reading, the following books:
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Resurrection and Moral Order&lt;/em&gt;, Oliver O’Donovan (started in 2017)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Theology and the Mirror of Scripture&lt;/em&gt;, Kevin Vanhoozer and Daniel Treier (started in 2017)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;How Buildings Learn&lt;/em&gt;, Stewart Brand (started in 2017)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;City of God&lt;/em&gt;, Augustine&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Technological Society&lt;/em&gt;, Jacques Ellul&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Meaning of the City&lt;/em&gt;, Jacques Ellul&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Ethics of Freedom&lt;/em&gt;, Jacques Ellul&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Blasphemy: A Radical Critique of our Technological Culture&lt;/em&gt;, Ivan Illich&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fitness:
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Run a half marathon.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Finish the &lt;a href="http://www.childrenscoloradofoundation.org/courage-classic/"&gt;Courage Classic&lt;/a&gt; with my dad.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Get back to my target/healthiest weight.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="flexible" class="level3"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Flexible&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Publish one essay at a larger publication (for money, if possible!).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Archive static versions of the prior versions of my website.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Improve the page load performance of this site (e.g. with progressive font-loading).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Make meaningful progress on &lt;a href="https://github.com/chriskrycho/lightning-rs"&gt;Lightning&lt;/a&gt; November–December.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lead a book club at Olo.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Get up to 20 consecutive pull-ups and 100 consecutive push-ups.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Print hard copies of at least one year of my website archive.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That seems like &lt;em&gt;plenty&lt;/em&gt; to go after this year. One thing that isn’t apparent here is that a fair bit of this is aimed at goals that extend past this year. There are things I want to do in the first half of my thirties if possible, of which some of these are a part. I don’t have those kinds of things written down (and when I write them down, I probably won’t publish them here!) but as I come into the broad swath of life that is just “adulthood”—not &lt;em&gt;young&lt;/em&gt; adulthood or &lt;em&gt;old age&lt;/em&gt;—I am increasingly mindful of the kinds of things I want to do that take more than a single year to accomplish. Some of these move the needle substantially in that direction, so hopefully I’ll get there!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 26 Dec 2017 09:35:00 -0500</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2017-12-26:/2017/2017-in-review-looking-forward.html</guid><category>productivity</category><category>writing</category><category>family</category><category>fitness</category><category>podcasting</category><category>software development</category><category>2017-review</category></item><item><title>2017 in Review: My Goals</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2017/2017-in-review-my-goals.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;As has been my habit for a few years now, I’m taking some time to reflect on the year as it comes to a close. Thinking about how this year went and what I accomplished, and how I would like the next year to go and what I would like to accomplish &lt;em&gt;then&lt;/em&gt;, has become an important part of my life. There is value in taking stock and making plans—as long as you hold those plans loosely. And this particular set of reflections majors on holding plans loosely.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The best place to start seems to be with a review of my goals for 2017, set out &lt;a href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2017/2016-review-6.html" title="2016 in Review, Part 6: Plans for 2017"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. In a post later this week, I’ll write up some thoughts on what I hope to accomplish in 2018—though, as you’ll see, there are some hints of that here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One other note: there are many things going on in our lives that don’t end up in these reflections—because these reflections (as I conceive them at present, at least) are about the kind of public-facing things I did this year. A blog is not a journal, even if there are some analogies between the two.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section id="major-goals" class="level2"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Major goals&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;ol type="1"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Graduate seminary.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Done!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;ol start="2" type="1"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Spend good time with my family.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This isn’t really a thing you can ever call &lt;em&gt;done&lt;/em&gt; in a real sense; there’s always more to do. But we did it well this year, and better than any previous year. I’m looking forward to building on the foundation we laid this year as we move into 2018.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;ol start="3" type="1"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Love our church well.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have much the same to say here as I do about family time. I’ll add that we did move across country and join a new church (and a new denomination!), and I expect to write at much greater length about the convictions which drove the &lt;em&gt;way&lt;/em&gt; we landed on our new congregation after moving across the country.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;ol start="4" type="1"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Work hard for Olo.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I shipped a &lt;em&gt;massive&lt;/em&gt; amount of code this year, including making some pretty significant architectural contributions for the main app I work on—laying the foundation for it to transition from being a &lt;em&gt;mobile&lt;/em&gt; web application to being a &lt;em&gt;responsive, progressive&lt;/em&gt; web application in 2018. I also built &lt;a href="https://true-myth.js.org"&gt;True Myth&lt;/a&gt; and made some pretty substantial progress on &lt;a href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/typing-your-ember/" title="Typing Your Ember"&gt;TypeScript in Ember.js&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;ol start="5" type="1"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Save money for a house.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Done!&lt;/strong&gt; And, to our surprise relative to the beginning of the year, we’re moving in less than a month from now!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;ol start="6" type="1"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Replace &lt;a href="https://github.com/getpelican/pelican"&gt;Pelican&lt;/a&gt; with &lt;a href="https://github.com/chriskrycho/lightning-rs"&gt;Lightning&lt;/a&gt; for this site.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Not done.&lt;/strong&gt; I basically ended up putting Lightning on hold entirely this year. New Rustacean and all of the things we had to do around moving just left me with insufficient time to make any sustained progress on it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section id="minor-goals" class="level3"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Minor goals&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;publish two episodes of New Rustacean every month (of various formats—not all the full-length teaching-a-subject type)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;On average… done.&lt;/strong&gt; But only on average. I put out a &lt;em&gt;lot&lt;/em&gt; more episodes in November and December than any other month, courtesy of the &lt;a href="http://www.newrustacean.com/show_notes/interview/rbr_2017/index.html"&gt;micro-interviews&lt;/a&gt; I conducted at &lt;a href="https://rust-belt-rust.com"&gt;Rust Belt Rust&lt;/a&gt;. The rest of the year, I did publish quite a few episodes, but not nearly as many as I would have liked – more like an average of 1–1.5 each month.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;publish 16–20 episodes of Winning Slowly&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Very much &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; done.&lt;/strong&gt; Winning Slowly did not go &lt;em&gt;at all&lt;/em&gt; the way we thought this year. Our ambitions were… ambitious, given we were both planning to finish graduate degrees and knew that &lt;em&gt;at least&lt;/em&gt; Stephen and possibly &lt;em&gt;both of us&lt;/em&gt; would be moving across the country. Total episodes published this year: 4.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;complete a full-length sprint triathlon&lt;a href="#fn1" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref1"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;run a &lt;a href="http://cityofoaksmarathon.com" title="City of Oaks Marathon"&gt;marathon&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Not done.&lt;/strong&gt; The spring ended up busier and, most importantly, more unpredictable schedule-wise than I hoped, and than allowed for sufficiently regular exercise as to be ready for a triathlon in the summer. And our move across the country both eliminated the final six weeks of training I would have needed for the marathon, and also left us 1,800 miles away from the marathon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;be able to do 15 consecutive pull-ups and 100 consecutive push-ups&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Not sure!&lt;/strong&gt; I haven’t done a max set in a few months. I &lt;em&gt;have&lt;/em&gt; been doing a bunch of push-ups and pull-ups since arriving in Colorado, so… maybe. I’ll edit this in a couple days after I do a max set!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;lose ten pounds and get back down to my target weight&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sadly, not done.&lt;/strong&gt; I have not yet gotten a good handle on what &lt;em&gt;specific&lt;/em&gt; dietary changes I’ll need to make to accomplish this goal, but the ones I tried this year didn’t do the trick. I’ll try something new in 2018.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;document all the undocumented features in Rust, and get the Rust reference all the way up to date (&lt;a href="https://github.com/rust-lang/rust/issues/38643"&gt;tracking issue&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Not done:&lt;/strong&gt; I made a fair bit of progress at the beginning of the year, but this is a &lt;em&gt;mammoth&lt;/em&gt; task. That said, it’s on my radar to try to help drive it forward (hopefully with community involvement) in 2018—it would be great for a complete and accurate reference to be part of the Rust 2019 epoch.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;finish a couple side projects (and bring in the associated money!)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Done.&lt;/strong&gt; In particular, I fixed the last couple bugs and tightened things down in the implementation of &lt;a href="https://holybible.com"&gt;HolyBible.com&lt;/a&gt;. While there’s a lot—oh is there a lot!—I would do differently now (3 years after I finished the base implementation of the app), I’m really delighted that in the last six months I’ve had exactly zero bug reports.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;teach in our small group at least a half dozen times&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Not done, &lt;em&gt;but&lt;/em&gt;…&lt;/strong&gt; this was an intentional choice as we started into the year, because there were a couple other guys who it was more helpful to have in that role for their &lt;em&gt;own&lt;/em&gt; training. I’ve taught a lot over the years, and both of those guys are going to be actively in church-planting roles in the next year or so.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;write at least one long essay for Mere Orthodoxy&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Done.&lt;/strong&gt; I published &lt;a href="https://mereorthodoxy.com/rhythms-family-worship/" title="The Rhythms of Family Worship"&gt;one essay on our family worship&lt;/a&gt; and another (just last week), &lt;a href="https://mereorthodoxy.com/faithful-extension-question-human-origins/" title="Faithful Extension and the Question of Human Origins"&gt;a book review essay&lt;/a&gt; on William T. Cavanaugh and James K. A. Smith’s _Evolution and the Fall_.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;publish the scripts and transcripts of New Rustacean as an ebook&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Not done.&lt;/strong&gt; I &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt; expect to tackle this in 2018, but it just ended up not being a high priority in 2017.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;publish hard copies of the archives of my blog, in a way that mirrors the style of the site at the time it was written&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Not done.&lt;/strong&gt; Same as with the New Rustacean ebook.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;fully archive the Blogger and WordPress versions of this blog as static HTML&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Started, but incomplete.&lt;/strong&gt; I pulled those archives down for the Blogger site, but have yet to do some systematic cleanup on the &lt;abbr&gt;HTML&lt;/abbr&gt;. (This &lt;em&gt;might&lt;/em&gt; actually happen by the end of the year, depending on what all I do on my week off, but as of the time I’m drafting this, it’s not done.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;move all the sites I host (mine and others) out of shared hosting and into a server I manage (probably Digital Ocean or Linode)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Not done.&lt;/strong&gt; I did get a Linode server configured, on which I’m running our family blog (&lt;a href="https://krycho.com"&gt;krycho.com&lt;/a&gt;), and which I should pretty easily be able to use for other non-static sites going forward. Though, as I’ve thought about it over the last year and change: it’s likely I’ll split it up into a small handful, with one consisting of a kind of “shared hosting” for the various friends’ WordPress blogs I host; and one consisting of my own and my family’s sites.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="in-summary" class="level3"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;In summary&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This year didn’t really go as we thought it would. A lot of that came down to finding a house plan we loved and could build on a lot that we equally loved—it shifted financial and temporal priorities alike. Add in some pretty serious family health issues in my extended family, and, well, no surprise some of my plans and goals didn’t pan out. That’s how it goes! The point of making these kinds of goals, for me, isn’t so much that I accomplish everything on my list as it is taking time to orient myself and to choose what I will and won’t &lt;em&gt;focus&lt;/em&gt; on in the year ahead. And in 2017, I did focus on many of the things on this list. Some of them ended up more important than expected; others less. Interestingly and importantly, though, almost nothing I really spent my time focusing on &lt;em&gt;wasn’t&lt;/em&gt; on the list. And that’s why I keep doing this year after year!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section class="footnotes"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn1"&gt;&lt;p&gt;750m swim, 20km (12mi) ride, 5km (3.1mi) run&lt;a href="#fnref1" class="footnote-back"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 24 Dec 2017 17:50:00 -0500</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2017-12-24:/2017/2017-in-review-my-goals.html</guid><category>productivity</category><category>writing</category><category>family</category><category>fitness</category><category>podcasting</category><category>software development</category><category>2017-review</category></item><item><title>2016 in Review, Part 6 of 6</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2017/2016-review-6.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;i class='editorial'&gt;I originally drafted a single, mammoth post reflecting on this whole year—but at more than 6,000 words, that seemed like a bit much. As such, I’ve broken it into a series of posts, to be published daily through the start of the new year. Hopefully they’re a bit more digestible that way!&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2016/2016-review-intro.html"&gt;Introduction, or: a ridiculous year summarized&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2016/2016-review-1.html"&gt;Part 1: Running headfirst into a wall of pneumonia.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2016/2016-review-2.html"&gt;Part 2: So. many. words. I had no idea how many words.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2016/2016-review-3.html"&gt;Part 3: Podcasting: Winning Slowly, New Rustacean, and more!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2016/2016-review-4.html"&gt;Part 4: Writing software for Olo and for open source.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2016/2016-review-5.html"&gt;Part 5: Getting things done in 2016 and beyond.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Part 6: Plans for 2017! (this post)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2017, I really only have a few big goals:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol type="1"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Graduate seminary.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Spend good time with my family.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Love our church well.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Work hard for Olo.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Save money for a house.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Replace &lt;a href="https://github.com/getpelican/pelican"&gt;Pelican&lt;/a&gt; with &lt;a href="https://github.com/chriskrycho/lightning-rs"&gt;Lightning&lt;/a&gt; for this site.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have a bunch of smaller goals, too, of course. That list includes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;publish two episodes of New Rustacean every month (of various formats—not all the full-length teaching-a-subject type)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;publish 16–20 episodes of Winning Slowly&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;complete a full-length sprint triathlon&lt;a href="#fn1" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref1"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;run a &lt;a href="http://cityofoaksmarathon.com"&gt;marathon&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;be able to do 15 consecutive pull-ups and 100 consecutive push-ups&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;lose ten pounds and get back down to my target weight&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;document all the undocumented features in Rust, and get the Rust reference all the way up to date (&lt;a href="https://github.com/rust-lang/rust/issues/38643"&gt;tracking issue&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;finish a couple side projects (and bring in the associated money!)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;teach in our small group at least a half dozen times&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;write at least one long essay for Mere Orthodoxy&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;publish the scripts and transcripts of New Rustacean as an ebook&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;publish hard copies of the archives of my blog, in a way that mirrors the style of the site at the time it was written&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;fully archive the Blogger and WordPress versions of this blog as static HTML&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;move all the sites I host (mine and others) out of shared hosting and into a server I manage (probably Digital Ocean or Linode)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But basically all of those are flexible (and, if I’m honest, so is #6 in the first list—though it’s a &lt;em&gt;high&lt;/em&gt; priority as far as the flexible ones go).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have a pretty good handle on how I’m going to chase those things. The productivity patterns I’ve established over the last couple years are serving me well so far, and I expect them to continue to. After graduation, things will obviously look a little different, and I’m looking forward to that, too. Being able to take vacations where I’m not losing ground by not working on school projects? That sounds truly amazing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m also looking forward to digging into more books I want to read and making progress on writing I want to do in the realm of theology, philosophy, ethics, and so on. I’ve spent nearly all the mental energy I have available for those subjects on seminary work over the past several years (with varying degrees of value for that effort). Once again being able to focus my own external studies as I like will be very freeing, I think. I hope to find some ways to continue to work at something like an academic level, and—crazy though it sounds right &lt;em&gt;now&lt;/em&gt;—I do hope to get a Ph.D. in &lt;em&gt;something&lt;/em&gt; in a few decades. But I am looking forward to having a lot of years of reading and writing outside academia between now and then.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All those goals are good, but ultimate I’m willing to just see what the year brings. I’d love to compose music again more regularly and at greater length. I’d love to write more fiction, and more (and better) poetry. But we’ll also be starting some schooling with Ellie, and dealing with the logistics of planning a move to Colorado sometime in late 2017 or the first half of 2018. We’ll be enjoying just not having nearly so much to do right after finishing seminary. It’s worth remembeirng to rest, and not do just jump into another season of being incredibly slammed by busyness. I plan to take some time to read novels and play video games, too. Those things are good for our souls in their own way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And come what may, I hope to glorify God in the midst of it. Rest, work, play, side projects, you name it—&lt;em&gt;soli deo gloria.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section class="footnotes"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn1"&gt;&lt;p&gt;750m swim, 20km (12mi) ride, 5km (3.1mi) run&lt;a href="#fnref1" class="footnote-back"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2017 08:00:00 -0500</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2017-01-01:/2017/2016-review-6.html</guid><category>writing</category><category>podcasting</category><category>software development</category><category>family</category><category>productivity</category><category>fitness</category><category>2016-in-review</category></item><item><title>2016 in Review, Part 5 of 6</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2016/2016-review-5.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;i class='editorial'&gt;I originally drafted a single, mammoth post reflecting on this whole year—but at more than 6,000 words, that seemed like a bit much. As such, I’ve broken it into a series of posts, to be published daily through the start of the new year. Hopefully they’re a bit more digestible that way!&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2016/2016-review-intro.html"&gt;Introduction, or: a ridiculous year summarized&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2016/2016-review-1.html"&gt;Part 1: Or: a ridiculous year summarized!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2016/2016-review-2.html"&gt;Part 2: So. many. words. I had no idea how many words.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2016/2016-review-3.html"&gt;Part 3: Podcasting: Winning Slowly, New Rustacean, and more!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2016/2016-review-4.html"&gt;Part 4: Writing software for Olo and for open source.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Part 5: Getting things done in 2016 and beyond. (this post)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2017/2016-review-6.html"&gt;Part 6: Plans for 2017!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At a number of points over the last few years, I’ve tackled the question of productivity. I always have far more I &lt;em&gt;want&lt;/em&gt; to get done than I’m able to actually get to. A few of those posts:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2014/boosting-my-productivity.html" title="Boosting My Productivity"&gt;Boosting My Productivity&lt;/a&gt; (December, 2014)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2016/a-new-schedule.html" title="A New Schedule"&gt;A New Schedule: Trying to make better use of my time toward my goals&lt;/a&gt; (July 2016)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A common theme of all productivity plans, of course, is that one can get more focused on the details of the plan than on actually being productive! I’m happy to say, however, that this &lt;em&gt;wasn’t&lt;/em&gt; the case for me with these productivity approaches. First, I have never allowed myself to be slavish about them. If I need to do something different on a given day, I do something different. Second, I am generally able to remember that the point of the plan is &lt;em&gt;what I’m getting done&lt;/em&gt;. So with that in mind, some comments particularly on the plan I sketched out &lt;a href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2016/a-new-schedule.html" title="A New Schedule"&gt;mid-year this year&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I fell off that wagon almost immediately. Readers who’ve stuck with me through these various updates will note that this ambitious plan preceded my disastrous 20-mile run and the ensuing bout of walking pneumonia by a matter of days. It took me until September to get back on the horse, so to speak, because even after I got over being sick, I was traveling—and nothing throws off my schedule like traveling! Happily, I got quite a bit done both during the conference trip I took and during the week I was in Colorado for my youngest sister’s wedding, but it wasn’t until after both of those that I was able to settle back into the routine I’d aimed for.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The major themes of that post were a detailed plan for my days, cutting out a lot of my social media, and thinking about weekends. The detailed plan for my days I kept off and on. I never consistently managed to have the block of time-for-side-projects at the end of my days, and that increasingly meant those things cut into weekends (impacting that goal as well). As for social media, that’s largely been a success: I now rarely get on Facebook, and only check Twitter from time to time. Certainly neither is much of a timesink anymore. I do continue to make heavy use of Slack outside of work, but I’ve found a good balance there (and the main communities I’m a part of have gone through their own adjustments as we’ve &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; found the need for this kind of focus and balance).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So it wasn’t perfect, but I did find it a very useful approach overall. I fully expect to stick with something very like it in 2017. Hopefully I won’t be pulling as many 10–11 hour days as I was in the latter half of 2016—but regardless, building this new discipline around the overall structure of each day was very helpful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One &lt;em&gt;big&lt;/em&gt; part of my approach to productivity that I’m definitely going to keep is the “pomodoro” technique. I first mentioned this in the &lt;a href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2014/boosting-my-productivity.html" title="Boosting My Productivity"&gt;first&lt;/a&gt; discussion I posted about this, but I’ve embraced it more and more. I work in 25-minute blocks, punctuated by 5-minute breaks. Nearly all of those 5-minute breaks entail walking, and as a result I get about 2–3 miles of walking in every day on top of my runs. That helps enormously with focus. This fall, I also embraced the &lt;em&gt;other&lt;/em&gt; half of the pomodoro technique: writing down goals and outcomes for each of those 25-minute blocks. Even more than the daily goals I discussed in the opening post of this series, this lower level of tracking has proved very helpful. It has given me a sense of what I have actually accomplished each day, and it has also helped me &lt;em&gt;focus&lt;/em&gt; as I’m trying to keep moving on various tasks each day. I highly recommend using the pomodoro approach (adapted as necessary to your particular circumstances, of course) as a tool for that kind of focus and productivity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’d be remiss if I didn’t also note the following &lt;em&gt;very&lt;/em&gt; substantial factors in my productivity:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;fitness/health:&lt;/strong&gt; if I’m active, I focus better. People say they don’t have time to exercise; I mean it when I say I don’t have time &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; to. I keep it pretty simple: running, cycling, swimming, and body-weight strength stuff. But I do it basically every day. And we eat fairly healthily. Both of those are incredibly important.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;sleep:&lt;/strong&gt; no matter how busy I am, I don’t pull all-nighters or anything of the sort. I get a minimum of 6 and usually 7–7½ hours of sleep every night. Even when I’m tired from pulling week after week of 10-hour work days, I can keep going because I get enough sleep.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;no commute:&lt;/strong&gt; working remotely is awesome for a lot of reasons, but one of them is that I don’t lose the hour or three every day to the road/subway/etc. that many people I know do. That’s a &lt;em&gt;lot&lt;/em&gt; of time over the course of a year. 48 working weeks means if you commute for an hour total every day, that’s 240 hours a year—that’s 30 8-hour days worth of “getting things done”.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perhaps at some point after I finish seminary I will expand the various things I do in productivity into a more complete series, but this gives you a good idea of what 2016 looked like, and what I expect 2017 to look like!&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 31 Dec 2016 09:30:00 -0500</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2016-12-31:/2016/2016-review-5.html</guid><category>writing</category><category>podcasting</category><category>software development</category><category>family</category><category>productivity</category><category>fitness</category><category>2016-in-review</category><category>pomodoro</category></item><item><title>2016 in Review, Part 4 of 6</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2016/2016-review-4.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;i class='editorial'&gt;I originally drafted a single, mammoth post reflecting on this whole year—but at more than 6,000 words, that seemed like a bit much. As such, I’ve broken it into a series of posts, to be published daily through the start of the new year. Hopefully they’re a bit more digestible that way!&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2016/2016-review-intro.html"&gt;Introduction, or: a ridiculous year summarized&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2016/2016-review-1.html"&gt;Part 1: Running headfirst into a wall of pneumonia.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2016/2016-review-2.html"&gt;Part 2: So. many. words. I had no idea how many words.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2016/2016-review-3.html"&gt;Part 3: Podcasting: Winning Slowly, New Rustacean, and more!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Part 4: Writing software for Olo and for open source. (this post)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2016/2016-review-5.html"&gt;Part 5: Getting things done in 2016 and beyond.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2017/2016-review-6.html"&gt;Part 6: Plans for 2017!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This year at Olo was a great year overall. I very much enjoy working with the people there, the tech stack is good and they’re paying me to do what I love, and if the product isn’t lighting my world on fire (online restaurant ordering is cool, but restaurants aren’t a passion of mine), that’s a tradeoff I can live with. Working with good people with a good tech stack on a product you find &lt;em&gt;fine&lt;/em&gt; rather than &lt;em&gt;amazing&lt;/em&gt; is actually pretty great. I’m grateful for previous jobs, but this one has superceded them in every possible way. I’m &lt;em&gt;glad&lt;/em&gt; to start work every day—and in truth, there have been more than a few days where I would have liked nothing more than to keep writing JavaScript rather than switching over to do some reading and writing for seminary. That bodes well for my future plans: post-seminary, I expect to bump from 30 to 40 hours a week with Olo&lt;a href="#fn1" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref1"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and keep making our software as awesome as I can. And I expect to enjoy that!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Speaking of numbers: GitHub reports that I contributed +29,463/−13,726 lines of code in our new mobile web ordering experience, which I helped build nearly from scratch this year. (That “negative” is stuff I rewrote or removed entirely by finding a better implementation.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Quite a bit of my &lt;a href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2016/2016-review-2.html"&gt;writing&lt;/a&gt; this year was technical, too: some ~33,000 of the words on my blog—fully a third of the things I published on this site apart from microblog posts and schoolwork—was about software. That included entries 11–18 of my &lt;a href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/rust-and-swift.html"&gt;Rust and Swift&lt;/a&gt; series, but about 20,000 words were assorted discussions of JavaScript, Rust, podcasting, functional programming, etc. A fair bit of that content came out of things I worked on for Olo, either directly (as in the case of &lt;a href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2016/what-is-functional-programming.html" title="What is Functional Programming? (And why should we care about it?)"&gt;this talk&lt;/a&gt;) or indirectly (as in the case of &lt;a href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2016/keyof-and-mapped-types-in-typescript-21.html" title="keyof and Mapped Types in TypeScript 2.1"&gt;this discussion of TypeScript 2.1&lt;/a&gt;) That’s a good mix, and I hope to continue putting out material that’s useful to others as well as interesting to me. (I do get tweets now and again confirming that the content is helpful, and I &lt;em&gt;don’t&lt;/em&gt; run analytics on the site at all—so if you like something I write, please tell me. It’s encouraging. And that goes for &lt;em&gt;any&lt;/em&gt; author you read, as a rule.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, I actually did a little bit of open-source contributing this year. Not as much as I’d like, but a little. And I also count New Rustacean as a pretty substantial contribution to the Rust community. The fact that it isn’t code doesn’t diminish what it’s doing. If you’re feeling like code is the only thing that &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; counts, recognize that all the code in the world isn’t that useful without explanations of how to use it, helping people become interested in the first place, and so on. Speaking of non-code contributions, the open-source contribution I’m &lt;em&gt;most&lt;/em&gt; proud of is certainly the &lt;a href="https://github.com/rust-lang/rfcs/pull/1636"&gt;Rust RFC&lt;/a&gt; I wrote and which was recently accepted and merged. It proposed (and it is now the official policy of the Rust project) that no new features may be added to the (stable version of the) language or the standard library without first being documented. This is a big deal for the language, and it was also a big deal for me, in that it was another place where—despite being far too busy to write a lot of Rust code this year—I could make a real difference in a community I’m passionate about. And one of my goals for next year is a direct follow-on from that: &lt;a href="https://github.com/rust-lang/rust/issues/38643"&gt;actually implementing the requirement&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The other big thing going on for me in the software world is that I started work on &lt;a href="https://github.com/chriskrycho/lightning-rs"&gt;Lightning&lt;/a&gt;, a new static site generator in Rust. (There’s another such project, &lt;a href="http://cobalt-org.github.io"&gt;Cobalt&lt;/a&gt;, which is already usable.) I’ve been pushing up against the limits of &lt;a href="http://docs.getpelican.com/en/stable/"&gt;Pelican&lt;/a&gt;, my current generator, for a while. And I’ve looked around time and again, and never found a CMS or SSG that does everything my peculiar publishing needs require (&lt;em&gt;especially&lt;/em&gt; in a way that I like!). And my needs are indeed peculiar, though probably not wholly unique; for most people, any one of &lt;a href="https://staticsitegenerators.net"&gt;&lt;em&gt;many&lt;/em&gt; other site generators&lt;/a&gt; would work just fine. So I’m doing what I’ve been thinking about doing for years, and building my own. My immediate goals are mostly just to have something that is super speedy and which checks off all my needs from a CMS/site generator. My longer-term goals include getting some good foundational knowledge I’ll need for &lt;a href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2016/ulysses-byword-and-just-right.html"&gt;my &lt;em&gt;next&lt;/em&gt; project&lt;/a&gt;. I’m a thousand lines in, and have some pieces working. I hope very much to move off of Pelican and onto Lightning (and get a freshened theme for this site) in 2017!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section class="footnotes"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn1"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Yes, Olo has been incredibly generous and hired me as a full-time employee at 30-hours-a-week with pro-rated salary. Like I said: amazing company.&lt;a href="#fnref1" class="footnote-back"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 30 Dec 2016 07:00:00 -0500</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2016-12-30:/2016/2016-review-4.html</guid><category>writing</category><category>podcasting</category><category>software development</category><category>family</category><category>productivity</category><category>fitness</category><category>2016-in-review</category></item><item><title>2016 in Review, Part 3 of 6</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2016/2016-review-3.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;i class='editorial'&gt;I originally drafted a single, mammoth post reflecting on this whole year—but at more than 6,000 words, that seemed like a bit much. As such, I’ve broken it into a series of posts, to be published daily through the start of the new year. Hopefully they’re a bit more digestible that way!&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2016/2016-review-intro.html"&gt;Introduction, or: a ridiculous year summarized&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2016/2016-review-1.html"&gt;Part 1: Running headfirst into a wall of pneumonia.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2016/2016-review-2.html"&gt;Part 2: So. many. words. I had no idea how many words.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Part 3: Podcasting: Winning Slowly, New Rustacean, and more! (this post)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2016/2016-review-4.html"&gt;Part 4: Writing software for Olo and for open source.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2016/2016-review-5.html"&gt;Part 5: Getting things done in 2016 and beyond.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2017/2016-review-6.html"&gt;Part 6: Plans for 2017!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Beyond &lt;a href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2016/2016-review-2.html"&gt;the written word&lt;/a&gt;, the other “writing”-type work I had this year—some of it including &lt;em&gt;actual&lt;/em&gt; writing in the form of detailed scripts—was podcasting!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr class="header"&gt;
&lt;th style="text-align: center;"&gt;Show&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th style="text-align: center;"&gt;Episodes&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th style="text-align: center;"&gt;Total time&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr class="odd"&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.winningslowly.org"&gt;Winning Slowly&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: center;"&gt;25&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: center;"&gt;11h 40m&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class="even"&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.newrustacean.com"&gt;New Rustacean&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: center;"&gt;22&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: center;"&gt;6h 46m&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class="odd"&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;a href="http://runwith.chriskrycho.com"&gt;Run With Me&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: center;"&gt;19&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: center;"&gt;1h 1m&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class="even"&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.sap-py.com"&gt;sap.py&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: center;"&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: center;"&gt;12m&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class="odd"&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Total&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;67&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;19h 39m&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Again, several of those numbers surprised me a bit. For one thing, I had to put New Rustacean on hiatus starting in October courtesy of the crunch I ended up with from the &lt;em&gt;Rust vs. Swift&lt;/em&gt; project colliding with the other summer-and-fall commitments I had. For another Stephen and I paused Winning Slowly between Seasons 4 and 5 (as we usually do) and also have taken a mid-season pause on Season 5 because of end-of-semester crunches for both of us and then his wife having a baby a few weeks earlier than expected. Yet in spite of that, almost 20 hours of audio content this year! If I hit that again in 2017, I’ll be happy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whether &lt;a href="http://www.sap-py.com"&gt;sap.py&lt;/a&gt; will be back, I have no idea. I love making the show with Jaimie, but it’s really up to her whether she wants to keep working on Python. Of late, she’s been working on &lt;a href="https://www.etsy.com/shop/PemberlyPrintables" title="Jaimie&amp;#39;s printable shop on Etsy"&gt;printable art&lt;/a&gt; instead, and that’s delightful in its own right. I’ve &lt;a href="http://runwith.chriskrycho.com/runs/14/"&gt;just&lt;/a&gt; gotten &lt;a href="http://runwith.chriskrycho.com"&gt;Run With Me&lt;/a&gt; going again in the past day; I got off track when my headphone microphone stopped working for a bit and never got back &lt;em&gt;on&lt;/em&gt; track when it started working again. I’m looking forward to once again talking about running while running.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I expect to be publishing an even wider variety of kinds of episodes of New Rustacean in 2017. Listeners should get another couple of interviews, a lot more of the “here is a Rust concept in detail” episodes (at least one a month in general, I hope!), news episodes, undoubtedly a few bonus episodes, and a new “Crates You Should Know” format designed to highlight crates I’ve found useful in my own Rust work. I continue to find Rust a wonderful language, and I hear regularly that this is one of people’s favorite programming podcasts. I hope to keep it that way!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We expect to wrap up &lt;a href="http://www.winningslowly.org/season-5.html" title="Winning Slowly Season 5: Structure and Agency"&gt;Season 5&lt;/a&gt; of &lt;a href="http://www.winningslowly.org"&gt;Winning Slowly&lt;/a&gt; mid-spring, and then begin recording Season 6 mid-to-late summer. All of that is pending how things go as Stephen finishes his dissertation and likely prepares to move across the country to take a job as a professor somewhere, of course. But that’s the plan—and yes, we already know the rough shape of Season 6, even this far out. We know the season topic, and have some basic ideas of where we want to go with it. As is usually the case with our “seasons” now, it will take ideas we’ve touched on here and there and turn them into a full-blown, months-long exploration of those ideas as applied to specific issues. Winning Slowly remains one of my very favorite projects, not least because there is (to our knowledge) nothing else out there doing quite the same thing. Tackling long-term trends in technology with a distinctively (though not always overtly) Christian perspective (but &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; a reductionist one) is apparently our gap to fill. We’ll take it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Two other podcasting-related bits. First, I wrote a &lt;a href="https://mereorthodoxy.com/theses-on-podcasting/" title="32 Theses (and several more words) on Podcasting"&gt;~5,000-word piece for Mere Orthodoxy&lt;/a&gt; explaining how the medium works, what its constraints are, and what is involved in doing it well. If podcasting is interesting to you, I think the piece is well worth your time—precisely because of, and not in spite of, its length! Second, I gave a pair of guest lectures for Stephen at N.C. State University this fall, which are both available in the &lt;a href="http://www.winningslowly.org/season-bonus.html"&gt;bonus section&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;a href="http://www.winningslowly.org"&gt;Winning Slowly&lt;/a&gt;. Those cover some of the same ground as the piece at Mere O, but they also talk a lot more about the details of finding a topic, an “authorial voice”, and an angle for your show.&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 29 Dec 2016 10:30:00 -0500</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2016-12-29:/2016/2016-review-3.html</guid><category>writing</category><category>podcasting</category><category>software development</category><category>family</category><category>productivity</category><category>fitness</category><category>2016-in-review</category></item><item><title>2016 in Review, Part 2 of 6</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2016/2016-review-2.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;i class='editorial'&gt;I originally drafted a single, mammoth post reflecting on this whole year—but at more than 6,000 words, that seemed like a bit much. As such, I’ve broken it into a series of posts, to be published daily through the start of the new year. Hopefully they’re a bit more digestible that way!&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2016/2016-review-intro.html"&gt;Introduction, or: a ridiculous year summarized&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2016/2016-review-1.html"&gt;Part 1: Running headfirst into a wall of pneumonia.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Part 2: So. many. words. I had no idea how many words. (this post)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2016/2016-review-3.html"&gt;Part 3: Podcasting: Winning Slowly, New Rustacean, and more!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2016/2016-review-4.html"&gt;Part 4: Writing software for Olo and for open source.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2016/2016-review-5.html"&gt;Part 5: Getting things done in 2016 and beyond.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2017/2016-review-6.html"&gt;Part 6: Plans for 2017!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of my goals for 2016 was to continue writing not only on this blog but in other outlets. I did a &lt;em&gt;lot&lt;/em&gt; of writing this year, but relatively little of it is published. But here’s a look at some of the numbers! Note that “This site” excludes republication of school papers, and that I don’t have an exact count for the school papers because I’ve already discarded a few of the shorter pieces, but their average length is well-known to me. More on the unpublished &lt;em&gt;Rust vs. Swift&lt;/em&gt; project below.&lt;a href="#fn1" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref1"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr class="header"&gt;
&lt;th style="text-align: center;"&gt;Category&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th style="text-align: center;"&gt;Words&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr class="odd"&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/m-div/"&gt;School&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: center;"&gt;~130,500&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class="even"&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;a href="https://mereorthodoxy.com/author/chris-krycho/"&gt;Mere Orthodoxy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: center;"&gt;~6000&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class="odd"&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: center;"&gt;This site&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: center;"&gt;~63,000&lt;a href="#fn2" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref2"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class="even"&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Rust vs. Swift&lt;/em&gt; project&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: center;"&gt;~9350&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class="odd"&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Total&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;~207,850&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of the writing for school, only a small fraction of it is &lt;a href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/m-div/"&gt;published here&lt;/a&gt;, unlike previous years. Roughly 75,000 words of that content is research notes I put together for an independent study I did—which was deeply profitable for me in terms of thinking through hermeneutical and theological systems, and which will hopefully be helpful for the professor for whom I prepared them, but which are not at all publishable. Another 10,000 of those words fit in a category charitably describable as “busy-work” and publishing them is &lt;em&gt;possible&lt;/em&gt; but would have no &lt;em&gt;value&lt;/em&gt;. The school-writing also includes the notes and manuscripts for my sermon-delivery class. You can find those sermons &lt;a href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/sermons/"&gt;on this site&lt;/a&gt; as well well, with audio, video, and the manuscripts available—but the notes are not worth publishing, as they’re entirely internal. Still: they’re words, I wrote them, and there are a lot of them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the plus side, I wrote one of the papers I’m proudest of from my entire seminary career in the spring: &lt;a href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2016/realism-and-antirealism.html"&gt;Realism and Antirealism—A key debate in the philosophy of science (with interesting implications for young-earth creationism)&lt;/a&gt;. I’m happy with it not least because I wrote it in a very compressed fashion because of some family health issues that hit at the end of that semester, and it still turned out extremely well because I had &lt;em&gt;planned&lt;/em&gt; it meticulously. Despite having only a single draft with one typo-level revision pass, it’s easily the best paper I’ve ever written. It turns out that doing a really careful outline helps when you’re working at this scale. I’ve not normally been a fan of outlining (and I’ve not normally found it helpful when I’ve tried it), but for any longer, more sustained argument, it’s absolutely necessary.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of the content on this site (excluding republication of school papers), an astounding ~14,000 of those words are in my “microblog” content. It’s amazing how much those little posts add up. That said, I’m surprised to see that I’ve put out as many &lt;em&gt;other&lt;/em&gt; words as I have this year on this site, and the total there is rather staggering. Writing on this site includes everything from &lt;a href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2016/ask.html" title="Ask: a short story"&gt;fiction&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2016/to-paint-god-as-a-man.html" title="To paint God as a man: an Advent poem"&gt;poetry&lt;/a&gt; to &lt;a href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2016/a-simple-childrens-catechism.html"&gt;a simple children’s catechism&lt;/a&gt; to &lt;a href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2016/what-is-functional-programming.html"&gt;an introduction to functional programming&lt;/a&gt;. I’m exceptionally pleased in retrospect to see how this came out, and I look forward to writing on equally varied terms in the year ahead.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some 13,000 of the words I wrote for this site were in my &lt;a href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/rust-and-swift.html"&gt;Rust and Swift&lt;/a&gt; series, a project I’ve enjoyed enormously since starting it in 2015 and would like to get back to in 2017. It went on hold because I was offered, and accepted, a contract to write a 30–40 page report for O’Reilly comparing the two languages, which was intended to come out this fall. Unfortunately, somewhere along the way some wires got crossed and my pitch and what they wanted didn’t end up being the same. Once that became clear (at the beginning of October), they opted to drop the project. This was a huge disappointment to me: it was a small hit financially, but a big one time-wise, as I sunk a &lt;em&gt;lot&lt;/em&gt; of hours into it in what was an already-very-busy fall; the project was over ¾ done when it was dropped.&lt;a href="#fn3" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref3"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A few big lessons I learned from this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol type="1"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Don’t overcommit. Even if the project had gone through without issue, it would have been more on my plate than I could reasonably handle. The fact that it was canceled after having done a lot of the work meant it was also &lt;em&gt;financially&lt;/em&gt; frustrating, but I had overcommitted regardless. Won’t do that again.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Be &lt;em&gt;even more&lt;/em&gt; clear up-front about the terms and goals of a project. I don’t know how we ended up with the crossed wires we did, but it was extremely frustrating.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;If you can get an advance, get an advance. Just saying.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In general, I’m quite pleased with the &lt;em&gt;volume&lt;/em&gt; of my output in 2016 (who wouldn’t be, right?). I’d definitely like a lot more of that to be public-facing in 2017, even if it’s lower in overall volume. I hope to take the material from that canceled &lt;em&gt;Rust vs. Swift&lt;/em&gt; project, expand it slightly, and self-publish it. I also hope to put together at least one substantive essay for Mere Orthodoxy next year. And of course there will probably be thousands of words in this space, too—inevitably more than I even realize.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section class="footnotes"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn1"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Note as well that this excludes all the &lt;a href="https://github.com/chriskrycho/newrustacean.com/tree/589cd13225cde91f92bfca93f6679f2395d78886/docs"&gt;podcast scripts&lt;/a&gt; I wrote this year! Those would add well over 10,000 more words to this count.&lt;a href="#fnref1" class="footnote-back"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn2"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Yes, that number includes these posts!&lt;a href="#fnref2" class="footnote-back"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn3"&gt;&lt;p&gt;They wanted an analysis of when you’d choose each language; I pitched a comparison along similar lines to my blog series, looking at the language design choices as a view into software engineering tradeoffs. When the mismatch became clear, I pointed out that “when to choose Rust vs. Swift” is, generally speaking, a roughly two-sentence answer: “Choose Rust for cross-platform, high-performance/low-level code. Choose Swift if you’re writing apps on an Apple platform.” This was not, apparently, obvious to everyone else involved. In the words of the internet: &lt;span style="whitespace: nowrap"&gt;¯\_(ツ)_/¯&lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="#fnref3" class="footnote-back"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 28 Dec 2016 07:00:00 -0500</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2016-12-28:/2016/2016-review-2.html</guid><category>writing</category><category>podcasting</category><category>software development</category><category>family</category><category>productivity</category><category>fitness</category><category>2016-in-review</category></item><item><title>2016 in Review, Part 1 of 6</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2016/2016-review-1.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;i class='editorial'&gt;I originally drafted a single, mammoth post reflecting on this whole year—but at more than 6,000 words, that seemed like a bit much. As such, I’ve broken it into a series of posts, to be published daily through the start of the new year. Hopefully they’re a bit more digestible that way!&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2016/2016-review-intro.html"&gt;Introduction, or: a ridiculous year summarized&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Part 1: Running headfirst into a wall of pneumonia. (this post)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2016/2016-review-2.html"&gt;Part 2: So. many. words. I had no idea how many words.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2016/2016-review-3.html"&gt;Part 3: Podcasting: Winning Slowly, New Rustacean, and more!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2016/2016-review-4.html"&gt;Part 4: Writing software for Olo and for open source.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2016/2016-review-5.html"&gt;Part 5: Getting things done in 2016 and beyond.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2017/2016-review-6.html"&gt;Part 6: Plans for 2017!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Wait, hold on,&lt;/em&gt; you say. &lt;em&gt;Go back. How did you get walking pneumonia?&lt;/em&gt; This is a fun story, and it’s a huge part of what made the other parts of the latter half of 2016 go the way they did.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I went for what I expected to be a 15–16 mile long run as part of training for the half-marathon I signed up for this year. The previous week &lt;a href="http://runwith.chriskrycho.com/runs/12/" title="Run summary on runwith.chriskrycho.com"&gt;I’d done a 14-mile run&lt;/a&gt;, so 15–16 would have been no problem. I was feeling &lt;em&gt;awesome&lt;/em&gt; on the run, so decided to extend it to 17. This was right at the edge of what makes good sense for a week-over-week increase in mileage; you generally want to stick with ~10% increases and max out at 20%; but 17 is right at that limit relative to 14. So I turned right to cut through another nearby town instead of left to head directly home when I was at roughly the 11-mile mark.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then, where I &lt;em&gt;did&lt;/em&gt; cut back toward home, I took a wrong turn out of a five-way intersection. (You can see on the north end of the map, in Youngsville, &lt;a href="https://www.strava.com/activities/644619792" title="Run overview on Strava"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;). I realized this half a mile on, but figured there would be a spot to cut over. There is not. So I got back to where I had taken the wrong turn, filled up my water bottle and hit the bathroom, and made my way home. But at this point, I was already at ~15 miles, and ~4 miles from home. As I got back into our town, I decided: why not just go ahead and extend out to 20 miles?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And the truth is, that extra three quarters of a mile probably didn’t matter a bit. 19.25 vs. 20 miles? Same difference in its effect on my immune system, which is to say: it completely crashed it. A 42% week over week increase in mileage is no joke. The little cold I picked up from my 2-year-old daughter turned into borderline bronchitis. Yay.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What with a busy spring preceding—I had no idea how much busier I would be taking 2 classes and working 30 hours a week than I had been taking 3 classes and working 20 hours a week—I didn’t manage a triathlon. I had contented myself with the thought that I’d likely set another PR in my half marathon, but after weeks of recovery from walking pneumonia, that thought fell apart as well. I lost about a minute per mile in my pace, and my mileage was shot as well. I never got it back—not least because of a writing project which went south on me. I ended up being sick off and on all fall, and I’m only now getting my feet back under me. Sad to say, one of those times I got sick was the week of the half marathon I signed up for, and I’d been getting loud, clear signals from my body on previous runs that I was pushing too hard. So no race &lt;em&gt;at all&lt;/em&gt; this year. But better that than pushing and injuring myself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The year also saw a so-far unreversed weight gain that I find incredibly frustrating. In the first six months of 2016, I gained about ten pounds—despite keeping up the same basic activity level. I attribute this to a combination of factors: metabolic shifts in my late 20s, shifting back to doing almost purely running rather than a mix of running, swimming, and cycling, and the impact of acclimation to a workout load. I’m far from overweight, but I’m also slower and generally a bit flabbier as a result.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here’s hoping 2017 is &lt;em&gt;much&lt;/em&gt; better in all these regards! I plan to do a sprint-length triathlon and a full marathon. And I hope to lose those ten pounds again and get back to that healthier overall weight. That combo seems like the thing to do the year I turn thirty and graduate seminary.&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 27 Dec 2016 17:00:00 -0500</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2016-12-27:/2016/2016-review-1.html</guid><category>writing</category><category>podcasting</category><category>software development</category><category>family</category><category>productivity</category><category>fitness</category><category>2016-in-review</category></item><item><title>2016 in Review, Introduction</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2016/2016-review-intro.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;i class='editorial'&gt;I originally drafted a single, mammoth post reflecting on this whole year—but at more than 6,000 words, that seemed like a bit much. As such, I’ve broken it into a series of posts, to be published daily through the start of the new year. Hopefully they’re a bit more digestible that way! This first day, you’re getting two posts; the rest of the year, one (at least: in this series!).&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Introduction, or: a ridiculous year summarized (this post)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2016/2016-review-1.html"&gt;Part 1: Running headfirst into a wall of pneumonia.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2016/2016-review-2.html"&gt;Part 2: So. many. words. I had no idea how many words.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2016/2016-review-3.html"&gt;Part 3: Podcasting: Winning Slowly, New Rustacean, and more!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2016/2016-review-4.html"&gt;Part 4: Writing software for Olo and for open source.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2016/2016-review-5.html"&gt;Part 5: Getting things done in 2016 and beyond.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2017/2016-review-6.html"&gt;Part 6: Plans for 2017!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;2016 was a long, difficult, strange, sometimes wonderful and sometimes dreadful year for me. It was one of the most professionally and scholastically enjoyable and rewarding years of my life, and also one of the most exhausting. As I often do at years-end, I am taking stock publicly of what went well, what went poorly, and what I might do different in a variety of categories—here, mostly in terms of my public-facing endeavors. This year’s summing-up post will also (for, I think, the first time) include some numbers! But first, a few comments on the big picture.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the end of 2015, I &lt;a href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2015/thoughts-on-2015-and-2016.html"&gt;offered a similar set of reflections&lt;/a&gt;. At the end of it, I laid out some plans for 2016:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am going to set a single goal in each of five major categories in my life:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;spiritual:&lt;/strong&gt; everything in my walk with God, including my own personal devotions, my involvement in the life of the church, and my “ministry” actions in general&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;family:&lt;/strong&gt; both quantity and quality time spent with my wife and my quickly-growing-up little girls&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;personal:&lt;/strong&gt; podcasting, blogging, and writing for &lt;a href="http://mereorthodoxy.com/author/chris-krycho/"&gt;other outlets&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;professional:&lt;/strong&gt; working in my new job and as a consultant, and carrying on toward the conclusion of my M. Div.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;health/fitness:&lt;/strong&gt; continuing to stay healthy, including eating well and continuing to stay fit by running and doing triathlon work&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Early in the year, I made the habit of writing these out formally on a day-by-day basis—and I did this off and on. If you were to look at my little (Moleskine-branded and delightful-to-me) daily planner, you’d see streaks of weeks where I noted specific tasks and whether I hit them or not, punctuated by weeks and months where I did nothing of the sort. I have always found it difficult to stick with these kinds of things, in part because I usually have a pretty good idea what I need to do on any given day without writing it down somewhere. (I use &lt;a href="https://www.omnigroup.com/omnifocus/" title="OmniFocus"&gt;other tools&lt;/a&gt; for tracking mid- and long-term deadlines for school.) In July, I started mashing this idea up with &lt;a href="http://bulletjournal.com" title="Bullet Journal site"&gt;bullet journaling&lt;/a&gt;, and I found that I (a) really like the system and (b) also didn’t stick with it consistently. A lot of that came down to the fact that I got thrown off—horribly—by getting a mild-but-still-utterly-debilitating case of walking pneumonia in July. (On which, more in a moment.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So much for last year’s ideas about &lt;em&gt;how&lt;/em&gt; I was going to hit those goals. How did I actually do at addressing them? The answer is: &lt;em&gt;okay&lt;/em&gt;. 2016 was not an amazing year. It was not a terrible year. But it had as many downs as ups.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My own walk with God remains &lt;em&gt;steady&lt;/em&gt;. Nothing amazing to report here, but I’m more than okay with that. I will perhaps say more on this in another post, but the older I get the more convinced I am that emotional highs are a trap. Sentiment and true religion are &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; the same thing; and Scripture calls us to &lt;em&gt;faithfulness&lt;/em&gt;, not &lt;em&gt;spiritual feelings&lt;/em&gt;. As such, in a year with this many bumps, I am glad to say that I had no horrible falls, and I read my Bible nearly every day and prayed every single day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our family learned some Bible verses, and started working on the Heidelberg Catechism. We shared the gospel with people as we were able, and met faithfully with our church. We were not extraordinary, and we were far from flawless, but I think we did &lt;em&gt;well&lt;/em&gt;. I hope and pray in God’s grace we are able to continue in faithfully doing well in the years to come. Certainly if there is one thing I hope to do more of in 2017 it is spend time with my girls. I am not a huge “kid person,” but these years are precious and go by quickly; far better to spend more time with them and have a podcast episode or a writing project go out later (or not at all) than to miss these little years.&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 27 Dec 2016 16:00:00 -0500</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2016-12-27:/2016/2016-review-intro.html</guid><category>writing</category><category>podcasting</category><category>software development</category><category>family</category><category>productivity</category><category>fitness</category><category>2016-in-review</category></item><item><title>Winning Slowly 5.05: “Faint Not”</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2016/winning-slowly-5-05-faint-not.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.winningslowly.org/5.05/"&gt;This&lt;/a&gt; is one of the most important episodes Stephen Carradini and I have ever published. We go after civil forfeiture &lt;em&gt;hard&lt;/em&gt;. Give it a listen!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.winningslowly.org/5.05/"&gt;Winning Slowly 5.05: “Faint Not”&lt;/a&gt;—Negative / Invisible / Legal (Organized): civil forfeiture and entrenched legal evil&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 04 Oct 2016 08:17:00 -0400</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2016-10-04:/2016/winning-slowly-5-05-faint-not.html</guid><category>podcasting</category><category>my writing elsewhere</category><category>links</category></item><item><title>32 Theses (and several more words) on Podcasting</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2016/32-theses-and-several-more-words-on-podcasting.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;A month ago, Alan Jacobs asked about quality conservative Christian podcasts. &lt;a href="https://mereorthodoxy.com/theses-on-podcasting/"&gt;Here’s&lt;/a&gt; a big part of why there are so few (at Mere Orthodoxy):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a Christian in the world of podcasting—I have both a “two dudes talking” show (Winning Slowly) and also a “one dude talking with maybe a brief musical intro and outro” show (New Rustacean)—I found much to agree with, but also much to clarify and a few things to disagree with…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, a set of theses on podcasting as a medium. Some of these are obvious; none are intended to be tendentious. Some of them warrant further explanation—for which, see below….&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After which, &lt;a href="https://mereorthodoxy.com/theses-on-podcasting/"&gt;32 theses (and another ~3,000 words)&lt;/a&gt; on the constraints and challenges of podcasting as a medium.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Aside: the format of this particular piece is heavily inspired by Jacobs’ own &lt;a href="http://iasc-culture.org/THR/channels/Infernal_Machine/2015/03/79-theses-on-technology-for-disputation/"&gt;“79 Theses on Technology. For Disputation.”&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 09 Aug 2016 10:30:00 -0400</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2016-08-09:/2016/32-theses-and-several-more-words-on-podcasting.html</guid><category>podcasting</category><category>my writing elsewhere</category><category>links</category></item><item><title>Winning Slowly Season 5</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2016/winning-slowly-season-5.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Up the ante&lt;/em&gt;, you say? Sure, we’ll tackle the small, easy problem of &lt;em&gt;systemic force and individual agency&lt;/em&gt; this season on &lt;a href="http://www.winningslowly.org"&gt;Winning Slowly&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.winningslowly.org/5.01/"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;5.01: A Ph.D.-Level Math Problem&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;—Structures and systems, agency and individuals: three axes (and a sub-axis) for thinking about the world we live in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We introduce our system for thinking about the “structure/agency” or “systems and individuals” problem: how do the systems and structures of our lives shape us? How do we shape them? How free are we, and where are the places where more freedom is good, and the places where it might actually be bad? How do we confront the structural issues we face, or strengthen and preserve the good systems we do have in place?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.winningslowly.org/5.01/"&gt;Listen to the whole thing!&lt;/a&gt; And then &lt;a href="mailto:hello@winningslowly.org?subject=5.01:%20A%20Ph.D.-Level%20Math%20Problem"&gt;tell us&lt;/a&gt; what you think.&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 09 Aug 2016 07:30:00 -0400</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2016-08-09:/2016/winning-slowly-season-5.html</guid><category>podcasting</category><category>links</category></item><item><title>Run With Me!</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2016/run-with-me.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;I may have gone mad with power or something, but I launched another podcast today! Crazy, I know.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s both more and less crazy than it might sound, though. More, because of what the podcast is, and less, because of what the podcast is. So what is it?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="//runwith.chriskrycho.com"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Run With Me&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; is a microcast, with 3–5-minute long episodes &lt;em&gt;about&lt;/em&gt; running, recorded &lt;em&gt;while&lt;/em&gt; running.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src="//cdn.chriskrycho.com/runwith/cover-web.jpg" title="_Run With Me_ cover art" alt="Run With Me" /&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;em&gt;Run With Me&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I allow myself an absolute maximum of ten minutes to edit and publish the episodes. (So far, I’ve never needed more than about &lt;em&gt;three&lt;/em&gt; minutes.) So, for anyone worried that I’m unnecessarily or unwisely adding something more to my already-full plate: don’t be. Apart from spending some of my relaxation time this weekend building the site, the only time I’ll spend on this will be time I would already be spending running or cooling down after a run.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So far (two episodes in!) it’s a ton of fun. I’ve enjoyed the process of recording it, and it’s nice to be able to talk about running confident that whoever listens is actually interested. (As I explain further on the show, that interest in not boring my audience is part of why I’m doing this, rather than just talking to people I know.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you have any interest in running, and especially if you like listening to podcasts while you run, I think you’ll enjoy this. I’d love it if you subscribed!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/podcast/run-with-me/id1102273878?mt=2"&gt;&lt;i class="fa fa-fw fa-music"&gt;&lt;/i&gt; iTunes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://overcast.fm/p418939-N58r18"&gt;&lt;i class="fa fa-fw fa-play-circle"&gt;&lt;/i&gt; Overcast&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://pca.st/5toh"&gt;&lt;i class="fa fa-fw fa-play-circle-o"&gt;&lt;/i&gt; PocketCasts&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://runwith.chriskrycho.com/feed.xml"&gt;&lt;i class="fa fa-fw fa-rss"&gt;&lt;/i&gt; Old-fashioned RSS&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A few comments on the podcast from a form/genre angle, and a few from a technical angel:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can think of &lt;a href="//www.manton.org/2016/01/new-podcast-timetable.html"&gt;“microcasts”&lt;/a&gt; as being not terribly dissimilar from a &lt;a href="//www.chriskrycho.com/micro/"&gt;microblog post&lt;/a&gt; in its own way. I’m happily stealing the idea of a microcast from &lt;a href="//www.manton.org"&gt;Manton Reece&lt;/a&gt;, whose &lt;a href="//timetable.manton.org"&gt;Timetable&lt;/a&gt; show is a delightful little thing. (It’s not original to him; a quick [Google search] will turn up instances of the term dating back several years at least, but he’s where I got the idea, and I think he’s certainly one of the first to be popularizing the form.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I find podcasting as a medium extremely interesting in general (I’m &lt;a href="//www.winningslowly.org"&gt;sure&lt;/a&gt; you would &lt;a href="//www.newrustacean.com"&gt;never&lt;/a&gt; have &lt;a href="//www.sap-py.com"&gt;guessed&lt;/a&gt; that), and I think microcasts will proliferate rapidly. As my friend &lt;a href="http://oluseyi.info"&gt;Oluseyi Sonaiya&lt;/a&gt; and I have often discussed, brevity is a real virtue in podcasting, and one too-little appreciated by many amateur producers in the space. &lt;a href="http://independentclauses.com"&gt;Stephen&lt;/a&gt; and I aim for that balance with &lt;a href="//www.winningslowly.org"&gt;Winning Slowly&lt;/a&gt;, and it’s always been a part of my consideration with &lt;a href="//www.newrustacean.com"&gt;New Rustacean&lt;/a&gt; as well. People’s time is valuable. Saying something and then &lt;em&gt;being done&lt;/em&gt; is a kindness to your audience.&lt;a href="#fn1" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref1"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And then, practically speaking, there’s the simple reality that it’s just &lt;em&gt;harder&lt;/em&gt; to record a long-form podcast while running. Especially a good one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At a tech level, producing the podcast is incredibly simple: I use the built-in microphone in the headphones that come with an iPhone to record, and do the recording and (extremely minimal) audio production in &lt;a href="https://geo.itunes.apple.com/us/app/ferrite-recording-studio/id1018780185?mt=8&amp;amp;at=1001l4KM"&gt;Ferrite&lt;/a&gt;. When I say minimal, I mean really minimal: I chop off the bits before I start talking, and the bits after I start talking, and I do all of that on my iPhone. Then I export to Dropbox, and from there to my CDN. That’s it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section class="footnotes"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn1"&gt;&lt;p&gt;No comments about the length of my blog posts, please.&lt;a href="#fnref1" class="footnote-back"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 11 Apr 2016 21:35:00 -0400</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2016-04-11:/2016/run-with-me.html</guid><category>fitness</category><category>podcasting</category><category>design</category></item><item><title>Static Site Generators and Podcasting</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2016/static-site-generators-and-podcasting.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Presently, I publish both &lt;a href="http://www.winningslowly.org/"&gt;Winning Slowly&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="http://www.newrustacean.com/"&gt;New Rustacean&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href="#fn1" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref1"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; using what is admittedly a bit of a quirky approach. It works well for me, and I think it’s worth documenting for other nerdy types out there, but if you’re just getting going with podcasting and you’re looking for the easy way to do it, let me warn you: &lt;em&gt;this isn’t it&lt;/em&gt;. Something like &lt;a href="https://soundcloud.com/for/podcasting"&gt;SoundCloud&lt;/a&gt; and a blog for show notes, or &lt;a href="https://wordpress.org"&gt;WordPress&lt;/a&gt; with &lt;a href="https://wordpress.org/plugins/powerpress/"&gt;Blubrry PowerPress&lt;/a&gt; is what you want instead. This approach works &lt;em&gt;extremely&lt;/em&gt; well for statically-generated sites, however, and I imagine a few people out there might find it useful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section id="the-short-version" class="level2"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The short version&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Generate the feeds with &lt;a href="http://reinventedsoftware.com/feeder/"&gt;Feeder&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Generate the site statically with something else (and it &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; doesn’t matter what).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Copy the feed into the generated site.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="the-long-version" class="level2"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The long version&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I generate the sites themselves with &lt;a href="http://docs.getpelican.com/en/3.6.3/"&gt;Pelican&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="http://www.newrustacean.com/show_notes/e001/index.html"&gt;&lt;code&gt;cargo doc&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, respectively. I was already comfortable with Pelican because it’s what I use to generate &lt;em&gt;this&lt;/em&gt; site (with a few &lt;a href="https://github.com/chriskrycho/chriskrycho.com/blob/master/pelicanconf.py"&gt;tweaks&lt;/a&gt; to the standard configuration, especially using &lt;a href="http://pandoc.org/"&gt;Pandoc&lt;/a&gt; rather than the Python Markdown implementation), so I ran with it for building the Winning Slowly site, and it has worked quite well for building the site itself. It just gets built locally and deployed via &lt;a href="https://pages.github.com/"&gt;GitHub Pages&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, it does not have built-in support for generating &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/RSS_enclosure"&gt;podcast feeds&lt;/a&gt;, even just the general case with enclosures. &lt;a href="https://itunespartner.apple.com/en/podcasts/overview"&gt;iTunes podcast support&lt;/a&gt; would have taken a lot of work to add.&lt;a href="#fn2" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref2"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; Instead, I chose to build the RSS feed semi-manually. &lt;em&gt;Semi&lt;/em&gt;-manually, because doing it totally manually is a recipe for making mistakes. XML is many things, but “easy to write correctly by hand” is not one of them. I use &lt;a href="http://reinventedsoftware.com/feeder/"&gt;Feeder&lt;/a&gt; to manage the feeds, and &lt;em&gt;it&lt;/em&gt; makes sure that the enclosure and iTunes elements are set correctly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The biggest upside to this is that I can use Pelican without modification to how it generates feeds (apart from optionally turning them off entirely). It just &lt;a href="https://github.com/WinningSlowly/winningslowly.org/blob/master/pelicanconf.py#L99"&gt;copies&lt;/a&gt; the feed I generate to the output file during its normal build process. As suggested above, I also &lt;em&gt;don’t&lt;/em&gt; generate the other feeds which Pelican supports, as we have no need for them; we only care about the podcast feed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This process works equally well, with very little modification, for New Rustacean. In that case, I’m generating the content by running Rust’s documentation tool, &lt;code&gt;cargo doc&lt;/code&gt;&lt;a href="#fn3" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref3"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; to render the “API docs” which serve as show notes. Notice the family resemblance between &lt;a href="http://www.newrustacean.com/show_notes/"&gt;my “show notes”&lt;/a&gt; and, say, the &lt;a href="http://sgrif.github.io/diesel/diesel/index.html"&gt;Diesel docs&lt;/a&gt;, which are both generated the same way. This is &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; a normal way of building a podcast website; you can hear me explain why I did it this way in &lt;a href="http://www.newrustacean.com/show_notes/e001/index.html"&gt;New Rustacean e001: Document all the things!&lt;/a&gt; In any case, I just take the show note-relevant parts of the documentation and put it in Feeder, generate the feed, and &lt;a href="https://github.com/chriskrycho/newrustacean.com/blob/master/Makefile#L32"&gt;copy that as part of the build process&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That’s it!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section class="footnotes"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn1"&gt;&lt;p&gt;And, incidentally, &lt;a href="http://www.sap-py.com"&gt;Sap.py&lt;/a&gt; and my &lt;a href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/sermons.xml"&gt;sermons&lt;/a&gt; feed.&lt;a href="#fnref1" class="footnote-back"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn2"&gt;&lt;p&gt;If I stick with Pelican long-term, I might look into adding it anyway, but honestly, I don’t love Pelican. The reasons have little to do with Pelican for itself, and a lot more to do with my particular and somewhat peculiar needs. That’s a post for another day. In any case, I’m likelier to use another generator—even one I write myself!—than to do the work to make Pelican do what I want.&lt;a href="#fnref2" class="footnote-back"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn3"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Technically, Rust’s documentation tool is &lt;code&gt;rustdoc&lt;/code&gt;, which &lt;code&gt;cargo doc&lt;/code&gt; wraps around. I never actually use &lt;code&gt;rustdoc&lt;/code&gt; directly, though.&lt;a href="#fnref3" class="footnote-back"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 28 Feb 2016 12:50:00 -0500</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2016-02-28:/2016/static-site-generators-and-podcasting.html</guid><category>software development</category><category>podcasting</category><category>python</category><category>rust</category></item><item><title>Women in Rust</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2016/women-in-rust.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;i class=editorial&gt;I posted these bullet points last night as a series of tweets on my &lt;a href="https://www.twitter.com/chriskrycho"&gt;main account&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/chriskrycho/status/686007510147309568"&gt;∞ January 9, 2016 21:11&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A thing I’d really, really like to see change—this is from the &lt;a href="http://www.newrustacean.com/"&gt;New Rustacean&lt;/a&gt; Twitter data. Unsurprising, but awful:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src="//cdn.chriskrycho.com/images/new-rustacean-followers.png" alt="@newrustacean Twitter follower gender data" /&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.twitter.com/newrustacean"&gt;@newrustacean&lt;/a&gt; Twitter follower gender data&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/chriskrycho/status/686007729371148289"&gt;∞ January 9, 2016 21:12&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Takeaway: the &lt;a href="https://www.twitter.com/rustlang"&gt;@rustlang&lt;/a&gt; community has many strengths, but like every tech community, we need to improve here—a lot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/chriskrycho/status/686008145752272896"&gt;∞ January 9, 2016 21:14&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Standing offer: if you’re a female &lt;a href="https://www.twitter.com/rustlang"&gt;@rustlang&lt;/a&gt; dev, I’d &lt;em&gt;love&lt;/em&gt; to feature your experience learning Rust on the show.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/chriskrycho/status/686008527937245185"&gt;∞ January 9, 2016, 21:15&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ll be doing some interview &lt;a href="https://www.twitter.com/newrustacean"&gt;@newrustacean&lt;/a&gt; episodes soon-ish—I want as many female voices in the mix as possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 10 Jan 2016 15:25:00 -0500</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2016-01-10:/2016/women-in-rust.html</guid><category>podcasting</category><category>tweetstorm</category><category>rust</category></item><item><title>Thoughts on 2015 (and 2016)</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2015/thoughts-on-2015-and-2016.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;As we come to the end of the year, I have been reflecting on the things I set out to do this year, and on my hopes for the coming year. At the start of the year, I posted a number of goals for my “public” life this year, and I also wrote up a number of personal goals for myself. Goals are well and good, but if I do not evaluate how I did on them, and think about areas I succeeded and areas I failed, and on how I might do better in the future, those goals will not make much difference. (&lt;em&gt;Much&lt;/em&gt; difference, I say, because I have long found that even just having goals makes a difference in how I approach the year.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the start of the year, I posted a list of &lt;a href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2015/public-ish-plans.html"&gt;“Public-ish Plans”&lt;/a&gt;. My self-evaluation on those counts isn’t amazing. The Winning Slowly goals, I managed: we have separate pages for each season, and we recorded two more seasons—each one better than those before. Hosting things on Digital Ocean and migrating my wife’s blogs off of Blogger and WordPress, not so much (read: not at all, though I did &lt;em&gt;start&lt;/em&gt; writing a Ghost theme for her current WordPress site… and haven’t touched it in at least six months.) I wrote some music this year, but not three minutes worth—you &lt;em&gt;can&lt;/em&gt; hear all 37 seconds of it &lt;a href="https://soundcloud.com/chriskrycho"&gt;on SoundCloud&lt;/a&gt;. I wrote &lt;a href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/poetry/"&gt;poetry&lt;/a&gt;; I managed to average about one poem a month starting in March. I wrote a few essays, but nothing close to one per month. I posted a whopping two book reviews (out of the six I hoped for), and both of those were written for school. I managed to add a picture to the About page, but I didn’t even come close to blogging about the family on a monthly basis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In sum: about 50/50 on those goals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That said, I managed quite a few other things &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; on that list this year. I started learning Rust, and started &lt;a href="http://newrustacean.com/"&gt;a podcast about it&lt;/a&gt; which is easily the most successful online endeavor I’ve ever undertaken, with a good 500 regular listeners. (That’s a small crowd on the internet, but massively more than any writing I’ve done, and actually larger than Winning Slowly’s current audience.) I have basically carried home a major transition effort for my main software development client, and helped them bring a new developer up to speed. I landed a new software development job, doing things I’m much more passionate about, which I’ll be starting in mid-January. I ran a triathlon (and placed third in my age group), and I set another personal record in the half-marathon I ran this fall.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the lessons I take away from this last year, then, is that it’s important to set goals, but it’s also important to let those goals change over time. Some of those goals are still things I’d like to accomplish—like migrating us to DigitalOcean, and getting Jaimie’s sites off of Blogger especially. Another (fairly obvious one) is prioritizing. I had a lot of major goals for last year, and in retrospect, I think I had &lt;em&gt;too many&lt;/em&gt;. It’s hard to keep all of those in sight of the course of the year, especially with other professional and scholastic demands to meet (themselves often good in their own right).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With all of these things in mind, I’m planning to approach 2016 a little differently. I haven’t made formal goals yet, but I have come up with the basic outline I want to use going forward.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, I am going to set a single goal in each of five major categories in my life:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;spiritual:&lt;/strong&gt; everything in my walk with God, including my own personal devotions, my involvement in the life of the church, and my “ministry” actions in general&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;family:&lt;/strong&gt; both quantity and quality time spent with my wife and my quickly-growing-up little girls&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;personal:&lt;/strong&gt; podcasting, blogging, and writing for &lt;a href="http://mereorthodoxy.com/author/chris-krycho/"&gt;other outlets&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;professional:&lt;/strong&gt; working in my new job and as a consultant, and carrying on toward the conclusion of my M. Div.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;health/fitness:&lt;/strong&gt; continuing to stay healthy, including eating well and continuing to stay fit by running and doing triathlon work&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note that this list is intentionally &lt;em&gt;unordered&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;a href="#fn1" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref1"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; My spiritual life remains the highest priority, because if my walk with God falters, everything else will go amok. Beyond that, however, the amount of time and effort I invest in each category not only can but should vary over time. Family will broadly remain in the second of those slots, though there may be days or the occasional week where one of the other concerns &lt;em&gt;very temporarily&lt;/em&gt; takes a higher priority. The others will adjust relative to each other as need be: there will be times when school requires more, and so my own writing gets less time, and there will be times when I have more flexibility and so am able to devote more to those personal interests, and so on. The goal here is not the mythical notion of “balance” but rather faithfulness, which has some superficial similarities but ultimately &lt;a href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2015/faithfulness.html"&gt;plays out rather differently&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m hoping, in light of those goals, to set annual, monthly, and daily goals in each of those categories. The daily goals should help me move toward the monthly goals, and the monthly goals toward the yearly goals. I only get to set one goal in each of those categories for each tier: at five goals, that’s already plenty! I hope that evaluating each day will help me be more focused and faithful, and that situating daily and monthly goals each in light of larger goals will help me actually accomplish those larger goals. We’ll see how it goes, of course. I’ll be back in a week or so with whatever goals I decide to make public in those categories, and again in a year with an evaluation rather like this one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section class="footnotes"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn1"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Under the covers, it’s literally an HTML unordered list.&lt;a href="#fnref1" class="footnote-back"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 26 Dec 2015 13:30:00 -0500</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2015-12-26:/2015/thoughts-on-2015-and-2016.html</guid><category>family</category><category>rust</category><category>podcasting</category></item><item><title>On Editing Podcasts</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2015/on-editing-podcasts.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Last week, Alan Jacobs posted &lt;a href="http://text-patterns.thenewatlantis.com/2015/08/podcasts.html"&gt;a few thoughts&lt;/a&gt; on the overall quality of podcasts. While he’s &lt;a href="http://text-patterns.thenewatlantis.com/2015/08/podcasts-redux.html"&gt;since acknowledged&lt;/a&gt; that part of his challenge with podcasts is that his bar is extremely high, I think his original piece bears quoting and responding to briefly, including a few thoughts about how Stephen and I handle &lt;a href="http://www.winningslowly.org"&gt;Winning Slowly&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From his piece:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Podcasts, overall, are&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol type="1"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;People struggling to articulate for you stuff you could find out by looking it up on Wikipedia (e.g. In Our Time);&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;People using old-timey radio tricks to fool you into thinking that a boring and inconsequential story is fascinating (e.g. Serial);&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;People leveraging their celebrity in a given field as permission to ramble incoherently about whatever happens to come to their minds (e.g. The Talk Show); or&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;People using pointless audio-production tricks to make a pedestrian story seem cutting-edge (e.g. Radiolab).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I actually happen to basically agree with those critiques. However, one category he left out is: &lt;em&gt;people podcasting the way people blog&lt;/em&gt;. And this is where many of the most interesting podcasts I listen to come in. It’s also basically where Winning Slowly fits: you can think of our show like an audio version of a blog post. It’s not as carefully considered or edited as a long-form magazine piece (or, in its respective medium, a professionally produced radio show). But like blog posts, the fact that it’s a bit more off the cuff and that it’s &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; the incredibly tight work that you find in a magazine can actually be attractive at times. Many of my favorite podcasts are very conversational and not heavily produced.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But—and here I think Jacobs is absolutely correct—all of the shows I really enjoy make a point to edit their shows. They clean up the audio from artifacts, they cut segments that were off topic, they make sure the levels are good between the different members of the podcast, and so on. And while you don’t have to do those things to have a podcast, any more than you need to edit the things you write to have a blog, you do need to do them if you want to have a &lt;em&gt;good&lt;/em&gt; show. Sadly, this is where a number of shows I otherwise might enjoy show themselves to the door.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is a reason Stephen and I spent a whole &lt;a href="http://www.winningslowly.org/season-0.html"&gt;“beta” season&lt;/a&gt; of &lt;a href="http://www.winningslowly.org"&gt;Winning Slowly&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href="#fn1" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref1"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; working not only on what we wanted the show to be about, but finding its voice and tone, the structure of the episodes, and the quality of our audio. We wrestled with the audio output from mediocre microphones and adopted seemingly silly practices like putting blankets over our heads and microphones and laptops while recording so that we can get better sound spaces. We have taken the time to learn about compression and limiting and other audio editing techniques, and work hard to get the mix between our intro and outro music and our own voices correct. And we cut things mercilessly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, here is the blooper reel from &lt;a href="http://www.winningslowly.org/3.05/"&gt;3.05&lt;/a&gt;, which consists of only the &lt;em&gt;funny&lt;/em&gt; parts of what I cut from the show (there was probably as much again that I just removed and didn’t include):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;audio class="media-embed" title="3.05 Bloopers" controls preload="metadata"&gt;
&lt;source src="http://www.podtrac.com/pts/redirect.m4a/cdn.winningslowly.org/3.05-bloopers.m4a"&gt;
&lt;source src="http://www.podtrac.com/pts/redirect.mp3/cdn.winningslowly.org/3.05-bloopers.mp3"&gt;
&lt;/audio&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That doesn’t begin to touch all the “umms” and long pauses and overly heavy breathing and do-overs we cut out (though, because this was a particularly rough episode, it does give you an idea). The result, as I think most of our listeners would agree, is a show that’s pretty tight as far as the audio goes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In terms of content, different shows will have a different feel, of course. Some will require more planning. &lt;a href="http://www.newrustacean.com/"&gt;New Rustacean&lt;/a&gt;, a new show on learning Rust I’m hoping to launch later this week or early next week, requires a &lt;em&gt;lot&lt;/em&gt; of planning. &lt;a href="http://www.sap-py.com/"&gt;Sap.py&lt;/a&gt;, the fun little show my wife and I are about to launch, about her adventures in learning Python, requires basically &lt;em&gt;no&lt;/em&gt; planning. Winning Slowly doesn’t require a lot of formal planning, but it does require Stephen and me to keep a good eye on ongoing stories in our fields of technology, religion, ethics, and art, and to discuss big-picture ideas regularly and actively. Some episodes, we outline carefully (like the one we recorded today, which will come out next Tuesday). For others, we can basically just wing it (like the one we recorded a week ago and which comes out tomorrow). But if our podcast is good, and I really do think it is, it is because we take the time to work at making it good. Just like you have to do on a blog, or really anything else in life.&lt;a href="#fn2" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref2"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section class="footnotes"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn1"&gt;&lt;p&gt;13 published episodes, and one we dropped entirely!&lt;a href="#fnref1" class="footnote-back"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn2"&gt;&lt;p&gt;One big difference between a podcast and a blog is that it actually takes a lot &lt;em&gt;more&lt;/em&gt; work to make a good podcast than a good blog post. Audio editing is much more involved than editing writing, and speaking intelligently for any length of time—whether off the cuff, with a detailed outline, or as an interviewer—is much harder to get right than writing, where you can polish to your heart’s content.&lt;a href="#fnref2" class="footnote-back"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 24 Aug 2015 20:16:00 -0400</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2015-08-24:/2015/on-editing-podcasts.html</guid><category>podcasting</category></item><item><title>Hey, Look—A Podcast!</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2014/hey-look-a-podcast.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Today, I was happy to be able to finally go public with a project on which I have been working for the last couple months (and for which I have been planning since mid-fall): &lt;a href="http://www.winningslowly.org/"&gt;Winning Slowly&lt;/a&gt;. Winning Slowly is a biweeklypodcast by yours truly and my good friend &lt;a href="http://stephencarradini.com"&gt;Stephen Carradini&lt;/a&gt; offering thoughtful commentary on trends in culture, technology, religion, ethics, and art.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of possible interest to my readers:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You can listen to the first episode, &lt;a href="http://www.winningslowly.org/2014/01/we-need-some-context/"&gt;We Need Some Context!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You can &lt;a href="http://www.winningslowly.org/feed.xml"&gt;subscribe to the feed&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You can follow and get updates via all sorts of social networks:
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Twitter: &lt;a href="https://twitter.som/winningslowly"&gt;@winningslowly&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;App.net: &lt;a href="http://app.net/winningslowly"&gt;@winningslowly&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://broadcast.app.net/40022/winning-slowly-episodes/"&gt;App.net broadcast&lt;/a&gt; – notifications on your phone or emails as you like&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://plus.google.com/u/0/+WinningslowlyOrgCast/"&gt;Google+&lt;/a&gt; (yes, shockingly enough)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We’re still very much in a “beta” phase. The audio quality needs significant improvement, our back-and-forth needs to get smoother (and, at times, more back- and-forth!), and so on. We’d love to hear your feedback. But be gentle.&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 28 Jan 2014 20:20:00 -0500</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2014-01-28:/2014/hey-look-a-podcast.html</guid><category>podcasting</category></item></channel></rss>