<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Chris Krycho - pomodoro</title><link>http://v4.chriskrycho.com/</link><description></description><lastBuildDate>Mon, 29 Jul 2019 19:25:00 -0400</lastBuildDate><item><title>Update: Writing Down What I Do</title><link>http://v4.chriskrycho.com/2019/update-writing-down-what-i-do.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;a href="https://v4.chriskrycho.com/2018/assumed-audiences.html"&gt;Assumed Audience&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/b&gt; people already persuaded of the value—at least to some extent—of “getting things done” strategies and having an idea of what you accomplished over the course of the year.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A few months ago, I described &lt;a href="https://v4.chriskrycho.com/2018/just-write-down-what-you-do.html"&gt;my current workflow&lt;/a&gt; for tracking what I do every day, using &lt;a href="https://bear.app"&gt;Bear&lt;/a&gt;. I’m still doing that, but I’ve made one small tweak that makes for a &lt;em&gt;much&lt;/em&gt; nicer experience, and I figured I’d write that up for anyone else who’s thinking about using Bear in a similar way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The main pain point I’d had using Bear as a daily logging app is that I &lt;em&gt;also&lt;/em&gt; use it for &lt;a href="https://v4.chriskrycho.com/zettelkasten/"&gt;my general note-taking&lt;/a&gt;, and I increasingly found that my pomodoro logs ended up mostly being &lt;em&gt;clutter&lt;/em&gt; in my overall list of notes. I also realized that I don’t look at, say, my daily logs past the end of a week, weekly logs past the end of the month, and so on. However, I &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt; like keeping them around through at least the end of my performance review cycle in case I want to drill down into more details about a particular task or accomplishment. I wasn’t really sure how to enjoy both long-term access and shoretr-term eliminating of clutter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then I noticed that Bear has an Archive function:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src="https://cdn.chriskrycho.com/file/chriskrycho-com/images/archive-bear.png" alt="" /&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Archiving in Bear&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Archiving removes your notes from your normal list view and makes them non-editable. However, they remain searchable in your library and wiki-style navigation links, like &lt;code&gt;[[2019.07.21]]&lt;/code&gt;, still work. This is &lt;em&gt;exactly&lt;/em&gt; what I wanted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once I discovered this, I made one very small tweak to my previous flow: whenever I do the work of summarizing a given time-span, I simply archive all the notes at the level below that. So, for example, after copying the daily summaries into a week and summarizing that week, I simply archive all the day entries. Any given set of logs only ever has a handful of notes in it—at most 12, in the case of my year-level log. This made the already-great experience of using Bear for this kind of logging that much better. Again: I commend it to you!&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 29 Jul 2019 19:25:00 -0400</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:v4.chriskrycho.com,2019-07-29:/2019/update-writing-down-what-i-do.html</guid><category>productivity</category><category>pomodoro</category><category>getting things done</category></item><item><title>My Current Setup</title><link>http://v4.chriskrycho.com/2019/my-current-setup.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;a href="https://v4.chriskrycho.com/2018/assumed-audiences.html"&gt;Assumed Audience&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/b&gt; people interested in productivity and work flow and app choice.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A friend was asking me the other day what my workflow looks like, and while I don’t generally spend a &lt;em&gt;lot&lt;/em&gt; of time writing about my working setup, I figured I’d throw up a quick post representing my &lt;em&gt;current&lt;/em&gt; list so that if people ask I can point them here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Two important notes on this, though: First, this is &lt;em&gt;just what I use&lt;/em&gt;. I make no particular claim that it’s &lt;em&gt;the best&lt;/em&gt;. There are lots of things here that are very specific to me and the way I work, and even to my specific mental quirks. Second, it’s far more important to care about the work you do than about the tools you use to get it done. The tools matter: some people say they don’t and I don’t think that’s right at all. But they don’t matter as much as they might &lt;em&gt;feel&lt;/em&gt; like they do, and tool fetishism is real. I think the happy point is finding tools which are good enough and fit comfortably enough into your workflow that they don’t &lt;em&gt;distract&lt;/em&gt; you, and then get back to the work you do!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;section id="software-development" class="level2"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Software development&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For software development, I currently use:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://code.visualstudio.com"&gt;VS Code&lt;/a&gt; as my primary text editor; I also occasionally use Sublime Text or Vim for specific tasks where it makes sense. Code is incredibly fast, impressively low in memory usage given it’s an Electron app, and remarkably customizable. My only outstanding complaint is that there’s no way to actually make it look like a native macOS app. Happily, I &lt;em&gt;can&lt;/em&gt; make it &lt;em&gt;behave&lt;/em&gt; like a native macOS app in all the ways that matter to me. Its support for both TypeScript and Rust—the two languages I spend the most time with right now—is &lt;em&gt;great&lt;/em&gt;. You’re welcome to see &lt;a href="https://gist.github.com/chriskrycho/f39442dd78ad6d150bcaaadd9fedf9f4"&gt;my full configuration&lt;/a&gt;; I keep it updated at that location via the &lt;a href="https://marketplace.visualstudio.com/items?itemName=Shan.code-settings-sync"&gt;Settings Sync&lt;/a&gt; plugin.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;macOS’ built-in Terminal app, just using its tabs for individual tasks. I have spent a lot of time with alternatives, including &lt;a href="https://iterm2.com"&gt;iTerm 2&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://sw.kovidgoyal.net/kitty/"&gt;kitty&lt;/a&gt;, and I’m comfortable in &lt;a href="https://github.com/tmux/tmux/wiki"&gt;tmux&lt;/a&gt; – but at the end of the day I just like the way Terminal &lt;em&gt;feels&lt;/em&gt; the best. It’s fast, light, and built-in macOS things all just work correctly out of the box.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://git-fork.com"&gt;Fork&lt;/a&gt; for a &lt;a href="https://git-scm.com"&gt;git&lt;/a&gt; &lt;abbr&gt;GUI&lt;/abbr&gt;. I’ve also used &lt;a href="https://www.git-tower.com"&gt;Tower&lt;/a&gt; in the past, but I’ve found Fork to be lighter, faster, and a better fit for the way I think and how I expect things to behave (e.g. for interactive rebasing). I do a ton of work in git on the command line as well.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;A mix, varying day by day, of Safari Tech Preview, Firefox, and Chrome for my test browsers. I substantially prefer Safari in nearly every way, but Chrome’s dev tools remain best in class for most things—with the exception of Grid, where Firefox is still the undisputed champion. (When I can, I do most of my JavaScript/TypeScript debugging in VS Code, though: it’s a much better experience.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://kapeli.com/dash"&gt;Dash&lt;/a&gt; for offline documentation access. There are other options out there, including some which are free, but Dash remains the best in my experience, and if nothing else it’s deeply integrated into my workflow and muscle memory.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That’s basically the whole list at the moment. I keep my software development workflow fairly light.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="research-and-writing" class="level2"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Research and writing&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For research and writing, I use:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://ia.net/writer"&gt;iA Writer&lt;/a&gt; for all my blogging and longer-form writing. This is a recent change; I had been a heavy user of &lt;a href="http://www.ulysses.app"&gt;Ulysses&lt;/a&gt; for the last few years. However, while Ulysses was the best option I had found for how I work, it’s never been quite &lt;em&gt;right&lt;/em&gt; for me. For one, I’ve always found Ulysses’ “feel” to be a bit heavy: it’s &lt;em&gt;just&lt;/em&gt; noticeably slower for me than most of the other writing apps, and I’m hypersensitive to input latency. I’ve also always disliked one of the things that makes many people love it: the way it abstracts Markdown into its “smart text objects.” iA Writer gives me the ability to manage a library in much the same way that Ulysses did, but in a way that feels more truly native on both macOS and iOS; it just uses normal Markdown (no fancy text objects); and it’s &lt;em&gt;fast&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;a href="#fn1" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref1" role="doc-noteref"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; That combo makes it a better fit for me.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://bear.app"&gt;Bear&lt;/a&gt; for my note-taking. I’ve talked about this &lt;a href="https://v4.chriskrycho.com/2018/starting-to-build-a-zettelkasten.html"&gt;a fair bit&lt;/a&gt; here &lt;a href="https://v4.chriskrycho.com/2018/zettelkasten-update-all-in-on-bear.html"&gt;before&lt;/a&gt;, so I won’t belabor the details. It’s an excellent, lightweight note-taking app. The main way it falls down for me is that it does not really handle nested block content in Markdown documents (e.g. it won’t correctly display a block quote inside another block quote, or a code sample inside a list, etc.). I’d also love it if it stored its library in a way that made it easier for me to interact with from other apps, i.e. as plain text on the local drive. (You can export content from it easily enough, which is great, but it’s not quite as seamless as I’d like.) Those nits are just that, though: nits. I’m very happy with Bear for my note-taking at this point.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.goldenhillsoftware.com/unread/"&gt;Unread&lt;/a&gt; on iOS for reading RSS, with &lt;a href="https://feedbin.com"&gt;Feedbin&lt;/a&gt; as my long-preferred RSS feed service backing it. (I’m a fan of paying for these kinds of services, so I’m happy to lay out the $5/month for Feedbin. Free alternatives exist, but I don’t love ad-driven models and avoid them where I can.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You’ll note that there are no apps for reading &lt;em&gt;longer&lt;/em&gt; material on that list. I could mention Apple Books as the place I read most ebooks I read, but that’s more a function of the alternatives not being meaningfully &lt;em&gt;better&lt;/em&gt; in the ways I care about.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="productivity" class="level2"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;“Productivity”&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For “productivity” concerns, I use:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://tadamapp.com"&gt;Tadam&lt;/a&gt; for a Pomodoro timer—because it’s precisely as annoyingly obtrusive as I need it to be, which is &lt;em&gt;very&lt;/em&gt;!—and &lt;a href="https://bear.app"&gt;Bear&lt;/a&gt; for &lt;a href="https://v4.chriskrycho.com/2018/just-write-down-what-you-do.html"&gt;tracking&lt;/a&gt; what I do each Pomodoro cycle, each day, each week, each month, and each year. That habit remains very helpful for me.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://culturedcode.com"&gt;Things&lt;/a&gt; for a to-do app. Things hits the sweet spot for me in terms of its ability to manage everything from simple tasks and recurring to-do items around the house up to complex multi-month-long projects. I particularly like its distinction between when I want to be &lt;em&gt;reminded&lt;/em&gt; about something and when that task is &lt;em&gt;due&lt;/em&gt;. I’ve used &lt;a href="https://www.omnigroup.com/omnifocus/"&gt;OmniFocus&lt;/a&gt; in the past, but it never quite &lt;em&gt;fit&lt;/em&gt; me; Things does. They’re very comparable in terms of features; it’s just that the way Things approaches those features works better for me.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://sparkmailapp.com"&gt;Spark&lt;/a&gt; as my email client, mostly for its snooze feature, which I use when I know I need to see an email &lt;em&gt;as an email&lt;/em&gt; sometime later, and its ability to integrate nicely with other apps. I have it connect to Things, and emails that require an &lt;em&gt;action&lt;/em&gt; get put there instead of snoozed. The combination lets me keep my inbox at Zero by the end of every day. And its lovely “Inbox Zero” images are a really nice touch:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src="https://f001.backblazeb2.com/file/chriskrycho-com/images/inbox-zero-spark.png" alt="" /&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Inbox Zero in Spark&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="podcasting" class="level2"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Podcasting&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For podcast production, I use:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.izotope.com/en/products/repair-and-edit/rx.html"&gt;iZotope RX&lt;/a&gt; (I’m using v6 Standard) for audio cleanup, as I &lt;a href="https://v4.chriskrycho.com/2018/izotope-rx-is-amazing.html"&gt;recently wrote about&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.apple.com/logic-pro/"&gt;Logic Pro X&lt;/a&gt; for the actual editing work most of the time, occasionally using &lt;a href="https://www.wooji-juice.com/products/ferrite/"&gt;Ferrite&lt;/a&gt;. Logic is overkill for what I do, but I’m &lt;em&gt;fast&lt;/em&gt; with it at this point, so I can’t see moving anytime soon, and there’s nothing else out there that I think is substantially &lt;em&gt;better&lt;/em&gt; (though there are other apps that are comparably good).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.overcast.fm/forecast"&gt;Forecast&lt;/a&gt; for encoding and including chapter breaks.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://reinventedsoftware.com/feeder/"&gt;Feeder&lt;/a&gt; for generating the &lt;abbr&gt;RSS&lt;/abbr&gt; feeds, since all my podcasts are currently built in ways that don’t support &lt;abbr&gt;RSS&lt;/abbr&gt; feed generation: &lt;a href="http://docs.getpelican.com/en/stable/"&gt;Pelican&lt;/a&gt; for &lt;a href="https://winningslowly.org"&gt;Winning Slowly&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://massaffection.com"&gt;Mass Affection&lt;/a&gt;,&lt;a href="#fn2" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref2" role="doc-noteref"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://doc.rust-lang.org/rustdoc"&gt;rustdoc&lt;/a&gt; for &lt;a href="https://newrustacean.com"&gt;New Rustacean&lt;/a&gt;. (If I ever manage to finish building my own site generator, it’ll have out-of-the-box support for custom RSS feed templates, so that I can have this stuff generated automatically for me!)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.netlify.com"&gt;Netlify&lt;/a&gt; for serving the actual static site content (i.e. HTML, CSS, and JS), and &lt;a href="https://www.backblaze.com/b2"&gt;Backblaze B2&lt;/a&gt; for hosting the audio.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://panic.com/transmit/"&gt;Transmit&lt;/a&gt; for actually uploading the audio files.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn1" role="doc-endnote"&gt;&lt;p&gt;iA Writer seems to get &lt;em&gt;randomly&lt;/em&gt; slow at times for reasons I haven’t yet identified, but at least for now, I’m taking that tradeoff over Ulysses’ habit of being a bit slow &lt;em&gt;all the time&lt;/em&gt;. As I’ve often noted before: &lt;a href="https://v4.chriskrycho.com/2016/ulysses-byword-and-just-right.html" title="Ulysses, Byword, and “Just Right”"&gt;my ideal writing app doesn’t exist&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;a href="#fnref1" class="footnote-back" role="doc-backlink"&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn2" role="doc-endnote"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Mass Affection isn’t dead! I promise!&lt;a href="#fnref2" class="footnote-back" role="doc-backlink"&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 19 Jan 2019 09:00:00 -0500</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:v4.chriskrycho.com,2019-01-19:/2019/my-current-setup.html</guid><category>productivity</category><category>pomodoro</category><category>apps</category><category>writing</category><category>reading</category><category>software development</category></item><item><title>Log All the Things!</title><link>http://v4.chriskrycho.com/2017/log-all-the-things.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;For the past few weeks, I’ve tried adding something new to my existing &lt;a href="http://v4.chriskrycho.com/2016/2016-review-5.html" title="Getting things done in 2016 and beyond"&gt;pomodoro routine&lt;/a&gt;: a daily and weekly summary of what I’ve done.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over the past few years, I’ve been a fairly steady practitioner of the habit of marking what I do in any given 25-minute work cycle. However, I’ve felt of late that while I usually had a good sense of what my goals had been and whether I had accomplished them for any given small &lt;em&gt;part&lt;/em&gt; of the day, I didn’t have a clear sense of what I had done over the day as a whole—much less at the end of a whole week.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I just started summarizing it at the end of each day, or early the next day, and pulling those summaries into a single document at the end of the week. (If you’re curious, I’ve been doing all of this in &lt;a href="http://www.bear-writer.com/"&gt;Bear&lt;/a&gt;, which of course I use in its Markdown mode.) So on any given Friday, I can actually look at my week as a whole and have some concrete sense of what I’ve accomplished.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ve only done this for the past three weeks, but I &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; like it and I intend to keep it up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The main thing I need to figure out how to integrate into it is non-work tasks. And really, that goes for my life in general right now. I’m &lt;a href="http://v4.chriskrycho.com/2017/on-decompression.html" title="On Decompression"&gt;still sorting through&lt;/a&gt; what it looks like to just be working a full-time job and having a few side projects. But I’d like to be able to look back at the end of each month and boil down those weekly summaries, and at the end of the year likewise with the months—and from the combination, actually know a bit more concretely what my year was like.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We’ll see how it goes. I’m sure I’ll be back with more to say in this space soon enough.&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 07 Jul 2017 20:00:00 -0400</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:v4.chriskrycho.com,2017-07-07:/2017/log-all-the-things.html</guid><category>productivity</category><category>pomodoro</category></item><item><title>2016 in Review, Part 5 of 6</title><link>http://v4.chriskrycho.com/2016/2016-review-5.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;i class='editorial'&gt;I originally drafted a single, mammoth post reflecting on this whole year—but at more than 6,000 words, that seemed like a bit much. As such, I’ve broken it into a series of posts, to be published daily through the start of the new year. Hopefully they’re a bit more digestible that way!&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://v4.chriskrycho.com/2016/2016-review-intro.html"&gt;Introduction, or: a ridiculous year summarized&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://v4.chriskrycho.com/2016/2016-review-1.html"&gt;Part 1: Or: a ridiculous year summarized!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://v4.chriskrycho.com/2016/2016-review-2.html"&gt;Part 2: So. many. words. I had no idea how many words.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://v4.chriskrycho.com/2016/2016-review-3.html"&gt;Part 3: Podcasting: Winning Slowly, New Rustacean, and more!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://v4.chriskrycho.com/2016/2016-review-4.html"&gt;Part 4: Writing software for Olo and for open source.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Part 5: Getting things done in 2016 and beyond. (this post)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://v4.chriskrycho.com/2017/2016-review-6.html"&gt;Part 6: Plans for 2017!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At a number of points over the last few years, I’ve tackled the question of productivity. I always have far more I &lt;em&gt;want&lt;/em&gt; to get done than I’m able to actually get to. A few of those posts:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://v4.chriskrycho.com/2014/boosting-my-productivity.html" title="Boosting My Productivity"&gt;Boosting My Productivity&lt;/a&gt; (December, 2014)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://v4.chriskrycho.com/2016/a-new-schedule.html" title="A New Schedule"&gt;A New Schedule: Trying to make better use of my time toward my goals&lt;/a&gt; (July 2016)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A common theme of all productivity plans, of course, is that one can get more focused on the details of the plan than on actually being productive! I’m happy to say, however, that this &lt;em&gt;wasn’t&lt;/em&gt; the case for me with these productivity approaches. First, I have never allowed myself to be slavish about them. If I need to do something different on a given day, I do something different. Second, I am generally able to remember that the point of the plan is &lt;em&gt;what I’m getting done&lt;/em&gt;. So with that in mind, some comments particularly on the plan I sketched out &lt;a href="http://v4.chriskrycho.com/2016/a-new-schedule.html" title="A New Schedule"&gt;mid-year this year&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I fell off that wagon almost immediately. Readers who’ve stuck with me through these various updates will note that this ambitious plan preceded my disastrous 20-mile run and the ensuing bout of walking pneumonia by a matter of days. It took me until September to get back on the horse, so to speak, because even after I got over being sick, I was traveling—and nothing throws off my schedule like traveling! Happily, I got quite a bit done both during the conference trip I took and during the week I was in Colorado for my youngest sister’s wedding, but it wasn’t until after both of those that I was able to settle back into the routine I’d aimed for.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The major themes of that post were a detailed plan for my days, cutting out a lot of my social media, and thinking about weekends. The detailed plan for my days I kept off and on. I never consistently managed to have the block of time-for-side-projects at the end of my days, and that increasingly meant those things cut into weekends (impacting that goal as well). As for social media, that’s largely been a success: I now rarely get on Facebook, and only check Twitter from time to time. Certainly neither is much of a timesink anymore. I do continue to make heavy use of Slack outside of work, but I’ve found a good balance there (and the main communities I’m a part of have gone through their own adjustments as we’ve &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; found the need for this kind of focus and balance).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So it wasn’t perfect, but I did find it a very useful approach overall. I fully expect to stick with something very like it in 2017. Hopefully I won’t be pulling as many 10–11 hour days as I was in the latter half of 2016—but regardless, building this new discipline around the overall structure of each day was very helpful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One &lt;em&gt;big&lt;/em&gt; part of my approach to productivity that I’m definitely going to keep is the “pomodoro” technique. I first mentioned this in the &lt;a href="http://v4.chriskrycho.com/2014/boosting-my-productivity.html" title="Boosting My Productivity"&gt;first&lt;/a&gt; discussion I posted about this, but I’ve embraced it more and more. I work in 25-minute blocks, punctuated by 5-minute breaks. Nearly all of those 5-minute breaks entail walking, and as a result I get about 2–3 miles of walking in every day on top of my runs. That helps enormously with focus. This fall, I also embraced the &lt;em&gt;other&lt;/em&gt; half of the pomodoro technique: writing down goals and outcomes for each of those 25-minute blocks. Even more than the daily goals I discussed in the opening post of this series, this lower level of tracking has proved very helpful. It has given me a sense of what I have actually accomplished each day, and it has also helped me &lt;em&gt;focus&lt;/em&gt; as I’m trying to keep moving on various tasks each day. I highly recommend using the pomodoro approach (adapted as necessary to your particular circumstances, of course) as a tool for that kind of focus and productivity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’d be remiss if I didn’t also note the following &lt;em&gt;very&lt;/em&gt; substantial factors in my productivity:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;fitness/health:&lt;/strong&gt; if I’m active, I focus better. People say they don’t have time to exercise; I mean it when I say I don’t have time &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; to. I keep it pretty simple: running, cycling, swimming, and body-weight strength stuff. But I do it basically every day. And we eat fairly healthily. Both of those are incredibly important.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;sleep:&lt;/strong&gt; no matter how busy I am, I don’t pull all-nighters or anything of the sort. I get a minimum of 6 and usually 7–7½ hours of sleep every night. Even when I’m tired from pulling week after week of 10-hour work days, I can keep going because I get enough sleep.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;no commute:&lt;/strong&gt; working remotely is awesome for a lot of reasons, but one of them is that I don’t lose the hour or three every day to the road/subway/etc. that many people I know do. That’s a &lt;em&gt;lot&lt;/em&gt; of time over the course of a year. 48 working weeks means if you commute for an hour total every day, that’s 240 hours a year—that’s 30 8-hour days worth of “getting things done”.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perhaps at some point after I finish seminary I will expand the various things I do in productivity into a more complete series, but this gives you a good idea of what 2016 looked like, and what I expect 2017 to look like!&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 31 Dec 2016 09:30:00 -0500</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:v4.chriskrycho.com,2016-12-31:/2016/2016-review-5.html</guid><category>writing</category><category>podcasting</category><category>software development</category><category>family</category><category>productivity</category><category>fitness</category><category>2016-in-review</category><category>pomodoro</category></item><item><title>Boosting My Productivity</title><link>http://v4.chriskrycho.com/2014/boosting-my-productivity.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;This fall, I have had a lot on my plate: building HolyBible.com, continuing to work for Quest Consultants, and doing a pastoral ministry internship. I needed to be more productive—a lot more. Happily, I have been, and it only took three small changes.&lt;a href="#fn1" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref1" role="doc-noteref"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section id="use-a-to-do-list" class="level2"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Use a To-Do List&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Making a list of items to accomplish has been incredibly helpful. I started using &lt;a href="https://www.omnigroup.com/omnifocus/"&gt;OmniFocus&lt;/a&gt; in August for class due dates and any work tasks not tracked in other ways.&lt;a href="#fn2" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref2" role="doc-noteref"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; At that point, I organized everything—a bit too much, actually. Over the last couple months, I took some good advice I have seen in a number of places:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do not over-organize. Most tasks can go in a simple inbox.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hit your due dates. Making it a habit to hit every due date will help you not to miss important tasks.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do not put due dates on things that do not need them. You will eventually stop paying attention to them—and also to the due dates that &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt; matter.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I try to knock out a few small things from my Inbox every day, and hit all the due dates I set for myself. I am missing fewer things, getting more things done, and getting them done sooner than I did before. I like my app, but I know people who have just used an old-fashioned planner. The trick is to find a strategy that works for you.&lt;a href="#fn3" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref3" role="doc-noteref"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="email-is-not-a-to-do-list" class="level2"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Email Is &lt;em&gt;Not&lt;/em&gt; A To-Do List&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At some point, I got in the habit of using my email as a to-do list. In theory, seeing a list of unanswered emails every day should have motivated me to respond to them. In reality, they just sat there and slowly piled up. At best, they nagged at me. At worst, I basically forgot them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I started using OmniFocus, I killed this habit. Now I make a task for anything I need to act on, and I delete or archive everything else.&lt;a href="#fn4" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref4" role="doc-noteref"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;4&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; If the task is time-sensitive, I put a due date on it; otherwise, my third rule above applies. I also have a repeating task reminding me to empty my inbox at the end of each day (“Inbox Zero”). Having an empty inbox at the end of every day removes a certain amount of mental baggage: I have a task for everything I &lt;em&gt;need&lt;/em&gt; to act on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="take-breaks" class="level2"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Take breaks&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, I have started using the &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pomodoro_Technique"&gt;“pomodoro”&lt;/a&gt; technique. The basic approach is to work steadily for 25 minutes, then take a 5 minute break.&lt;a href="#fn5" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref5" role="doc-noteref"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;5&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; After four such cycles, I take a slightly longer break—usually 15 minutes. On each break, I walk around and do something unrelated to whatever I am working on. I also write down a brief summary of what I did on that cycle.&lt;a href="#fn6" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref6" role="doc-noteref"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;6&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; There is nothing complicated about this: I just use a simple timer to track the work and break cycles.&lt;a href="#fn7" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref7" role="doc-noteref"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;7&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; I have seen a &lt;em&gt;dramatic&lt;/em&gt; improvement in my ability to sustain my concentration on my tasks throughout the day since I started.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are a few reasons for that improvement. First, I have dedicated break times, so I know that I can go check social media, read tech and news sites, etc. &lt;em&gt;later&lt;/em&gt;. That makes it easier to concentrate on work for the blocks in between; the distractions can wait. Second, it puts a limit on those break times. We have all been surprised to find we have lost an hour reading online; using a timer helps prevent that. Third, getting up and moving around helps keep my brain active—I can tell that the movement considerably improves my alertness and concentration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These breaks have other benefits, too. There is mounting evidence that sitting all day is terrible for our health. Even exercising as much as I do &lt;a href="http://www.npr.org/2011/04/25/135575490/sitting-all-day-worse-for-you-than-you-might-think" title="Sitting All Day: Worse For You Than You Might Think"&gt;cannot fully counteract&lt;/a&gt; a sedentary lifestyle. However, there is also evidence that getting up and moving on a regular basis &lt;em&gt;does&lt;/em&gt; help. Walking briskly, I usually manage a fifth or a quarter of a mile on a five-minute break. That adds up over the course of a day: if I am disciplined about walking on my breaks, I regularly walk 2–3 miles in a day, even with lunch and other non-walking breaks in the mix.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have also found the breaks spiritually helpful. One of the requirements for my pastoral ministry internship was to memorize Ephesians. Five-minute breaks are &lt;em&gt;perfect&lt;/em&gt; for memorizing and reviewing Scripture, so I was able to be productive on those breaks, even while letting my brain relax from my other work. It is similarly useful for dedicated times of prayer throughout the day. The combination of scripture memory and prayer has been invaluable in combatting sin and stirring up my affections for Christ.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In short, I get a triple benefit by doing pomodoros. I am more productive when I am working, my body will remain healthier because I am less sedentary, and I am growing in holiness and intimacy with God. Of all the changes I made this semester, incorporating pomodoros into my day has been the most important, and I plan to make it a regular part of my life henceforth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn1" role="doc-endnote"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is just what I do. It may not work for you. It may even drive you crazy.&lt;a href="#fnref1" class="footnote-back" role="doc-backlink"&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn2" role="doc-endnote"&gt;&lt;p&gt;I.e., things not covered by JIRA, Trello, Bitbucket issues, etc.&lt;a href="#fnref2" class="footnote-back" role="doc-backlink"&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn3" role="doc-endnote"&gt;&lt;p&gt;While &lt;a href="https://www.omnigroup.com/omnifocus/"&gt;OmniFocus&lt;/a&gt; suits me, I would recommend &lt;a href="https://en.todoist.com/"&gt;Todoist&lt;/a&gt; to most people instead: it is less expensive and easier to use, and while it does not do &lt;em&gt;everything&lt;/em&gt; OmniFocus does, it can easily do everything most people need.&lt;a href="#fnref3" class="footnote-back" role="doc-backlink"&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn4" role="doc-endnote"&gt;&lt;p&gt;I archive order confirmations, messages from friends, and work conversations, and delete everything else.&lt;a href="#fnref4" class="footnote-back" role="doc-backlink"&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn5" role="doc-endnote"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Why the 25/5 pattern? That seems to be a limit in human cognition; it lines up closely with research on student attention spans in the classroom.&lt;a href="#fnref5" class="footnote-back" role="doc-backlink"&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn6" role="doc-endnote"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This helps me see what I have done over the course of a day and gives me a sense of progress. It is also extremely useful when writing up a weekly report for an employer.&lt;a href="#fnref6" class="footnote-back" role="doc-backlink"&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn7" role="doc-endnote"&gt;&lt;p&gt;I have used &lt;a href="http://www.tomighty.org/"&gt;Tomighty&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/app/pomodoro-one/id907364780?mt=12"&gt;Pomodoro One&lt;/a&gt;, which are both free and work well. The app is not the point, though: an old-fashioned kitchen timer will do just as well.&lt;a href="#fnref7" class="footnote-back" role="doc-backlink"&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 18 Dec 2014 08:05:00 -0500</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:v4.chriskrycho.com,2014-12-18:/2014/boosting-my-productivity.html</guid><category>email</category><category>inbox zero</category><category>productivity</category><category>pomodoro</category></item></channel></rss>