<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Chris Krycho</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/</link><description></description><atom:link href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/feeds/prayers.xml" rel="self"></atom:link><lastBuildDate>Sun, 12 Jan 2014 11:15:00 -0500</lastBuildDate><item><title>Prayer of Thanksgiving</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2014/prayer-thanksgiving-jan-12-2014.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Oh God—our creator and father; our savior-king, lord, and friend; our helper, teacher, and comforter—thank you for your unfailing love toward us. We marvel: you are the lord of light and of life, the maker of heaven and earth; you have set your glory above the heavens, and yet you are mindful of men and women like us. And not only mindful! You delight in us and love us in spite of our rebellion against you. You gave infinitely of yourself that we might be redeemed. Oh Lord, how majestic is your name in all the earth!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As we have gathered here to worship, and as we bring you these gifts, we remember that everything we give to you is yours already. You do not &lt;em&gt;need&lt;/em&gt; anything of us; everything in all the world is yours already. All that we have we have from you—not only our possessions, but even our lives—so we pray that you be exalted in our giving, in our singing, and in the preached word. May we be those who in our giving gladly demonstrate that you are more precious to us than the things of this world. May Christ be exalted in our own hearts, in the work of this congregation, in the lives of the members of this church, in the community around us, and in the efforts of missionaries around the world as we give. Thank you so much for your steadfast love toward us!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We pray all these things in the name of Jesus Christ our risen Lord. Amen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="references"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 12 Jan 2014 11:15:00 -0500</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2014-01-12:2014/prayer-thanksgiving-jan-12-2014.html</guid><category>prayers</category></item></channel></rss>