<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Chris Krycho</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/</link><description></description><atom:link href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/feeds/quotes.xml" rel="self"></atom:link><lastBuildDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2014 21:25:00 -0500</lastBuildDate><item><title>Worship Leader</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2014/worship-leader.html</link><description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A faithful worship leader magnifies the greatness of God in Jesus Christ
through the power of the Holy Spirit by skillfully combining God&amp;#8217;s Word with
music, thereby motivating the gathered church to proclaim the gospel, to
cherish God&amp;#8217;s presence, and to live for God&amp;#8217;s&amp;nbsp;glory.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2014 21:25:00 -0500</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2014-12-02:2014/worship-leader.html</guid><category>quotes</category></item><item><title>Doctrine</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2014/doctrine.html</link><description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Doctrine is not merely an affair of the tongue, but of the life; is not
apprehended by the intellect and memory merely, like other branches of
learning; but is received only when it possesses the whole soul, and finds its
seat and habitation in the inmost recesses of the heart&amp;#8230;. To doctrine in
which our religion is contained we have given the first place, since by it our
salvation commences; but it must be transfused into the breast, and pass into
the conduct, and so transform us into itself, as not to prove&amp;nbsp;unfruitful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 04 Nov 2014 23:02:00 -0500</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2014-11-04:2014/doctrine.html</guid><category>quotes</category></item><item><title>Soul History</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2014/soul-history.html</link><description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The short story is the pastoral form for narrating &lt;em&gt;Heilsgeschichte&lt;/em&gt;
(salvation history) in the vocabulary of &lt;em&gt;Seelsgeschichte&lt;/em&gt; (soul history). In
the &lt;em&gt;Heilsgeschichte&lt;/em&gt; of Judges, for instance, the enmity of the Midianiites
is kerygmatically integrated into the historical narrative and shown to be a
part of salvation; in the &lt;em&gt;Seelsgeschichte&lt;/em&gt; of Ruth the bitter emptiness of
Naomi is pastorally attended to under the dynamics of providence and guided to
a concluding fullness. In the &lt;em&gt;Heilsgeschichte&lt;/em&gt; of Exodus the formidable and
unyielding Egyptians are judged and defeated in the catastrophic plagues and
miraculous sea crossing; in the &lt;em&gt;Seelsgeschichte&lt;/em&gt; of Ruth the everday
ordinariness of gleaning in the barley fields is used as a means for
accomplishing redemption. In the &lt;em&gt;Heilsgeschichte&lt;/em&gt; of Joshua the gigantically
walled fortress Jericho is surrounded and conquered by the total community of
God in colorful parade, accompanied by brilliantly sounding trumpets, and the
promised land is entered; in the &lt;em&gt;Seelsgeschichte&lt;/em&gt; of Ruth an old levirate law
is patiently and quietly worked through by some old men at the city gates of
provincial Bethlehem, and a link is forged in the genealogical chain of the&amp;nbsp;Messiah.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 28 Mar 2014 13:05:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2014-03-28:2014/soul-history.html</guid><category>quotes</category></item></channel></rss>