<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Chris Krycho - reading</title><link>http://v4.chriskrycho.com/</link><description></description><lastBuildDate>Sat, 17 Aug 2019 09:25:00 -0400</lastBuildDate><item><title>Review: Shades of Milk and Honey</title><link>http://v4.chriskrycho.com/2019/review-shades-of-milk-and-honey.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;i class=editorial&gt;I keep my book review ratings simple—they’re either &lt;em&gt;required&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;recommended&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;recommended with qualifications&lt;/em&gt;, or &lt;em&gt;not recommended&lt;/em&gt;. If you want the TL;DR, this is it:&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Recommended:&lt;/b&gt; Regency period piece styled with language and plot reminiscent of an Austen novel… but with more magic and less irony and social commentary. I picked it up because I &lt;a href="https://v4.chriskrycho.com/2018/the-calculating-stars.html"&gt;loved&lt;/a&gt; her Lady Astronaut books and Jaimie has loved this series for years. In a turn I did not expect (because, well, this is not my genre!), it proved not only to be &lt;em&gt;good&lt;/em&gt; (which I did expect) but also to be a genuine page-turner; I stayed up late one night last week to finish it. A nice little magic system, excellent use of period literary style, good characters, engaging plot. Will read the rest of the series!&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 17 Aug 2019 09:25:00 -0400</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:v4.chriskrycho.com,2019-08-17:/2019/review-shades-of-milk-and-honey.html</guid><category>book reviews</category><category>fantasy</category><category>reading</category></item><item><title>My Current Setup</title><link>http://v4.chriskrycho.com/2019/my-current-setup.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;a href="https://v4.chriskrycho.com/2018/assumed-audiences.html"&gt;Assumed Audience&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/b&gt; people interested in productivity and work flow and app choice.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A friend was asking me the other day what my workflow looks like, and while I don’t generally spend a &lt;em&gt;lot&lt;/em&gt; of time writing about my working setup, I figured I’d throw up a quick post representing my &lt;em&gt;current&lt;/em&gt; list so that if people ask I can point them here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Two important notes on this, though: First, this is &lt;em&gt;just what I use&lt;/em&gt;. I make no particular claim that it’s &lt;em&gt;the best&lt;/em&gt;. There are lots of things here that are very specific to me and the way I work, and even to my specific mental quirks. Second, it’s far more important to care about the work you do than about the tools you use to get it done. The tools matter: some people say they don’t and I don’t think that’s right at all. But they don’t matter as much as they might &lt;em&gt;feel&lt;/em&gt; like they do, and tool fetishism is real. I think the happy point is finding tools which are good enough and fit comfortably enough into your workflow that they don’t &lt;em&gt;distract&lt;/em&gt; you, and then get back to the work you do!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;section id="software-development" class="level2"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Software development&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For software development, I currently use:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://code.visualstudio.com"&gt;VS Code&lt;/a&gt; as my primary text editor; I also occasionally use Sublime Text or Vim for specific tasks where it makes sense. Code is incredibly fast, impressively low in memory usage given it’s an Electron app, and remarkably customizable. My only outstanding complaint is that there’s no way to actually make it look like a native macOS app. Happily, I &lt;em&gt;can&lt;/em&gt; make it &lt;em&gt;behave&lt;/em&gt; like a native macOS app in all the ways that matter to me. Its support for both TypeScript and Rust—the two languages I spend the most time with right now—is &lt;em&gt;great&lt;/em&gt;. You’re welcome to see &lt;a href="https://gist.github.com/chriskrycho/f39442dd78ad6d150bcaaadd9fedf9f4"&gt;my full configuration&lt;/a&gt;; I keep it updated at that location via the &lt;a href="https://marketplace.visualstudio.com/items?itemName=Shan.code-settings-sync"&gt;Settings Sync&lt;/a&gt; plugin.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;macOS’ built-in Terminal app, just using its tabs for individual tasks. I have spent a lot of time with alternatives, including &lt;a href="https://iterm2.com"&gt;iTerm 2&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://sw.kovidgoyal.net/kitty/"&gt;kitty&lt;/a&gt;, and I’m comfortable in &lt;a href="https://github.com/tmux/tmux/wiki"&gt;tmux&lt;/a&gt; – but at the end of the day I just like the way Terminal &lt;em&gt;feels&lt;/em&gt; the best. It’s fast, light, and built-in macOS things all just work correctly out of the box.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://git-fork.com"&gt;Fork&lt;/a&gt; for a &lt;a href="https://git-scm.com"&gt;git&lt;/a&gt; &lt;abbr&gt;GUI&lt;/abbr&gt;. I’ve also used &lt;a href="https://www.git-tower.com"&gt;Tower&lt;/a&gt; in the past, but I’ve found Fork to be lighter, faster, and a better fit for the way I think and how I expect things to behave (e.g. for interactive rebasing). I do a ton of work in git on the command line as well.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;A mix, varying day by day, of Safari Tech Preview, Firefox, and Chrome for my test browsers. I substantially prefer Safari in nearly every way, but Chrome’s dev tools remain best in class for most things—with the exception of Grid, where Firefox is still the undisputed champion. (When I can, I do most of my JavaScript/TypeScript debugging in VS Code, though: it’s a much better experience.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://kapeli.com/dash"&gt;Dash&lt;/a&gt; for offline documentation access. There are other options out there, including some which are free, but Dash remains the best in my experience, and if nothing else it’s deeply integrated into my workflow and muscle memory.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That’s basically the whole list at the moment. I keep my software development workflow fairly light.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="research-and-writing" class="level2"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Research and writing&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For research and writing, I use:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://ia.net/writer"&gt;iA Writer&lt;/a&gt; for all my blogging and longer-form writing. This is a recent change; I had been a heavy user of &lt;a href="http://www.ulysses.app"&gt;Ulysses&lt;/a&gt; for the last few years. However, while Ulysses was the best option I had found for how I work, it’s never been quite &lt;em&gt;right&lt;/em&gt; for me. For one, I’ve always found Ulysses’ “feel” to be a bit heavy: it’s &lt;em&gt;just&lt;/em&gt; noticeably slower for me than most of the other writing apps, and I’m hypersensitive to input latency. I’ve also always disliked one of the things that makes many people love it: the way it abstracts Markdown into its “smart text objects.” iA Writer gives me the ability to manage a library in much the same way that Ulysses did, but in a way that feels more truly native on both macOS and iOS; it just uses normal Markdown (no fancy text objects); and it’s &lt;em&gt;fast&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;a href="#fn1" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref1" role="doc-noteref"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; That combo makes it a better fit for me.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://bear.app"&gt;Bear&lt;/a&gt; for my note-taking. I’ve talked about this &lt;a href="https://v4.chriskrycho.com/2018/starting-to-build-a-zettelkasten.html"&gt;a fair bit&lt;/a&gt; here &lt;a href="https://v4.chriskrycho.com/2018/zettelkasten-update-all-in-on-bear.html"&gt;before&lt;/a&gt;, so I won’t belabor the details. It’s an excellent, lightweight note-taking app. The main way it falls down for me is that it does not really handle nested block content in Markdown documents (e.g. it won’t correctly display a block quote inside another block quote, or a code sample inside a list, etc.). I’d also love it if it stored its library in a way that made it easier for me to interact with from other apps, i.e. as plain text on the local drive. (You can export content from it easily enough, which is great, but it’s not quite as seamless as I’d like.) Those nits are just that, though: nits. I’m very happy with Bear for my note-taking at this point.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.goldenhillsoftware.com/unread/"&gt;Unread&lt;/a&gt; on iOS for reading RSS, with &lt;a href="https://feedbin.com"&gt;Feedbin&lt;/a&gt; as my long-preferred RSS feed service backing it. (I’m a fan of paying for these kinds of services, so I’m happy to lay out the $5/month for Feedbin. Free alternatives exist, but I don’t love ad-driven models and avoid them where I can.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You’ll note that there are no apps for reading &lt;em&gt;longer&lt;/em&gt; material on that list. I could mention Apple Books as the place I read most ebooks I read, but that’s more a function of the alternatives not being meaningfully &lt;em&gt;better&lt;/em&gt; in the ways I care about.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="productivity" class="level2"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;“Productivity”&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For “productivity” concerns, I use:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://tadamapp.com"&gt;Tadam&lt;/a&gt; for a Pomodoro timer—because it’s precisely as annoyingly obtrusive as I need it to be, which is &lt;em&gt;very&lt;/em&gt;!—and &lt;a href="https://bear.app"&gt;Bear&lt;/a&gt; for &lt;a href="https://v4.chriskrycho.com/2018/just-write-down-what-you-do.html"&gt;tracking&lt;/a&gt; what I do each Pomodoro cycle, each day, each week, each month, and each year. That habit remains very helpful for me.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://culturedcode.com"&gt;Things&lt;/a&gt; for a to-do app. Things hits the sweet spot for me in terms of its ability to manage everything from simple tasks and recurring to-do items around the house up to complex multi-month-long projects. I particularly like its distinction between when I want to be &lt;em&gt;reminded&lt;/em&gt; about something and when that task is &lt;em&gt;due&lt;/em&gt;. I’ve used &lt;a href="https://www.omnigroup.com/omnifocus/"&gt;OmniFocus&lt;/a&gt; in the past, but it never quite &lt;em&gt;fit&lt;/em&gt; me; Things does. They’re very comparable in terms of features; it’s just that the way Things approaches those features works better for me.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://sparkmailapp.com"&gt;Spark&lt;/a&gt; as my email client, mostly for its snooze feature, which I use when I know I need to see an email &lt;em&gt;as an email&lt;/em&gt; sometime later, and its ability to integrate nicely with other apps. I have it connect to Things, and emails that require an &lt;em&gt;action&lt;/em&gt; get put there instead of snoozed. The combination lets me keep my inbox at Zero by the end of every day. And its lovely “Inbox Zero” images are a really nice touch:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src="https://f001.backblazeb2.com/file/chriskrycho-com/images/inbox-zero-spark.png" alt="Inbox Zero in Spark" /&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Inbox Zero in Spark&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="podcasting" class="level2"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Podcasting&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For podcast production, I use:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.izotope.com/en/products/repair-and-edit/rx.html"&gt;iZotope RX&lt;/a&gt; (I’m using v6 Standard) for audio cleanup, as I &lt;a href="https://v4.chriskrycho.com/2018/izotope-rx-is-amazing.html"&gt;recently wrote about&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.apple.com/logic-pro/"&gt;Logic Pro X&lt;/a&gt; for the actual editing work most of the time, occasionally using &lt;a href="https://www.wooji-juice.com/products/ferrite/"&gt;Ferrite&lt;/a&gt;. Logic is overkill for what I do, but I’m &lt;em&gt;fast&lt;/em&gt; with it at this point, so I can’t see moving anytime soon, and there’s nothing else out there that I think is substantially &lt;em&gt;better&lt;/em&gt; (though there are other apps that are comparably good).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.overcast.fm/forecast"&gt;Forecast&lt;/a&gt; for encoding and including chapter breaks.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://reinventedsoftware.com/feeder/"&gt;Feeder&lt;/a&gt; for generating the &lt;abbr&gt;RSS&lt;/abbr&gt; feeds, since all my podcasts are currently built in ways that don’t support &lt;abbr&gt;RSS&lt;/abbr&gt; feed generation: &lt;a href="http://docs.getpelican.com/en/stable/"&gt;Pelican&lt;/a&gt; for &lt;a href="https://winningslowly.org"&gt;Winning Slowly&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://massaffection.com"&gt;Mass Affection&lt;/a&gt;,&lt;a href="#fn2" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref2" role="doc-noteref"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://doc.rust-lang.org/rustdoc"&gt;rustdoc&lt;/a&gt; for &lt;a href="https://newrustacean.com"&gt;New Rustacean&lt;/a&gt;. (If I ever manage to finish building my own site generator, it’ll have out-of-the-box support for custom RSS feed templates, so that I can have this stuff generated automatically for me!)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.netlify.com"&gt;Netlify&lt;/a&gt; for serving the actual static site content (i.e. HTML, CSS, and JS), and &lt;a href="https://www.backblaze.com/b2"&gt;Backblaze B2&lt;/a&gt; for hosting the audio.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://panic.com/transmit/"&gt;Transmit&lt;/a&gt; for actually uploading the audio files.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn1" role="doc-endnote"&gt;&lt;p&gt;iA Writer seems to get &lt;em&gt;randomly&lt;/em&gt; slow at times for reasons I haven’t yet identified, but at least for now, I’m taking that tradeoff over Ulysses’ habit of being a bit slow &lt;em&gt;all the time&lt;/em&gt;. As I’ve often noted before: &lt;a href="https://v4.chriskrycho.com/2016/ulysses-byword-and-just-right.html" title="Ulysses, Byword, and “Just Right”"&gt;my ideal writing app doesn’t exist&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;a href="#fnref1" class="footnote-back" role="doc-backlink"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn2" role="doc-endnote"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Mass Affection isn’t dead! I promise!&lt;a href="#fnref2" class="footnote-back" role="doc-backlink"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 19 Jan 2019 09:00:00 -0500</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:v4.chriskrycho.com,2019-01-19:/2019/my-current-setup.html</guid><category>productivity</category><category>pomodoro</category><category>apps</category><category>writing</category><category>reading</category><category>software development</category></item><item><title>Trying a New Book-Reading Strategy</title><link>http://v4.chriskrycho.com/2018/trying-a-new-book-reading-strategy.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;a href="https://v4.chriskrycho.com/2018/assumed-audiences.html"&gt;Assumed Audience:&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/b&gt; people broadly interested in reading, writing, learning, and research systems.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today I started trying a new(-to-me!) approach to deeply reading books, with some relatively light reading (so that I can get the practice).&lt;a href="#fn1" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref1" role="doc-noteref"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; I’m hoping to be able to grow this skill and use it effectively for learning deeply in 2019. The strategy is pretty simple:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol type="1"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Use very quick, light marks in the margins: &lt;code&gt;✓&lt;/code&gt; for agreement, &lt;code&gt;x&lt;/code&gt; for disagreement, &lt;code&gt;~&lt;/code&gt; for something that’s worth noting as halfway right but worth clarifying, and &lt;code&gt;*&lt;/code&gt; for key arguments. This is basically the tack I’ve taken for a long time, but I’ve dropped all underlining or bracketing from the process: they’re slow, and I’m not really persuaded they’re more helpful than just adding a quick mark, as the really helpful bits come later in my experience.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;On finishing reading each chapter (or major section):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pull in the quotes I want to keep from it. Interact with them as makes sense.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Create a note with a short summary of the argument of the chapter. Link from it to the quotes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The goal here is to have a quick view into the contents of the chapter, including the various quotes that were particularly salient from it.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;On finishing the book, summarize the argument of the book by using the quotes and summaries of the chapters along the way to guide me in formulating my own interpretation of the author’s arguments. Add in some explicit interaction with the argument-in-sum.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Along the way, I’ll also write up other thoughts and interactions with the text, linking them to the other notes as makes sense.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once I have these kinds of notes, I will have a lot of material available to put to whatever use. Most importantly, I will have done a lot more active thinking about the ideas I encountered, and will have quick access to those thoughts to build on later. But I will also be able to use both those quick references to the book and to my own thoughts as prompted by the book to generate writing prompts for blog posts, book reviews, teaching notes, and so on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You’ll notice that this is quite similar in a number of ways to &lt;a href="https://v4.chriskrycho.com/2018/just-write-down-what-you-do.html"&gt;my approach to logging my work&lt;/a&gt;; that’s intentional. I have found that an extremely fruitful way to be able to quickly grasp what I have &lt;em&gt;done&lt;/em&gt; over a given span. It seems likely that this variant on it will be equally useful for quickly grasping what I have &lt;em&gt;read&lt;/em&gt; over a given span.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One other note: I will definitely not be doing this for &lt;em&gt;everything&lt;/em&gt; I read. That would be laborious indeed! I plan to do this for books which I find to be of particularly high value this way. Many books simply do not warrant it, and indeed warrant little more than a quick skim (or to be put aside entirely). I wrote a couple days ago about my intent to use my time more carefully in 2019; one part of that is carefully distinguishing in &lt;em&gt;how&lt;/em&gt; I read as well as &lt;em&gt;what&lt;/em&gt; I read.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn1" role="doc-endnote"&gt;&lt;p&gt;I’m reading &lt;cite&gt;The Shepherd Leader: Achieving Effective Shepherding in Your Church&lt;/cite&gt;, by Timothy Z. Witmer, as part of the elder training work at my church, as I have been nominated to and expect to stand for the office of elder in mid-2019. That might not seem like light reading to you, but I’ve read an awful lot of academic theology over the last decade and no few books in this same vein during my M. Div. work.&lt;a href="#fnref1" class="footnote-back" role="doc-backlink"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 26 Dec 2018 09:10:00 -0500</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:v4.chriskrycho.com,2018-12-26:/2018/trying-a-new-book-reading-strategy.html</guid><category>Zettelkasten</category><category>note-taking</category><category>research</category><category>reading</category></item><item><title>2018: Some Closing Thoughts</title><link>http://v4.chriskrycho.com/2018/some-closing-thoughts.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;a href="https://v4.chriskrycho.com/2018/assumed-audiences.html"&gt;Assumed Audience:&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/b&gt; mostly my future self!—but you’re welcome to read along and see my thoughts on how 2018 went for me and what I hope 2019 will look like.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As has long been my tradition&lt;a href="#fn1" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref1" role="doc-noteref"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; I’m wrapping up the year by looking back at what happened in it and thinking about what I’d like to do in the year ahead. I say little here about family or church, but that should not be taken as an indicator of importance: in fact, my commitments in those two spheres deeply inform everything else!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section id="section" class="level2"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;2018&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;2018 was not the year I hoped or expected it might be. It was difficult in a great many ways, and the more so as the year went on. It was not the single hardest year I’ve had—that title goes without question to 2016—but it’s up there. There’s still a lot of good in the mix, but it was hard.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section id="podcasting" class="level3"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Podcasting&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had intended to publish about twice as many episodes of &lt;a href="https://newrustacean.com"&gt;New Rustacean&lt;/a&gt; this year as I was ultimately able to release. My goal was actually to be releasing 3–4 episodes each month, and to cover most of the rest of the language! As it turned out, I was able to release only 1–2 episodes per month. I’m nonetheless very happy with the episodes I &lt;em&gt;did&lt;/em&gt; release this year. And &lt;a href="https://newrustacean.com/show_notes/bonus/burnout/"&gt;my episode on burnout&lt;/a&gt; may end up being one of the most important things to come out of the show, from the email responses I’ve received about it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We launched a new design of the &lt;a href="https://winningslowly.org"&gt;Winning Slowly website&lt;/a&gt; and we were able to record and publish about three quarters of the episodes we had planned for Season 6 before the burnout tanked me. There’s a wrap-up episode we recorded and which should be out in a few days (after I edit it!). We also released our 100th episode, which was fun! It was frustrating not to be able to finish everything we had planned, but I remain proud of the work we’ve done there over the last five years, and this season had a couple really important episodes in it. If you didn’t listen to anything else, I’d commend &lt;a href="https://winningslowly.org/6.04/"&gt;6.04: Move Slowly and Fix Things&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://winningslowly.org/6.06/"&gt;6.06: A Kind of Blindness&lt;/a&gt;. The latter, on “big data” and the difference between information and wisdom, is one of my single favorite episodes of the show.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="reading-and-writing" class="level3"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Reading and writing&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also set out this year to read a lot of books—I had a list of a 14 pieces of nonfiction on the list—and in the end I finished &lt;em&gt;none&lt;/em&gt; of them. I participated in a reading group which covered much of &lt;cite&gt;Domain Modeling Made Functional&lt;/cite&gt;, and I made it through the first fifth or so of St. Augustine’s &lt;cite&gt;City of God&lt;/cite&gt;, but I didn’t even manage to finish a few books I had started &lt;em&gt;last&lt;/em&gt; year! The only things I managed to finish were novels:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I finished rereading &lt;cite&gt;The Wheel of Time&lt;/cite&gt; and enjoyed some new-to-me “popcorn” in the form of &lt;a href="http://v4.chriskrycho.com/2018/agent-of-change.html"&gt;&lt;cite&gt;Agent of Change&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I devoured Mary Robinette Kowal’s &lt;a href="http://v4.chriskrycho.com/2018/the-calculating-stars.html"&gt;&lt;cite&gt;The Calculating Stars&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="http://v4.chriskrycho.com/2018/review-the-fated-sky.html"&gt;&lt;cite&gt;The Fated Sky&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I read a couple Hugo and Nebula award winners: Larry Niven’s &lt;a href="http://v4.chriskrycho.com/2018/ringworld-review.html"&gt;&lt;cite&gt;Ringworld&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and N.K. Jemisin’s &lt;cite&gt;The Fifth Season&lt;/cite&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While those novels were basically the only thing I read, I very much like the habit of writing very short reviews I started with those novels. I expect to keep that habit, and it should be useful as I dig back into nonfiction in the future!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Speaking of writing: for all that this year felt like it was unproductive in some ways, I still ended up blogging to the tune of somewhere around 75,000 words across about 95 posts.&lt;a href="#fn2" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref2" role="doc-noteref"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; That’s a solid showing for a year full of burnout (even if burnout itself &lt;a href="https://v4.chriskrycho.com/burnout"&gt;ended up being the subject of no few of those&lt;/a&gt;: about 6,000 words).&lt;a href="#fn3" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref3" role="doc-noteref"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; But one of my goals for the year was to publish a few longer-form essays, possibly even getting paid for them. That certainly did not happen; I did not manage to publish even a single essay at Mere Orthodoxy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="health" class="level3"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Health&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I ran a fair bit, and am slowly adjusting to living at roughly 7,000 feet above sea level instead of about 400 feet above sea level. But for the third year in a row, I did &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; manage to run a race. I can still feel, and the more so at this altitude, the lingering effects of the mild case of walking pneumonia I came down with in the summer of 2016. The one thing I did manage in terms of exercise and health was a &lt;em&gt;lot&lt;/em&gt; of cycling. Despite my dad’s being in the midst of ongoing monthly chemo treatments for a brain tumor, he and I rode 80 miles in two days together for the &lt;a href="http://www.childrenscoloradofoundation.org/courage-classic"&gt;Courage Classic&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="work" class="level3"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Work&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Work has been a mixed bag. On the one hand, I accomplished a lot this year. Despite a number of large roadblocks that were entirely outside my control, I led a very important effort to hit several meaningful milestones. I also kept pushing the state of our tooling forward, including some important open-source work, and at the end of November gave a “tech talk” on technical costs which seems to have made a real (if, so far, still small!) impact on the entire organization.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, work directly triggered the burnout I experienced. To be sure, I had plenty of existing stressors from moving across and walking through my dad’s fight with cancer with the rest of my family. But the things that pushed me over the edge from &lt;i&gt;tired and worn down&lt;/i&gt; to &lt;i&gt;burnout&lt;/i&gt; were challenges at work. There were the aforementioned roadblocks. There were some high-stress projects. But most of all, there is a lack of alignment between my engineering and business philosophies and those in play at Olo. Those aren’t &lt;em&gt;moral&lt;/em&gt;, but prudential and strategic, kinds of differences—but that does not make them unimportant! More on this below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="in-sum" class="level3"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;In sum&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In spite of the burnout, and notwithstanding all the things I did not get done, I’m grateful for this year. My dad has so far not only survived his battle with a brain tumor but is thriving overall. I managed to come through my experience of burnout mostly okay. Our new church has been a great blessing to us, and we’ve been able to step into serving in many ways already.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="section-1" class="level2"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;2019&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So looking forward into 2019, my hopes (I dare not call them plans anymore):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section id="podcasting-1" class="level3"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Podcasting&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I want to publish the dozen more episodes of &lt;a href="https://newrustacean.com"&gt;New Rustacean&lt;/a&gt; that I had planned for 2018! At my current rate of about two a month, that’ll take me the first six months or so of the year. Once I’m through that list, I’ll have covered the entirety of the language and quite a few of the most important crates in the ecosystem. But there are always new things happening, so I’ll have some interesting decisions to make about where to take the show.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m also going to keep producing &lt;a href="https://winningslowly.org"&gt;Winning Slowly&lt;/a&gt; with Stephen Carradini. We have not yet nailed down what Season 7 will focus on or look like yet, but we’re far from done. The issue is not finding something to talk about, but narrowing it down to which specific things we want to zoom in on! We also have an interview lined up in January (which will come out as an inter-season standalone episode) which we’re &lt;em&gt;very&lt;/em&gt; excited about. It’ll be quite different from the other interviews we’ve done, and represents an important step forward for the show.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="reading-and-writing-1" class="level3"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Reading and Writing&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My reading and writing goals for the year ahead are intentionally modest. I’ve consistently failed to achieve my more ambitious goals over the past few years, and I’m rather chastened by that. I also have to remind myself fairly often that I will, Lord willing, have many decades of life when I &lt;em&gt;don’t&lt;/em&gt; have my kids around. That means both that there is plenty of time to spend on reading and writing later and that there is &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; very much time to spend with my daughters later. Insofar as I want to continue reading and writing in important ways—and I do!—I need to make my reading and writing time count by approaching them in more focused and targeted ways.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have people ask me quite regularly for recommendations on various topics, and I simply can’t give them! That needs to change, so I want to read at least four popular level books on theology or culture—about one a quarter. My plan is to review them in this space, but also (more importantly!) to be able to point people in my church toward or away from them. In the long-term, I would love to take up a role (official or not) as a custodian of our church’s library.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also want to keep my mind sharp and growing on theology, culture, politics, art, etc. I’ve very much felt the lack of engagement on that over the last few years (and have said so here more than once). In that connection, I aim to work through two academic works on theology, and two on some other aspect of culture. I have yet to decide what those will be. Most likely I’ll start by finishing the volumes I already started, but I also expect to spend a bit of time on Patristic Christology, as I’m teaching a class on the person and nature of Jesus in August for our church.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Writing-wise, I know that I’ll continue blogging here. However, I actually hope to blog &lt;em&gt;less&lt;/em&gt; overall. The time I spent writing 70,000 words this year was time well-spent, but as I note &lt;a href="https://v4.chriskrycho.com/2018/intentional-cyclicality.html" title="Intentional Cyclicality (March)"&gt;time&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://v4.chriskrycho.com/2018/writing-plans-for-the-rest-of-2018.html" title="Writing Plans for the Rest of 2018 (May)"&gt;again&lt;/a&gt;, I have a hard time &lt;a href="http://v4.chriskrycho.com/2018/cant-stop-wont-stop.html" title="Can’t Stop, Won’t Stop (September)"&gt;&lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; blogging&lt;/a&gt;. I plan to work on that in a couple ways.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, I’m going to try to evaluate, with each idea I have, whether it should be a blog post or just go in my &lt;a href="https://v4.chriskrycho.com/zettelkasten/"&gt;Zettelkasten&lt;/a&gt;. So much of my writing over the last decade has been a kind of &lt;a href="https://v4.chriskrycho.com/2018/blog-as-note-taking-tool.html"&gt;public thinking-out-loud&lt;/a&gt;. That’s good, but I also feel much more need to polish something if I’m going to publish it than if it’s a private note. The way I polish a blog post is nothing like the way I polish essays, of course, but I do spend some time clarifying and adding nuance. Even when &lt;a href="https://v4.chriskrycho.com/2018/assumed-audiences.html"&gt;specifying an assumed audience&lt;/a&gt;, I need to be more careful if I am writing for others than if I am working something out by writing about it for myself. As a result, I expect a lot of things which might have ended up on the blog in the past to just go in &lt;a href="https://bear.app"&gt;Bear&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Second, I plan (and we’ll see how this goes), I’m going to try &lt;em&gt;very&lt;/em&gt; hard to write fewer blog posts in favor of more well-developed essays. About a month ago, I started drafting an essay which seems like it might be legitimately important. Unfortunately, even though it is certainly more worth my time than the things I &lt;em&gt;have&lt;/em&gt; written since then (&lt;a href="http://v4.chriskrycho.com/2018/internal-and-external-parameter-names-in-javascript-and-typescript.html"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://v4.chriskrycho.com/2018/starting-to-build-a-zettelkasten.html"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://v4.chriskrycho.com/2018/zettelkasten-update-all-in-on-bear.html"&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://v4.chriskrycho.com/2018/stewarding-my-reserves.html"&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://v4.chriskrycho.com/2018/hey-siri-record-a-zettel.html"&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://v4.chriskrycho.com/2018/javascript-is-c.html"&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;), I have not made progress since the day I started it. It’s not that my notes on research and note-taking are worthless. Rather, it’s that there is a cost to spending my limited time on writing those instead of more important writing efforts.&lt;a href="#fn4" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref4" role="doc-noteref"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;4&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; At a minimum, I intend to do even &lt;em&gt;less&lt;/em&gt; polish on those posts than I have to date, when I let myself write them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="health-1" class="level3"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Health&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have a handful of goals for this year in terms of physical health:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I want to lose about 10 pounds. I’m at a healthy weight currently, but I felt and performed at my best a few years ago when I was down in my target weight range. This is going to require tweaking the &lt;em&gt;content&lt;/em&gt;, rather than the &lt;em&gt;quantity&lt;/em&gt;, of what I eat, and introduce more variation into the kinds of exercise I’m doing. I can tell both that my metabolism has shifted as I’ve hit my 30’s, and that I’ve acclimated to the workout load that I’ve more-or-less consistently held over the last eight years. It’s annoying, honestly!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I plan to participate in the &lt;a href="http://www.childrenscoloradofoundation.org/courage-classic"&gt;Courage Classic&lt;/a&gt; again with my dad, and I’d like to do the 80-mile route at least one of the days. Maybe both days, if he and I are both trained for it! Unfortunately, this probably means investing in a new bike. The one I have currently is almost twenty years old, and it’s a good bike… but it’s increasingly going to need parts replaced. So: CraigsList here I come.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I’d like to complete another half marathon, probably in May. I don’t particularly care what my pace ends up being: I just want to get back in the rhythm and routine of training and completing the event. I went through a similar push after we moved to North Carolina, and 30 months later I ran the best race of my life. Now, I know that &lt;a href="https://runkeeper.com/user/chriskrycho/activity/684713960"&gt;the sub-1:25 time I ran back in 2015&lt;/a&gt; is not something I’m apt to see again, especially at altitude, but I’d like to get back to that kind of consistency and discipline (and I’ll see where it gets me!).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Given that I’m currently planning two events in late spring and summer, I also need to find something to do in the fall and winter next year, just to keep up my fitness level &lt;em&gt;for&lt;/em&gt; something. Previous years, I had the same issue for the spring, and the year I was in my very best shape, I played Ultimate in the spring and fall &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; did a super sprint triathlon in the summer. So: something like that again, perhaps.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="work-1" class="level3"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Work&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I close in on the end of the first decade of my career, I’m &lt;a href="https://v4.chriskrycho.com/2018/career-trajectory.html"&gt;thinking a lot&lt;/a&gt; about what I want the next decade of my career to look like. I don’t expect to be able to figure it all out ahead of time, of course. At the same time, I’m resolved to find opportunities that align more with my values and the general aims for my career I’ve started developing. As I suggested above, I’ve found that I’m not on the same page as, well, &lt;em&gt;most&lt;/em&gt; businesses about how to approach a great many questions. There is no short-term fix for this; but in the longer-term I want to have enough independence to do things more in line with my &lt;a href="https://winningslowly.org"&gt;“winning slowly”&lt;/a&gt; view of the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One part of that is that I intend to push forward on a few things I’ve been plotting for a few years now. I started learning Rust back in the summer of 2015 for a &lt;em&gt;reason&lt;/em&gt;, and I’m coming back to that reason this year. I don’t in the least regret the detour that I’ve gone on in the meantime: New Rustacean remains one of my favorite things I’ve done, and is certainly a more important contribution than any code I could have written in that time. But the project that got this all started has my attention again, and I will be spending some of my personal time on it this year.&lt;a href="#fn5" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref5" role="doc-noteref"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;5&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; It’s the kind of thing that I rather hope &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; my career a few years down the line—but there’s a boatload of work to do to get there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another part is looking at a much longer horizon even. Over the past three years, I’ve become increasingly interested in programming language theory and practice. I have some ideas and insights I think are genuinely valuable and &lt;em&gt;relatively&lt;/em&gt; unique (at a minimum they’re not currently in use in industry anywhere, and I’ve yet to find any papers touching on them) and I would like to see them land at some point. Getting there is a long game; I am not exaggerating when I say that if I ever really make this happen, I expect it to be in my 40s. Probably my &lt;em&gt;late&lt;/em&gt; 40s. But that gives me time to learn in the meantime: to build small languages and see what that process is like, to find ways to collaborate on existing language projects, to learn a wide array of existing languages in more detail, and so on. If the ideas I have are ever to come to fruition, all of those things are necessary precursors for my efforts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here in late 2018, I have &lt;em&gt;just&lt;/em&gt; started on much of that: I am reading a book on programming language development and taking an awful lots of notes along the way. I will be completing the exercises in the book, and I will also be trying to learn enough to build my own little toy languages along the way. I am getting some practice in the pragmatics of it by collaborating with Dave Herman on &lt;a href="https://github.com/tc39/proposal-do-expressions"&gt;the &lt;code&gt;do&lt;/code&gt; expressions JavaScript proposal&lt;/a&gt;, which we hope to make substantial progress on in 2019. These kinds of programming language ideas will &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; be the emphasis in 2019, but they will be a piece, in the interest of laying the foundations I will need later.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="in-sum-1" class="level3"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;In sum&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hope 2019 is a less difficult year than 2018 was. I am also aiming to be more effective in accomplishing the things I care about, in part by setting more modest goals for myself. Keep podcasting. Read a few books of a few specific sorts. Write some essays, at the expense of some blog posts. Start on some new projects, but not in a hurry or a rush. Love my family and love my church.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn1" role="doc-endnote"&gt;&lt;p&gt;I’ve been doing this since 2007, but I’m not linking you to the blog post I wrote that year. There’s nothing quite like reading things I wrote halfway through college to make me cringe. There is some good stuff there, but also: 20-year-old Chris Krycho was, uhh… &lt;em&gt;very&lt;/em&gt; emotional. And the way I approach my faith has shifted a lot since then.&lt;a href="#fnref1" class="footnote-back" role="doc-backlink"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn2" role="doc-endnote"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Running &lt;code&gt;wc -w&lt;/code&gt; on the posts I wrote in 2018 reports 80,911 words, but that number includes all the post metadata. Assuming an average of 65 words of metadata per post, across the 96 posts I wrote, that comes out to around 6,250 words. So: very roughly 75,000, for an average of about 780 words per post. Not too shabby!&lt;a href="#fnref2" class="footnote-back" role="doc-backlink"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn3" role="doc-endnote"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Meta note: that includes this post. So the final count depends on how long I make the previous footnote. And this one. Such recursion!&lt;a href="#fnref3" class="footnote-back" role="doc-backlink"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn4" role="doc-endnote"&gt;&lt;p&gt;So: what of this kind of year-end review, which is itself not exactly one of those more important writing projects? Good point. I find his exercise helpful, though, and I’d almost certainly be doing it privately in nearly identical terms. I have found this practice helpful over the years, despite never coming near accomplishing the specific goals I’ve set myself, so I expect to keep up this habit.&lt;a href="#fnref4" class="footnote-back" role="doc-backlink"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn5" role="doc-endnote"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is another reason for the emphasis on focusing my writing time on high-value projects. Time I spend writing random blog posts is time I am &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; spending on these programming efforts.&lt;a href="#fnref5" class="footnote-back" role="doc-backlink"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 23 Dec 2018 14:35:00 -0500</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:v4.chriskrycho.com,2018-12-23:/2018/some-closing-thoughts.html</guid><category>writing</category><category>reading</category><category>podcasting</category><category>burnout</category><category>fitness</category><category>health</category><category>career</category></item><item><title>Assumed Audiences</title><link>http://v4.chriskrycho.com/2018/assumed-audiences.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;i class=editorial&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Assumed audience:&lt;/strong&gt; everyone on the internet.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am working on a post about something I think is interesting in programming, and shared it with a friend last night to get some feedback on what I had written so far. His response made me realize that the post left me open to wild and massive misinterpretation of my intent. (The specific details aren’t really that interesting for my broader point here.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was thinking about how to clarify that, and it took me back to a Winning Slowly episode we recorded back in 2015, with the wonderful title &lt;a href="https://winningslowly.org/2.02/"&gt;Basketballs ≠ Pumpkins&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In which we talk about… the general phenomenon of things you say on the internet going viral (often when you least expect them to). How do you deal with the reality that your audience is never limited but may universalize at any moment? What is the audience’s responsibility, and what are creators’ responsibilities? How do we deal charitably with authors writing “in-house” on controversial topics?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The basic problem here is that a blog post is open to everyone on the internet to read… but &lt;em&gt;everyone on the internet&lt;/em&gt; is far too broad an audience for, well, basically &lt;em&gt;any&lt;/em&gt; post I write. (Or indeed any post anyone writes.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What’s more, for any given post I write, there is an &lt;em&gt;implicit&lt;/em&gt; audience. You as reader just have no way of knowing who I have in mind. Maybe I &lt;em&gt;am&lt;/em&gt; thinking of “the whole internet,” but that certainly isn’t the case for &lt;em&gt;most&lt;/em&gt; posts. So what if I just made my intended audience explicit?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My current best solution for handling this phenomenon is an “assumed audience” heading on the top of a post. It won’t head off &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; the nonsense, of course. But it at least gives people a frame of reference. A few examples that leap to mind:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Assumed audience:&lt;/strong&gt; other theologically conservative Christians in the &lt;abbr title="Presbyterian Church in America"&gt;PCA&lt;/abbr&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Assumed audience:&lt;/strong&gt; people curious about functional programming&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Assumed audience:&lt;/strong&gt; experienced Rust developers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Assumed audience:&lt;/strong&gt; people outright hostile to religious belief&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each of those are people I might actually address on this blog—and there are plenty of others, of course. What’s potentially useful about this kind of thing is that good-faith readers know how to approach the content. Bad-faith readers will of course do with any text what they will. I cannot stop someone from hate-reading me. All I can do is put up sign-posts for people who are &lt;em&gt;interested&lt;/em&gt; in good faith readings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, if you’re a die-hard devotee of dynamic programming languages, a note that the assumed audience is people interested in advanced static types tells you that my point isn’t persuading &lt;em&gt;you&lt;/em&gt;, but persuading someone else entirely. You can adjust your read accordingly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Likewise, if I’m writing on Christian ethics with an assumed audience of secular progressives, and you’re a fundamentalist Christian, you can read with the understanding that I will frame things differently for someone who disagrees with me about everything (down to and including the nature of reality itself!) than if we were having an “in-house” conversation! You can adjust your read accordingly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m increasingly convinced something like this is important. &lt;em&gt;Very&lt;/em&gt; important, even.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s worthwhile to blog and write publicly—some of the best feedback I get on things I write is from total strangers!—but it’s also very difficult to write effectively when everything must be couched in forty-eight layers of nuance and qualification just in case someone from a different tribe happens along.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Maybe I’ll just be this weird guy over here marking my posts this way, or maybe it’ll catch on with other weird people and a few corners of the internet will be a little less open to misunderstanding. Maybe people will completely ignore them and engage in full on flame wars on Twitter and Hacker News. (That seems more likely than not.) I think it’s worth a shot anyway. Let’s try it and find out!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Edit, October 19, 2018:&lt;/strong&gt; Thanks to &lt;a href="https://stephencarradini.com"&gt;Stephen Carradini&lt;/a&gt; for reminding me to include a shout-out to Sarah Constantin’s blog &lt;a href="https://srconstantin.wordpress.com"&gt;Otium&lt;/a&gt;, which introduces posts with a similar heading, “Epistemic status,” to indicate how confident the author is or isn’t about the contents of the given post. I meant to include a shout-out to Otium in the original writeup and just spaced it!&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 18 Oct 2018 19:00:00 -0400</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:v4.chriskrycho.com,2018-10-18:/2018/assumed-audiences.html</guid><category>writing</category><category>reading</category></item><item><title>Ringworld Review</title><link>http://v4.chriskrycho.com/2018/ringworld-review.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;i class=editorial&gt;I keep my book review ratings simple—they’re either &lt;em&gt;required&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;recommended&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;recommended with qualifications&lt;/em&gt;, or &lt;em&gt;not recommended&lt;/em&gt;. If you want the TL;DR, this is it:&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Recommended:&lt;/strong&gt; In want of a bit of classic sci-fi, I recently picked up Larry Niven’s &lt;cite&gt;Ringworld&lt;/cite&gt; and read it this week. I enjoyed it, but more than that I find it hard to say. I’m still not sure exactly what to describe it as: an exploratory high concept romp, maybe. The characters were fine, the plot serviceable, and the two high concepts very high indeed. (Certainly the more interesting of those conceits is the one &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; advertized by the title of the book.) I’m not sad I read it; I also don’t think I’d read it again. I might even call it a bit overrated.&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 14 Oct 2018 17:30:00 -0400</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:v4.chriskrycho.com,2018-10-14:/2018/ringworld-review.html</guid><category>science fiction</category><category>book reviews</category><category>reading</category></item><item><title>RSS Triage is Just Like Email Triage</title><link>http://v4.chriskrycho.com/2018/rss-triage-is-just-like-email-triage.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;I’ve heard people say they find &lt;abbr&gt;RSS&lt;/abbr&gt; overwhelming: the constant flow of new items. I find that managing &lt;abbr&gt;RSS&lt;/abbr&gt; well is not actually all that hard though; it just takes the same kind of discipline as keeping an empty inbox does.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In short: keep my reading list restrained, and have a strategy to keep up to date on that list.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My strategy for keeping up to date is simple, too: for every time, either read it, send it to Pocket to read later (on my Kobo, via Kobo’s Pocket integration), or mark it as read. Then move on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As for the Pocket items: clear &lt;em&gt;those&lt;/em&gt; out after long enough, too: I go through my backlog every so often and if I haven’t read it yet and it has been in my to-read list for more than a month or two, I decide to read it &lt;em&gt;now&lt;/em&gt; or just remove it. (At some point you just have to admit that you’re &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; going to read something, and that it’s okay. We all have limited time.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With that simple strategy, &lt;abbr&gt;RSS&lt;/abbr&gt; becomes more than merely “manageable” for me: I get to read a lot of things I actually &lt;em&gt;want&lt;/em&gt; to read, and it’s focused in a way that Twitter or Apple News or whatever else isn’t.&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 22 Aug 2018 18:15:00 -0400</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:v4.chriskrycho.com,2018-08-22:/2018/rss-triage-is-just-like-email-triage.html</guid><category>rss</category><category>reading</category></item><item><title>A Meander</title><link>http://v4.chriskrycho.com/2018/a-meander.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;This is a meander. I have a bunch of mostly-unformed thoughts, and I want to write, and the two come out here, together, in the next few minutes before I start my workday proper (because I stayed up late last night working on open source software and got up late accordingly, and so have a great deal less of &lt;a href="http://v4.chriskrycho.com/2017/knowing-your-rhythms.html" title="“Knowing Your Rhythms”"&gt;my normally-allocated writing time&lt;/a&gt; available today).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;section id="section" class="level2"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;1.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Open-source software is a very strange place, and the dynamics of it favor those of us who already have well-paying jobs and lots of flexibility in our schedule.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This isn’t &lt;em&gt;necessarily&lt;/em&gt; a bad thing. It means that anyone who wants to use open-source contribution as a gauge of someone’s fitness to work is making a pretty foolish decision, though: they’re inherently cutting off a whole sector—dare I say it, a whole &lt;em&gt;class&lt;/em&gt;—of people who simply do not (and, barring being given a pretty surprising break, will never) have that kind of stability and flexibility.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="section-1" class="level2"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;2.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Twitter is really, &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; bad for meaningful discussion. I follow both &lt;a href="https://mobile.twitter.com/noahpinion"&gt;Noah Smith (@noahpinion)&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://mobile.twitter.com/lymanstoneky"&gt;Lyman Stone (@lymanstoneky)&lt;/a&gt;, and they’re both extremely interesting follows, and they’re both clearly &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; smart and &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; well-informed, and in their off-Twitter writing they both do a good job of fairly representing others’ views and interacting with them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Twitter, their arguments are a disaster.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is not specific to Smith and Stone. This is Twitter in one pair of interlocutors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Seriously: stop tweeting and start blogging again, if you have an &lt;em&gt;argument&lt;/em&gt; to make rather than just a pithy, one-off observation or a link to share.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="section-2" class="level2"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;3.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can get a surprising amount of writing done in 5 minutes, if you’re willing to just word-vomit. (This whole post, start to finish, took me 12 minutes.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="section-3" class="level2"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;4.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I need to read more poetry; more rich, good fiction; more rich, good nonfiction. I’ve read a lot of nonfiction in the last five years, but I wouldn’t call most of it &lt;em&gt;rich&lt;/em&gt;. Most of it—most of my seminary reading, that is—was &lt;em&gt;just okay&lt;/em&gt;; very little of it engaged deeply with thought critical of its own perspective. (Major exceptions: David Koyzis’ really excellent &lt;em&gt;Political Visions and Illusions&lt;/em&gt;, Alvin Plantinga’s &lt;em&gt;Where the Conflict Really Lies&lt;/em&gt;, and of course St. Athanasius’ &lt;em&gt;On the Incarnation&lt;/em&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But I find that my own writing is far sharper, clearer, and better when I’m drawing &lt;em&gt;widely&lt;/em&gt; and from &lt;em&gt;deep wells&lt;/em&gt;. Widely, because I find that too much time in the same spot overly narrows my focus, whether that is apologetics or programming languages. From deep wells because, frankly, there is too much out there which warrants nothing more than a skim &lt;em&gt;at most&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And that is all!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 09 Feb 2018 07:00:00 -0500</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:v4.chriskrycho.com,2018-02-09:/2018/a-meander.html</guid><category>writing</category><category>open-source software</category><category>ethics</category><category>reading</category><category>literature</category></item><item><title>A Book List!</title><link>http://v4.chriskrycho.com/2017/a-book-list.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;I’ve just posted my in-progress &lt;a href="http://v4.chriskrycho.com/2017-book-list.html"&gt;2017 Book List&lt;/a&gt;. I’ll update it with books as I finish them, and I’ll also update it with reviews (even of the “here’s a brief comment” variety) as I do them. This is something I’ve been thinking about doing for my own sake for a while, and bumping into &lt;a href="http://tbrown.org/notes/2017/06/23/reading-and-sharing/"&gt;this post by Tim Brown&lt;/a&gt; reminded me how much I want to be sharing what I read with other people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sometimes I get myself spun up on thinking that I need to be reviewing books with the best of them. In reality, I really just want to do like Tim says in that post (emphasis his):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I am reading and sharing ideas about what I have read, I feel like my best self. &lt;em&gt;I want more of that feeling.&lt;/em&gt;… I’m wondering if acknowledging what I read, along with a substantial visual (a book cover image?) and any highlights or notes, could feel just as good as having a physical book…. Maybe I could list my piles of books here on my website, and link them to blog post entries with highlights/notes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That’s it exactly. So I’m going ahead and doing the work: I’m going to keep that list up to date, and I’m going to try to write and share &lt;em&gt;something&lt;/em&gt; about every book I read for the rest of the year. It doesn’t have to be a lot—just a sentence or two will do in many cases. “I liked it” or “This had a lot of potential but didn’t quite measure up to it.” Something simple like &lt;a href="https://wynnnetherland.com/reviews/to-hell-and-back-europe-1914-1949/"&gt;what Wynn Netherland does&lt;/a&gt;, or something long and careful when it makes good sense.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Maybe someday I’ll be able to write one of those killer reviews that ends up changing a whole conversation, or maybe I’ll just have a bunch of interesting notes I can look back on later and be able to see what I thought about a book when I’m curious a decade later. Either way, I think it’ll be a nice win.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So: &lt;a href="http://v4.chriskrycho.com/2017-book-list.html"&gt;book list&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 08 Jul 2017 21:45:00 -0400</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:v4.chriskrycho.com,2017-07-08:/2017/a-book-list.html</guid><category>reading</category><category>writing</category></item><item><title>On Decompression</title><link>http://v4.chriskrycho.com/2017/on-decompression.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;I’ve been thinking about reading plans and book lists. And about rest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Plans and lists may not sound like rest to you; that’s fine: they don’t to me, either. I’ve been eager to move back into the kinds of reading I’m actively interested in doing now that I’m done with my seminary degree. But one of the challenges is that I need—and I’m &lt;em&gt;very&lt;/em&gt; aware of this need—to decompress a bit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The last roughly 8 years have been &lt;em&gt;going&lt;/em&gt; fairly constantly. I began my first job after college the day after Jaimie and I got back from our honeymoon. For the next two years I worked full-time there &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; taught myself web development and then did 8–10 hours a week of web development consulting on the side while she finished school. I kept up that pace for another year and a half after that other than a slight break just after Ellie was born, and then we moved to North Carolina for me to get an M. Div. from &lt;a href="http://www.sebts.edu"&gt;SEBTS&lt;/a&gt;. Since we moved here, I’ve always been working—anywhere from 20 to 60 hours a week, always in at least one class a semester and often as many as three. All along the way, I’ve also been reading and writing for myself: these things are relaxing for me. And for the sheer joy and need of a good outlet, I added podcasting along the way as a hobby.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the takeaway of all of that is that I’ve had to be &lt;em&gt;extremely&lt;/em&gt; structured and disciplined with my time. I have always had a detailed schedule and an idea of what I wanted or needed to be working on at any given time: from learning new things in software to writing blog posts, and from actually programming as a job to writing papers for seminary.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s time to breathe a bit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I feel very keenly the need to &lt;em&gt;decompress&lt;/em&gt;. Not to stop doing things, but to add some slack to the schedule, to keep my number of hard external commitments low and to keep any self-imposed pressures low as well. That will let me recharge and avoid burnout, and it will give me lots of good time to just hang out with Jaimie and our little girls. We’ve made space for the family all the way through, but it has always been a matter of scheduling it and fitting it in. I’m looking forward to a season where it’s just normal for us to play and read and do life together. As I said: a kind of decompression, letting things stretch back out a bit and decreasing the tension of always being on a tight schedule.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That means that until about January 2018, I am not making myself a &lt;em&gt;reading list&lt;/em&gt; in the way I want to in the future. Why do I even want that? Because I &lt;em&gt;need&lt;/em&gt; it. So the better question is: why do I think I need a reading list or a plan?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m a voracious, multi-disciplinary reader, but this has two problems. One is I can be a bit like a squirrel: always seeing something shiny in that new subject &lt;em&gt;over there&lt;/em&gt;. The other is that I can get sucked incredibly deep into one genre so that I end up reading only theology or programming or the like for six months. Having a plan and a reading list will help me both dig deeply and in focused ways into the subjects on which I want to think (and write!) more, but it will also help me balance that with a good mix of other kinds of reading from other fields—something which is both broadly helpful and which inevitably &lt;a href="http://2012-2013.chriskrycho.com/art/and-the-stew-tastes-good/"&gt;produces a better mix of insights&lt;/a&gt; than just reading one subject in isolation does.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But, for all the reasons outlined above: not now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I still have books I want to read over the rest of this year. The list right now looks like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fyodor Dostoevsky, &lt;em&gt;The Idiot&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Daniel Kahneman, &lt;em&gt;Thinking, Fast and Slow&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Oliver O’Donovan, &lt;em&gt;Resurrection and Moral Order&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Brandon Sanderson, the various sequels to &lt;em&gt;Alcatraz Versus the Evil Librarians&lt;/em&gt; (which I read and quite enjoyed last month)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Charles Taylor, &lt;em&gt;A Secular Age&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;J. R. R. Tolkien, &lt;em&gt;Beren and Lúthien&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That’s a “list,” but it’s a list composed of exactly one kind of book: whatever I feel like reading. There are other books I’ve already started that aren’t on that list because while they’re important to me, they’re not decompressive at all: they feel like work, like pressure. And what I and my family need right now—especially in the midst of planning a cross-country move to be nearer our families in a new home!—is to relieve pressure, not add more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So now I’m going to go read one of those books on our porch. Whichever one I feel like. And then I’ll read whichever one I feel like &lt;em&gt;next&lt;/em&gt;. And if the list changes, that’s fine too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;i class="editorial"&gt;Note: I cross-posted this to &lt;a href="http://krycho.com"&gt;our new family blog&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 10 Jun 2017 10:00:00 -0400</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:v4.chriskrycho.com,2017-06-10:/2017/on-decompression.html</guid><category>reading</category><category>writing</category><category>rest</category></item><item><title>Constant Evaluation</title><link>http://v4.chriskrycho.com/2016/constant-evaluation.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;I’m reading John Frame’s &lt;em&gt;The Doctrine of the Christian Life&lt;/em&gt;, and find a great deal to commend in it, but also some real head-scratchers. The same page, for example (287), includes both of these quotes—&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On rejecting mere traditionalism:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This [Paul’s example of self-sacrifice for evangelism] means that in our evangelistic methodology, and indeed in our worship (for that also has an evangelistic element, [1 Corinthians] 14:24–25), our goal must not be to please ourselves, but to bend and stretch, toa ccept discomfort and the trauma of change, in order to speak the Christian faith to the contemporary world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the Fathers:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have had much more time to study Scripture than did the early church fathers like Clement and Justin Martyr. And in some ways, I think, contemporary orthodox Reformed theology has a far deeper and more precise understanding of the gospel than did the church fathers. I say this contrary to those evangelicals who are joining Eastern Orthodox churches in order to return to the supposedly more profound teachings of the early church fathers. Although the Fathers did wonderful work in their day, standing heroically for the faith amid terrible oppressions, their writings were confused on many important points, such as the Trinity and justification by faith. (287)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first quote is an &lt;em&gt;excellent&lt;/em&gt; summary of the Christian obligation to continually reapply the testimony of Scripture to the present. The book is full of these kinds of enormously helpful bits; I have written far more ✓ than ✗ marks—i.e., many more affirmations than rejections—in this text.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But that second quote makes me want to bang my head against the desk. When Frame waves his hand at “the Fathers” and declares “their writings” “confused on… the Trinity and justification by faith,” I am left saying: &lt;em&gt;Which Fathers?&lt;/em&gt; and, even more importantly, &lt;em&gt;Frame, where do you think we &lt;em&gt;got&lt;/em&gt; our doctrine of the Trinity, if not the Fathers?&lt;/em&gt; To be sure, there is plenty of variation in quality and reliability of the Fathers. Origen is a brilliant, fascinating hot mess of a theologian, for example, while Irenaeus, Hillary, Augustine, Athanasius, and others are no less sure or reliable than any major Reformed author. Moreover: reading early Reformed writers makes it very clear that &lt;em&gt;they&lt;/em&gt; thought the Fathers broadly reliable and helpful!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Every author has strengths and weaknesses. Even the most helpful require &lt;em&gt;constant&lt;/em&gt; evaluation.&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 13 Sep 2016 07:10:00 -0400</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:v4.chriskrycho.com,2016-09-13:/2016/constant-evaluation.html</guid><category>classwork</category><category>SEBTS</category><category>M.Div.</category><category>reading</category></item></channel></rss>