<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Chris Krycho - rest</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/</link><description></description><lastBuildDate>Sun, 09 Dec 2018 21:15:00 -0500</lastBuildDate><item><title>Stewarding My Reserves</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2018/stewarding-my-reserves.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.chriskrycho.com/2018/assumed-audiences.html"&gt;Assumed Audience:&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/b&gt; anyone and everyone, but &lt;em&gt;especially&lt;/em&gt; people who have followed along as &lt;a href="https://www.chriskrycho.com/burnout.html"&gt;I have written about my experience of burnout&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ve slowly but surely been coming out of this burnout over the last seven weeks or so. I pulled &lt;em&gt;hard&lt;/em&gt; on some levers at work and got some changes there, which gave me the space to start recovering. I have also been working aggressively at identifying what steps I need to take to deal with my mental health more generally—including dealing with a bunch of griefs that have mounted up over many, many years, and which I have (for various reasons, many of them good) simply set aside to deal with later. Do that too long, and later becomes &lt;em&gt;now&lt;/em&gt;, whether you want it to or not.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I find that this recovery phase has its own dangers, subtler but no less real than being in the thick of the burnout was. Now, I’m tempted to dive back into the deep end—to forget just how rough a spot I was in not that many weeks ago, and pick up too much, and… land myself back in that mess. As one of my pastors put it to me last week (putting to words things I’d been thinking), it’s easy to forget that just because we’re through the burnout doesn’t mean we have any reserves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Spoiler: he was right. I don’t have any reserves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I felt, this week, a bit of a slide toward the same malaise and cynicism and deep fatigue that characterized me for a good long chunk of the year—and it’s no surprise why. We’ve been going nonstop since before Thanksgiving. I drove away from my house for a quick personal trip only twelve hours after we got back from visiting Jaimie’s family in Texas over that holiday. I gave one of the best (and probably one of the most important) tech talks I’ve ever given at Olo the day after I got back from that trip. I helped finish getting &lt;a href="https://blog.rust-lang.org/2018/11/29/a-new-look-for-rust-lang-org.html"&gt;the Rust website redesign&lt;/a&gt; out the door in time for the &lt;a href="https://blog.rust-lang.org/2018/12/06/Rust-1.31-and-rust-2018.html"&gt;Rust 2018 Edition launch&lt;/a&gt; this week.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And it is very obvious to me that this has been &lt;em&gt;too much&lt;/em&gt;. I need to steward my recovery carefully, so that it proves to be a genuine recovery and not merely a little upswing before dipping back into burnout. I need to go ahead and deal with those unprocessed griefs. I need to say no to more things outside my family and work, no matter how good or appealing those things are. In the medium term, I need to build better patterns of life around all these things, so that I don’t end up again where I was in early October.&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 09 Dec 2018 18:15:00 -0500</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2018-12-09:/2018/stewarding-my-reserves.html</guid><category>burnout</category><category>productivity</category><category>rest</category></item><item><title>Making Things Helps</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2018/making-things-helps.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;As a small bit of follow-up to my recent post on &lt;a href="https://www.chriskrycho.com/2018/cant-stop-wont-stop.html" title="Can’t Stop, Won’t Stop"&gt;blogging as part of what helps with my burnout&lt;/a&gt;, I thought it worth noting that this principle is a bit broader than just &lt;em&gt;blogging&lt;/em&gt; for me. Writing (currently mostly expressed in the form of blogging) is deep in me, and so blogging remains a helpful outlet.&lt;a href="#fn1" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref1"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; But so a fair number of other things which might look like &lt;em&gt;work&lt;/em&gt; to other people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tonight I started putting together some thoughts on what some extensions to an open source software library I maintain might look like.&lt;a href="#fn2" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref2"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; This after what has to be a record-setting week: the kind in which I reviewed and merged 60 pull requests for a ridiculous crunch of a project I’m on at work. I’m exhausted. I had another one of those moments this evening where I started crying a bit as I was sitting down to eat dinner and praying beforehand. Why? Just because I’m &lt;em&gt;that&lt;/em&gt; emotionally wrung out: nothing was wrong in the particular moment at all, and probably the “trigger” was actually the small bit of relief of being &lt;em&gt;away&lt;/em&gt; from the particular (very weird) stressors of this project at work for a while.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So why in the world did I start writing up thoughts about an open-source library after that? And why have I been spending my evenings reading all about a particularly nerdy bit of computer science this week?&lt;a href="#fn3" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref3"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; Because, as I suggested at the beginning, these things are what end up feeling restful or re-energizing to me. (That might make me weird. I’m okay with that. I’ve been weird for a long time.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Much of the advice around burnout emphasizes “not working.” There’s good reason for that, but it’s important to understand the underlying reasons for that advice. Burnout &lt;em&gt;usually&lt;/em&gt; stems from work-related stress, for an appropriately broad definition of “work.”&lt;a href="#fn4" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref4"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;4&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; Besides the stressors themselves, many of us—whether we admit it or not!—put far too much of our self-worth into our work. Putting it aside leaves us feeling worthless or useless. If your burnout is coming from the combo of stress and having invested your self-worth in your work, then you’re not likely to get better until you disengage from that work &lt;em&gt;entirely&lt;/em&gt; for large stretches of time: that is, until you are &lt;em&gt;forced&lt;/em&gt; to divest your self-worth from your work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But there are other ways burnout comes to pass. For me, it’s a combination of particular work stressors with the stress my family has undergone over the last year: a cross-country move, building a house, and most of all my father’s (so far blessedly successful) fight with a brain tumor. The work stressors are largely not related to the work &lt;em&gt;load&lt;/em&gt;, though; and I have by God’s grace kept my personal sense of meaning and value detached from my job. Insofar as my work is involved, the burnout is much more about frustrations and stymied aims and boredom with certain parts of the job than it is about overwork! The net of that is that doing some open-source brainstorming in the evenings is not a way of reinforcing the things that have caused this (though it very well &lt;em&gt;could&lt;/em&gt; become that). Rather, left in the same kinds of space as my blogging (“not on a schedule, not on a deadline, but whenever I feel like it”), it ends up being a &lt;em&gt;counter&lt;/em&gt; to burnout.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All of which is a long way of saying: if you’re experiencing burnout, you need to figure out &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt; if you want to have a chance of getting through it. Otherwise good advice will actually mislead you otherwise. If your problem is that you’ve dumped all your self-worth into your open-source work, &lt;em&gt;stop doing open-source work&lt;/em&gt;. On the other hand, if the cause of your burnout is that you’re deeply invested in caretaking for someone in your family, it might well be that doing something that looks like &lt;em&gt;work&lt;/em&gt; to someone else—even writing a novel or something similarly massive in scale—might be a genuine relief and outlet for you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For me, &lt;em&gt;genuine rest&lt;/em&gt; often includes writing and learning and thinking and creating—not by themselves, but as part of a healthy mix that includes many other good things: a healthy dose of exercise and building LEGO contraptions with my daughters and watching &lt;cite&gt;The Expanse&lt;/cite&gt; with my wife, and enjoying the company of good friends over good food and good drinks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section class="footnotes"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn1"&gt;&lt;p&gt;I’ve actually been blogging longer than I’ve been writing software in any meaningful way. I did tiny bits of Visual Basic and C++ in middle school and high school, and I started picking up &lt;abbr&gt;HTML&lt;/abbr&gt; and &lt;abbr&gt;CSS&lt;/abbr&gt; for the sake of my website and blog in college. I didn’t pick up programming in a more general sense until I learned Fortran for my senior capstone project in physics!&lt;a href="#fnref1" class="footnote-back"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn2"&gt;&lt;p&gt;I’m thinking about &lt;code&gt;Future&lt;/code&gt; and/or &lt;code&gt;Task&lt;/code&gt; extensions to &lt;a href="https://github.com/chriskrycho/true-myth"&gt;True Myth&lt;/a&gt;, for those of you interested in the details. I’ll have a GitHub issue up sometime soon-ish, and might blog about it here as well.&lt;a href="#fnref2" class="footnote-back"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn3"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Conflict-free_replicated_data_type"&gt;&lt;abbr title="Conflict-free Replicated Data Type"&gt;CRDT&lt;/abbr&gt;s&lt;/a&gt;, for my fellow software nerds out there. &lt;a href="http://archagon.net/blog/2018/03/24/data-laced-with-history/" title="Data Laced With History"&gt;This introduction&lt;/a&gt; is absolutely outstanding, as are a number of the pieces it links to. Among other things, I actually &lt;em&gt;understand&lt;/em&gt; a few concepts in set theory I’ve had a hard time wrapping my head around in the past, because the explanations here are so good.&lt;a href="#fnref3" class="footnote-back"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn4"&gt;&lt;p&gt;As I talked about in my &lt;a href="https://newrustacean.com/show_notes/bonus/burnout/"&gt;New Rustacean episode about burnout&lt;/a&gt;, lots of things which &lt;em&gt;aren’t&lt;/em&gt; “work” in the “what I do to pay the bills” sense can also be triggers.&lt;a href="#fnref4" class="footnote-back"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 28 Sep 2018 20:45:00 -0400</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2018-09-28:/2018/making-things-helps.html</guid><category>burnout</category><category>open-source software</category><category>productivity</category><category>rest</category></item><item><title>On Decompression</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2017/on-decompression.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;I’ve been thinking about reading plans and book lists. And about rest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Plans and lists may not sound like rest to you; that’s fine: they don’t to me, either. I’ve been eager to move back into the kinds of reading I’m actively interested in doing now that I’m done with my seminary degree. But one of the challenges is that I need—and I’m &lt;em&gt;very&lt;/em&gt; aware of this need—to decompress a bit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The last roughly 8 years have been &lt;em&gt;going&lt;/em&gt; fairly constantly. I began my first job after college the day after Jaimie and I got back from our honeymoon. For the next two years I worked full-time there &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; taught myself web development and then did 8–10 hours a week of web development consulting on the side while she finished school. I kept up that pace for another year and a half after that other than a slight break just after Ellie was born, and then we moved to North Carolina for me to get an M. Div. from &lt;a href="http://www.sebts.edu"&gt;SEBTS&lt;/a&gt;. Since we moved here, I’ve always been working—anywhere from 20 to 60 hours a week, always in at least one class a semester and often as many as three. All along the way, I’ve also been reading and writing for myself: these things are relaxing for me. And for the sheer joy and need of a good outlet, I added podcasting along the way as a hobby.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the takeaway of all of that is that I’ve had to be &lt;em&gt;extremely&lt;/em&gt; structured and disciplined with my time. I have always had a detailed schedule and an idea of what I wanted or needed to be working on at any given time: from learning new things in software to writing blog posts, and from actually programming as a job to writing papers for seminary.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s time to breathe a bit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I feel very keenly the need to &lt;em&gt;decompress&lt;/em&gt;. Not to stop doing things, but to add some slack to the schedule, to keep my number of hard external commitments low and to keep any self-imposed pressures low as well. That will let me recharge and avoid burnout, and it will give me lots of good time to just hang out with Jaimie and our little girls. We’ve made space for the family all the way through, but it has always been a matter of scheduling it and fitting it in. I’m looking forward to a season where it’s just normal for us to play and read and do life together. As I said: a kind of decompression, letting things stretch back out a bit and decreasing the tension of always being on a tight schedule.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That means that until about January 2018, I am not making myself a &lt;em&gt;reading list&lt;/em&gt; in the way I want to in the future. Why do I even want that? Because I &lt;em&gt;need&lt;/em&gt; it. So the better question is: why do I think I need a reading list or a plan?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m a voracious, multi-disciplinary reader, but this has two problems. One is I can be a bit like a squirrel: always seeing something shiny in that new subject &lt;em&gt;over there&lt;/em&gt;. The other is that I can get sucked incredibly deep into one genre so that I end up reading only theology or programming or the like for six months. Having a plan and a reading list will help me both dig deeply and in focused ways into the subjects on which I want to think (and write!) more, but it will also help me balance that with a good mix of other kinds of reading from other fields—something which is both broadly helpful and which inevitably &lt;a href="http://2012-2013.chriskrycho.com/art/and-the-stew-tastes-good/"&gt;produces a better mix of insights&lt;/a&gt; than just reading one subject in isolation does.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But, for all the reasons outlined above: not now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I still have books I want to read over the rest of this year. The list right now looks like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fyodor Dostoevsky, &lt;em&gt;The Idiot&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Daniel Kahneman, &lt;em&gt;Thinking, Fast and Slow&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Oliver O’Donovan, &lt;em&gt;Resurrection and Moral Order&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Brandon Sanderson, the various sequels to &lt;em&gt;Alcatraz Versus the Evil Librarians&lt;/em&gt; (which I read and quite enjoyed last month)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Charles Taylor, &lt;em&gt;A Secular Age&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;J. R. R. Tolkien, &lt;em&gt;Beren and Lúthien&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That’s a “list,” but it’s a list composed of exactly one kind of book: whatever I feel like reading. There are other books I’ve already started that aren’t on that list because while they’re important to me, they’re not decompressive at all: they feel like work, like pressure. And what I and my family need right now—especially in the midst of planning a cross-country move to be nearer our families in a new home!—is to relieve pressure, not add more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So now I’m going to go read one of those books on our porch. Whichever one I feel like. And then I’ll read whichever one I feel like &lt;em&gt;next&lt;/em&gt;. And if the list changes, that’s fine too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;i class="editorial"&gt;Note: I cross-posted this to &lt;a href="http://krycho.com"&gt;our new family blog&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 10 Jun 2017 10:00:00 -0400</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2017-06-10:/2017/on-decompression.html</guid><category>reading</category><category>writing</category><category>rest</category></item></channel></rss>