<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Chris Krycho - rewrite</title><link>http://v4.chriskrycho.com/</link><description></description><lastBuildDate>Wed, 04 Sep 2019 21:30:00 -0400</lastBuildDate><item><title>rewrite Dev Journal: How I Started</title><link>http://v4.chriskrycho.com/2019/rewrite-dev-journal-how-i-started.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;a href="https://v4.chriskrycho.com/2018/assumed-audiences.html"&gt;Assumed Audience&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/b&gt; practitioners or interested lookers-on for software development—especially indies.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This week, I started the &lt;i&gt;actually writing software&lt;/i&gt; phase of working on &lt;a href="https://rewrite.software"&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;i&gt;re&lt;/i&gt;write&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. As of yesterday evening, I actually have a bit of code that, although useless in every way, and not especially attractive, does in fact displays a single reference on an iPhone screen. I have an incredibly, impossibly long way to go.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It doesn’t matter: I &lt;em&gt;started&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had the day off on Monday courtesy of Labor Day, and I chose to spend the chunk of it that &lt;em&gt;wasn’t&lt;/em&gt; focused on chores and housework and family time on actually getting this thing moving. I’ve been dreaming for over four years now. That time wasn’t wasted, by a long shot, but as I noted in &lt;a href="https://v4.chriskrycho.com/2019/announcing-rewrite.html"&gt;my announcement post&lt;/a&gt;, you can plan forever… or you can just start building at some point.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The problem I had—as I noted &lt;a href="https://v4.chriskrycho.com/2019/starting.html"&gt;back in July&lt;/a&gt;—is that I didn’t actually feel like I knew &lt;em&gt;how&lt;/em&gt; to start. This a mammoth project, for one thing. For another, doing this kind of indie work requires dramatically improving my design and product chops. And of course, developing for native apps means learning whole new technology stacks as well!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ve known all along that the only way to get anywhere was to break the problem down. You know: the same as always in software development. Find something small to start on. I had already identified which &lt;em&gt;part&lt;/em&gt; of the app to dig into first: reference management. This is a place where I could have something that is useful to &lt;em&gt;me&lt;/em&gt; in reasonably short order (I want to be able to update my own reference library on my iPad!). Even that was daunting, though—still far too large.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, Monday, I asked: &lt;i&gt;What is the smallest possible reference-related functionality I could build?&lt;/i&gt; The answer, I concluded, was: &lt;i&gt;just display an existing library of references.&lt;/i&gt; Then I went further, because “display an existing library of references” is surprisingly complicated. It involves, at a minimum:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;defining how to display a reference
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;…and therefore also designing the data structures representing references&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;actually building that display&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;defining how to display a list of references to the user—which things to include, which not to, etc.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;actually building that list&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;making it so that tapping on an item in a list displays the detailed view defined previously&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;making it so you can get back &lt;em&gt;out&lt;/em&gt; of the detail view to the list view again&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;loading a list of references from somewhere, e.g. a BibTeX file from iCloud Drive&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;parsing that list of references into the internal data structures designed to represent them&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, for an experienced iOS or macOS developer, some of those things might feel trivial enough that they don’t even warrant their own bullet point. But I’m &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; an experienced iOS or macOS developer; I have no idea how to do any of this! What’s more breaking it down that way means that I have small, discrete tasks that I can go after in small blocks of time. Remember: this is a side project, which I am fitting in around my day job, my church commitments, and time with friends and family. I have to be able to make progress in small blocks of time! I have to &lt;em&gt;feel&lt;/em&gt; that progress, at least a little, so that I can keep going.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Every bullet point on the list I came up with represents a discrete item of work. It not only &lt;em&gt;may&lt;/em&gt; but &lt;em&gt;must&lt;/em&gt; be small, so that I can do it in an evening or three. It needs to be done in such a way that later steps can build on it—but it doesn’t actually need to be anything like what those later steps will transform it into. It just needs to be enough to keep momentum moving, and done in such a way that later changes are not too difficult to make.&lt;a href="#fn1" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref1" role="doc-noteref"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Monday evening, I took the items I had identified and turned them into GitHub Issues in a GitHub project, called &lt;b&gt;Display a BibTeX Library&lt;/b&gt;. (I’ll talk about how I’m using GitHub projects a little at some point in the future; it’s a nice flow so far.) Every single one of those items, no matter how apparently small, got its own card. One of them, about Swift-Rust interop, got a note saying, roughly, “I’m pretty sure this will need to be its own whole sub-project.” And looking at that list… I felt a lot less daunted! Every one of the tasks involves something I don’t know how to do yet—but only &lt;em&gt;one&lt;/em&gt; thing I don’t know how to do yet, not &lt;em&gt;many&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last night, I took the first item on the list: display a single reference item. Not &lt;em&gt;parsing&lt;/em&gt; them, not even from a string hard-coded into the app, and certainly not loading a file or anything like that. Just hard-coding in a data structure and displaying it on the screen. And, over the course of a few hours, including &lt;em&gt;lots&lt;/em&gt; of searching&lt;a href="#fn2" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref2" role="doc-noteref"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; for answers about specific SwiftUI error messages,&lt;a href="#fn3" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref3" role="doc-noteref"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; I managed to implement that one thing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I said above: it’s &lt;em&gt;useless&lt;/em&gt; in the strict sense. It’s not especially pretty, either. But it’s progress. I started. And now I have that little sense of momentum, and I can keep going!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn1" role="doc-endnote"&gt;&lt;p&gt;If you think this sounds like the ideas current in the best parts of agile software development—working to make future changes easy; iterating rapidly; delivering the smallest possible chunks of value, and doing so continuously—you’re not wrong!&lt;a href="#fnref1" class="footnote-back" role="doc-backlink"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn2" role="doc-endnote"&gt;&lt;p&gt;“Searching,” not “Googling,” because I only very rarely Google anything. I search, with &lt;a href="https://duckduckgo.com"&gt;Duck Duck Go&lt;/a&gt; as my starting point and its &lt;a href="https://duckduckgo.com/bang"&gt;! search commands&lt;/a&gt; as power tools for searches in specific places.&lt;a href="#fnref2" class="footnote-back" role="doc-backlink"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn3" role="doc-endnote"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Wow&lt;/em&gt; could SwiftUI’s compiler diagnostics use some improvement! I sincerely hope that the Swift team in general and the SwiftUI folks in particular take a close look at Rust and Elm for inspiration here.&lt;a href="#fnref3" class="footnote-back" role="doc-backlink"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 04 Sep 2019 21:30:00 -0400</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:v4.chriskrycho.com,2019-09-04:/2019/rewrite-dev-journal-how-i-started.html</guid><category>rewrite</category><category>rewrite dev journal</category><category>software development</category><category>productivity</category></item><item><title>Starting</title><link>http://v4.chriskrycho.com/2019/starting.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;a href="https://v4.chriskrycho.com/2018/assumed-audiences.html"&gt;Assumed Audience&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/b&gt; anyone who has ever struggled to start something new and unknown and therefore difficult and intimidating.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am sitting here on a weekday evening, trying to figure out exactly how to &lt;em&gt;start&lt;/em&gt; building &lt;a href="https://rewrite.software"&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;i&gt;re&lt;/i&gt;write&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. There is an enormous amount to be done, and I genuinely have no idea how to do… almost any of it. I asked myself: “Where would I start if this were a web app?”—because web apps are my bread and butter, the place I have spent the majority of my time over the last half decade.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the answer is that I &lt;em&gt;still&lt;/em&gt; don’t know. I have only started two completely “greenfield” projects in my entire career. In every other case someone else had done &lt;em&gt;this&lt;/em&gt; part, and in most cases I was working with a product manager or someone like that, who was divvying up the tasks. And those two greenfield projects were (a) extremely well-scoped and (b) of a very different sort than this one is. The last time I started a truly greenfield app, it was for a web app… but a web app &lt;em&gt;extremely&lt;/em&gt; heavy on words: exactly my home terrain, as it were, on the web. Not that different from a blog.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is not like that. The problems to solve—managing references, dealing with PDFs, writing large documents, building up projects, you name it: they are all &lt;em&gt;completely&lt;/em&gt; new to me. And it’s just me: no product owner handing me feature specs.&lt;a href="#fn1" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref1" role="doc-noteref"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; I’m out of my comfort zone even in terms of the technologies I’m using: no deep comfort with the web stack here to fall back on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Can I do this? Yes. I can. I’ll figure it out. I have figured out hard things before. But it doesn’t change the fact that &lt;em&gt;starting is hard&lt;/em&gt;, and I have no idea how to begin.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m going to start anyway. Most of what I build these next few weeks will almost certainly get thrown away. That’s okay. I’ll have started. That’s enough for now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An aside, a confession: I have made an enormous amount of progress on my website redesign over the last month. Some of that is because it’s just plain fun. Some of it, though, is because it’s easier to keep working in my comfort zone than to buckle down and get started on the hard new thing where I have &lt;em&gt;no&lt;/em&gt; comfort at all. Time to get into it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn1" role="doc-endnote"&gt;&lt;p&gt;however ill defined!&lt;a href="#fnref1" class="footnote-back" role="doc-backlink"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 16 Jul 2019 21:00:00 -0400</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:v4.chriskrycho.com,2019-07-16:/2019/starting.html</guid><category>rewrite</category><category>software development</category></item><item><title>Announcing rewrite</title><link>http://v4.chriskrycho.com/2019/announcing-rewrite.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;a href="https://v4.chriskrycho.com/2018/assumed-audiences.html"&gt;Assumed Audience&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/b&gt; people interested in note-taking, research, and long-form writing.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the past four years, I have been dreaming of an absurdly ambitious application: a tool that can actually handle research writing &lt;em&gt;well&lt;/em&gt;. Good research writing—whether it’s a college paper or a Ph.D. thesis, a journal publication or a magazine article, a scholarly blog or a big book—is a complex and challenging task. At a &lt;em&gt;minimum&lt;/em&gt;, research writing includes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;finding resources, tracking references to them, and citing them correctly&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;taking, and making good use of, notes—including quotes from those references&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;writing large, complex, highly structured documents&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;publishing in a &lt;em&gt;very&lt;/em&gt; specific format for everything from typeface to page margins to citation styles&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are tools out there which handle &lt;em&gt;some&lt;/em&gt; of those pieces well—a few genuinely great notes apps in particular, and some solid contenders in the reference management space. They don’t play together well, though—whether it’s sync errors between apps, the disjointed experience of using tools which know almost nothing about each other, fighting with different journals’ styles, or the simple pain of trying to &lt;em&gt;write&lt;/em&gt; in what is really a &lt;i&gt;desktop publishing tool&lt;/i&gt; (looking at you, Microsoft Word).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And I would know: over the course of my M.Div., I wrote well over a hundred thousand words of papers; and never mind the many books’ worth of notes I took.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I eventually found a flow that worked for me during those years, pulling together &lt;a href="https://daringfireball.net/projects/markdown"&gt;Markdown&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/BibTeX"&gt;BibTeX&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://pandoc.org"&gt;pandoc&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href="https://citationstyles.org"&gt;&lt;abbr title="citation style languages"&gt;CSL&lt;/abbr&gt;s&lt;/a&gt; to generate Word documents. (I wrote about that &lt;a href="https://v4.chriskrycho.com/2015/academic-markdown-and-citations.html"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, if you’re curious.) It did what I wanted! But it was arcane: even after years of working that way, I could never remember the various script invocations involved without looking them up. In short: there was something wonderful there… but the user experience was terrible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even by the time I wrote &lt;a href="https://v4.chriskrycho.com/2015/academic-markdown-and-citations.html"&gt;that blog post&lt;/a&gt;, I was thinking: &lt;i&gt;what would a genuinely great app in this space look like?&lt;/i&gt; I had sketched out the basics in a notebook early that month—&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src="https://f001.backblazeb2.com/file/rewrite/first-page.jpeg" title="a picture of the first page of my working notebook" alt="the first page of my working notebook" /&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;the first page of my working notebook&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;—and I haven’t stopped thinking about it ever since. &lt;i&gt;How do you do reference management well? What makes for a good note-taking system? How do you author large, complex documents with easy reference to those notes? How do you pull all those all together for publishing? How do you make it a &lt;em&gt;great&lt;/em&gt; app &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; make it cross-platform?&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the past four years, I have been doing two things in preparation for building &lt;b&gt;&lt;i&gt;re&lt;/i&gt;write&lt;/b&gt; (the working title for this app):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;filling up that same notebook with design constraints, software architecture considerations, and business model ideas&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;developing the technical skills I’ll need to actually deliver on that dream&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even with those years of planning, though, I’d be lying if I said I feel ready to take this on: this project is huge. It will take years to get to a minimum viable product. But you can plan forever and never ship… or you can just get moving, whether you feel ready or not. I quietly launched &lt;a href="https://buttondown.email/rewrite"&gt;a newsletter&lt;/a&gt; for the project back at the end of April, and over the past few weeks since getting back from vacation—and having at last &lt;a href="https://v4.chriskrycho.com/2019/finishing-things-on-the-internet.html"&gt;wrapped up New Rustacean&lt;/a&gt;—I have been working on it in earnest. I started digging into &lt;a href="https://developer.apple.com/xcode/swiftui/"&gt;SwiftUI&lt;/a&gt;, and have been sketching out more detailed &lt;abbr title="user interface"&gt;UI&lt;/abbr&gt; ideas, and even decided on what to build first.&lt;a href="#fn1" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref1" role="doc-noteref"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And so today, I’m publicly “launching” the project, by which I mean: giving it a little more fanfare than I have previously by blogging about it here &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; by giving it its own website: &lt;a href="https://rewrite.software"&gt;rewrite.software&lt;/a&gt;. For now, it’s just a simple landing page with a form to sign up for the mailing list, mostly there so I have a place to direct people to sign up for &lt;a href="https://buttondown.email/rewrite"&gt;the project mailing list&lt;/a&gt;. Anything more than that would be a distraction from what I really need to be doing now: learning and building!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hope some of you will follow along as I take on this absurdly ambitious project, and I expect to be blogging about my adventures in Swift and SwiftUI, Rust, and more in the years to come!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn1" role="doc-endnote"&gt;&lt;p&gt;I’m going to try to ship a nice tool for managing references. It’ll be good to have the experience of actually &lt;em&gt;shipping&lt;/em&gt; an app. More on that&lt;a href="#fnref1" class="footnote-back" role="doc-backlink"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 06 Jul 2019 21:50:00 -0400</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:v4.chriskrycho.com,2019-07-06:/2019/announcing-rewrite.html</guid><category>rewrite</category><category>software development</category><category>note-taking</category></item></channel></rss>