<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Chris Krycho - running</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/</link><description></description><lastBuildDate>Sun, 19 May 2019 14:30:00 -0400</lastBuildDate><item><title>2019 Colfax Half Marathon</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2019/colfax-half-marathon.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.chriskrycho.com/2018/assumed-audiences.html"&gt;Assumed audience:&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/b&gt; people into the details of endurance running and races. (Yes, I know that’s probably a vanishingly small part of my normal readership. That’s just fine.)&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today I ran the half marathon event in the &lt;a href="https://www.runcolfax.org"&gt;Colfax Marathon&lt;/a&gt;. You can see the details &lt;a href="https://www.runningahead.com/logs/2667b469aeda433382cbcc8ed413d964/workouts/b6d8515e11024cd5badd240ef0515b11"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; (I prefer &lt;a href="https://www.strava.com/activities/2380401838/overview"&gt;Strava’s presentation&lt;/a&gt;, but you have to have an account to see most of it.) I finished at 1:29:56 wall time, and 1:29:50 chip time. (The difference is because I started at the &lt;em&gt;back&lt;/em&gt; of the first corral instead of the &lt;em&gt;front&lt;/em&gt; and had to wait for a few dozen people to get moving in front of me.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am exceedingly pleased with this outcome. It would have gone better had I followed my race plan and not pushed so hard on the climbs—and the fact that I am still a bit sick I noticed throughout. Still: I could not be happier with my first race at altitude.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;58th overall, out of 4617 = top 1.25%&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;48th among men, out of 1830 = top 2.7%&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;19th among 30–39-year-olds, out of 671 = top 2.9%&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Somewhat more details observations on the race:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol type="1"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I went out too fast. I felt &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; good at first, and paid for it at the end. This is not new to me; I’ve done it in most races. Over the summer, I need to actively practice doing negative splits on tempo runs—and I need to do that with both downhills &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; uphills… see the next point! I also need to practice hitting specific tempos so I can do a better job holding myself to a given speed at a given time.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Hills, even little ones like this, still just murder my legs’ ability to keep spinning. &lt;em&gt;Especially&lt;/em&gt; given the profile of &lt;a href="https://www.strava.com/routes/18686447"&gt;my next race&lt;/a&gt; (it has literally 4× as much climb as today’s race did, and it starts ~1,800 feet higher), I need to spend some time this summer doing two things (in &lt;em&gt;addition&lt;/em&gt; to continuing strength training and the point noted in #1):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol type="1"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cycling! That should be a really helpful complement and strengthen exactly the muscles I need.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Speed work! Now that I have a really solid aerobic base again, I need to start amping up my anaerobic capacity in kind.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Not being sick would also help. Not that I can perfectly control that, of course, but I could feel the effect that had in terms of general physical fatigue and getting light-headed and a rather unhappy headache for the last five miles or so.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Bringing my own water is essential. I can &lt;em&gt;never&lt;/em&gt; hydrate well enough with cups along the way. Best bet is probably a belt: I don’t need a &lt;em&gt;lot&lt;/em&gt;, but more than I had today. I hydrated reasonably well ahead of the race, but I do not doubt this contributed to the headache and light-headedness. (I know they were at least partially from being sick, though, because I had those symptoms &lt;em&gt;all week&lt;/em&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Next time I run a race, I want to actually plan out a specific tempo and effort level on a per-mile basis, and see how that works. I &lt;em&gt;suspect&lt;/em&gt; it will help. The main possible downside I see is that I might &lt;em&gt;under&lt;/em&gt;-do it going at it that way, but if I end up having a lot of juice left I can probably make up a fair bit of that just by crushing the final 5k.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All of those thoughts on what I do next notwithstanding, I remain &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; happy with this outcome, and I am glad to be getting back into the swing of things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One final note: the best data I can find online suggests that 5,000 feet of altitude is worth ~15–20 seconds/mile at this distance; that would make this race &lt;em&gt;very&lt;/em&gt; close to my best. I suspect I would have run the same course at sea level &lt;em&gt;somewhat&lt;/em&gt; faster… but not 15–20s/mi faster. Why? See #1 and #2 above: the real problem was that I went out too fast and didn’t have enough leg strength left over at the end, &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; that I didn’t have the aerobic or anaerobic capacity. (Looking at the &lt;a href="https://www.strava.com/activities/2380401838/overview"&gt;heart rate data&lt;/a&gt; from the race confirms this, and I noticed it even during the run: my problem the last few miles was leg endurance; my HR was actually &lt;em&gt;dropping&lt;/em&gt; in miles 10–13.)&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 19 May 2019 14:30:00 -0400</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2019-05-19:/2019/colfax-half-marathon.html</guid><category>running</category><category>fitness</category></item><item><title>Seeing Things Through</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2019/seeing-things-through.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.chriskrycho.com/2018/assumed-audiences.html"&gt;Assumed Audience&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/b&gt; Just about anyone. But especially people interested in ideas of “productivity” or accomplishing the things we set out to do.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have on my mind this week starting things, and finishing things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I picked up a chest strap heart-rate monitor again a week ago, and took a run with it. It felt like starting (&lt;em&gt;again&lt;/em&gt;, in this case!) with running. I am training for a couple of half marathons and a long couple days’ of road cycling in the Rocky Mountains in between them. As I wrote in a &lt;a href="https://www.chriskrycho.com/2019/serious-running-and-my-heart-rate-monitor.html"&gt;blog post earlier this week&lt;/a&gt;, putting that chest strap on flipped the little switch in my brain that said “This is serious running again.” It helps to have registered for those races and committed to that event. I have &lt;em&gt;always&lt;/em&gt; done better at running when I have had a concrete goal in view. It has helped me with &lt;em&gt;finishing&lt;/em&gt;. Though I have had to skip out on a few races I have registered for by way of illness or (in one case) moving across the country, I have only failed to train up sufficiently for a race I had registered for &lt;em&gt;once&lt;/em&gt; (and that, too, was a function of illness, though it wasn’t initially clear to me).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over the past four months I decided it was time to start working seriously on some things I have been thinking about for a long time now. One is developing an app (really: a family of them) that I have been nooding on for almost four years now. Another is learning how to build programming languages. Still another is writing some long-form essays, the subjects of which I have been mulling on in some way or another for as long as five years. My challenge in these kinds of projects is twofold: in many cases, the projects themselves are large enough as to seem daunting to me. In others, though I start them, I find the finishing difficult when I am already tired with the many other things on my plate. Having specific and concrete goals would, it seems to me, &lt;em&gt;help&lt;/em&gt;—just as in running.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have, several times now, started open source software projects and never finished them. I have started a (genuinely interesting!) novel/novella/short story (the format is hard to nail down for this idea!) three or four times, and never seen it through. I have a handful of &lt;em&gt;very good&lt;/em&gt; essays sitting in my drafts folder that I began either for this site or for Mere Orthodoxy during my seminary years; some of them are 90% done and had I taken just another half an hour they would have been ready to go.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Strange though it might seem to people who see only what looks like very high productivity from me, I have a surprisingly hard time &lt;em&gt;finishing&lt;/em&gt; things. Starting them is easy. But sitting down, week in and week out, to get them across the line—it is &lt;em&gt;hard&lt;/em&gt;. The more amorphous the task, the less clear-cut “done” is, the harder I find it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of my goals for the rest of my thirties is to get better at this: at picking specific projects and leaning into them until I finish them. Even if that means setting aside other good and important projects along the way. There are only so many hours in the day, and there are many few of them available for side projects when one aims to be a good husband and father. I am still getting a handle on this; more reports from the field as I hopefully improve at it!&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 02 Mar 2019 20:10:00 -0500</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2019-03-02:/2019/seeing-things-through.html</guid><category>writing</category><category>software development</category><category>productivity</category><category>running</category></item><item><title>“Serious” Running and My Heart Rate Monitor</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2019/serious-running-and-my-heart-rate-monitor.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.chriskrycho.com/2018/assumed-audiences.html"&gt;Assumed Audience&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/b&gt; People interested in habits, fitness, or emotions, or especially how they intersect&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today I took the second “long” run of my training season for &lt;a href="http://www.runcolfax.org"&gt;the first&lt;/a&gt; of two half marathons I’m running this year (in May; &lt;a href="https://www.enduranceraceseries.com/palmer-lake"&gt;the other&lt;/a&gt; is in September). As I was showering afterward, I kept feeling that something was &lt;em&gt;right&lt;/em&gt; in my world again—that I was actually &lt;em&gt;seriously&lt;/em&gt; training for a half marathon again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Two things about that thought caught my attention.&lt;a href="#fn1" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref1" role="doc-noteref"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; The first: it is telling of how deeply a part of my life running in general and half marathons in particular have become over the last 8 years. I could say much more about that, and perhaps I will in some future post. For &lt;em&gt;this&lt;/em&gt; post, though, I want to focus on the second: &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt; it felt right to me. After all: this is &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; the first time I’ve been training seriously for a half marathon in a few years. The last time I successfully completed a half marathon was 2015, but I have &lt;em&gt;trained&lt;/em&gt; for one every year since then—failing to run them only because of a mix of sickness (in 2016 and 2018) and moving across the country instead (in 2017).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why, then, did I feel today like I was seriously training for the first time in years? I laughed out loud when I realized: this was the first time I put on my chest strap heart rate monitor since mid-2017. I picked up an Apple Watch Series 2 that April, and decided its wrist-based heart-rate monitoring was good &lt;em&gt;enough&lt;/em&gt; for my purposes and stuck with it for the last couple years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I really like the Apple Watch in a lot ways. I’ve increasingly been frustrated by its limitations, though—from the lack of reliable feedback on heart rate zones; to the annoying little wrist flick I have to do to see my current stats, since the screen is not constantly on; to the fact that it &lt;em&gt;has&lt;/em&gt; to be attached directly to my wrist, no matter how cold it is and therefore how inconvenient that is; to the ways it just loses my heart-rate signal at times, especially when cycling. So, today, I strapped back on my my Garmin with its ANT+ chest strap-style heart-rate monitor and took &lt;a href="https://www.strava.com/activities/2173404125"&gt;a run&lt;/a&gt; with it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;That&lt;/em&gt; was the difference: putting on a chest strap and a &lt;abbr&gt;GPS&lt;/abbr&gt; watch. Now, that probably seems weird to you. It seems a little weird to me! What I realized, though, is that I had been wearing a chest strap heart rate monitor since I started training for my first half marathon, all the way back in January 2011. The particular strap and the particular associated watch have varied over the years, but all the time until mid-2017, there was a watch on my wrist and a strap around my chest. Somewhere along the way I (wholly subconsciously!) learned to associated those physical cues with training seriously. So when I put a chest strap heart rate monitor again today, it flipped that switch in my brain, and things felt right again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sometimes it is easy for us to forget just how thoroughly our physicality matters. The deep reality is that we are &lt;em&gt;embodied minds&lt;/em&gt;—the two undivorceable.&lt;a href="#fn2" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref2" role="doc-noteref"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; Things like chest straps end up mattering to us. It seems strange that such a little thing would affect me so much, but affect me deeply it does. All the little ways I have trained my body matter. Though I could train it differently… I probably won’t, in this case. More on that, and on Apple Watch, sometime in the future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn1" role="doc-endnote"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Yes, I was thinking about what I was thinking. This is normal for me.&lt;a href="#fnref1" class="footnote-back" role="doc-backlink"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn2" role="doc-endnote"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Yes, modulo qualifications about divine activity in the time between our death and our resurrection. There are many mysteries about that state; I will be content with “mystery” as the description for it. The point in any case is that we are destined for resurrection (one way or another): body and mind united again forever (to joy or to damnation).&lt;a href="#fnref2" class="footnote-back" role="doc-backlink"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 24 Feb 2019 20:12:00 -0500</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2019-02-24:/2019/serious-running-and-my-heart-rate-monitor.html</guid><category>fitness</category><category>running</category><category>thinking</category><category>habit</category></item><item><title>Neither Being Dumb Nor Giving In</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2018/neither-being-dumb-nor-giving-in.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;One of the ways I respond to my experience of burnout is &lt;em&gt;refusing&lt;/em&gt; to let the fact that I’m experiencing burnout set the terms of my life. I cannot ignore the fact that I’m burnt out unless I want to make things worse. But I also recognize that with experiences like burnout, letting them dominate our mental lives can make things significantly worse, too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is a fine little dance here: acknowledging the reality of the hard things we experience, while not narrowing our lives to &lt;em&gt;merely&lt;/em&gt; those hard things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An example of the way I try to walk this line in my own life: I am not holding myself to some of the exercise goals I set for myself before the worst of the burnout set in… but I am still exercising every day. That half marathon I wanted to run at the end of this month? I’m not running it. On too many runs in the last few weeks my body has simply shut down a few miles into a run. Two miles in, six miles in, three miles in… none of them are anything like 13.1 miles. So while I’ve managed a 14-mile run this training season, in the weeks since I did I have gotten loud, clear signals that continuing to push myself toward the race was a bad idea.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That doesn’t mean I’m going to stop running, though. It means I’m going to be careful and wise about it. I’m going to listen to my body even more carefully when I’m out on a run than I normally do (and I’m not one of those people who keeps running when they shouldn’t anyway!). I’m going to switch some days over to doing Pilates with my wife instead of running. But also, on days like this past Saturday, when I felt &lt;em&gt;terrible&lt;/em&gt; emotionally and wanted nothing more than to lay in bed… I got up and went for a 4-mile run. It helped.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Again: I won’t be dumb about my response to my burnout and pretend it doesn’t exist. But I also refuse to let especially the emotional experience of burnout be wholly determinative of what I do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An aside, and a thing I will come back to in the future: you may have noticed that I have avoided writing of burnout as something external to me. This is intentional. Too often in our discussions of burnout, depression, or the like, we externalize them—a way of distancing ourselves from them, usually aimed at the same kinds of things I’ve gestured at in this little post. For reasons I’ll come back to, I don’t think that’s quite the right solution: burnout is not a foe outside myself to vanquish, but a set of emotional, physical, and spiritual things &lt;em&gt;about&lt;/em&gt; myself. Again: more on that in the future.&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 15 Oct 2018 09:20:00 -0400</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2018-10-15:/2018/neither-being-dumb-nor-giving-in.html</guid><category>burnout</category><category>exercise</category><category>running</category></item></channel></rss>