<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Chris Krycho - science fiction</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/</link><description></description><lastBuildDate>Sun, 19 Aug 2018 16:00:00 -0400</lastBuildDate><item><title>The Calculating Stars</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2018/the-calculating-stars.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&amp;lt;i class=editorial&amp;gt;I keep my book review ratings simple—they’re either &lt;em&gt;required&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;recommended&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;recommended with qualifications&lt;/em&gt;, or &lt;em&gt;not recommended&lt;/em&gt;. If you want the TL;DR, this is it:&amp;lt;/i&amp;gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Required:&lt;/strong&gt; Mary Robinette Kowal’s alt-history of the space program (after a meteor strike!) is wonderful—smashingly-good plotting which somehow makes a half decade span feel &lt;em&gt;urgent&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;fast-paced&lt;/em&gt;; a fantastic lead character; an interesting examination of women’s friendships; and frank treatment of both sexism and mental illness without being preachy about either. This was one of my favorite pieces of science-fiction I’ve read in a long time.&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 19 Aug 2018 16:00:00 -0400</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2018-08-19:/2018/the-calculating-stars.html</guid><category>book reviews</category><category>science fiction</category><category>sexism</category></item><item><title>Agent of Change</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2018/agent-of-change.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;i class=editorial&gt;I keep my book review ratings simple—they’re either &lt;em&gt;required&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;recommended&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;recommended with qualifications&lt;/em&gt;, or &lt;em&gt;not recommended&lt;/em&gt;. If you want the TL;DR, this is it:&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Recommended:&lt;/strong&gt; Sometimes you just need “popcorn”—and Sharon Lee and Steve Miller’s first novel is exactly that. (Just… pardon the frequent POV switches.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At my friend &lt;a href="http://stephencarradini.com"&gt;Stephen&lt;/a&gt;’s recommendation (“a surprisingly fun sci-fi adventure romp. Lots of romantic tension, surprisingly chaste (and pretty satisfying) payoff [with] some of the coolest, most interesting protagonist aliens I’ve read about in a long time”) I picked up Sharon Lee and Steve Miller’s &lt;em&gt;Agent of Change&lt;/em&gt;,&lt;a href="#fn1" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref1"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and I quite enjoyed it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sometimes, in the midst of hammering away at work and dealing with the tumult of moving into a new house, it’s nice to grab the literary equivalent of a bag of chips or a bowl of popcorn. This is that. There was nothing in this book that was anything like as interesting or engaging as sci-fi &lt;a href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2017/icehenge.html" title="Icehenge (review on this site)"&gt;can be&lt;/a&gt;—but it was, in Stephen’s words, an &lt;em&gt;adventure romp&lt;/em&gt;, and that was perfect. The characters are fun, well-drawn if never particularly surprising. The plot is essentially an escape story (and in more ways than it first appears).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The only real &lt;em&gt;problem&lt;/em&gt; on display with the book is that it completely disregards anything like modern conventions around point-of-view. A paragraph break is sufficient for a total change of internal perspective. This drove me crazy the entire book.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Might I read another entry in this universe, the next time I’m looking for merely a romp? Indeed I might.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section class="footnotes"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn1"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Agent of Change&lt;/em&gt; is the first book in their Liaden series. It’s also listed as anything &lt;em&gt;but&lt;/em&gt; the first book, because republication and branding have dropped it at its chronological position in their larger universe… but book &lt;em&gt;nine&lt;/em&gt; it is not, whatever Amazon tells you.&lt;a href="#fnref1" class="footnote-back"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 16 Feb 2018 06:30:00 -0500</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2018-02-16:/2018/agent-of-change.html</guid><category>book reviews</category><category>science fiction</category></item><item><title>Icehenge</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2017/icehenge.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;i class=editorial&gt;I keep my book review ratings simple—they’re either &lt;em&gt;required&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;recommended&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;recommended with qualifications&lt;/em&gt;, or &lt;em&gt;not recommended&lt;/em&gt;. If you want the TL;DR, this is it:&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Recommended:&lt;/strong&gt; this is good sci-fi—the kind that makes you think while also being a bit of a page-turner.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kim Stanley Robinson comes highly recommended, so in a moment of overwhelming need to read science fiction the other evening, I snagged a novel of his in ebook form, and read it over the weekend. I loved it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Do you remember being 6? I have only the barest glimmers of it. An image will come rushing back sometimes, of something I experienced then—a moment of delight, or horror, all at once, full of sensation and bright color and feeling. Or a smell will bring something from my teenage years back: cut grass makes me think of two-a-day practices for football, without fail. But the past is behind me in a way that is hard to describe, and which I have often thought about, but rarely so much as in the days I was reading (and in the days since finished reading) this little novel about the politics of Mars and a slowly-colonizing Solar System.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because &lt;em&gt;Icehenge&lt;/em&gt;, its name notwithstanding, really isn’t much at all about a massive Stonehenge-like construction, all of ice, on Pluto. It’s about memory, and what it would be like to live to 600 in a body that ages slowly but with a mind still incapable of holding on to the past, and the stories we tell to make sense of the world, and the hunger for truth, and the things that get in the way of the pure pursuit of the truth, and power, and loneliness, and what the past means and how we get at it in the present.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I expect to be reading considerably more of KSR.&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 14 Aug 2017 21:00:00 -0400</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2017-08-14:/2017/icehenge.html</guid><category>book reviews</category><category>science fiction</category><category>mars</category></item></channel></rss>