<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Chris Krycho</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/</link><description></description><atom:link href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/feeds/sebts.xml" rel="self"></atom:link><lastBuildDate>Sat, 25 Apr 2015 10:00:00 -0400</lastBuildDate><item><title>An Uncomfortable Fit</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2015/an-uncomfortable-fit.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;I grew up in a small, non-denominational, baptistic, charismatic church.
Speaking in tongues, the use of private prayer languages, claims to words of
knowledge and prophecies, and the expectation of miraculous healings were
common. Unfortunately, even granting a continuationist view of the gifts, the
church&amp;rsquo;s practice was never in line with New Testament guidelines for the
gifts&amp;mdash;no translation of tongues, for example, or requirement that prophecy be
fulfilled for the prophet to be judged true. I grew disillusioned with the
charismatic approach to the gifts by late high school, and spent several of the
following years as a near-cessationist. I remain skeptical of most charismatic
churches&amp;rsquo; practice of the gifts, but am not a cessationist: I see no compelling
exegetical argument for the position. I am especially open to the likelihood of
the miraculous gifts in frontier missions context, where they serve to validate
the proclamation of the gospel over and above demonic powers worshipped in
polytheistic, animistic, and shamanistic cultures.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In college, I spent two years attending a fairly traditional Southern Baptist
church. For the latter half of my time in college and the three years following,
I was a member of a non-demoninational, baptistic, broadly evangelical church
with my wife Jaimie. During that time, I remained baptistic, but began to become
concerned with the lack of confessional moorings in most baptistic churches
(denominational or non-denominational alike). Along the way, I shifted from the
non-Calvinistic views held by most charismatics and Baptists to an Edwardsian
Calvinism and developed stronger convictions about church polity. Finally, since
moving to North Carolina, we have been committed members at First Baptist Church
of Durham&amp;mdash;a healthy, elder-led, Calvinistic Southern Baptist church that we
love.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, even here, we find that we are not totally &amp;ldquo;at home&amp;rdquo;; it is not quite
right to call even Calvinistic Southern Baptists &amp;ldquo;my tradition&amp;rdquo;. Indeed, it is
perhaps most accurate to say that I have not yet &lt;em&gt;found&lt;/em&gt; my tradition. What I
have found instead are points to appreciate in a number of traditions, and an
increasing identification (at least from the outside) with many elements of the
Presbyterian tradition. A friend once described me as a &amp;ldquo;Pres-matic Bapt-erian&amp;rdquo;,
and he seems to have been right. I find much to appreciate in the charismatic
background from which I sprang, and much to value in the Baptist tradition where
I currently live&amp;mdash;but at the end of the day, it is only my credobaptist
convictions keeping me within the Baptist world, rather than transitioning into
Presbyterianism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From the charismatic tradition in which I grew up, I learned the value of
affections oriented toward Christ. It is not enough to &lt;em&gt;understand&lt;/em&gt; the things
of God; we must also love him and one another. Our faith must be true &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt;
experiential. John reminds us that &amp;ldquo;this is eternal life, that they know you the
only true God, and Jesus Christ whom you have sent&amp;rdquo; (John 17:3) and that
&amp;ldquo;Whoever says he is in the light and hates his brother is still in darkness&amp;rdquo; (1
John 2:9). Moreover, they emphasized that walking in the Holy Spirit is
essential to the healthy Christian life. Though I might now characterize the
Spirit&amp;rsquo;s primary work differently from the church of my childhood, I still
affirm whole-heartedly that the Christian life is deeply and profoundly
dependent on the Holy Spirit. Paul enjoins us, &amp;ldquo;But I say, walk by the Spirit,
and you will not gratify the desires of the flesh.... If we live by the Spirit,
let us also keep in step with the Spirit&amp;rdquo; (Galatians 5:16, 25). Likewise, John
reports Jesus&amp;rsquo; shocking statement that it is &lt;em&gt;better&lt;/em&gt; for us that he left and
sent the Spirit than that he should have remained with us (John 16:7ff.). The
life of the Christian must be a Spirit-filled and Spirit-empowered life. We can
never overemphasize the work of the Spirit in our lives (though we may sometimes
articulate that work inaccurately).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From the Southern Baptist churches I have attended I have gained a deeper
appreciation for the importance of evangelism and missions. Whether from the
Great Commission in Matthew 28:18&amp;ndash;20 or the similar notes sounded in Luke
24:45&amp;ndash;49 and then throughout the book of Acts, it is clear that God&amp;rsquo;s people
are called to evangelize wherever we go. (Closely related to the above point,
however, this is not mere salesmanship. As Luke points out in Acts 1:8, the
power for the church&amp;rsquo;s missionary work is the Holy Spirit, not human wisdom.) If
the church forgets that her first and foremost calling is the proclamation of
the gospel to all the nations, she will rapidly fall off the cart in one
direction or another.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The historic Baptist emphasis on regenerate church membership and the
congregation&amp;rsquo;s responsibility for discipline are also essential ingredients to
healthy, flourishing churches (and therefore for flourishing individual
Christians). The countless &amp;ldquo;one another&amp;rdquo; passages of the New Testament (e.g.
John 13:34&amp;ndash;35, Ephesians 4:25&amp;ndash;32) emphasize mutual service as an essential
mark of Christian fellowship. Moreover, the well-known church discipline
passages (Matthew 18:15&amp;ndash;20) indicate clearly that the members of a congregation
are to look out for each other&amp;rsquo;s spiritual well-being. Although this care has
sometimes been twisted to abuse in other churches, we are blessed to participate
in a context where the passages&amp;rsquo; emphasis on forgiveness and restoration is kept
front and center. Meaningful membership and congregational care through church
discipline are not universally popular, but they are among the hallmarks of our
particular corner of the Southern Baptist convention. This kind of care for the
saints is not only necessary: it is &lt;em&gt;beautiful&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From my Presbyterian friends I have increasingly come to appreciate a more
thoroughly confessional identity and the value of churches connected not only by
sharing funds but also by polity. Acts 15 highlights that the early church
resolved its most significant outstanding tension not by letting each church go
its own way doctrinally, but by issuing a decision that was binding on &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; the
churches. Granted: the presence of the apostles then means our situation is not
identical. Still, the event demands attention. Even a church with the
illustrious history and (apostolic!) leadership of the congregation at Antioch
did not feel equipped to make serious doctrinal decisions without consulting the
rest of the church. This is not to deny that there are clear marks of local
congregational responsibility throughout the epistles, only that the New
Testament pattern was of churches in active contact, cooperation, and doctrinal
dependence with each other in a way that appears &lt;em&gt;very&lt;/em&gt; similar to a
proto-presbytery, and quite unlike the radical autonomy of Baptist churches.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also find the historic Reformed articulation of the relationship between the
various spheres of life extremely compelling. Calvin and his heirs often
advocated clearly and coherently for the goodness of the created order and for
human activity therein. Here, vocation (including the arts) is taken not merely
as a means to gospel proclamation, but as genuinely good in itself. This theme
runs throughout Scripture: God commanded man to work before the Fall (cf.
Genesis 2:5,15), and though work has been corrupted and made toilsome by the
Fall, it remains good. The world itself was created good (Genesis 1), and though
it groans with us for redemption (Romans 8:19&amp;ndash;23) it still proclaims the glory
of God (see Psalm 19 for just one of many examples). Many evangelicals pay lip
service to the goodness of creation and vocation, but few outside the high
church traditions (especially Anglican, Lutheran, and Presbyterian) carry the
doctrine through in their practice. This leaves me hungry for the kind of
intellectual, vocational, and artistic engagement I see in those traditions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From late modern evangelicalism more broadly I have imbibed both my essential
Christian temperament&amp;mdash;my unsettled, &amp;ldquo;post-denominational&amp;rdquo; eccesiastical
identity included!&amp;mdash;and two other essential ingredients: a sense of
catholicity, and a desire to do more and better in caring for &amp;ldquo;the least of
these.&amp;rdquo; Set against Jesus&amp;rsquo; &amp;ldquo;new command&amp;rdquo; in John 13, the divisions within the
church are painful realities we should strive to see undone wherever possible.
Our disagreements are not trivial; we cannot simply toss them aside. We can,
however, glory in our common experience of &amp;ldquo;mere Christianity&amp;rdquo; and take
opportunities where possible to worship our risen Lord together. We can also
work together across denominational boundaries to care for the orphans and
widows (James 1:27), to confront injustice in this age. The needs of the world
around us are severe and painful; the various wings of the church can and should
unite to bring what tastes we can of the justice and mercy of Christ&amp;rsquo;s kingdom
into the present age&amp;mdash;in the church, and everywhere else (Micah 6:8).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, and perhaps most importantly, I have found in &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; of these movements
a consistent emphasis on the centrality, authority, and sufficiency of
Scripture. From my charismatic, Arminian-leaning youth minister to the pastors
of the middle-America Bible church I attended during and after college to the
elders of Calvinistic Baptist church we now call home, all have pointed
consistently to God&amp;rsquo;s word as his ultimate self-revelation. These churches have&lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; lived out a commitment to the idea that God&amp;rsquo;s word is living and active
(Hebrews 4:12) and profitable in every way (2 Timothy 3:16&amp;ndash;17).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perhaps unsurprisingly, given the number of shifts in my past, the transition to
another tradition would be relatively straightforward; apart from the issue of
believer&amp;rsquo;s baptism, Presbyterianism looks quite appealing even now. Even beyond
these more important convictional differences, I do not fit comfortably within
the Baptistic tradition culturally. Its populism often verges on (and sometimes
crosses into) anti-intellectualism. Its broadly helpful focus on evangelism and
missions too often translates into a reductive approach that reduces all spheres
of life to vehicles for gospel-proclamation&amp;mdash;not recognizing that while in
God&amp;rsquo;s providence they often serve as such, the myriad spheres of life are good
in their own right. The Southern Baptist identification with the culture of the
South is also problematic for someone culturally not a Southerner.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Discussions on the nature of the church and the history of the Baptist movement
in this class have largely solidified my pre-existing discomfort within the
Baptist tradition and somewhat intensified the struggle to define my
ecclesiastical identity. The theological commitments and cultural habits of
(especially Southern) Baptists trouble me deeply. Reading &lt;em&gt;The Baptist Way&lt;/em&gt; had
precisely the opposite effect Norman intended: his polemical rhetoric bore the
marks of profound ignorance of other traditions. Much of the reading on
believers&amp;rsquo; baptism was similarly dismissive&amp;mdash;arguing not against the substance
of other positions, but instead against caricatures thereof. Dockery&amp;rsquo;s call for
renewal and consensus was more helpful, but it, too, had a sectarian bent. The
denomination&amp;rsquo;s (and the broader tradition&amp;rsquo;s) deep anti-intellectualism and
lasting suspicion of creeds and confessions make it unlikely that Southern
Baptists will be able to claim the confessional identity or theological
consensus they need.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is an unfortunate reality that my experience of Baptists has too often been
marked by denominational sectarianism,  anti-intellectualism and
anti-creedalism, and reductionistic and utilitarian approaches to God&amp;rsquo;s world.
To be sure, there are exceptions to these trends, and I am grateful for them.
But it means that, credobaptist though I am, &amp;ldquo;Baptist&amp;rdquo; and especially &amp;ldquo;Southern
Baptist&amp;rdquo; are not and cannot be my ecclesiastical &lt;em&gt;identity&lt;/em&gt; unless they comes to
mean something very different than they have for many years. In the meantime, I
will remain a &amp;ldquo;Pres-matic Bap-terian&amp;rdquo;, and deeply grateful for the traditions
that have shaped me and especially our current church&amp;mdash;even when they are not a
&amp;ldquo;perfect fit&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 25 Apr 2015 10:00:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2015-04-25:2015/an-uncomfortable-fit.html</guid><category>M. Div.</category><category>SEBTS</category><category>papers</category></item><item><title>Repent and Be Baptized</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2015/repent-and-be-baptized.html</link><description>&lt;h2 id="baptismal-theology-and-practice"&gt;Baptismal Theology and Practice&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are only two practices embraced universally throughout the Christian
church: baptism and the Lord&amp;rsquo;s Supper. Even with these, serious differences
remain, reflecting deeper distinctions in the theology and practice of the
church. In the case of baptism, the questions of its meaning and mode tend to
reflect the believer&amp;rsquo;s views on the nature of God&amp;rsquo;s saving work, the covenant
community, and the church. Who should be baptized, and how, where, and under
what circumstances are difficult, important questions. Believers must consider
them carefully and hold their conclusions humbly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="baptismal-theology"&gt;Baptismal Theology&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Baptism should be applied to believers, and is best carried out by immersion.
However, while Baptist churches have often tended toward a dogmatic position on
these, leading to a frequent practice of rebaptism, more caution is
necessary—especially on the second point.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="meaning"&gt;Meaning&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Baptism is the covenant sign of one&amp;rsquo;s entrance into the Christian faith, and
also a means of grace in the life of the Christian—not &lt;em&gt;saving&lt;/em&gt; grace, but real
grace nonetheless, in the same way that fellowship with the saints, the
preaching of the word, and the Lord&amp;rsquo;s supper are.&lt;sup id="fnref:1"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:1" rel="footnote"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; God works grace in the
life of believers in their obedience to his commands, of which baptism is among
the clearest in the New Testament (Matt. 28:18–20, Acts 2:38). Moreover, it is
the symbol and in some mysterious way also a means of the believer&amp;rsquo;s union with
Christ in his death and resurrection (Rom. 6:3–4, Col. 2:8–14), an element of
his union with Christ&amp;rsquo;s church (Eph. 4:4–6), and his appeal to God for a pure
conscience (1 Pet. 3:21–22).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Baptism is not merely a symbolic ordinance&lt;sup id="fnref:2"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:2" rel="footnote"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; but, as these passages make
clear, a place in which God works uniquely in the life of the believer. Neither
is paptism a work necessary for salvation, as is clear from the salvation of the
thief on the cross (Luke 23:42–43, as well as from many other places that teach
that faith alone is necessary for salvation). Nor is there warrant in Scripture
for the idea that baptism is a means of regeneration or cleansing from original
sin. Nonetheless, paptism is ordinarily a part of God&amp;rsquo;s saving work in his
people&amp;rsquo;s lives. The reality that some are saved who are never baptized does not
mean it plays no part in the believer&amp;rsquo;s life, but rather that its part is in&lt;em&gt;sanctification&lt;/em&gt; rather than in &lt;em&gt;justification&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="mode"&gt;Mode&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nearly all Baptists historically have argued on the basis of the New Testament
language that baptism &lt;em&gt;must&lt;/em&gt; be by immersion. The word βαπτίζω, usually
transliterated to English as &amp;ldquo;baptize&amp;rdquo; rather than translated, is a secondary
verb derived from the root βάπτω, broadly meaning simply &amp;ldquo;to dip or immerse.&amp;rdquo;
While a full exegetical treatment is beyond the scope of this essay, two points
must be remembered in any discussion of baptism. First, the normal meaning of
both these words &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; dipping or immersion, and there are a number of examples
which strongly suggest going down into and coming up out of standing water
(Matt. 3:6–17, Mark 1:4–11, John 3:22, Acts 8:36–39). Second, however, the
lexical domain of these verbs and of the various words derived from them within
the New Testament alone is broader than dipping or immersion, and certainly
includes the notion of washing.&lt;sup id="fnref:3"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:3" rel="footnote"&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moreover, its figurative uses throughout the New Testament range far more
broadly than &amp;ldquo;immersion&amp;rdquo; alone: it includes partaking of trials (Mark 10:38,
Luke 12:50); the transfoming work of the Spirit (Matt. 3:11, Acts 1:5, Acts
11:16), and even the Israelites&amp;rsquo; passing through water without getting wet (1
Cor. 10:2). The most significant of these metaphorical texts is Paul&amp;rsquo;s argument
that in baptism believers have been united with Christ in his death and
resurrection (Rom. 6:3–4, Col. 2:8–14). The parallel imagery between the two is
clear and potent: baptism visualizes death and resurrection. However, Paul&amp;rsquo;s
parallel uses of the word &amp;ldquo;baptism&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;baptize&amp;rdquo; (e.g. 1 Cor. 12:13, Gal. 3:27)
with &amp;ldquo;in Christ&amp;rdquo; demonstrate that the point of these passages is union with
Christ—not mode of baptism. Immersion illustrates this reality most effectively,
but immersion is not commanded.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It should be granted, then, that the primary meaning of the word group is of
dipping or immersion, but that it also includes a broader sense of washing or
transformation. Likewise, given what documents there are from the first and
second century, it seems safe to say that baptism was normally by immersion in
the early church. However, it is too much to say that immersion is &lt;em&gt;demanded&lt;/em&gt; by
the language used or by the examples in the New Testament. Rather, it should be
preferred as the &lt;em&gt;best&lt;/em&gt; way of expressing visually the death, burial and
resurrection of the believer with Christ as well as the cleansing and
transformative elements of the practice. At the same time, those who practice
baptism by immersion should not reject baptisms by sprinkling or pouring as
false or unbiblical baptisms.&lt;sup id="fnref:4"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:4" rel="footnote"&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="subject"&gt;Subject&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The debate over the &lt;em&gt;subject&lt;/em&gt; of baptism is similarly heated. There are
essentially two positions on who should be baptized (with some variations in
each position): that only new believers should be baptized, or that new
believers and the children of believers should be baptized. While there are some
important differences regarding the &lt;em&gt;meaning&lt;/em&gt; of the baptism of believers, it is
the universal practice of all Christian churches. The baptism of infants or
as-yet-unbelieving children of newly converted parents, however, has been
attributed a wide number of meanings, ranging from cleansing from original sin
and the beginning of the individual&amp;rsquo;s own work of salvation (the Catholic view)
to entrance into the covenant community conditioned on personal faith (the
Presbyterian view).&lt;sup id="fnref:5"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:5" rel="footnote"&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the one hand, the vast majority of Christians throughout all history prior to
the 20th century baptized infants. On the other hand, the believer is
responsible finally to submit to the Bible, tradition notwithstanding; if the
Scriptures teache credobaptism, even the weight of so much tradition must be set
aside. Nonetheless, church history is often illuminating for difficult
interpretive issues.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The earliest unambiguous mention of infant baptism is Tertullian&amp;rsquo;s condemnation
of the practice in 198 A.D. Less than two decades later, though, Hippolytus
advocated the baptism of children incapable of answering for themselves less
than two decades later (parents or other relatives were to speak on behalf of
their children).&lt;sup id="fnref:6"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:6" rel="footnote"&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Some argue that the commands for those baptized in earlier
documents such as the &lt;em&gt;Didache&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sup id="fnref:7"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:7" rel="footnote"&gt;7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; precludes children&amp;rsquo;s having been baptized,
but this is an argument from silence—andthese same kinds of commands appear in
the &amp;ldquo;Apostolic Tradition&amp;rdquo; following the instruction regarding children. In any
case, practice in the church was mixed by the end of the second century at the
latest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The evidence from New Testament practice is also ambiguous.&lt;sup id="fnref:8"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:8" rel="footnote"&gt;8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; It is true that
in the cases where the recipients of baptism are clearly delineated, they are
believers. However, any argument regarding the household baptisms is necessarily
an argument from silence. There is no grounds in the text for asserting that
&lt;em&gt;none&lt;/em&gt; of the households that received baptism included infants or small
children incapable of professing faith.&lt;sup id="fnref:9"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:9" rel="footnote"&gt;9&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; To say otherwise is to read one&amp;rsquo;s
theological presuppositions into the text. By the same token, however,
paedobaptists have no more warrant than do credobaptists for claiming these
passages as clear evidence for their view. Believers may of course argue that
these passages should be interpreted in light of their understanding of the rest
of the New Testament—but without the dogmatism too often present on both sides.
The passages simply do not say; indeed, no passage in the New Testament even
speaks clearly about believing children.&lt;sup id="fnref:10"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:10" rel="footnote"&gt;10&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thus, the subject of baptism can be determined only through the passages that
teach about its meaning and function in the life of the believer. Covenantal
paedobaptists&lt;sup id="fnref:11"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:11" rel="footnote"&gt;11&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; argue that, in continuity with the pattern of the Abrahamic
Covenant, children of believers—that is, children of those who are themselves
members of the covenant community of faith—should be baptized. They note,
rightly, that the major points of discontinuity marked off by the New Covenant
are with the &lt;em&gt;Mosaic&lt;/em&gt; covenant rather than the Abrahamic Covenant. As such, they
suggest that just as the (male) children of members of the Abrahamic covenant
were circumcised to symbolize their entrance into the covenant community, so
likewise (all) children of members of the New Covenant should be baptized. The
covenant view rightly distinguishes between the role of the symbol and the
necessary faith of the believer. It also rightly identifies the church with
Abraham&amp;rsquo;s offspring (cf. Luke 3:7–9) and takes seriously the teaching in both
Testaments that Abraham and his offspring were saved by faith, not merely by
being members of the people of Israel (see esp. Gal. 3:1–6).&lt;sup id="fnref:12"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:12" rel="footnote"&gt;12&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, while the Abrahamic covenant led directly to the New Covenant, it
nonetheless had an ethnic or national bent to it that the New Covenant does not.
The Abrahamic covenant was with Abraham and his offspring in a specific nation,
though for the good of all nations (Gen. 12:1–7, 15:1–21, 17:1–14). Circumcision
was established for Abraham and his descendants as their act of covenant (Gen
17:9–14). Yet the New Testament unambiguously does away with circumcision as the
mark of participation in God&amp;rsquo;s community (cf. Acts 10:1–48, 16:3, 1 Cor. 7:18,
Gal. 2:3, 5:2). The New Covenant circumcision is one &amp;ldquo;made without hands&amp;rdquo; (Col.
2:11; cf. Deut. 30:6, Rom. 2:29) and is tied directly to baptism—&amp;ldquo;the
circumcision of Christ&amp;rdquo; (Col. 2:11b–12).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The covenant paedobaptist is right that baptism is to the church what
circumcision was to the Jews, but wrong about how entrance into the covenant
community now comes about.&lt;sup id="fnref:13"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:13" rel="footnote"&gt;13&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Again: salvation was always by faith, but the
people of God are no longer constituted ethnically or nationally, but by faith
alone. To become one of God&amp;rsquo;s people in the Abrahamic covenant was to join the
nation of Israel; even when, as in Ruth&amp;rsquo;s case, that commitment was one of faith
it was also national and ethnic. It is no longer. Those who are to be baptized
are those who have become disciples (Matt. 28:18–20), repented (Acts 2:38–39),
been united with Christ in his death and resurrection (Rom. 6:3, Col 2:12), put
on Christ (Gal. 3:27), asked God for cleansing from sin (Acts 22:17) and for a
clear conscience (1 Pet. 3:21). In the New Covenant, &lt;em&gt;only&lt;/em&gt; those who profess
faith are marked as belonging to the people of God.&lt;sup id="fnref:14"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:14" rel="footnote"&gt;14&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In line with the practice described in the New Testament, then, only believers
should be baptized today: those who have made a clear and credible profession of
faith. However, those who affirm believer&amp;rsquo;s baptism should be careful not to
overstate their case. While the New Testament does incline this way, there is no
slam-dunk case, and no therefore warrant for sneering at those who disagree.
Moreover, other convictions held in light of one&amp;rsquo;s position on baptism must be
held moderately, in light of the provisional character of the doctrine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="excursus-rebaptism"&gt;Excursus: Rebaptism&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rebaptism is a serious matter. It argues that the first baptism a person
underwent was not in fact a Christian baptism at all, for one should not
otherwise be rebaptized. There is only one instance of rebaptism recorded in the
New Testament: that of the believers in Ephesus (Acts 19), who had not been
baptized in the name of Jesus at all. If the meaning, mode, and subject of
baptism as outlined above are correct, then it is appropriate to rebaptize those
who have been baptized as unbelievers (including as children) or by those who
are not orthodox Christians (e.g. Mormons). However, it is inappropriate to
rebaptize those who were baptized by a mode other than immersion,&lt;sup id="fnref:15"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:15" rel="footnote"&gt;15&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; for the
mode of baptism is neither a primary issue nor a point asserted dogmatically
anywhere in Scripture. Moreover, it is also inappropriate to rebaptize those who
were baptized as believers, but by churches holding differing views on the
meaning of baptism but which are nonetheless true Christian churches. Any
baptism applied to a believer on a valid profession of faith by a true church
ought to be respected by other Christian churches.&lt;sup id="fnref:16"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:16" rel="footnote"&gt;16&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="baptismal-practice"&gt;Baptismal Practice&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id="baptism-and-the-lords-supper"&gt;Baptism and the Lord&amp;rsquo;s Supper&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many Baptists have argued that the Lord&amp;rsquo;s Supper should be reserved for those
who have been baptized as believers, by immersion—a position that dates from the
origin of Baptist life (in the writings of William Kiffen) to the present day
(see the Baptist Faith and Message 2000 for just one example). A minority of
Baptists throughout the history of the movement (famously including John Bunyan)
have argued to the contrary: that the table ought to be open to any who have
given a valid profession of faith, or are members in good standing of other
Christian churches. Finally, a yet-smaller group has practiced local-church-only
communion, in which only the members of a given congregation may partake of
communion there. The first position, though most common, is perhaps least
sustainable in the author&amp;rsquo;s view. The fully open and local-church-only views are
more self-consistent in their interpretation of the relevant passages on the
Lord&amp;rsquo;s Supper.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All those answering this question are attempting to deal rightly with the
reality that coming to the Table is a serious matter. The New Testament teaches
that Christians are not to partake of the meal with those who are in unrepentant
sin (1 Cor. 5) and warns that judgment will come on those who themselves partake
of the meal while unrepentant (1 Cor. 11:20–30). Moreover, unrepentant sin is
the only boundary set around the table in the New Testament. But arguing that
being mistaken about even a practice so central as baptism constitutes
unrepentant sin is problematic. There are other doctrines of
denomination-forming importance, and which believers regard as sin issues; if
this logic were to be applied consistently, Christians could never share the
Table with anyone who did not share their every denominational distinctive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As Mike Bergman comments, the Lord&amp;rsquo;s Table is for disciples—for all those who
will be eating the supper together when the Lord returns.&lt;sup id="fnref:17"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:17" rel="footnote"&gt;17&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; The &amp;ldquo;closed&amp;rdquo;
communion position wrongly restricts the practice on the basis of a doctrinal
distinctive—one having little to do with the meaning of the Table itself.
Baptism is important, but to be incorrect on a secondary (albeit important)
issue is not remotely as unrepentant sin.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Advocates of closed communion sometimes argue for a modified version of this
position. Instead, they argue that participation in the Lord&amp;rsquo;s Supper requires
that one already have been baptized, and that since paedobaptism or baptism by a
mode other than immersion are by (their) definition not baptisms at all, such
believers should not be admitted to the table.&lt;sup id="fnref:18"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:18" rel="footnote"&gt;18&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; However, this is also
problematic. First of all, it assumes facts not in evidence. The New Testament
makes no comment on the issue whatsoever, presumably because it was not an issue
(regardless of the question of credo- or paedobaptism), leaving one with no
direct exegetical warrant for drawing the line here. Moreover, the result is to
exclude from the table other believers whose faith in Christ one fully
acknowledges and who one is confident will share in the feast at the end of
ages—on the basis of a debated interpretive issue, where the New Testament draws
no such line. Again, this reduces in no uncertain terms to the idea that
doctrinal differences are sufficient for excluding people from the Table, and
sets one rapidly on the path to sectarianism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, advocates of the local-church-only position rightly note that the local
church, and especially her shepherds, have a responsibility for the souls of
those who partake of the Table. Again, the New Testament is clear that partaking
of the talbe in known, unrepentant sin is a cause for judgment; it is likewise
clear that churches are as part of the practice of church discipline remove
unrepentant members from the table. Since the local church cannot ordinarily
know the spiritual condition of a visitor, it is safer to restrict communion
only to those about whom the congregation does have knowledge: members. However,
this position is similarly hard to sustain from the New Testament. While
churches are to remove from membership and access to the table those who are in
unrepentant sin, there is no indication of restricting the Table only to those
in the local congregation. Moreover, the text most often cited as evidence for
this position (1 Cor. 11:28) actually speaks to individuals holding themselves
accountable, rather than to churches holding their members accountable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Given that the New Testament pattern is indeed of baptism, the question once
again is whether the issue of baptism is so certain as to warrant this kind of
restriction. If, as argued above, there are grounds for holding a credobaptist
position only with considerable humility, Christians must likewise take care not
to draw too thick a line around other elements of the church&amp;rsquo;s practice on the
basis of baptismal doctrine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="baptism-and-the-local-church"&gt;Baptism and the Local Church&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many of the same arguments applied to the Lord&amp;rsquo;s Supper have been applied to the
issue of church membership, and many of the same concerns are in play. However,
many Baptist churches today practice open communion but closed membership, and a
number of high-profile Baptist leaders throughout history have advocated for
open membership as well as open communion.&lt;sup id="fnref:19"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:19" rel="footnote"&gt;19&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Baptists have universally argued
for a regenerate church membership, and believer&amp;rsquo;s baptism by immersion has&lt;em&gt;usually&lt;/em&gt; been understood to be a prerequisite for membership, since other forms
of baptism have been deemed invalid.&lt;sup id="fnref:20"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:20" rel="footnote"&gt;20&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Moreover, since a local church is not
merely a group of believers who happen to come together, but a group united
around common affirmations about the nature of the Christian life and the truths
Scripture teaches, local churches rightly have a higher bar for membership than
merely that a person appears truly to be saved.&lt;sup id="fnref:21"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:21" rel="footnote"&gt;21&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Churches should certainly not admit to membership those who affirm their stance
on baptism yet continue to refuse it. In cases where the person affirms
paedobaptism, though, membership may not be wholly out of bounds—for the same
reason that the Lord&amp;rsquo;s supper is not: the unity of the body of Christ matters
enormously. It will &lt;em&gt;usually&lt;/em&gt; be best in such circumstances to direct the
individual to another evangelical church in the area that practices
paedobaptism.&lt;sup id="fnref:22"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:22" rel="footnote"&gt;22&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; This best reflects the importance and seriousness of baptism.
However, there may be times when the best option is to admit such an individual
to membership—e.g., in cases where the baptistic church is the evangelical
congregation in the area. Baptism is important, but not so important as to leave
a regenerate individual or family without fellowship. Until Christ returns and
finally sets all doctrines aright, people should gather with those with whom
they share core doctrinal affiliations where possible—and be welcomed as
brothers and sisters in Christ where it is &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; possible. Such a practice may,
by the grace of God, be used a little to knit together again the fractured body
of the church catholic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id="is-baptism-a-church-ordinance"&gt;Is baptism a church ordinance?&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some believers argue that baptism is specifically a church ordinance, and as
such that it should never (or only in very rare circumstances) be carried out
outside the church. Since baptism is the believer&amp;rsquo;s initiation into the church,
it is the right only of the church to carry it out.&lt;sup id="fnref:23"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:23" rel="footnote"&gt;23&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; However, in nearly
every case in the New Testament, the newly baptized believers constituted the
first members of the church, and baptism is rarely mentioned outside of &amp;ldquo;church
planting&amp;rdquo; narratives. In the few cases where baptisms in the local church &lt;em&gt;are&lt;/em&gt;
discussed (1 Cor. 15:29), the content is simply not relevant. Indeed, Jesus
himself presided over (but did not participate in) a great many baptisms prior
to the formation of the local church, and evidently to a different end than
&amp;ldquo;Christian baptism&amp;rdquo;—certainly the symbolism of death, burial, and resurrection
with Christ remained hidden from those recipients of baptism. As with John&amp;rsquo;s
baptism, this seems to have been a baptism &amp;ldquo;for repentance from sins&amp;rdquo; (Mark
1:4). Given the relative silence of Scripture on the subject, it again seems
best not to stake out too strong a position on who may and may not baptize.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Certainly the normal circumstance will be baptism in the context of a local
church, because the local church is the home of Christian ministry. However,
this is not a normative practice; should a person come to faith in the context
of a parachurch ministry, there is no basis for arguing that it is
&lt;em&gt;categorically&lt;/em&gt; wrong for the parachurch ministry to perform the convert&amp;rsquo;s
baptism. To be sure, a parachurch ministry that consistently baptizes new
converts may run the risk of usurping the church&amp;rsquo;s role—but in this case, the
baptismal practice is a reflection of the problem, not itself the problem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="the-age-for-baptism"&gt;The Age for Baptism&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Given the credo-baptist position that only those who have made a credible
profession of faith should be baptized, the question arises: how old must
someone be to offer a profession that the church deems credible and therefore
administers baptism? Put negatively, is there an age below which such a baptism
would be more akin to paedo- than to credobaptism? Or should any profession of
faith be accepted, regardless of the child&amp;rsquo;s age? There are a number of good
arguments in favor of baptizing even very young children after a clear
profession of faith.&lt;sup id="fnref:24"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:24" rel="footnote"&gt;24&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; First, there is no evidence in Scripture for delaying
baptism after clear professions of faith: baptism normally followed a profession
of faith immediately.&lt;sup id="fnref:25"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:25" rel="footnote"&gt;25&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Second, delaying baptism as a sort of &amp;ldquo;litmus test&amp;rdquo;
for baptism implies that something besides repentance and faith in Christ is
necessary for salvation. Third, it is not giving false assurance to affirm even
a child&amp;rsquo;s trust in Christ through the gospel—perhaps even to the contrary (Mark
10:13–16). Moreover, the New Testament pattern for confirmation of salvation is
always a matter of encouraging those who &lt;em&gt;have&lt;/em&gt; made a profession to hold fast
to it (cf. Heb. 2, 4, 6, 10), rather than discouraging people from profession or
baptism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, there are also a number of reasons to consider delaying baptism for
children.&lt;sup id="fnref:26"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:26" rel="footnote"&gt;26&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; One caution against baptizing young adults who have made a
profession is the historic practice of baptistic churches, and that of many
baptistic churches outside the United States, where baptism has been and remains
a matter for adulthood. Another is the reality that young children, being easily
swayed by their parents or peers, might be inclined to make false professions of
faith—even apparently sincere ones. Of course, &lt;em&gt;any&lt;/em&gt; profession of faith may be
made for the wrong reasons.&lt;sup id="fnref:27"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:27" rel="footnote"&gt;27&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; It is not the church&amp;rsquo;s job to prevent false
profession from being made, but to respond appropriately when a false profession
has been made (Matt. 18, 1 Cor. 5). Moreover, as noted above, Scripture is
simply silent on the age of non-adults baptized, so making a hard and fast rule
is unwarranted. It may nonetheless be wise to baptize only individuals who are
judged capable of making their own professions of faith—perhaps those in their
early pre-teen years and onward, as judged together by parents and church
leaders in each case.&lt;sup id="fnref:28"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:28" rel="footnote"&gt;28&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="summary"&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Baptism is the sign of the New Covenant, and should be applied to the members of
that covenant: believers. The preferred mode is immersion, but other modes may
be allowed if circumstances demand. Similarly, the church is the ordinary
context and her members the normal adminstrators of baptism, but it matters most
that a person be baptized by an orthodox Christian in the Trinitarian formula.
Those who have been baptized as believers ought not be rebaptized, regardless of
mode. Those who have not been baptized as believers may partake of the Lord&amp;rsquo;s
table, but should not ordinarly become members of a Baptist church. In all these
things, the people of God ought to rejoice in their participation in the death
and resurrection of Christ.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;h2 id="bibliography"&gt;Bibliography&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bergman, Mike. &amp;ldquo;Why We Practice &amp;lsquo;Open&amp;rsquo; Communion.&amp;rdquo; SBC Voices. Posted September 9, 2011. http://sbcvoices.com/why-we-practice-open-communion/ (accessed March 24, 2015).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dever, Mark E. &amp;ldquo;Baptism in the Context of the Local Church.&amp;rdquo; In &lt;em&gt;Believer&amp;rsquo;s Baptism: Sign of the New Covenant in Christ&lt;/em&gt;. Edited by Thomas R. Schreiner and Shawn D. Wright. Nashville: B&amp;amp;H Academic, 2007. 329&amp;ndash;352.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finn, Nathan. &amp;ldquo;Baptism as a Prerequisite to the Lord&amp;rsquo;s Supper: A White Paper from the Center for Theological Research.&amp;rdquo; Fort Worth: The Center for Theological Research, Southwestern Baptist Theological Seminary, 2006.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;———, &amp;ldquo;A Baptist perspective on -re-baptism-&amp;ldquo;. BRNow.org. Posted February 25, 2013. http://www.brnow.org/Opinions/Guest-Columns/February-2013/A-Baptist-perspective-on-re-baptism (accessed March 28, 2015).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Freeman, Curtis W. &amp;ldquo;Analysis: Should Baptist churches adopt open membership? Yes.&amp;rdquo; The Baptist Standard. Posted on April 21, 2010. https://www.baptiststandard.com/news/faith-culture/11047-analysis-should-baptist-churches-adopt-open-membership-yes (accessed March 28, 2015).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Garrett, James Leo. &amp;ldquo;Analysis: Should Baptist churches adopt open membership? No.&amp;rdquo; The Baptist Standard. Posted on April 21, 2010. https://www.baptiststandard.com/news/faith-culture/11048-analysis-should-baptist-churches-adopt-open-membership-no (accessed March 28, 2015).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moore, Russell D. &amp;ldquo;Table Manners.&amp;rdquo; &lt;em&gt;Touchstone&lt;/em&gt;, Sept/Oct 2011. http://www.touchstonemag.com/archives/article.php?id=24-05-016-v (accessed March 28, 2015).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Norman, R. Stanton. &lt;em&gt;The Baptist Way: Distinctives of a Baptist Church&lt;/em&gt;. Nashville: Broadman &amp;amp; Holman Publishers, 2005.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Piper, John. &amp;ldquo;How Important is Church Membership&amp;rdquo; (sermon, Bethlehem Baptist Church, July 13, 2008).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;———. &amp;ldquo;Teaching and Admonishing One Another in All Wisdom&amp;rdquo; (sermon, Bethlehem Baptist Church, July 27, 2008).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;———. &amp;ldquo;What Is Baptism, and How Important Is It?&amp;rdquo; (sermon, Bethlehem Baptist Church, July 20, 2008).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Starke, John. &amp;ldquo;Should We Baptize Small Children? Yes.&amp;rdquo; The Gospel Coalition. Posted February 23, 2011. http://www.thegospelcoalition.org/article/should-we-baptize-small-children-yes (accessed March 28, 2015).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wax, Trevin. &amp;ldquo;Should We Baptize Small Children? No.&amp;rdquo; The Gospel Coalition. Posted February 21, 2001. http://www.thegospelcoalition.org/blogs/trevinwax/2011/02/21/should-we-baptize-small-children/ (accessed March 28, 2015).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;White, Thomas. &amp;ldquo;What Makes Baptism Valid?&amp;rdquo; In &lt;em&gt;Restoring Integrity in Baptist Churches&lt;/em&gt;, edited by Thomas White, Jason G. Duesing, and Malcolm B. Yarnell, III. Grand Rapids: Kregel Publications, 2008. 107&amp;ndash;118.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Lord&amp;rsquo;s Supper belongs in a distinct category, insofar as it is a means
of &lt;em&gt;special&lt;/em&gt; grace in the Christian life, but it fits in this list as well.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:2"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Contra Thomas White, &amp;ldquo;What Makes Baptism Valid?&amp;rdquo; in &lt;em&gt;Restoring Integrity
in Baptist Churches&lt;/em&gt;, eds. Thomas White, Jason G. Duesing, and Malcolm B.
Yarnell, III (Grand Rapids: Kregel Publications, 2008), 110–111.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:2" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 2 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:3"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;See e.g. Luke 11:38, where it is clear the Pharisees were not surprised
that Jesus failed to take a whole-body bath; or Mark 7:4, where the same word is
used of washing after returning from the market; or Hebrews 6:2, 9:10, where it
refers to ritual purification&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:3" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 3 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:4"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was the pattern of the early church, as evidenced by the very early
&amp;ldquo;Didache&amp;rdquo;, which argued for baptism by immersion if possible and by pouring if
necessary (&lt;em&gt;Didache&lt;/em&gt; 7).&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:4" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 4 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:5"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This may be taken as a secondary argument against paedobaptism—a point
made to the author and others by Nathan Finn in a number of personal
conversations and in several class lectures, 2013–2015.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:5" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 5 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:6"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Apostolic Tradition of Hippolytus of Rome 21.4.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:6" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 6 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:7"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Didache 7.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:7" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 7 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:8"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Contra many Baptists, e.g. R. Stanton Norman, &lt;em&gt;The Baptist Way:
Distinctives of a Baptist Church&lt;/em&gt; (Nashville: Broadman &amp;amp; Holman Publishers,
2005), 110–112; White, 109–110.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:8" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 8 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:9"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Contra e.g. Norman, 110–111.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:9" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 9 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:10"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The nearest the New Testament comes to it are: Jesus&amp;rsquo; welcome of little
children (Mark 10:13–16), Paul&amp;rsquo;s admonitions to those married to unbelievers for
the sake of their spouse and children (1 Cor. 7:12–16), and Paul&amp;rsquo;s instructions
to presumably believing children and their parents (Eph. 6:1–4, Col. 3:20–21) .&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:10" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 10 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:11"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For constraints of time and space, the author has left aside other views,
many of which are both historically and practically significant and deserves
serious interaction, but which have in the author&amp;rsquo;s view less Scriptural warrant
(to varying degrees) than the covenant position.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:11" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 11 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:12"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is also perhaps surprising that in all the controversy stirred up by
the Judaizers in the early church, there is no mention of hostility over
children being excluded from the New Covenant—a fairly striking change between
the two. This is especially so given that the distinction between Old and New
Covenants did not preclude the Judaizers from arguing for many &lt;em&gt;other&lt;/em&gt; points of
even stronger continuity between Mosaic practice and that of the church—still
less Abrahamic practice and that of the church. However, this is another
argument from silence and so cannot be taken as strong evidence one way or the
other. (Personal conversation with Doug Serven, August 5, 2010.)&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:12" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 12 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:13"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;John Piper, &amp;ldquo;What Is Baptism, and How Important Is It?&amp;rdquo; (sermon,
Bethlehem Baptist Church, July 20, 2008).&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:13" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 13 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:14"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The contested passages in Acts are left aside because, as has been noted,
they do not prove what either side claims they do. Lydia believed, and her
household was baptized—does this mean her household had no infants in it and
everyone in it converted with her? It is impossible to say.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:14" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 14 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:15"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Contra e.g. Nathan Finn, &amp;ldquo;A Baptist perspective on -re-baptism-&amp;ldquo;,
BRNow.org, posted February 25, 2013,
http://www.brnow.org/Opinions/Guest-Columns/February-2013/A-Baptist-perspective-on-re-baptism
(accessed March 28, 2015).&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:15" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 15 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:16"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This, of course, partly begs the question, for it leaves aside the matter
of what constitutes a &amp;ldquo;true Christian church&amp;rdquo;—certainly a contested issue,
and one beyond the scope of this paper. At a minimum, no group which rejects
orthodox Trinitarianism and Christology may be included. At most, some major
denominations may be excluded. The author is inclined to treat believers&amp;rsquo;
baptisms even by groups with serious doctrinal problems such as Roman
Catholics as valid, however, so long as the specific congregation by which
the believer was baptized rightly proclaimed a gospel of repentance from
sins and salvation through the finished work of Christ alone.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:16" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 16 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:17"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mike Bergman, &amp;ldquo;Why We Practice &amp;ldquo;Open&amp;rdquo; Communion,&amp;rdquo; SBC Voices, posted
September 9, 2011, http://sbcvoices.com/why-we-practice-open-communion/
(accessed March 24, 2015).&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:17" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 17 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:18"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;See e.g. Nathan Finn, &amp;ldquo;Baptism as a Prerequisite to the Lord&amp;rsquo;s Supper: A
White Paper from the Center for Theological Research,&amp;rdquo; (Fort Worth: The
Center for Theological Research, Southwestern Baptist Theological Seminary,
2006); and Russell D. Moore, &amp;ldquo;Table Manners,&amp;rdquo; &lt;em&gt;Touchstone&lt;/em&gt;, Sept/Oct 2011,
http://www.touchstonemag.com/archives/article.php?id=24-05-016-v (accessed
March 28, 2015).&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:18" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 18 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:19"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Curtis W. Freeman, &amp;ldquo;Analysis: Should Baptist churches adopt open
membership? Yes,&amp;rdquo; The Baptist Standard, posted April 21, 2010,
https://www.bapti ststandard.com/news/faith-culture/11047-analysis-should-baptist-churches-adopt-o pen-membership-yes (accessed March 28, 2015).&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:19" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 19 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:20"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;James Leo Garrett, &amp;ldquo;Analysis: Should Baptist churches adopt open
membership? No,&amp;rdquo; The Baptist Standard, posted April 21, 2010,
https://www.baptiststandard.com/news/faith-culture/11048-analysis-should-baptist-churches-adopt-op en-membership-no (accessed March 28, 2015).&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:20" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 20 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:21"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So rightly, Moore in his discussion of the Lord&amp;rsquo;s Table in &amp;ldquo;Table
Matters.&amp;rdquo;&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:21" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 21 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:22"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Close friendships between evangelical churches and their leaders would be
a boon in this sort of work—as well as in kingdom ministry in general.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:22" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 22 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:23"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;See e.g. Mark E. Dever, &amp;ldquo;Baptism in the Context of the Local Church,&amp;rdquo; in&lt;em&gt;Believer&amp;rsquo;s Baptism: Sign of the New Covenant in Christ&lt;/em&gt;, eds. Thomas R.
Schreiner and Shawn D. Wright (Nashville: B&amp;amp;H Academic, 2007), 329–331;
White, 112–114. Both merely &lt;em&gt;assert&lt;/em&gt; this point; neither demonstrates it.
Dever rightly grants that there is no biblical instruction about &lt;em&gt;who&lt;/em&gt;
should baptize (331) while failing to note that there is similarly no
express statement that it is a church ordinance.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:23" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 23 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:24"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The following was adapted from John Starke, &amp;ldquo;Should We Baptize Small
Children? Yes,&amp;rdquo; The Gospel Coalition, posted February 23, 2011,
http://www.thegospelcoalition.org/article/should-we-baptize-small-children-yes
(accessed March 28, 2015).&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:24" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 24 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:25"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So likewise Dever, 345.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:25" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 25 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:26"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The following was adapted from Trevin Wax, &amp;ldquo;Should We Baptize Small
Children? No,&amp;rdquo; The Gospel Coalition, posted February 21, 2001,
http://www.thegospelcoalition.org/blogs/trevinwax/2011/02/21/should-we-baptize-small-children/
(accessed March 28, 2015).&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:26" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 26 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:27"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Baptism: Theology and Practice: A Statement by the Elders&amp;rdquo;, First
Baptist Church of Durham, 2014, 11.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:27" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 27 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:28"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First Baptist Church of Durham, 11–12.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:28" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 28 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 28 Mar 2015 22:00:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2015-03-28:2015/repent-and-be-baptized.html</guid><category>M. Div.</category><category>SEBTS</category><category>papers</category></item><item><title>Be Holy!</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2014/be-holy.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;i class="editorial"&gt;I would like to preface the following review by noting that
Andy Davis is not just any author, and indeed not just any pastor. He is one of
&lt;em&gt;my&lt;/em&gt; pastors. This makes the task of writing a critical book review somewhat
strange. On the one hand, I wanted to write this review as I would any such. On
the other hand, I wanted to take care to show respect to a man whom God has used
to shepherd me and my family for the past two years since we moved to North
Carolina, and whom I regard very highly for his faithfulness in serving the
church gathered as First Baptist Church of Durham. I hope I have struck the
balance appropriately. And as I hope will become clear, though there were a few
places where this book could be stronger, it is nonetheless extraordinarily
valuable. I have been challenged and indeed have grown in holiness because of
having read it. I commend it to you.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;An Infinite Journey: Growing toward Christlikeness&lt;/em&gt;, by Andrew M. Davis,
Greenville: Ambassador International, 2014, 480 pages.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="overview"&gt;Overview&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Andrew Davis&amp;rsquo; &lt;em&gt;An Infinite Journey&lt;/em&gt; is a careful, thorough, heavy exploration of
the doctrine and practice of sanctification in the Christian life. Davis, the
long-time pastor of First Baptist Church in Durham, North Carolina and an
adjunct professor at nearby Southeastern Baptist Theological Seminary, has
clearly dedicated considerable time and consideration to the topic of holiness
and growth in the Christian life, and this consideration is on display
throughout what is ultimately a very helpful book.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Davis begins by introducing the concepts which permeate the rest of the book:
the saving work of God in Christ and the Christian&amp;rsquo;s lasting dependence on the
Holy Spirit. Perhaps surprisingly (at least to the casual reader), he opens not
with the topic of sanctification, but with justification, arguing that all real
Christian growth must be predicated on a right understanding of the gospel.
Thus, he spends some time tracing out the story of salvation, culminating in
Christ&amp;rsquo;s atoning death on the cross and resurrection, and his institution of the
church and sending the Holy Spirit to save and then shape the internal lives of
Christians throughout the ages. He further argues that all Christians are
involved in two &amp;ldquo;infinite journeys&amp;rdquo;&amp;mdash;the external journey of evangelism and
discipleship, and the internal journey of growth in holiness. Both, he notes,
are essential for the health of the Christian: to be deficient in either is to
demonstrate either ignorance or hard-heartedness toward the things of God.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After this introduction, Davis turns to a map of the second of these journeys:
the internal path of growing Christ-likeness. His thesis is that sanctification
is a four-part process, involving a continuous sequence of knowledge, faith,
character, and action, each feeding into the next. Knowledge of God produces
faith; increasing faith produces Christlike character; a more Christlike
character results in more Godward actions; and those Godward actions in turn
lead to a greater knowledge of God himself. Davis dedicates a section of the
book to each of these ideas, examining in detail Scriptural support for the
concept and then examples of the element in the lives of figures in Scripture,
especially Christ. Finally, he turns to a section dedicated to application,
looking at the knowledge-faith-character-action cycle as a whole in both
Scripture and a variety of day-to-day scenarios.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="analysis"&gt;Analysis&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Davis&amp;rsquo; treatment of the doctrines of sanctification is thorough and compelling,
most of all because it is drenched in Scripture. Early in the book, Davis
explicitly spells out his commitment to the centrality, sufficiency, and
authority of Scripture, and the text of the book backs this up. It is common to
hear authors affirm the importance of Scripture; it is rare to see it so born
out so clearly in their writing. Even apart from the explicit references on
nearly every page, the text bears the unmistakable imprint of Davis&amp;rsquo; own
practice of memorizing books of the Bible. Allusions, near quotes, and implicit
references to Scripture appear multiple times on nearly every page.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This Scriptural emphasis leads to the book&amp;rsquo;s other great strengths. First, Davis
makes no point without basing the assertion on Scripture, and he draws on every
section of the Bible to demonstrate the importance of each aspect of his map for
growth in holiness. Moreover, he follows Scripture&amp;rsquo;s lead in grounding
sanctification in the work of Christ mediated to us by the Holy Spirit. Davis&amp;rsquo;
emphasis on the work of the Spirit is especially helpful. Though he is by no
means a charismatic in the modern sense of the word, it is clear that he is
gripped by the reality that sanctification simply does not happen without the
work of the Holy Spirit. This is an essential corrective for two kinds of
churches: those tempted to ignore the Spirit, and those tempted to ignore all
the works of the Spirit apart from those that result in visible signs. Rightly,
Davis&amp;rsquo; doctrine of sanctification is trinitarian: holy people whole-heartedly
worship the Father in Spirit-empowered dependence on the finished work of the
Son.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Second, this Scriptural care allows Davis to navigate the difficult topic of
Spirit-dependent human effort that characterizes Biblical sanctification.
Because sanctification is the one aspect of salvation in which people are called
to work (e.g. in Phil. 2:12), many believers are tempted to treat sanctification
as a wholly human endeavor. Davis repudiates this notion, showing again and
again that sanctification&amp;mdash;like the justification that precedes it and the
glorification that will follow it&amp;mdash;is ultimately a work of God and one that
brings him all glory. No person will be able to claim the credit for their own
sanctification before God at the day of judgment. At the same time, he also
rejects a Keswickian spirituality (&amp;ldquo;let go and let God&amp;rdquo;), even when dressed up
as mere gospel dependence. However much in vogue the notion may be that we can
do nothing and God does everything for us, it is simply not true. God requires
us actively to seek him and his holiness. Davis rightly recognizes both these
dangers and charts a course between them. The pursuit of holiness is empowered
by the Holy Spirit, and believers must always fix their eyes on the finished
work of Christ and the promise of future glory. Yet believers keep their eyes on
Christ and rely on the Spirit &lt;em&gt;to work&lt;/em&gt;&amp;mdash;not to sit still and trust God to
float them toward holiness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The book does have a few weaknesses. First, although the book&amp;rsquo;s length and
thoroughness are valuable in many ways, they also make this a difficult sell for
anyone who is not already a dedicated reader. Moreover, while much of the length
was inevitable in a work this thorough on a topic this complex, the book could
be substantially shorter were it edited more carefully. Trimming the lengthy
introduction and removing some repetition, unnecessary explanations, and
clarifications would make the work stronger as well as shorter and more
approachable. Given Davis&amp;rsquo; goals&amp;mdash;to stir up believers to pursuing
holiness&amp;mdash;this would be profoundly helpful, as it would allow for the book to
be used in a broader variety of contexts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Second, a number of Davis&amp;rsquo; references to words&amp;rsquo; meanings in Greek are either
extraneous or inaccurate. In particular, he regularly committed the so-called
etymological fallacy, ascribing meaning to words based on their components
rather than their actual use in the language. (This led him several times to
disagree with every modern major translation!) He also sometimes referenced
English words derived from Greek terms, but in cases where the derivation is
irrelevant to the present meaning of the English word (e.g. &lt;em&gt;poem&lt;/em&gt; from
&lt;em&gt;poiema&lt;/em&gt;). Gladly, no major issues in the text hung on these cases. Nonetheless,
the misuses were distracting, and since in most cases they were also
unnecessary, they actually &lt;em&gt;weakened&lt;/em&gt; the book for me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That these are the only significant issues in such a large and thorough book is
a significant achievement, and both could readily be addressed in future
editions of the work. Taken as a whole, Davis&amp;rsquo; book shines. As Davis points out,
holiness necessarily entails both knowledge of the things of God and zeal for
his glory. The book drips with Davis&amp;rsquo; passion for God and his urgent desire that
God&amp;rsquo;s people seek holiness, and it lays out a thoughtful and (most importantly)
Scriptural plan for how his people shall become holy. Lord willing, the volume
will be a reliable guide to sanctification for the church for years to come.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note on publication:&lt;/strong&gt; This paper was first published online on January 1,
2015. However, I wrote this and submitted it in mid-December, and have backdated
it accordingly.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 10 Dec 2014 12:00:00 -0500</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2014-12-10:2014/be-holy.html</guid><category>M. Div.</category><category>SEBTS</category><category>FBC Durham</category><category>papers</category><category>book reviews</category></item><item><title>The "New" Covenant</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2014/the-new-covenant.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;It is common for pastors, popular teachers, and even some scholars to treat the
&amp;lsquo;New Covenant&amp;rsquo; of Jeremiah 31 as something wholly distinct from the previous
covenants. In this reading, the New Covenant is specific to the work of Christ
in the New Testament age, and was never experienced by any &amp;ldquo;Old Testament
believers&amp;rdquo;. Those believers remained under the previous (Abrahamic and
especially Mosaic and Davidic) covenants, while New Testament believers are New
Covenant believers. For this view, they draw on the ways that the New Covenant
language was picked up by the authors of the New Testament, especially in
Hebrews.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Though this reading has an ancient pedigree, going back at least as far as
Jerome, it is ultimately incorrect. First, it fails to take the content of
Jeremiah&amp;rsquo;s vision on its own terms. As Jeremiah traces out his vision of the
New Covenant in chapters 31&amp;ndash;33, he explicitly includes the language of
law-keeping, temple working and priests, and a Davidic king over the land of
Israel. These were not merely symbolic expectations, but fully fleshed out
hopes for and visions of a restoration of the covenant God made with Israel at
Sinai. Indeed, the terms of priestly temple sacrifice and law-keeping used
throughout the section presuppose the covenant language of Deuteronomy and the
discussion in Deuteronomy 30 of the circumcised heart. Thus, Hill and Walton
note (and likewise Thomas suggested) that in many ways it is more appropriate
to speak of a &lt;em&gt;renewed&lt;/em&gt; covenant than of a totally &lt;em&gt;new&lt;/em&gt; covenant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Second, the reading of the &amp;lsquo;New Covenant&amp;rsquo; as &lt;em&gt;wholly&lt;/em&gt; new misses the ways the
other authors of the Old Testament responded to this promise. In particular,
Ezra&amp;rsquo;s prayer in Ezra-Nehemiah makes it abundantly clear that he considered the
people&amp;rsquo;s return to the land after their 70-year-exile a fulfillment of the
prophecy. If it was not a complete fulfillment&amp;mdash;as indeed that same prayer
acknowledges, for the people&amp;rsquo;s hearts were still wayward&amp;mdash;it nonetheless
represented at least a partial fulfillment. There were once again Jewish people
living in the land, performing temple sacrifice and following Yahweh. Though
the Davidic king had not yet been reinstated, and though the people&amp;rsquo;s hearts
had not yet had the law so thoroughly stamped on them that they no longer
needed teachers, the promise was partly fulfilled.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Third, even in the age after Christ&amp;rsquo;s coming it is clear that the vision
remains only fulfilled in part. True: there was a significant break in the
shape of history in the incarnation, life, death, resurrection, and ascension
of the Son. Yet God&amp;rsquo;s law is not yet written so thoroughly on anyone&amp;rsquo;s heart
that no man needs to teach his neighbor. Christians still wrestle with sin.
Moreover, as the author of Hebrews notes, this Davidic king who fulfills the
New Covenant hopes has not yet put everything in subjection under his feet
(Heb. 2). He is seated at the right hand of God, exalted above the heavens, and
has inaugurated his reign, but he has not yet &lt;em&gt;consummated&lt;/em&gt; reign. The same
author who affirms so strongly that Jesus is the fulfillment of the New
Covenant hope affirms as well that the New Covenant is not yet fully completed.
The ancient Jews lived in an &amp;ldquo;already but not yet&amp;rdquo; after the return from Exile.
In the work of Christ, that &amp;ldquo;already&amp;rdquo; is significantly advanced&amp;mdash;but the &amp;ldquo;not
yet&amp;rdquo; remains until he returns.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is not to say that there is &lt;em&gt;nothing&lt;/em&gt; new about the New Covenant. Unlike
in Deuteronomy 30, where the people were enjoined to repent and circumcise
their own hearts, the work in Jeremiah&amp;rsquo;s vision is wholly God&amp;rsquo;s. Too, the New
Testament&amp;rsquo;s embrace of New Covenant language in terms of Jesus&amp;rsquo; work means that
Christians &lt;em&gt;should&lt;/em&gt; understand that something new has happened in Christ.
Specifically, Christ has done what Israel could not. Jesus kept the law
perfectly, needing no one to teach him; he served as both priest and sacrifice
to make atonement for the sins of the people; he rules and judges righteously
as the Davidic Branch who represents Yahweh; he even reconstituted Israel in
his twelve disciples. Jesus Messiah &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; the fulfillment of the New Covenant.
He is the hope toward which the Old Testament saints looked.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Augustine, not Jerome, had the right of it. All the Old Testament saints were
participants in the New Covenant. They looked forward to that which they did
not see, but they too were saved by faith in Christ. They did not have the full
revelation with which New Testament saints are blessed. They saw from far off
that of which Christians now enjoy the fullness. But Jesus&amp;rsquo; work in bringing
about the New Covenant was not something foreign to the covenants that had gone
before; it was the fulfillment of all of them. Here was the offspring of the
woman who would crush the serpent&amp;rsquo;s head, the offspring of Abraham in whom all
nations would be blessed, the prophet like Moses who would give the law anew,
the true Israel who would keep the law rightly, the offspring of David who
would do justice for his people and for the nations. Jeremiah&amp;rsquo;s New Covenant
promised the fulfillment of what had gone before. It was new in that Jesus
finally accomplished what no Israelite ever had. It was the renewal of the old
in that what Jesus accomplished was precisely the hope set before Israel from
the beginning.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 11 May 2014 20:00:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2014-05-11:2014/the-new-covenant.html</guid><category>M. Div.</category><category>SEBTS</category></item><item><title>The Uniqueness of the Incarnation</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2014/the-uniqueness-of-the-incarnation.html</link><description>&lt;h2 id="i-the-centrality-and-uniqueness-of-the-incarnation"&gt;I. The Centrality and Uniqueness of the Incarnation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Incarnation of the Son of God is the ground of all Christian hope. It is the
&amp;ldquo;central miracle asserted by Christians.&amp;rdquo;&lt;sup id="fnref:1"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:1" rel="footnote"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Without the Incarnation, there
would be no salvation. Not only would the other aspects of redemption (Christ&amp;rsquo;s
life, teaching, death on the cross, resurrection, and ascension) not be
possible, but parts of the restoration of humanity hinge on the Incarnation
itself. The Incarnation was a unique event in history, with unique theological
significance. At no other time has God manifested himself as a human being. The
Spirit&amp;rsquo;s present indwelling of all believers is a direct result of and carries
forward the reconciliation of divinity and humanity that occured in the person
of Jesus Christ. A healthy church depends on a healthy Christology, for it is
only in Christ and by Christ&amp;rsquo;s Spirit that the church exists&amp;mdash;and there can be
no healthy Christology without a robust doctrine of the Incarnation. It is in
the Incarnation that Jesus the Messiah must be understood: a single person
uniting all that it is to be God and all that it is to be human.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="a-biblical-affirmations"&gt;A. Biblical Affirmations&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each of the Gospels opens in a way that emphasizes the unique nature of Jesus
Christ. Matthew begins with a genealogy that situates him in the story of
Israel, then immediately shows in narrative that from his conception he was also
divine (Matt. 1&amp;ndash;2, esp. 1:1, 1:23). Mark, ever brief, introduces the Messiah
with the astounding words, &amp;ldquo;Jesus Christ, the Son of God&amp;rdquo; (Mark 1:1).&lt;sup id="fnref:2"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:2" rel="footnote"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Luke
inverts Matthew&amp;rsquo;s order: miraculous birth first, genealogy second. He situations
Jesus not only in Israel&amp;rsquo;s story but in humanity&amp;rsquo;s, tracing his lineage to Adam
(Luke 1:26&amp;ndash;28, 2:8&amp;ndash;38, 3:23&amp;ndash;38). John reaches out to Greek philosophy and
turns it on its head, proclaiming the coming of the uncreated &lt;em&gt;logos&lt;/em&gt; into
creation (John 1:1&amp;ndash;18). The sum effect of the gospel-tellers is to emphasize
that in Jesus Christ, something profoundly unique had happened.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perhaps nowhere are the importance and uniqueness of the Incarnation more
evident than in the Epistle to the Hebrews. The anonymous letter emphasizes from
its first words the uniqueness of Jesus&amp;rsquo; incarnation and ministry (Heb. 1:1&amp;ndash;2).
It argues that the Incarnation was essential to his roles as priest (2:17&amp;ndash;18,
4:15, 5:5&amp;ndash;10, 7:26&amp;ndash;8:2), destroyer of death (2:14&amp;ndash;15), and propitiatory
sacrifice (2:9, 7:27, 9:11&amp;ndash;28, 10:12&amp;ndash;14, 10:19&amp;ndash;22). It is not only that Jesus
died to save people from their sins, but that he became human and lived to that
end and more besides&amp;mdash;a consistent theme throughout the New Testament. Thus,
Zechariah&amp;rsquo;s prophecy (Luke 1:76&amp;ndash;79) includes salvation from sin, but also light
coming into the world, death&amp;rsquo;s power coming to an end, and peace reigning in the
cosmos. Likewise, John couples the Incarnation to the doctrine of adoption (John
1:12). Paul exults in the Incarnation as the grounds of the reconciliation of
all things, humanity included (Col 1:19&amp;ndash;20). Moreover, he explicitly couples
the Messiah&amp;rsquo;s full humanity to humans being filled in him in turn (Col.
2:9&amp;ndash;10)&amp;mdash;a theme Peter picks up as well, noting that the saints actually
become &amp;ldquo;partakers of the divine nature&amp;rdquo; (2 Peter 1:4).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In short, the New Testament affirms that the Incarnation itself was an essential
element in the salvation of humanity&amp;mdash;not merely as a prerequisite for other
parts of Christ&amp;rsquo;s work. The Incarnation is the means by which human nature is
brought once again into fellowship with the Godhead. Christ is the
eschatological firstfruits of this restoration. As he is, so will all the saints
be in glory: restored to unbroken fellowship between humanity and humanity&amp;rsquo;s
Creator.&lt;sup id="fnref:3"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:3" rel="footnote"&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="b-the-theology-of-the-church"&gt;B. The Theology of the Church&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The importance of the Incarnation has been affirmed by the church throughout her
history. The Church Fathers fleshed out the orthodox doctrine of the Incarnation
over the first four centuries of the history of the church, with various
controversies erupting every century.&lt;sup id="fnref:4"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:4" rel="footnote"&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; This work culminated in the lasting
affirmations and denials of the Chalcedonian formula.&lt;sup id="fnref:5"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:5" rel="footnote"&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; In fact, nearly every
theological controversy in the early church was a Christological controversy,
and every such controversy hinged on issues pertaining to the nature of the
Incarnation. The Fathers recognized that the details of God&amp;rsquo;s becoming man were
essentials of the faith. The hope of human salvation would be lost entirely if
Jesus were not a single person in whom &amp;ldquo;all the fullness of deity dwells bodily&amp;rdquo;
(Col. 2:9) and who &amp;ldquo;likewise partook of [flesh and blood]&amp;rdquo; (Heb. 2:14).&lt;sup id="fnref:6"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:6" rel="footnote"&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Incarnational thoelogizing did not end in the patristic period; it has remained
foundational for further reflection on the natures of God and humanity. Indeed,
patristic theology has been influential on nearly every major orthodox
theologian since the Reformation&amp;mdash;whether directly or mediated by the
Reformers. Athanasius&amp;rsquo; Christology, with its emphasis on the transformational
effect of the Incarnation itself on humanity&amp;rsquo;s state,&lt;sup id="fnref:7"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:7" rel="footnote"&gt;7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; has proven
particularly influential. If advocates of &amp;ldquo;incarnational&amp;rdquo; theologies have
sometimes pressed this recovery in unhelpful directions (see below), they have
also provided a helpful reminder of what God&amp;rsquo;s becoming man has &lt;em&gt;already&lt;/em&gt;
accomplished: the first step of the eschatological transformation of humanity.
&amp;ldquo;The crucified Christ stands in solidarity with humanity, not merely as ane
xample of confrontation with the world to be imitated by us &lt;em&gt;but as the reality
of new humanity in which we may and must participate&lt;/em&gt;.&amp;rdquo;&lt;sup id="fnref:8"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:8" rel="footnote"&gt;8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Jesus&amp;rsquo; humanity is
an essential ingredient in human salvation and in the sanctified life of the
believer in the present&amp;mdash;the Spirit mediating Christ&amp;rsquo;s humanity to the
believer&amp;rsquo;s&amp;mdash;as well as of a glorified reality in the future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="ii-in-life-and-ministry"&gt;II. In Life and Ministry&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Given the importance&amp;mdash;indeed, the essential character&amp;mdash;of the doctrine of the
Incarnation, it is clear that the church must strive to maintain the doctrine.
It is insufficent only to affirm it in principle; the church must cherish this
reality in practice and protect it from loss. Unfortunately, both in the Western
church broadly and in evangelicalism in particular, the centrality and
uniqueness of the Incarnation have sometimes been lost through neglect or abuse.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="a-absence"&gt;A. Absence&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The church may first of all fail with regard to its theology of the Incarnation
by losing it, whether by doctrinal negation or by simple unobservance. The
threat of outright denial of the doctrine has been dangerously common in church
history. As noted above, many of the early Christological heresies relted
directly to the nature of the Incarnation, and variations on these heresies have
continued to arise to the present day. In the Reformation era, for example, the
Anabaptist movement included many who affirmed a &amp;ldquo;heavenly flesh&amp;rdquo; view in which
Jesus was not Mary&amp;rsquo;s descendant but sent from heaven without human parentage
whatsoever&amp;mdash;a loss of Christ&amp;rsquo;s full humanity. More recently, both Mormons and
Jehovah&amp;rsquo;s Witnesses have affirmed adoptionist views&amp;mdash;a loss of Christ&amp;rsquo;s full
deity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The anti-supernatural bent of many liberal theologies in the last several
centuries has similarly resulted in a rejection of the doctrine of the
Incarnation. For many liberals theologians, Jesus was representative of the
God-consciousness in us all at its best and adopted by God as a special figure
in human history accordingly.&lt;sup id="fnref:9"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:9" rel="footnote"&gt;9&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Any such outright rejection clearly results in
the loss of all that the doctrine entails&amp;mdash;not least any hope of real
salvation. If Jesus was merely a man who was particularly helpful or holy, he
could not redeem other humans. He could at best set others a good example. His
death and his resurrection&lt;sup id="fnref:10"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:10" rel="footnote"&gt;10&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; can have symbolic power only. They do not save.
They inspire or impress at best, and intimidate with their inimitability at
worst.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All such views leave those who embrace them without ultimate salvific hope. As
Gregory Nazianzen commented during the Arian controversy, &amp;ldquo;For that which He has
not assumed he has not healed; but that which is united to His Godhead is also
saved. If only half Adam fell, then that which Christ assumes and saves may be
half also; but if the whole of his nature fell, it must be united to the whole
nature of Him that was begotten, and so be saved as a whole.&amp;rdquo;&lt;sup id="fnref:11"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:11" rel="footnote"&gt;11&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Though no conservative scholars would actively deny the importance of the
Incarnation, their passive neeglect can be nearly as problematic. Sadly, the
doctrine receives receives little attention among evangelicals. The crucicentric
bent of the evangelical movement has often led to other aspects of the Son&amp;rsquo;s
work being overlooked, so that the Incarnation, Resurrection, and Ascension of
Christ are all often treated as mere prerequisites for or accessories to his
atoning death.&lt;sup id="fnref:12"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:12" rel="footnote"&gt;12&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Even when unintentional, this loss-by-neglect results in
real problems in the church&amp;rsquo;s understanding of God&amp;rsquo;s work in Christ and
humanity. Many of the borderline gnostic tendencies latent in evangelical
theology eschatology, and the corresponding spiritualization and
de-physicalization of evangelical eschatology, must be laid at least in part at
the feet of a deficient theology of the Incarnation. This can only lead to a
dimming of future hope&amp;mdash;who really wants to be a disembodied spirit somehow
strumming a harp forever?&amp;mdash;which in turn produces real challenges in the life
and faith of believers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="b-incarnational-theology-a-two-fold-error"&gt;B. &amp;ldquo;Incarnational Theology&amp;rdquo;: A Two-Fold Error&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The church may also err by misapplying its theology of the Incarnation. It has
become increasingly common to speak of &amp;ldquo;incarnational theology&amp;rdquo; as a way of
describing the Christian mission to the world: Christians ought to &amp;ldquo;incarnate&amp;rdquo;
Christ to the world as Christ &amp;ldquo;incarnated&amp;rdquo; the Godhead to humanity.&lt;sup id="fnref:13"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:13" rel="footnote"&gt;13&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; There
is much to appreciate in this sentiment. It represents an appropriate
recognition that humans are God&amp;rsquo;s image-bearers. It pays heed to the New
Testament&amp;rsquo;s assertion that Christians are representatives of Christ. It takes
seriously Paul&amp;rsquo;s shocking language of &amp;ldquo;filling up what is lacking in Christ&amp;rsquo;s
afflictions&amp;rdquo; (Col. 1:24). It rightly points to the synthesis of missionary
activity and social activism that represents the best of evangelicalism.&lt;sup id="fnref:14"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:14" rel="footnote"&gt;14&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;
Yet for all that, applying the language of incarnation to believers is a serious
mistake in two ways.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, this kind of &amp;ldquo;incarnational&amp;rdquo; language is a misapplication of Paul&amp;rsquo;s
&amp;ldquo;body&amp;rdquo; metaphor for the church, contra the proponents of &amp;ldquo;incarnational
theology&amp;rdquo;, and notwithstanding Scripture&amp;rsquo;s many calls to imitate Christ.&lt;sup id="fnref:15"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:15" rel="footnote"&gt;15&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;
Paul uniformly used the language to teach the unity of the people of God&amp;mdash;never
evangelism. The authors of the New Testament chose other images for proclaiming
Christ instead: fishermen (Matt. 4:19), harvest workers (Luke 10:2), servants
working in the absence of their master (Matt. 24:45&amp;ndash;51), or ambassadors and
representatives (2 Cor. 5:20)&amp;mdash;to name just a few. At no point, though, does
the Bible use the metaphor of the body to describe Christian witness to the
world. Nor does it support the idea that ordinary men and women can mediate the
presence of God to people. The Incarnation may (and indeed should) prompt
evangelism, but this response is not itself &amp;ldquo;incarnational.&amp;rdquo; The people of God
do not incarnate God the Son, but represent him in other ways. That does not
negate the helpful instincts expressed in the incarnational theologizing of the
last few years. It simply means that this doctrine can be expressed more
accurately and helpfully.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Second, the church loses a great deal when incarnational theology is about
anyone other than Jesus. God becoming man was an astounding and singular event.
As Lewis commented, &amp;ldquo;It was the central event in the history of the Earth&amp;mdash;the
very thing that the whole story has been about.&amp;rdquo;&lt;sup id="fnref:16"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:16" rel="footnote"&gt;16&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; When theologians speak of
&amp;ldquo;incarnating&amp;rdquo; Christ, the sheer shock of the event fades. The focus shifts from
the Son&amp;rsquo;s work in humanity to the human response to the Son. The doctrine of the
Incarnation above all ought to lead to worship born of reflection not on human
endeavors, but on divine intervention to undo human brokenness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="iii-conclusion"&gt;III. Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Both the centrality of the Incarnation and its uniqueness are essential to
healthy Christian theology. A robust doctrine of the Incarnation leads to
greater worship and deeper future hope. Understood rightly, it leads to deeper
faith in the Word who &amp;ldquo;became flesh and dwelt among us&amp;rdquo; (John 1:14), and so to
more faithful obedience to the gospel. The believer seeks peace and justice and
above all that others may know Christ not because the he himself incarnates
Christ, but because the Incarnation has produced a radical transformation in his
life (and in the lives of all who believe). &amp;ldquo;Christ gives his sanctified
humanity to us, so that we may partake of him and his goodness.... God assumed
our umanity in Jesus of Nazareth, healed our humanity with his own being, and
gave our sanctified humanity back to us.&amp;rdquo;&lt;sup id="fnref:17"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:17" rel="footnote"&gt;17&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; The church must therefore take
care to protect the doctrine, both from reject or loss through neglect and from
misappropriations of the language of incarnation that distract from the work of
the Son. The Incarnation itself is essential and central in God&amp;rsquo;s work in the
life of believers. It must never be obscured, diminished, or denied.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id="appendix-the-chalcedonian-definition"&gt;Appendix: The Chalcedonian Definition&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;sup id="fnref:18"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:18" rel="footnote"&gt;18&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;For the synod is opposed to those who presume to rend asunder the mystery
of the Incarnation into a double Sonship, and it deposes from the priesthood
those who dare to say that the Godhead of the Only-begotten is passible; and it
withstands those who imagine a mixing or confusion of the two natures of Christ;
and it drives away those who erroneously teach that the form of a servant which
he took from us was of a heavenly or some other substance; and it anathematizes
those who feign that the Lord had two natures before the union, but that these
were fashioned into one after the union.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wherefore, following the holy Fathers, we all with one voice confess our Lord
Jesus Christ one and the same Son, the same perfect in Godhead, the same perfect
in manhood, truly God and truly man, the same consisting of a reasonable soul
and a body, of one substance with the Father as touching the Godhead, the same
of one substance with us as touching the manhood, like us in all things apart
from sin; begotten of the Father before the ages as touching the Godhead, the
same in the last days, for us and for our salvation, born from the Virgin Mary,
the Theotokos, as touching the manhood, one and the same Christ, Son, Lord,
Only-begotten, to be acknowledged in two natures, without confusion, without
change, without division, without separation; the distinction of natures being
in no way abolished because of the union, but rather the characteristic property
of each nature being preserved, and concurring into one Person and one
subsistence (ὑπόστασις), not as if Christ were parted or divided into two
persons, but one and the same Son and only-begotten God, Word, Lord, Jesus
Christ; even as the Prophets from the beginning spoke concerning him, and our
Lord Jesus Christ instructed us, and the Creed of the Fathers has handed down to
us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id="bibliography"&gt;Bibliography&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Barnes, Kenneth A. &amp;ldquo;&amp;lsquo;And the Word Became Flesh&amp;rsquo;: The Incarnation: A Model
    For Evangelism.&amp;rdquo; DMin diss., Southeastern Baptist Theological Seminary,
    1990.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bultmann, Rudolf. &amp;ldquo;New Testament and Mythology: The Mythological Element in
    the Message of the New Testament and the Problem of its Reinterpretation.&amp;rdquo;
    In &lt;em&gt;Kerygma and Myth: A Theological Debate&lt;/em&gt;. Edited by Hans Werner Bartch.
    Revised and translated by Reginald H. Fuller. 1953. Reprint, New York:
    Harper Torchbooks, 1961.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Clifford, Ross and Philip Johnson. &lt;em&gt;The Cross Is Not Enough: Living as
    Witnesses to the Resurrection&lt;/em&gt;. Grand Rapids: Baker Books, 2012.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Darbyshire, David L. &amp;ldquo;Incarnational Evangelism: An Intentional Approach to
    Sharing the Good News in a Boundary Environment.&amp;rdquo; DMin diss., Southeastern
    Baptist Theological Seminary, 1989.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Langmead, Ross. &lt;em&gt;Word Made Flesh: Towards an Incarnational Missiology&lt;/em&gt;.
    Lanham: University Press of America, Inc., 2004.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Letham, Robert. &lt;em&gt;The Holy Trinity: In Scripture, History, Theology, and
    Worship&lt;/em&gt;. Phillipsburg: P&amp;amp;R, 2004.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lewis, C. S. &lt;em&gt;Miracles: A Preliminary Study&lt;/em&gt;. London: Geoffrey Bless, 1947.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Morris, Leon. &lt;em&gt;The Atonement: Its meaning and significance&lt;/em&gt;. Downers Grove:
    Inter-Varsity Press, 1983.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;William E. Pannell. &amp;ldquo;Evangelism: Solidarity and Reconciliation.&amp;rdquo; In
    &lt;em&gt;Incarnational Ministry: The Presence of Christ in Church, Society, and
    Family: Essays in Honor of Ray S. Anderson&lt;/em&gt;, edited by Christian D. Kettler
    and Todd H. Speidell. Colorado Springs: Helmers &amp;amp; Howard, 1990.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Speidell, Todd H. &amp;ldquo;Incarnational Social Ethics.&amp;rdquo; In Speidell, 140&amp;ndash;152.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stevenson, James and B. J. Kidd, eds. &lt;em&gt;Creeds, Councils, and Controversies:
    Documents Illustrative of the History of the Church A.D. 337-461&lt;/em&gt;. New York:
    Seabury Press, 1966.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;C. S. Lewis, &lt;em&gt;Miracles: A Preliminary Study&lt;/em&gt; (London: Geoffrey Bless,
1947), 131.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:2"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Scripture citations throughout from the English Standard Version.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:2" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 2 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:3"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Athanasius &lt;em&gt;On the Incarnation&lt;/em&gt; 14, 20.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:3" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 3 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:4"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cf. Justin Martyr &lt;em&gt;First Apology&lt;/em&gt; (second century), Irenaeus &lt;em&gt;Against
Heresies&lt;/em&gt; (third century), Athanasius &lt;em&gt;On the Incarnation&lt;/em&gt; (fourth century),
Cyril of Alexandria, multiple volumes of works against Nestorianism (fifth
century).&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:4" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 4 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:5"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;See Appendix: The Chalcedonian Definition.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:5" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 5 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:6"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gregory Nazianzen &lt;em&gt;Epistle CI&lt;/em&gt;.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:6" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 6 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:7"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Athanasius &lt;em&gt;On the Incarnation&lt;/em&gt; 14, 44.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:7" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 7 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:8"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Todd H. Speidell, &amp;ldquo;Incarnational Social Ethics,&amp;rdquo; in &lt;em&gt;Incarnational
Ministry: The Presence of Christ in Church, Society, and Family: Essays in
Honor of Ray S. Anderson&lt;/em&gt;, eds. Christian D. Kettler and Todd H. Speidell
(Colorado Springs: Helmers &amp;amp; Howard, 1990), 143. Emphasis mine.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:8" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 8 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:9"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cf. Rudolf Bultmann, &amp;ldquo;New Testament and Mythology: The Mythological
Element in the Message of the New Testament and the Problem of its
Reinterpretation,&amp;rdquo; in &lt;em&gt;Kerygma and Myth: A Theological Debate&lt;/em&gt;, ed. Hans
Werner Bartch, rev. and trans. Reginald H. Fuller (1953; repr., New York:
Harper Torchbooks, 1961), 33&amp;ndash;35.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:9" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 9 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:10"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The resurrection is of course customarily denied in such theologies as
well.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:10" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 10 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:11"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gregory Nazianzen &lt;em&gt;Epistle CI&lt;/em&gt;.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:11" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 11 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:12"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cf. the reduction of all of Christ&amp;rsquo;s works to aspects of the atonement in
Leon Morris, &lt;em&gt;The Atonement: Its meaning and significance&lt;/em&gt; (Downers Grove:
Inter-Varsity Press, 1983); and see the similar critique in Ross Clifford
and Philip Johnson, &lt;em&gt;The Cross Is Not Enough: Living as Witnesses to the
Resurrection&lt;/em&gt; (Grand Rapids: Baker Books, 2012).&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:12" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 12 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:13"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cf. Ross Langmead, &lt;em&gt;Word Made Flesh: Towards an Incarnational Missiology&lt;/em&gt;
(Lanham: University Press of America, Inc., 2004), 9, 20, 36, 47&amp;ndash;58; David
L. Darbyshire, &amp;ldquo;Incarnational Evangelism: An Intentional Approach to Sharing
the Good News in a Boundary Environment&amp;rdquo; (DMin diss., Southeastern Baptist
Theological Seminary, 1989), 46&amp;ndash;50; Kenneth A. Barnes, &amp;ldquo;&amp;lsquo;And the Word
Became Flesh&amp;rsquo;: The Incarnation: A Model For Evangelism&amp;rdquo; (DMin diss.,
Southeastern Baptist Theological Seminary, 1990), 32&amp;ndash;43, 48, 50, 57.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:13" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 13 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:14"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cf. William E. Pannell, &amp;ldquo;Evangelism: Solidarity and Reconciliation,&amp;rdquo; in
Speidell, 203.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:14" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 14 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:15"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Barnes (36&amp;ndash;38) rightly notes that imitating Christ is an essential
element in the Christian life, but makes numerous hermeneutical missteps in
his attempt to extend those texts to justify an &amp;ldquo;incarnational&amp;rdquo; theology.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:15" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 15 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:16"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Miracles&lt;/em&gt;, 131.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:16" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 16 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:17"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Speidell, 149.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:17" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 17 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:18"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;The Chalcedonian Definition of the Faith,&amp;rdquo; in &lt;em&gt;Creeds, Councils, and
Controversies: Documents Illustrative of the History of the Church A.D.
337-461&lt;/em&gt;, eds. James Stevenson and B. J. Kidd (New York: Seabury Press,
1966), 352–353.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:18" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 18 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 06 May 2014 08:15:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2014-05-06:2014/the-uniqueness-of-the-incarnation.html</guid><category>M. Div.</category><category>SEBTS</category><category>papers</category></item><item><title>Communicatio Idiomatum</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2014/communicatio-idiomatum.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;The &amp;ldquo;communication of attributes&amp;rdquo; (Latin &lt;em&gt;communicatio idiomatum&lt;/em&gt;) is a summary
of one of the essential Christian affirmations about the Incarnation of the Son
of God: that in the Incarnation, the person Jesus shared both divine and human
attributes. The properties of divinity and humanity &lt;em&gt;both&lt;/em&gt; fully existed in
Jesus the Messiah; they did not cross into each other, but were united in the
Son. The Son then could choose to use whichever attributes were appropriate to
him at a given time: he could both ride in a boat (consistent with being a human
being) or forgive sins (consistenly only with being God). This carries through
to all aspects of the Son&amp;rsquo;s work upon his incarnation: he has a human will and a
divine will, neither of which overrides the other but both of which are
exercised together as appropriate. The divine will is already in line with the
will of the Father; the human will he chooses to subject to the Father. By
analogy: one may know both English and French, and if so one speaks each
language as appropriate&amp;mdash;there is no implied division in a person simply
because he knows more than one language.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This communication of attributes was accomplished so that no part of either the
Son&amp;rsquo;s pre-existing humanity divinity or newly-embraced humanity was either
changed or diminished in the Incarnation. The two were &lt;em&gt;united&lt;/em&gt;, but they were
not altered or subsumed. This important reality was articulated in the four
negations of the Chalcedonian definition:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Jesus, the two natures were united &lt;em&gt;without confusion&lt;/em&gt;. The Incarnation
    was not like mixing wine and water to produce a &lt;em&gt;tertium quid&lt;/em&gt;, a third
    thing like both of the others but not actually either of them, even while no
    longer distinguishable from each other. Jesus was both God and man, not a
    new thing that was neither wholly God nor wholly man.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Jesus, the two natures were united &lt;em&gt;without diminishing&lt;/em&gt;. The Incarnation
    was not like putting a drop of wine in the ocean so that the wine simply
    dissipates and is meaningless. Thus Apollinarian view that the Son&amp;rsquo;s divine
    nature subsumed and overwhelmed the human nature was rejected. In Jesus both
    human and divine natures were fully present, and neither overwhelmed the
    other.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Jesus, the two natures were united &lt;em&gt;without mixture&lt;/em&gt;. The Incarnation was
    not the result of combining two things that were unlike to produce a new
    thing which could still be separated into the old things. In other words,
    the Son&amp;rsquo;s becoming man was not like sodium joining with chloride to produce
    salt, which is entirely different from either sodium or chloride.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Jesus, the two natures were united &lt;em&gt;without separating&lt;/em&gt;. The Incarnation
    was not like bundling together a pair of sticks which could just as easily
    be pulled apart. The Son did not shed his humanity upon his resurrection or
    his ascension; he remains now and forever a human being as well as divine.
    Thus all the experiences, actions, and sayings of Jesus are attributable to
    one person (rather than suggesting that the divine Son did some things and
    the human being did another&amp;mdash;one stick and another stick acting in distinct
    ways). Rather, one person, Jesus, walked (and walks) with both natures,
    lived (and lives) both kinds of lives, existed (and exists) in both ways.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thus, the attributes of God and of humanity were both &lt;em&gt;communicated&lt;/em&gt;&amp;mdash;they had
communion&amp;mdash;in Christ. In Jesus, the human and divine did not mingle into a
distinctionless soup, did not overwhelm each other, cannot be separated, and did
not create some new thing unlike human or God. Jesus is fully God and fully man,
forever.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 03 May 2014 14:00:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2014-05-03:2014/communicatio-idiomatum.html</guid><category>M. Div.</category><category>SEBTS</category></item><item><title>Perfectionism</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2014/perfectionism.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;The theory of perfectionism suggests that believers ultimately come to a point
in their &lt;em&gt;present&lt;/em&gt; walk with God where they stop willfully sinning. This stands
in contrast to non-perfectionistic views which believe the end of willful sin
comes only at &lt;em&gt;glorification&lt;/em&gt; after one&amp;rsquo;s death.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Modern perfectionism was advocated by John Wesley at some points during his
ministry and adopted as a hallmark of the Wesleyan tradition (though Wesley
himself abandoned the view late in life). In the Wesleyan view, the believer at
some point during his life experiences a &amp;ldquo;second blessing&amp;rdquo; in which the Holy
Spirit supernaturally empowers the believer to overcome the rest of his natural
(fleshly) tendency toward sin. This moment must be apprehended by the believer
in faith&amp;mdash;it is not guaranteed to all believers but is granted to those who
seek it in faith. The Wesleyans draw this view primarily from the apostle John&amp;rsquo;s
note that &amp;ldquo;No one who lives in [Christ] keeps on sinning&amp;rdquo; (1 John 3:6), as well
as from various other passages which suggest that Christians may &lt;em&gt;stop&lt;/em&gt; sinning.
Moreover, they note the biblical commands to holiness and argue that these
strongly imply (if not demand) that believers be able actually to live truly
holy lives. Thus, believers should pray regularly for this empowering act of the
Spirit in their lives so that they may fulfill God&amp;rsquo;s will that they be truly
holy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The view has some significant and serious problems, not least in the &lt;em&gt;rest&lt;/em&gt; of
the book from which they primarily draw their support: John himself notes that
when (not if) believers sin, they have an advocate with the Father in the person
of Jesus himself (1 John 2:1). Similarly, the testimony of Paul and his ongoing
struggles with sin after conversion and his explicit denial of having reached
perfection (cf. Romans 7, Philippians 2) indicates that even for extraordinarily
faithful believers, perfection will remain an unfilled but longed-for state
until death.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Practically, the view readily leads to frustration and even despair on the one
hand or profound hubris on the other. Those who, despite their pleading and
(true!) faith do not have any experience of &amp;ldquo;second blessing&amp;rdquo; and instead remain
aware of their ongoing struggle with sin may find themselves thinking they are
simply weak in the faith and that they will never accomplish God&amp;rsquo;s plan for
their holiness. This could not be further from the truth: those most faithfully
walking with God are in fact those &lt;em&gt;most&lt;/em&gt; aware of their own sinfulness. On the
other hand, those who think they have found this holiness end up self-deceived.
They proclaim their own sinlessness, and prove hypocrites. They may end up
holding themselves up as superior to others (even if only in their own minds).
They certainly will not go on as they ought in the process of mortifying their
own sins, because they are convinced they have none.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 03 May 2014 14:00:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2014-05-03:2014/perfectionism.html</guid><category>M. Div.</category><category>SEBTS</category></item><item><title>The Divinity of Jesus</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2014/the-divinity-of-jesus.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;The divinity of Jesus is and has been from the beginning a core component of
the Christian faith. There are several reasons why Christians have always
affirmed and indeed &lt;em&gt;must&lt;/em&gt; affirm the deity of Christ. First, Scripture itself
clearly testifies to the fully deity of Jesus as the Son of God. To name just a
few:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the Incarnation passage in John&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Thomas&amp;rsquo; outburst of faith, &amp;ldquo;My lord and my God!&amp;rdquo; to Jesus upon his
    resurrection&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Thomas&amp;rsquo; outburst of faith, &amp;ldquo;My lord and my God!&amp;rdquo; to Jesus upon his
    resurrection&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the quotes throughout the New Testament but especially in Hebrews where God
    is quoted as addressing Jesus as God&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the quotes throughout the New Testament but especially in Hebrews where God
    is quoted as addressing Jesus as God&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the obvious reality that the early church prayed to and worshipped Jesus&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So the Christian is first of all obliged by the Scriptures to acknowledge Jesus
as God. Beyond this, however, is the reason that it had to be God Incarnate who
saved human beings and not merely another human being (still less any other
created thing). First, salvation entails reconciliation between God and
humanity. That is, the salvation Christ accomplished was not only between God
and human beings as individuals, but between God and &lt;em&gt;human nature&lt;/em&gt; which was
broken in the fall and separated from God in whose image it was made. That
Christ is the image of the invisible God (Colossians 1:15, Hebrews 1:3) is not
only an affirmation of the nature of the divine Son but an affirmation of the
restored humanity of Jesus the Messiah.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Second, Jesus was a substitution for human sins. For this he of course had to
be a human being (as the author of Hebrews notes: the blood of sheep and goats
could not make purification for human sins). However, he had also to be God.
Even if one mere human lived a perfectly sinless life, this perfect life would
not be transferrable to another human being: it would be his alone, and would
have no extra righteousness to give to another. But Jesus is fully God, and has
&lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; righteousness. Indeed, it is the righteousness of God&amp;mdash;infinite,
boundless, untainted by sin&amp;mdash;that Christians receive by faith. It is not one
man&amp;rsquo;s righteousness somehow wafted across a courtroom (to borrow N. T. Wright&amp;rsquo;s
metaphor), but the righteousness of God in which humans participate because
they are united with Christ.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, Jesus came to overcome death. To die, he had to be a man, but to bring
life he had to be God. Human beings do not have in themselves the power of life
(still less to overcome death)&amp;mdash;but God whose very name is &amp;ldquo;I AM&amp;rdquo;/&amp;rdquo;HE IS&amp;rdquo; has
life in himself. Jesus the divine Son had and has life &lt;em&gt;in himself&lt;/em&gt;, and he
therefore can and did overcome death. In his restored humanity, death no longer
has any power. His resurrection was the first moment when this divine power of
life broke into the fallen reality and gave a formerly mortal human body
immortality. Believers have in one sense already died and been raised in him,
and in another sense look forward to a fuller participation in that divine
reality of life that does not end. Death died in the resurrection because
Christ was &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; merely a man, because his return from the grave was not like
Lazarus&amp;rsquo; a mere rescuscitation but the triumph of divine life over human
frailty.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 03 May 2014 14:00:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2014-05-03:2014/the-divinity-of-jesus.html</guid><category>M. Div.</category><category>SEBTS</category></item><item><title>The Nature of Justification (redux)</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2014/the-nature-of-justification-redux.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Put most simply, to be justified is to be &lt;em&gt;right&lt;/em&gt; with God&amp;mdash;to be &amp;ldquo;righteous&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Being right with God is a complex and multifaceted reality. To understand it,
however, one must understand how &lt;em&gt;God&lt;/em&gt; is just and righteous, because Christian
righteousness is &lt;em&gt;Christ&amp;rsquo;s&lt;/em&gt; righteousness (2 Corinthians 5:21). God&amp;rsquo;s
righteousness is intrinsic to him; it is expressed in his righteous deeds, most
especially in judging justly. His justice, in turn, is expressed in the most
gracious and merciful manner imaginable: he punished sin and defeated death in
himself, rather than in the people who deserved punishment and had brought death
on themselves. Moreover, he also removes the power of sin in their lives so that
they ultimately may &lt;em&gt;stop&lt;/em&gt; breaking fellowship with him and each other and may
stop acting in such a way as to earn the penalty of sin (death). So God&amp;rsquo;s
justice and righteousness are seen in that he restores people to unbroken
relationship with him, removes from them not only their guilt but their
brokenness and inevitable tendency toward sin.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If this is the righteousness that is granted to Christians in Christ, then it is
more than (though not less than) a change in judicial state before God.
Christians have forensic justification in Christ&amp;mdash;they are declared &amp;ldquo;not
guilty&amp;rdquo; in him&amp;mdash;because they are united with him. Colossians 2:9&amp;ndash;14 drives
home this connection clearly: believers are filled in Christ, buried in death
and raised to life with him in baptism. This new life and participation in
Christ is then the grounds of God&amp;rsquo;s setting aside the legal demands that stood
against the believer: they are nailed to the cross because Christ was nailed to
the cross and the believer &lt;em&gt;is in Christ&lt;/em&gt;. All trespasses are forgiven, because
the believer is no longer operating under his own nature but is full of Christ,
and in Christ the fullness of God dwells bodily.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So then to be justified, to be made right with God, is to have all of Christ&amp;rsquo;s
righteousness as &lt;em&gt;actually&lt;/em&gt; one&amp;rsquo;s own. It is not a legal fiction, but a
spiritual reality. The believer is right with God; he may not always live in
accord with this reality, but he is. By analogy: a husband is always married to
his wife; even if he strays by cheating on her, he remains truly married to her.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This view of justification cuts off at its core any kind of works-righteousness
view of righteousness. The righteousness that believers possess is always
entirely God&amp;rsquo;s righteousness mediated to them by the Spirit through their
participation in the resurrected Son. It is not, as in the Roman Catholic view,
participatory righteousness in which the believer contributes his own
righteousness (even if by faith and the Spirit&amp;rsquo;s power) and the remainder is
accomplished by God. Nor is it that God &lt;em&gt;chooses&lt;/em&gt; to see the believer as if he
is righteous when in actuality he is not (yet) righteous because sanctification
is incomplete. Rather, no part of the believer&amp;rsquo;s righteousness&amp;mdash;right state,
and not only right standing&amp;mdash;is his own. Rather, it is always all of God. When
acting righteously, one &lt;em&gt;demonstrates&lt;/em&gt; that one is justified, but whoever is in
Christ is already truly righteous.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 03 May 2014 14:00:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2014-05-03:2014/the-nature-of-justification-redux.html</guid><category>M. Div.</category><category>SEBTS</category></item><item><title>The Spirit's Work in Conversion (redux)</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2014/the-spirits-work-in-conversion-redux.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;The Holy Spirit&amp;rsquo;s work in conversion, as in all the works of the Spirit, is the
part of executing the will of the Father in the person of the Son. The Spirit
brought about the Incarnation, and raised Jesus from the dead; now the Spirit
makes the Son&amp;rsquo;s work efficacious in the hearts of believers. The Father
originated the work of salvation; the Son (in his incarnation, life, death,
resurrection, and ascension) was and is the means of salvation; the Spirit is
the one who guarantees and accomplishes salvation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To begin, the Spirit opens unbelievers&amp;rsquo; eyes to their need for salvation.
Sinners apart from the Spirit are lost and hopeless, with either no awareness of
need for God (passivity) or an active rejection of God (rebellion). The Spirit
opens an unregenerate individual to see his need for salvation, providing an
awareness of sinfulness and separation from God, and prompting desire for
restored relationship and righteousness. This all happens in the preaching of
the gospel, which the Spirit makes effective in the person&amp;rsquo;s mind&amp;mdash;even as the
Spirit was responsible for the existence of the gospel in Scripture to begin
with. Thus the Spirit inspired the words of the gospel and then brings them to
fruition: the Spirit is executor of God&amp;rsquo;s will.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moreover, the Spirit enables faith in Jesus Christ as the resurrected Son of
God, as savior and lord.&lt;sup id="fnref:1"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:1" rel="footnote"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; In this recognition of one&amp;rsquo;s need and decisive
change in the will&amp;mdash;toward rather than away from God&amp;mdash;the Spirit brings about
the regeneration of the human heart. Regeneration unites the new believer to
Jesus Christ: he comes to participate in the Son&amp;rsquo;s perfected, divinized
humanity. Indeed, believers &amp;ldquo;become partakers of the divine nature&amp;rdquo; (2 Peter
1:4). Where once the believer&amp;rsquo;s heart rejected God, God now appears good and
delightful and worthy of worship and trust. Where once one thought nothing of
engaging in sin, one now increasingly hates and rejects sin and strives to sin
no more. The Spirit replaces a heart of stone with a heart of flesh, and moves
believers from darkness to light.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having accomplished the salvation of an individual soul, the Spirit brings the
believer into the community of faith. No person&amp;rsquo;s salvation is singular or
independent. Maturity and completion happen as one participates in the
restoration of relationship not only with God but with other human beings. The
people of God all participate &lt;em&gt;together&lt;/em&gt; through the Spirit in Jesus the Son. It
is the Spirit who makes the people of God the body of Christ. And the Spirit
seals the people of God for redemption, keeping them steadfast in their faith as
they build one another up through fellowship and the proclamation of the word
and participation in the ordinances&amp;mdash;all of which are Spirit-empowered to
continue God&amp;rsquo;s gracious work in the believer&amp;rsquo;s life, leading ultimately to final
salvation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Believers have differed on the particulars of this enabling throughout
history, but all affirm that the Spirit does indeed enable faith as a
minimum assertion. My own position is that the Spirit does not only &lt;em&gt;enable&lt;/em&gt;
faith but &lt;em&gt;supplies&lt;/em&gt; it to hearts which would otherwise reject God. That is,
the Spirit is not merely the ultimate ground but also the proximate cause of
regeneration.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 03 May 2014 14:00:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2014-05-03:2014/the-spirits-work-in-conversion-redux.html</guid><category>M. Div.</category><category>SEBTS</category></item><item><title>Further Upward and Further In</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2014/further-upward-and-further-in.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Humanity was meant for something more than its current state. Those of us who
are in Christ are, by the grace of God, slowly being transformed into that
&lt;em&gt;something more&lt;/em&gt;. We are being made like God. This is the essential nature of
the process of sanctification: slow transformation from our current state into
the image of God. Sanctification is one of the most important ideas in the
Bible, and many things besides people were sanctified in the course of salvation
history. Sanctification is being set apart for service to God, being made &amp;ldquo;holy&amp;rdquo;
&amp;mdash;including especially the various elements used in the pre-Christ sacrificial
system. This kind of holiness entails both moral uprightness and distinction
from the mundane.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We first recognize that moral failure is a reality&amp;mdash;a sad and tragic reality,
but a reality nonetheless&amp;mdash;in the life of the Christian. Even after
experiencing regeneration and justification, we remain &lt;em&gt;simultus justus et
peccator&lt;/em&gt;, to borrow Luther&amp;rsquo;s famous phrase: simultaneously justified and yet
sinners. We remain in the world &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; of the world, rather than in it but not of
it. We are not yet wholly set apart for God&amp;rsquo;s works, but too often continue to
pursue fallen ends via fallen means. We need to be transformed so that we pursue
God&amp;rsquo;s ends (ultimately: God himself) as he has called us, rather than the things
of the earth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But God in his wisdom has ordained that we &lt;em&gt;grow&lt;/em&gt; into this. We are justified at
a single moment by faith in Christ, and our sanctification will ultimately be
finished in a single moment when we are glorified upon our death. In the
interval, though, God has called us to pursue him, to strive for the holiness
which Christ exemplified for us. As we do, we learn to trust him more and rely
more thoroughly on his power and wisdom rather than our own, and this too is
part of the process of sanctification. When we are perfected, it will not be a
matter of suddenly being able to do on our own what we could not before, but
rather that we will finally depend wholly on God.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this we are growing into the full maturity of humanity. Our model is Jesus
Christ: the God-man who shows us what it means to be a perfect human being. He
taught us over and over again not only by example but by direct affirmation that
his life was characterized above all by dependence on his Father and that he
acted not on his own power but that of the Spirit. In our sanctification, we
learn to walk the same way. As in our justification, this comes about because we
are being united to Christ by the indwelling Spirit&amp;mdash;so our growing humanity is
also growing to participate in the life of the Trinity. We pursue the Father and
his ways, empowered by the Spirit to partake of Christ&amp;rsquo;s risen, divinized
humanity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This way of putting it is often jarring to western theologians, but is fully
orthodox and has been part of the Eastern Orthodox tradition for sixteen
centuries and more. It draws directly on the language of 2 Peter 1:4, which
reminds us that we are partakers of the divine nature. It was on that very basis
that Peter laid out his enjoinder to grow in the various measures of
sanctification: faith, virtue, knowledge, self-control, steadfastness,
godliness, brotherly affection, and love (a list that bears what is surely not a
coincidental similarity to Paul&amp;rsquo;s fruit of the Spirit). Sanctification is our
wholehearted pursuit of the things of God, not on our own power but by his
gracious work in us, until we someday attain to full maturity and depend wholly
on the Spirit&amp;rsquo;s uniting us to Christ.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 29 Apr 2014 08:15:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2014-04-29:2014/further-upward-and-further-in.html</guid><category>M. Div.</category><category>SEBTS</category></item><item><title>Right Standing Before God</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2014/right-standing-before-god.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Any discussion of the work of God in Christ has to include the idea of
justification: it is an important throughout the Bible, and is especially
prominent in Paul&amp;rsquo;s writings on salvation (which comprise a substantial part of
the New Testament and most of our systematically theological reflection on
salvation arises). The word &amp;ldquo;justify&amp;rdquo; and its nominal forms are used to
translate words from the &lt;em&gt;dikaoō&lt;/em&gt;  (δικαιόω) word group in Greek, which includes
a number of related concepts, all circling in various ways around the notion of
justice and right action and just and righteous character. Since
&amp;ldquo;justification&amp;rdquo;&amp;mdash;being justified&amp;mdash;before God is a central idea in Scripture
and an essential element of our salvation, we should be careful to understand
what exactly this concept means.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most basically, for a person to be justified is for him or her to be righteous,
and correspondingly to have acted rightly&amp;mdash;in the eyes of God. At a bare
minimum, this of course requires both the performance of good works and the
rejection of sin. However, justification means more than simply having checked
off a series of boxes corresponding to specific good works while having avoided
other boxes corresponding to bad or sinful actions. It means being regarded as
having done righteously and justly by God, and God sees our hearts, so even
doing what is right and shunning what is wrong may not be sufficient: we often
have entirely the wrong motives in such actions. We seek the approval of men
instead of to please God; we want the social or personal benefits that follow
from doing nice things for others; we enjoy stoking the fires of our own pride.
In any case, we do not even act rightly, still less do so for the glory of God.
So the idea that we might be justified on our own merits is hopeless.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Second, we should note that ordinary notions of justification often tend to
include many of the right (that is, Biblical) concepts of justification in them,
but in shallower forms than Scripture supplies. In particular, the use of the
term has shifted somewhat from when it was used to translate the  word group
from Greek into English. When we say, &amp;ldquo;he was justified,&amp;rdquo; we do not mean that
someone did the right thing, but that whatever someone did, he had grounds for
doing. We can of course turn this back to our needs by noting that we have
grounds only for right-hearted obedience and none for sinning. Still, this is
less than the biblical idea of justification&amp;mdash;of being considered to have done
rightly in every way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the &amp;ldquo;Christian&amp;rdquo; to be justified, we must be able to stand before God and he
consider us righteous in every word and deed and thought and attitude of the
heart. This happens in two ways (inseparable from each other): forensic
justification and imputed righteousness through union with Christ. In &amp;ldquo;forensic
justification,&amp;rdquo; God legally acquits us of guilt for committed sin and righteous
deeds left undone. The list of offenses we committed was nailed to the cross
(cf. Colossians 2:13&amp;ndash;15). This can happen because we are united with Jesus the
Son of God by the Spirit of God. As Paul notes in 2 Corinthians 5:21, the
sinless Christ became sin that we might become the righteousness of God. All
that is Christ&amp;rsquo;s is ours; we are one with him and so we have all his
righteousness. (The word &amp;ldquo;righteousness&amp;rdquo; here derives from the same root as we
translate &amp;ldquo;justification&amp;rdquo;&amp;mdash;these ideas are inextricably linked.) Finally, God
himself justifies us, calling us righteous, because Jesus Christ has both lived
in perfect righteousness and paid the penalty for our sins, propitiating the
wrath of God (cf. Romans 3).&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 22 Apr 2014 08:15:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2014-04-22:2014/right-standing-before-god.html</guid><category>M. Div.</category><category>SEBTS</category></item><item><title>Halfway to His Own Thesis</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2014/halfway-to-his-own-thesis.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Five Smooth Stones for Pastoral Work&lt;/em&gt;, by Eugene H. Peterson. Grand Rapids:
Eerdmans, 1980. 241 pp. $20.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="overview"&gt;Overview&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In &lt;em&gt;Five Smooth Stones for Pastoral Work&lt;/em&gt;, Eugene Peterson advocates for a
biblically grounded rather than psychologically-driven approach to pastoral
work. He argues that the idea that pastors must first of all be up to date and
current has things precisely backwards: the pastor&amp;rsquo;s responsibility is to lead
his congregation back to timeless realities, not into the hippest fads of the
day. He suggests that the &lt;em&gt;Megilloth&lt;/em&gt;, the &amp;ldquo;five scrolls&amp;rdquo; of Songs of Songs,
Ruth, Lamentations, Ecclesiastes, and Esther, have particular lessons to teach
pastors as they seek to bring &amp;ldquo;what is essential in the human condition, not
what is accicental&amp;rdquo; (p. 2) down into the &amp;ldquo;idiosyncrasies of the local and the
personal&amp;rdquo; (p. 5). A failure either to hold fast to the eternal word and will of
God, or to bring it home to those to whom the pastor ministers, will leave the
people without what they most deeply need: a shepherd through the vagaries and
trials of life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Peterson provides a substantial introduction to the book (some ten percent or so
of the book&amp;rsquo;s text), in which he traces out his thesis in detail. He then
divides the rest of the book into five discussions of pastoral work, grounding
each in one of those &amp;ldquo;five scrolls.&amp;rdquo; In each, Peterson interacts with the
psychologizing tendency of the present day, the history of the interpretation of
the Biblical book in question, and how pastors might learn from and apply the
lessons of the book to their own work in their own congregations. For Peterson,
Song of Songs is a model for directing God&amp;rsquo;s people into richer prayer, Ruth is
a picture of situating individual stories in the context of salvific history,
Lamentations is a guide to walking with people through their suffering,
Ecclesiastes is a help in rejecting false religion in place of the fear of God,
and Esther is a pointer to the essentially communal nature of the people of God.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="analysis"&gt;Analysis&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Curiously, the most significant problem with the book might at first appear to
be one of its great strengths. Peteron&amp;rsquo;s skill as a writer is such that he can
sometimes carry the reader along by sheer rhetorical effect&amp;mdash;but this is in
some sense a result antithetical to the purpose of the text. In a text
explicitly and self-consciously aiming to point pastors away from technique and
the tendency to mistake emotion for changed lives, the contrast with what
Peterson actually does in large swaths of the book is striking and unfortunate.
There are too many places where Peterson relies on the emotional impact of his
words rather than on the text itself. Nearly the whole chapter on Esther falls
into this trap, as do large swaths of the chapters on Ecclesiastes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is not so much that the points Peterson makes in these chapters are wrong:
many of them are quite on target. It is that, disconnected from the text from
which he purports to draw them, they become mere floating assertions about the
world&amp;mdash;assertions that, however beautifully made, we may take or leave as they
strike us. There is too much technique in Peterson&amp;rsquo;s theologizing and too little
of the Scripture to which he enjoins his readers to return.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Granted that Peterson makes no claim to be writing exegetical commentaries on
the text, but he opens the book with the reminder that &amp;ldquo;we don&amp;rsquo;t, and we must
not, lay our own foundations&amp;rdquo; (p. 11). Indeed, he (quite rightly) spends the
whole introduction pleading for pastors to ground their work not in the trends
of the day but in the &amp;ldquo;eternal will and word of God&amp;rdquo; (p. 5). It is a strange
thing that he should then spend so much of the book on his own ruminations and
not wrestling with the particulars of those texts. This is a significant loss,
because when Peterson does remain more closely engaged with the text, as in his
chapters on Ruth and Lamentations, and as in some parts of his treatment of
Ecclesiastes, the effect is marvelous. The reader is drawn into wonder at the
way God&amp;rsquo;s word guides us effectively for pastoral ministry. The pastor is
reminded that the circumstances and trials he and his flock face are not things
newly sprung up in the late twentieth or early twenty-first century, but the
sorts of things for which God has already supplied guides and instruction in the
Scriptures.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But this is no surprise: this is Peterson&amp;rsquo;s own thesis. The power of our faith,
the fruitfulness of pastoral ministry (and the effectiveness of our books
thereon) is not in our technique but in grappling deeply with the word of God in
our own situations. The more he grapples with the Scriptures, the more his
technique serves the text, the better Peterson&amp;rsquo;s book is&amp;mdash;and vice versa. Where
technique serves exposition, the reader is built up. Where exposition falls
aside and rhetoric reigns, the reader may be moved emotionally, but little
remains when that glow fades.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thus, for four of the five chapters in the book, Peterson&amp;rsquo;s success in advancing
his thesis may largely be measured by the extent to which he engages the text.
In Ruth and Lamentations, the narrative and poetry respectively drive the
discussion, and so the chapters are profoundly helpful. The discussion of Ruth
helps the pastor see his peoples&amp;rsquo; personal stories rightly&amp;mdash;and thus, to help
his people see their own stories rightly. They are not the end-all and be-all
that modern psychology might make them out to be, but neither are they
insignificant. Indeed, they are all the more significant precisely &lt;em&gt;because&lt;/em&gt;
they are part of something much bigger than themselves. The discussion of
Lamentations helps a pastor to see the necessity both of walking &lt;em&gt;through&lt;/em&gt;
suffering and sorrow with his flock and of helping them come to resolution in
the right time. Petersons&amp;rsquo; treatment of Ecclesiastes, as a guide to saying &lt;em&gt;no&lt;/em&gt;
to false religion, seems to be an accurate analysis of the book, but Peterson
veers away from the Text. He deals too little with the specific ways in which
&lt;em&gt;Qoheleth&lt;/em&gt; confronts our culture and too much in the sweeping generalizations
about the value of those confrontations. Least helpful of all is his treatment
of Esther, in which he rightly diagnoses severe problems in the culture around
us but leaves aside almost everything in the book itself. We desperately need
the kind of rebuke to individualism he suggests here. Whether Esther can support
that kind of rebuke, still less offer an alternative vision of the people of
God, is left aside in favor of a good but largely-unrelated discussion of Saul
and Amalek and the shape of ministry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Peterson&amp;rsquo;s treatment of the Song of Songs deserves its own analysis. The text is
notoriously hard to interpret, and has been subject to countless different
readings. Peterson falls squarely into the allegorical camp, though he gives the
allegorical reading something of a twist. The urgency of romantic (both
emotional and sexual) desire so prominent in the book he transmutes into a
picture of the Christian&amp;rsquo;s right desire for communion with God. This was the
chapter in which Peterson hewed &lt;em&gt;most&lt;/em&gt; closely to the text, and so it was the
chapter least susceptible to the problems outlined above. As with all treatments
of the Song, though, the effectiveness of the chapter hinges on whether one
finds Peterson&amp;rsquo;s interpretation accurate. (I did not.) Insofar as one grants
Peterson&amp;rsquo;s interpretation, though, the chapter is an effective argument for the
necessity of prayer, and especially of the pastor leading his people to pray
with greater fervency.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="conclusion"&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Five Smooth Stones for Pastoral Work&lt;/em&gt; is in some ways a very good book, but in
others it falls short&amp;mdash;an especially unfortunate reality given the very real
problems at which it aimed. That Peterson wants to see pastors grounding their&lt;em&gt;pastoring&lt;/em&gt; in the Scriptures as well as their preaching and teaching is clear.
Less clear is whether this book will be as effective as it could have been in
accomplishing that end. Good pastoral work does not run aground only on the
rocks of psychology. Rhetoric is an equally deadly reef, and it may be the more
tempting to a skilled writer passionate for the recovery of Biblical pastoral
work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The chapters on Ruth and Lamentations were excellent and profoundly helpful
treatments of the topics they addressed, and Peterson&amp;rsquo;s treatment of Song of
Songs was at least interesting. Because he exchanged exposition for effect in
his treatments of Ecclesiastes and Esther, though, the book falters. Though his
words never failed to pack an emotional punch, they were too often hollowed out
by their lack of a connection to the text. In this, these chapters serve as an
accidental and unfortunate illustration of the necessity of Peterson&amp;rsquo;s own
thesis. We need not more effective psychology, nor more powerful lnaguage, but a
deeper reliance on and connection to the word of God.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 12 Apr 2014 08:00:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2014-04-12:2014/halfway-to-his-own-thesis.html</guid><category>M. Div.</category><category>SEBTS</category><category>book reviews</category></item><item><title>The Spirit and Christian Formation</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2014/the-spirit-and-christian-formation.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Discussions of the person of the Holy Spirit in modern Christianity tend to
focus on the third person of the Trinity&amp;rsquo;s obviously miraculous activity in the
world&amp;mdash;the &amp;ldquo;gifts&amp;rdquo; that characterize the charismatic movement and the
associated controversy. Though these gifts are certainly part of the recorded
history of the Spirit&amp;rsquo;s work, the church&amp;rsquo;s focus thereupon (whether positive or
negative) on the gifts has had the unfortunate side effect of hiding many of the
other, arguably more central and essential actions of the Spirit in the life of
the believer. Just as the Spirit is the person who mediates to us the work of
Christ in our salvation and brings about our conversion, the Spirit is the one
who leads us into greater participation in the renewed humanity the Son has
accomplished in his incarnation, life, death, resurrection, and ascension. The
Spirit is the one who progressively deepens our union with Christ and reshapes
us to be like Him who saved us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Spirit accomplishes these ends in a variety of ways, all of which are
themselves worthy of further reflection. First of all, it was the Spirit who
superintended the writing of Scripture, the self-revelation of the Triune
Godhead for our salvation and sanctification. If Christian formation is in no
small measure a matter of growing to know our Creator&amp;mdash;if we are being restored
to active relationship with one who made us for that very relationship&amp;mdash;then
the ways in which our Creator has revealed himself are supremely important.
Without Scripture, we would know little of God; through it we enter in the deep
mysteries. The first part the Spirit plays in our formation, then, is in having
guided every hand from Moses&amp;rsquo; to John&amp;rsquo;s in the writing of the word of God. Upon
this foundation comes the Spirit&amp;rsquo;s second work: opening our eyes to understand
that Scripture. The things of God are foolishness to unregenerate people, but
beautiful and savory to those who have been given spiritual life. The word of
God can seem dense and opaque to those who do not believe, but every believer in
Christ finds that more and more these mysteries unfold: this is the Spirit at
work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As we come to understand the person of God and the things he has commanded us in
his word, we find that we are still weak and struggle to do them. Here, too, the
Spirit is at work, for it is the Spirit who empowers our obedience. We know that
the same Spirit that raised Christ from the dead is at work in us&amp;mdash;and this is
the only hope we have of overcoming sin and growing in holiness. Part and parcel
of this, the Spirit empowers us to endure the suffering that God uses to make us
more dependent on him and more faithful to him. Likewise, when in the course of
our lives we are tempted to fall away, it is the Spirit who helps us continue to
hold fast to the faith. Moreover, the Spirit intercedes for us when we do not
know how to pray ourselves. When we are beset by temptation, when tempted to
fall away, when exhausted from the battle, when wearied of the pursuit of
holiness, the Spirit prays for us. Nor is the Spirit&amp;rsquo;s work directed solely to
individuals. All of these realities are corporate, and in all of them we grow in
unity and kindness toward one another. The Spirit is our bond of peace.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In summary, then, we have both the Spirit and the Son praying for us to the
Father who delights to answer those prayers, and the Spirit empowering us walk
in the Son&amp;rsquo;s life with the Father&amp;mdash;hallelujah!&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 09 Apr 2014 09:00:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2014-04-09:2014/the-spirit-and-christian-formation.html</guid><category>M. Div.</category><category>SEBTS</category></item><item><title>The Spirit and Conversion</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2014/the-spirit-and-conversion.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;The Holy Spirit is the member of the Triune Godhead who actively brings about
our conversion. It is the Spirit who regenerates a person, indwells him, and
seals him for the day of salvation. The spirit makes the gospel powerfully
effective for salvation so that those who hear it may believe and be saved. On
these points all are agreed, since they are backed by straightforward statements
in Scripture. The particulars, however, are a matter of some controversy, and so
bear further consideration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are two broad views of the Spirit&amp;rsquo;s work in regeneration. In the non-
Calvinist view (whether Arminian, Roman Catholic, or variations thereon in other
streams of Christian tradition), the Spirit does preparatory work in the hearts
of the unregenerate and provides God&amp;rsquo;s grace to enable people to choose whether
to respond to the gospel or not. However it is articulated (most commonly as
&amp;ldquo;prevenient grace&amp;rdquo; in Baptist circles), this view emphasizes that the Spirit&amp;rsquo;s
work is essential in making available the effects of Christ&amp;rsquo;s work on the cross
to whomever will believe. Without the Spirit&amp;rsquo;s work, regeneration through faith
is impossible, because no one will believe. With the Spirit&amp;rsquo;s work, men are
enabled to choose freely whether to follow God or no.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the Calvinist view, by contrast, the Spirit not only works in a preparatory
sense, but is also the active agent in bringing about conversion. People choose
as they will, and people dead in their trespasses always choose sin over
God&amp;mdash;this is the essence of our fallen nature. What is needed, in this view, is
not only the grace-given ability to choose (as in a prevenient grace view) but a
grace-changed heart so that we will freely choose God. No matter how free our
choice, unless the effects of original sin in us are undone, we continue freely
to choose sin and to reject God. The Spirit, then, takes away hearts of stone
and gives instead beating hearts of flesh that can respond to God. He gives eyes
to see the light he shines as well as the light itself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The essential disagreement between the two views is to whom the Spirit gives
such eyes: to all men who hear the gospel, or only to the elect. Based on Paul&amp;rsquo;s
arguments in 1 Corinthians, Ephesians, and elsewhere, I take it to be the
latter. If the Spirit opened everyone&amp;rsquo;s eyes to see truly the goodness of God,
if he gave to everyone hearts of flesh rather than hearts of stone all would
believe. Regeneration logically precedes (but temporally coincides with) faith:
the unregenerate heart cannot and does not believe. So the Spirit gives hearts
that can and do believe, and in that very moment, we believe. The Spirit gives
us not only the opportunity to exercise faith, but also the faith that we
exercise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However the act of regeneration is accomplished, the Spirit is efficaciously at
work. In both views, the gospel &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; powerful for salvation&amp;mdash;whether by tilling
the soil or by actually causing the seed to sprout. People hear the gospel and
the Spirit uses that mightily. Then, once people have believed, the Holy Spirit
continues to work. He immediately indwells the believer, giving our mortal
bodies spiritual vitality. Thus Paul says that the same Spirit who raised Christ
from the dead is now at work in all believers. This indwelling seals our
conversion, ensuring we hold fast until we die or Christ returns. He
increasingly shapes our behaviors and attitudes to be more in line with those of
God, making us holy as God is holy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In short, the Spirit is the one who makes Christ&amp;rsquo;s work effective for salvation.
He enables and empowers the gospel to produce conversion.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 03 Apr 2014 08:15:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2014-04-03:2014/the-spirit-and-conversion.html</guid><category>M. Div.</category><category>SEBTS</category></item><item><title>The Resurrection is Essential</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2014/the-resurrection-is-essential.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Paul tells us that if Jesus was not raised from the dead, then we are still dead
in our trespasses (1 Corinthians 15:17). This simple statement uncovers a great
deal about the necessity of Christ&amp;rsquo;s resurrection as well as his death on our
behalf, as does much of the rest of the New Testament&amp;rsquo;s view of the
resurrection. Paul tells us, for example, that Christ died for our trespasses
and was raised for our justification (Romans 4:25). Likewise, he notes Jesus&amp;rsquo;
resurrection from the dead is intrinsically linked to our own life (e.g. Romans
8:11). Moreover, we know that if Jesus was not raised from the dead, then
neither will we be (1 Corinthians 15:16). We know that it was in the
resurrection that Jesus was shown to be the Son of God in power (Romans 1:4) and
thus the one who reigns over all things. Moreover, we note that the preaching of
the apostles as recorded in Acts refers to the resurrection of Christ as the
evidence that he is indeed the Jewish messiah and the judge of the earth&amp;mdash;
indeed, from Acts we see that the apostolic message &lt;em&gt;centered&lt;/em&gt; on the
resurrection of Christ. Likewise, the very shape of the gospels is such that
each in its own way climaxes not with Jesus&amp;rsquo; death but with his resurrection, as
if to say that the central issue of our faith is not the death of Christ but his
being raised from the dead.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As we put together all these pieces, it becomes clear that the resurrection is
integral in our salvation. It is not merely the &amp;ldquo;seal&amp;rdquo; upon the work Jesus did
at the cross, the evidence that the cross accomplished what it needed to. It is
part and parcel of our salvation, in and of itself. It is true that the
resurrection does indeed ratify the elements of the saving work of Christ that
were accomplished on the cross, but this is not all that it does. It seems clear
from the evidence of the New Testament that the resurrection itself is
efficacious in saving us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If our mortal bodies are corrupted by sin, as we know they are, and if the
penalty of sin is death, as we know it is, then something more than payment for
sin must happen. Payment for sin is necessary, and so Jesus&amp;rsquo; substitutionary
atonement in death on the cross is essential to our salvation. However, there is
more that is essential to our salvation. Reconciliation between God and man
began in the Incarnation, as in Jesus the Son of God united humanity and deity
in perfect fellowship once again, and it was accomplished (though not yet
finished) in the resurrection as Jesus took up a restored body in which the
power of sin and death were finally broken: an image of what our bodies will be
in the age to come.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Likewise, we know that if we die as things were before the Resurrection, even
were our sins paid for, we remain mortal and would never rise again of our own
merits. In his resurrection, Jesus triumphed over death&amp;mdash;the last enemy&amp;mdash;and
we know that the same Spirit that raised him from the dead will raise us from
the dead. We know that Jesus&amp;rsquo; resurrection is the means of our justification. He
paid for our sins in his atoning death, but he sets us right with God in his
triumphant new life. We know that his reign as the rightful heir of all things
was inaugurated in his resurrection, not in his death.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In short, essential as was his death for our salvation, the resurrection of
Christ is no less important in our being restored to life with God.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 18 Mar 2014 08:00:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2014-03-18:2014/the-resurrection-is-essential.html</guid><category>M. Div.</category><category>SEBTS</category></item><item><title>The Servant of God</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2014/the-servant-of-god.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;The Servant pictured in Isaiah is one of the most famous images in the Old
Testament for Christians. The language applied to him in Isaiah 53 in particular
has long been understood by Christians to point directly to Jesus as the atoning
savior. The role of the Servant in the book is somewhat more complex than a
simple prediction of Jesus as subtitutionary atonement however: it encompasses
that idea, but does much more as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The label of Servant is applied to two (or possibly three) different roles in
Isaiah: the nation of Israel, and one who suffers and works on behalf of Israel.
This latter role certainly contains messianic overtures, but may also include
poetic references to Isaiah&amp;rsquo;s own suffering on behalf Israel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The theme of the Servant first appears in chapter 40, and is immediately and
directly applied in reference to Israel/Jacob. The same is true of its
appearance in chapters 41 and 43, though the language used of the servant in
chapter 42 suggests an individual and not the nation, and should perhaps be
taken as pointing to a king who represents the nation given the national
context. Beginning in chapter 45 and moving forward, the Servant increasingly
appears as the individual who acts for Israel on Yahweh&amp;rsquo;s behalf.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whether the Servant-Israel or the Servant-for-Israel (as we might label them),
the Servant exists to be God&amp;rsquo;s agent in bringing about the obedience of the
nations. The Servant-Israel experiences cleansing and purification to that end,
while the Servant-for-Israel experiences suffering in place of Israel, for her
sins and to save her from her unrighteous ways.&lt;sup id="fnref:1"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:1" rel="footnote"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; In both cases, the suffering
is part of God&amp;rsquo;s plan to lead the nations out of their idolatry to participate
in his covenant with Israel. The shape of the role taken by the Servant differs,
though, and as the book progresses the need for the Servant-for-Israel becomes
more and more clear, because the Servant-Israel is simply not up to the task (as
was made clear by the first 39 chapters of the book!).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thus, the Servant-for-Israel acts on behalf of Israel in the latter parts of
chapters 40&amp;ndash;55. He picks up kingly responsibilities of doing justice and
righteousness in the earth (a theme Isaiah seems to take up from the Psalms and
elaborate). He stands as Israel&amp;rsquo;s representative in dealing with her sin. He
brings the nations in to participate in Israel&amp;rsquo;s covenant life with God. In some
sense, the messianic king figure becomes True Israel on Israel&amp;rsquo;s behalf.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The transition between Servant-Israel and Servant-for-Israel not only picks up
messianic overtones, but also hints at autobiographical elements for Isaiah
himself. Lest Christian readers be skittish at this notion, wanting to preserve
the text&amp;rsquo;s unique way of pointing to Jesus: it is hardly uncommon for figures in
the Old Testament to prefigure the messiah in various ways. Here it is Jesus&amp;rsquo;
role as Prophet we see prefigured, just asthe entire Levitical system prefigured
him as Priest and David prefigured him as King. Isaiah&amp;rsquo;s suffering on behalf of
Israel is a clear parallel to Jesus&amp;rsquo; ministry, and Jesus himself makes this
clear in his teaching in the New Testament, where he emphasizes that he came in
part to close eyes and ears as well as open them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The result of the progression is that the reader moves from seeing Israel as
God&amp;rsquo;s servant to recognizing the need for a servant who will work as God&amp;rsquo;s agent
on Israel&amp;rsquo;s behalf, to seeing that even Isaiah was an incomplete picture of this
servant. The one of whom Isaiah prophesied would be not only Prophet but also
king and both priest and sacrifice on behalf of the people. He would not only
speak of the nations coming to participate in fellowship with God in the Zion of
Israel, he would bring it about himself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Notably, the redemption pictured in Isaiah goes beyond subtitution for
sins, and includes restoration to a holy nature&amp;mdash;a theme that is picked up
clearly in the New Testament but too often overlooked by modern readers.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 11 Mar 2014 15:45:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2014-03-11:2014/the-servant-of-god.html</guid><category>M. Div.</category><category>SEBTS</category></item><item><title>Wisdom and Folly</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2014/wisdom-and-folly.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;The book of Proverbs opens with a lengthy introduction to the topic of wisdom,
expounding its virtues and necessity and contrasting them with the costs of
folly, before moving into the proverbs for which it is named. After a short
introductory statement, the book moves into a series of extended metaphors for
wisdom and folly to illustrate the point. These metaphors are those of the two
women, the two houses, and the two ways&amp;mdash;with the choices between the two
illustrated in each case by the simple youth who may choose one or the other and
become either wise or a fool.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The two women of the book are the Ladies Wisdom and Folly. Throughout the first
nine chapters, the two stand in opposition to each other everywhere. Wisdom
calls out on the streets, by the gates, and in the highest point of the city.
She represents the first aspect of God&amp;rsquo;s order in the world, that foundational
principle on which the world is built. She is an attribute of the creation God
made and a reflection of his desires and character. By contrast, the adulteress
(or &amp;ldquo;foreign woman&amp;rdquo;) who leads astray a simple youth and destroys him in chapter
7 is a picture not only of the particular follies of adultery but a
personification of all that is foolish: wherever wisdom stands and calls out, so
too does the adulteress&amp;mdash;Lady Folly in one of her most deceptive forms. She is
an image of what it means to go against the grain of God&amp;rsquo;s created order, and
the consequence of going with her is death. No surprise, that: going against the
structure of God&amp;rsquo;s reality has &lt;em&gt;always&lt;/em&gt; led to death, beginning in Genesis 3.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The two ways and two houses pick up this same motif and trace it out further.
One way leads to life, the other to death. One house is steadfast and sure,
while the other crumbles. One belongs to Wisdom, the other to Folly. These
images Jesus picks up again in his own teaaching in the New Testament: The way
that leads to life is narrow, and few find it, but the way that leads to
destruction is wide and many walk it. The wise man builds his house on the rock
that is Jesus&amp;rsquo; word, but the foolish man builds his house on the sand that is
worldly wisdom. The naïve youth may answer Lady Wisdom&amp;rsquo;s invitation and follow
her along the way of wisdom to the house of wisdom and so become wise, or he may
answer Lady Folly&amp;rsquo;s call, walk down folly&amp;rsquo;s road to the house of destruction and
so become a fool.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The idea of the &amp;ldquo;wise person&amp;rdquo; and the &amp;ldquo;fool&amp;rdquo; then come up time and again
throughout the rest of the book. Whatever one decides has the enormous
consequences that the book traces out: fools become insolent, ignorant,
murderous rebels against God, while wise people become gracious, temperate,
gentle followers of God.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 11 Mar 2014 15:00:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2014-03-11:2014/wisdom-and-folly.html</guid><category>M. Div.</category><category>SEBTS</category></item><item><title>Job—The Mourner</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2014/job-the-mourner.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;The book of Job has most commonly been read as theodicy, i.e. as a defense of
God&amp;rsquo;s goodness in the face of human suffering and the existence of evil in the
world. This reading has a number of difficulties, not least in that though the
characters in the book raise this question, neither God in his appearance nor
the narrator offer an answer to it. Indeed, the final shape of the book is such
that the reader has some understanding of why &lt;em&gt;Job&lt;/em&gt; suffered as he did&amp;mdash;but
only some. God&amp;rsquo;s reasons for acting in the particular ways he did remain hidden,
and (more importantly) the answers we see in Job&amp;rsquo;s specific case are clearly not
applicable to every case of human suffering.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One possible way out of this problem is to approach the text from a different
angle. Supposing that Job was not written as a theodicy, but as an exploration
of an entirely different need, how might we read the book more profitably? One
suggestion is that the central issue in the text is how Job might move from a
position of ritual mourning back into a position of ritual life&amp;mdash;and this
approach does indeed yield significant exegetical fruit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All of Job&amp;rsquo;s troubles experienced in the first two chapters of the book
warranted his entering a state of ritual mourning: he experienced calamity in
the loss of his possessions, the death of his sons and daughters, and the onset
of a skin disease. The Levitical law proscribed the kinds of mourning an
Israelite would undergo under each of these circumstances, and none were
trivial. Though Job as a non-Israelite would not have lived under the Levitical
law, he &lt;em&gt;did&lt;/em&gt; live in a culture that embraced that pattern of ritual mourning in
response to these problems, and the Israelite audience would have recognized his
behavior as such. Thus, in Job 1&amp;ndash;2, we see Job respond to his great calamity by
tearing his clothes, going out of the town and sitting on the trash heap, and
scraping his skin with a shard of pottery. These were not merely expressions of
his grief (though, to be sure, he was grieved) but symbolic statements that he
had entered a state of ritual death in a period of mourning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Job now needed a way to move back to ritual life, the ordinary state of affairs.
Culturally, &amp;ldquo;comforters&amp;rdquo; were the means afforded him for this end, and this
explains the efforts of Eliphaz, Bildad, Zophar, and (eventually) Elihu. Each in
his way sought to help Job come to terms with his loss, become right with God,
and return to ordinary life. Since the three each embraced both the so-called
&amp;ldquo;retribution principle&amp;rdquo; and its corollary&amp;mdash;that God rewards the righteous and
punishes the wicked, and that accordingly prosperity and suffering are
indicators of righteousness and wickedness respectively&amp;mdash;they all tried to
convince Job that he ought to repent of his apparent sin.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Notably, however, none could persuade Job of any sin warranting such suffering
as he endured, and moreover the book agrees with Job: the narrative prologue
first chapters tells us that Job was &amp;ldquo;blameless and upright&amp;rdquo; and that &amp;ldquo;in all
this [his initial response to loss] he did not sin.&amp;rdquo; Job&amp;rsquo;s bitter response
midway through the book (&amp;ldquo;Miserable comforters are you all!&amp;rdquo;) makes perfect
sense in this context: they were not relieving him of his state of ritual death,
for their words offered no way forward. Thus, Job increasingly turns away from
answering his friends to pleading with God to appear and answer him, though as
Job acknowledges, no one can contend with God. Still: even against the largely
accurate answers Elihu provides in chapters 32&amp;ndash;36, Job was unmoved. He needed
something else.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When God appears, he does not answer Job&amp;rsquo;s questions, but neither does he accuse
him of sin. Rather, he shows Job his wisdom, and how greatly his wisdom exceeds
Job&amp;rsquo;s understanding. This, it seems, &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; what Job needed in order to move from
mourning back to life. He is able to say, &amp;ldquo;Before, I had heard of you, but now
my eyes have seen you,&amp;rdquo; and &lt;em&gt;this&lt;/em&gt; is what triggers his return to normal life at
the end of the book. Moreover, his statement of repentance in Job 42 makes a
great deal more sense this way: he now turned away (&amp;ldquo;repented&amp;rdquo; in the bare
sense) &lt;em&gt;from&lt;/em&gt; dust and ashes&amp;mdash;not repenting of some unnamed sin &lt;em&gt;in&lt;/em&gt; dust and
ashes. Indeed, this (the common reading) would hardly make sense, given that Job
immediately puts off his dust and ashes and returns to his life. Job was able to
move from ritual death to ritual life because he had encountered God. As a
result, Job did return to all the ordinary parts of life. Whereas the mourner
was forbidden from feasting, worshipping, and sexual activity, Job participates
in all three in the conclusion of the book. His friends and family come and eat
with him. He offers sacrifice for his friends. He fathers more children.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thus, taking Job in light of ancient near eastern mourning ritual helps us
understand the book&amp;rsquo;s message and structure far more clearly than taking it as a
theodicy. The text does not seek to answer why God allows evil. Indeed, it
inverts the question: who are we to think we could understand? In Job we have
instead a recognition that the only thing that will really satisfy the soul of
one experiencing the deep suffering that life brings is an encounter with the
living God. The only thing that could move Job from ritual death to ritual life
is the only thing that can move us from spiritual death to spiritual life&amp;mdash;not
mere academic knowledge of facts about God, but encountering him as one who may
be known.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 11 Mar 2014 14:30:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2014-03-11:2014/job-the-mourner.html</guid><category>M. Div.</category><category>SEBTS</category></item><item><title>What He Did Not Assume</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2014/what-he-did-not-assume.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;There have been many broken and flawed Christologies over the years, and in
truth many of them continue to crop up in mainstream evangelicalism. Nearly
every major heresy the church confronts (and no few of its littler skirmishes)
revolve around issues of the nature of the Incarnate Son of God. From the
earliest days of the church, there has been a tension between those emphasizing
Jesus&amp;rsquo; humanity at the cost of his deity and those emphasizing his deity at the
cost of his humanity. The clear testimony of Scripture, however, is that Jesus
was everything that it is to be God and also everything that it is to be human.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When we say, then, that in the Incarnation the Son of God &amp;lsquo;took his flesh from
Mary&amp;rsquo;, we are emphasizing that he inherited from her all that it means to be a
human being. Nothing was missing or absent. The Word who was from the
beginning, and through whom the Father created the world, and indeed for whom
the world exists, took upon himself human body and soul/mind/spirit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He participated fully in all the weaknesses of human existence. He became
subject to common colds and the need to expel waste from his body. He
experienced teething pains, and he needed to eat and sleep. He experienced real
temptation to sin, more fully than has any other human because he resisted it
to the last. He bore the sorrows of life in a world filled with suffering and
war and death. He was in everything the word means &lt;em&gt;human&lt;/em&gt;. As the author of
Hebrews puts it:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since therefore the children share in flesh and blood, he himself likewise
partook of the same things, that through death he might destroy the one who
has the power of death, that is, the devil, and deliver all those who through
fear of death were subject to lifelong slavery. For surely it is not angels
that he helps, but he helps the offspring of Abraham. Therefore he had to be
made like his brothers in every respect, so that he might become a merciful
and faithful high priest in the service of God, to make propitiation for the
sins of the people. For because he himself has suffered when tempted, he is
able to help those who are being tempted. (Hebrews 2:14&amp;ndash;18)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We share in flesh and blood; he shared in flesh and blood. He became like us in
every respect&amp;mdash;not partially, not in some respects, but in every respect. He
suffered when he was tempted; the lures and draws of the world did not simply
pass by him without any challenge whatsoever. He took from Mary &lt;em&gt;everything&lt;/em&gt;
about humanity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This matters because, as the Fathers pointed out, what he has not assumed has
not been redeemed. Redemption is more than (though of course not less than)
propitiation for sins. It is the re-uniting of humanity with God, so that all
the myriad ways in which human nature has been broken may be set once again how
it ought to be. It is the restoration of &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; the things that were broken in
humanity by the Fall. There is no part of humanity that was not broken by the
Fall, no part that does not need restoration, no part that was not cut off from
fellowship with God. Thus, there is no part of humanity that is not in need of
redemption, and so anything the Son did not take up of our humanity when he
became Jesus the Christ is still broken.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If Jesus had only the mind of God and not a human mind, then our minds are still
unredeemed. If Jesus&amp;rsquo; body was not the Son&amp;rsquo;s body but a drone-like extension of
his will, then our minds remain unredeemed. If Jesus&amp;rsquo; will was not a human will
but purely and only a divine will, then our wills remain unredeemed. In each
case, if Jesus was not both God and man in his nature, we are lost. In this
sense, then, few things are of more theological import than the nature of the
incarnation. The cross and resurrection, powerful though they are, do not have
their intended effect of redeeming lost women and men unless the Incarnation was
the complete joining of God and man in Jesus. And so: praise be to God! For when
Jesus took his flesh from Mary, he took up humanity whole and entire, leaving
nothing out, and joined it with his deity whole and entire, leaving nothing out.
So now we through him participated in the divine nature (2 Peter 1:4), just as
he participated in human nature.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 05 Mar 2014 15:30:00 -0500</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2014-03-05:2014/what-he-did-not-assume.html</guid><category>M. Div.</category><category>SEBTS</category></item><item><title>Adam's Sin and Our Death</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2014/adams-sin-and-our-death.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;How exactly human beings&amp;rsquo; guilt relates to Adam&amp;rsquo;s guilt is a question of no
small theological import, and it has unsurprisingly been the topic of much
theological discussion&amp;mdash;not to say debate&amp;mdash;over the past many hundreds of
years. The central passage is Romans 5:12&amp;ndash;14:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Therefore, just as sin came into the world through one man, and death through
sin, and so death spread to all men because all sinned&amp;mdash;for sin indeed was in
the world before the law was given, but sin is not counted where there is no
law. Yet death reigned from Adam to Moses, even over those whose sinning was
not like the transgression of Adam, who was a type of the one who was to come.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The basic historic, orthodox&lt;sup id="fnref:1"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:1" rel="footnote"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; views of this position may be summarized as
follows:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;All humans are guilty of Adam&amp;rsquo;s sin because they were in his loins when he
  sinned, and so have not only been contaminated with his sinful nature but also
  actively sinned when he sinned, and so are guilty and under judgment of death
  from their very conception&amp;mdash;a position most famously and forcefully
  articulated by Augustine.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;All humans are born guilty of Adam&amp;rsquo;s sin because he acted as the federal head
  of the human race and so we are imputed guilty in him, just as when we
  partipate in the humanity of the new federal head of humanity&amp;mdash;Jesus
  Christ&amp;mdash;his righteousness is imputed to us. In this view, humans are born
  subject to the punishment of sin (including death) because all of us are
  &lt;em&gt;counted&lt;/em&gt; guilty in Adam, just as we experience the blessings of holiness
  when in Christ because we are &lt;em&gt;counted&lt;/em&gt; righteous in him (the historic
  Reformed view).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;All humans are born innocent of Adam&amp;rsquo;s guilt, but by dint of descent from him
  have the same corrupted sinful nature he did, and therefore all &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt; sin and
  incur guilt before a holy God. Furthermore, as Adam&amp;rsquo;s descendants, all are
  born separated from God and therefore mortal. In this view, humans are born
  innocent of guilt but inevitably sin because of their fallen humanity and die
  because of their separation from God. This is the view articulated by the
  Baptist Faith and Message 2000.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most basic logic of the passage seems to run most closely in line with this
last articulation. Paul argues that &amp;ldquo;sin came into the world through one man,
and death through sin, and so death spread to all men because all sinned&amp;rdquo;. While
Augustine and the Reformers both took this latter phrase to mean &amp;ldquo;all sinned &lt;em&gt;in
Adam&lt;/em&gt;&amp;rdquo; it must be recognized that the idea that all sinned &amp;ldquo;in Adam&amp;rdquo; is foreign
to the text. Indeed, the sentence that follows immediately on the heels of this
first declaration suggest that it is individuals&amp;rsquo; sins committed in their own
lives, and not Adam&amp;rsquo;s sin, that is in view here. Otherwise, the distinction
between the sins that some committed before the law came and the sins that
others committed after the law came makes little sense. So likewise does the
distinction between Adam&amp;rsquo;s sin and that of those who followed him, even those
whose sin was not like his.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most significant textual challenge to this understanding comes in Paul&amp;rsquo;s
statement that &amp;ldquo;death spread to all men because all sinned&amp;rdquo;&amp;mdash;a statement that
is hard to reconcile with the notion of the lack of conscious sin in infants or
the mentally handicapped. Certainly many humans die in infancy, and indeed many
die &lt;em&gt;in utero&lt;/em&gt; long before the cognitive ability to make any choice whatsoever
has developed. Thus, there is at least some sense in which Paul&amp;rsquo;s argument
entails the death of human beings who have not yet come under condemnation for
their own sin because of Adam&amp;rsquo;s sin.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;None of the views outlined above resolve this tension perfectly. The Augustinian
view seems overly bound up in Augustine&amp;rsquo;s views on sexual intercourse as the
means of the transmission of sin to human nature. The federal headship view
places more emphasis on the idea of imputation than this passage seems to
support, but deals forthrightly with the issue of death in the lives of those
who have committed no sins. The idea that humans are born innocent of specific
guilt but subject to a sin nature that leads inevitably to sin seems to do
justice to the basic flow of Paul&amp;rsquo;s argument, but struggles with the
application of death to those who have not sinned.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Integrating the latter two options seems the best solution. People die because
Adam corrupted human nature, and all participate in his corrupted human
nature&amp;mdash;a nature separated from the fellowship with God essential to human
immortality&amp;mdash;unless united to a &lt;em&gt;different&lt;/em&gt; human nature. People are guilty
for their own sins, not for Adam&amp;rsquo;s, but they die because they share Adam&amp;rsquo;s
basic nature, which came out of his guilt. In due time, they themselves sin
they &lt;em&gt;earn&lt;/em&gt; the death in which they already shared by dint of their broken
humanity. Even this solution, it must be admitted, remains somewhat messier
than we might like, but it is to be preferred as best dealing with all the
evidence before us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I leave aside non-orthodox positions such as the Pelagian view that people
are born able to live perfectly righteous lives, with uncorrupted natures, which
runs against the clear teaching of Scripture that all sin and moreover that all
&lt;em&gt;inevitably&lt;/em&gt; sin because of the fallenness of our humanity.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 05 Mar 2014 15:00:00 -0500</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2014-03-05:2014/adams-sin-and-our-death.html</guid><category>M. Div.</category><category>SEBTS</category></item><item><title>The Name of Sin</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2014/the-name-of-sin.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Sin is described in various ways in the Old and New Testaments, and these various
descriptions and names tell us much about how the authors of the Bible
conceived of the power than enslaves us apart from Christ.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Old Testament has several terms its authors often use to describe the broad
concept of sin:&lt;sup id="fnref:1"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:1" rel="footnote"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;lsquo;avah&lt;/em&gt;, meaning &amp;ldquo;bent&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;crooked&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;lsquo;aval&lt;/em&gt;, which includes the idea of a lack of integrity, so is often
  given as &amp;ldquo;iniquity&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;lsquo;avar&lt;/em&gt;, meaning &amp;ldquo;to cross over&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;transgress&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;ra&amp;lsquo;&lt;/em&gt;, meaning &amp;ldquo;the rule of evil&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;ma&amp;lsquo;al&lt;/em&gt;, meaning &amp;ldquo;breach of trust&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;pasha&amp;lsquo;&lt;/em&gt;, meaning &amp;ldquo;to revolt&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;refuse subjection to a rightful
  authority&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From these we see that humanity&amp;rsquo;s brokenness before God in the Old Testament was
often conceived of in terms of doing things the wrong way, or in rejection of
the rightful authority, or a mix of the two. Rebellion against the creator and
his created order are essential ingredients of the concept of sin for the Old
Testament authors. To do evil is to be in rebellion against the right way God
established for things to be done, to reject his &lt;em&gt;shalom&lt;/em&gt; and replace it with
destruction and disharmony.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most common term for sin in the Old Testament, however, and the one usually
translated into the English &amp;ldquo;sin&amp;rdquo; is &lt;em&gt;chatha&lt;/em&gt;, meaning &amp;ldquo;to miss the mark&amp;rdquo;.
Sinning was thus not necessarily always a matter of active, willful rejection
of God. It was also simply failing, by dint of corrupted human nature, to do as
God called humanity to do, in any and all spheres of life. Sin was thus a
pervasive and corrupting influence on &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; of human existence, not only on
those who were consciously rebelling against God.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unsurprisingly, the New Testament picks up on many of these same ideas. Though
the specific terms used have different semantic ranges than those in the Old
Testament, as a group they cover much of the same territory:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;parabasis&lt;/em&gt;, &amp;ldquo;the transgression of a boundary&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;parakoe&lt;/em&gt;, &amp;ldquo;disobedience to a voice&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;paraptoma&lt;/em&gt;, &amp;ldquo;falling where one should have stood upright&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;agnoema&lt;/em&gt;, &amp;ldquo;failing to know what one should have known&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;hettema&lt;/em&gt;, &amp;ldquo;diminishing what should have been fully rendered&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;anomia&lt;/em&gt;, failing to observe a law&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;plemmeleia&lt;/em&gt;, &amp;ldquo;a discord in the harmonies of God&amp;rsquo;s universe&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To the Old Testament range, they add this final notion of discord in the created
order&amp;mdash;a concept that was present in the Old Testament, to be sure, in the
notion of lost &lt;em&gt;shalom&lt;/em&gt;, but which was not so directly expressed. Again, as in
the Old Testament, these emphasize both failure to do and active rejection of
what is right. And, as in the Old Testament, the New Testament authors&amp;rsquo; concept
of sin is most commonly expressed in a single word meaning &amp;ldquo;missing the mark&amp;rdquo;:&lt;em&gt;hamartia&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This congruence between the Old and New Testament views of sin emphasizes the
fundamental unity between the various authors&amp;rsquo; understanding of the issues at
stake. Sin is everything about humanity&amp;rsquo;s failure to follow God&amp;rsquo;s ways and live
in accord with his design for the universe. It encompasses the whole range of
human foibles, from  accidental failure and ignorance to the kind of rebellion
that shakes its fist at the heavens or boldly (and foolishly) proclaims that
there is no God. Sin is getting it wrong&amp;mdash;or, to put it another way that
better captures the breadth of Scriptural language on the issue, not getting it&lt;em&gt;perfectly&lt;/em&gt; right, for whatever reason.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;List drawn from Stanley Grenz, &lt;em&gt;Theology for the Community of God&lt;/em&gt;.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 05 Mar 2014 14:30:00 -0500</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2014-03-05:2014/the-name-of-sin.html</guid><category>M. Div.</category><category>SEBTS</category></item><item><title>In the Day That You Eat of It</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2014/in-the-day-that-you-eat-of-it.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;When God placed Adam in the Garden of Eden, he told him he could eat freely of
any fruit in the garden except one: the tree of the knowledge of good and evil.
If he ate from that tree, however, he would die the very day he ate of it
(Genesis 2:17). When, in Genesis 3, Adam and Eve ate the fruit of the tree of
the knowledge of good and evil, however, they did &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; die&amp;mdash;at least, not
physically. Indeed, Adam lived to be over nine hundred years old.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What, then, did God mean when he told Adam that he would sure die the very day
he ate of the tree? Did he lie, or make a mistake, or change his mind after the
fact? Plainly put, no: none of these are true. Rather, all of them mistake the
nature of the death entailed in God&amp;rsquo;s word to Adam. The death Adam immediately
experienced was not physical death but spiritual death. Physical death was a
consequence&amp;mdash;a symptom, as it were&amp;mdash;of his spiritual death.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This spiritual death was multifold, and we see the various elements of it traced
out in the explanation of the fall given in Genesis 3. First of all came
separation from God. Rather than being in right relationship with the creator,
Adam now needed restoration. Whereas he had enjoyed fellowship and relationship
with his maker, now Adam experienced fear at the thought of encountering him,
so that he hid himself when God came walking in the garden in the cool of the
day. The rest of the Old Testament traces this theme out in great detail; it is
constantly asking the question, &amp;ldquo;How may these unrighteous people come before a
holy God?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Second, God removed Adam from the means of grace he had supplied to sustain his
mortal body. He had provided a tree of life from which Adam could eat so that
his body would go on living without fail. After the fall, Adam was removed from
this supply, and so his body began to fall apart. He began to experience the
first phase of physical death: aging and decay. He no longer had access to the
supernatural sustenance he required not to die.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Third, he immediately experienced relational brokenness. The previously holy
and mutually delightful relationship he had experienced with his wife would now
be characterized by mutual blame and recriminations. Likewise, his sons would
not be loving brothers: one would kill the other. No more would he live in a
world characterized by peace and harmony, but one shaped by conflict and war.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of all of these, though, it was the first that was most important and deepest.
Adam&amp;rsquo;s separation from God was at the root of all the other problems he now
faced. It was the lack of God&amp;rsquo;s spirit in him that led to his physical death.
It was the lack of God&amp;rsquo;s presence in their midst, and the brokenness of his
image in them, that led men and women to be in conflict rather than mutually
supporting one another. With this separation came a warp in the character of
humanity that comprised the final part of Adam&amp;rsquo;s immediate death: no more would
his will be ready to obey God. Instead, he (and all his descendants) would be quick
to turn aside to go against the grain of God&amp;rsquo;s universe. Given the opportunity,
all would sin, and no one would turn away from sin without God&amp;rsquo;s intervention.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thus, Adam &lt;em&gt;did&lt;/em&gt; experience death the very day, indeed the very moment, that he
ate of the tree of the knowledge of good and evil. The death was more profound
and more horrifying than physical death alone would have been, though, because
it was a death that stretched to every point of his life, from his family and
the tasks with which God had entrusted him, to his very connection with God.
Everything became broken in him, and he no longer knew God. In gaining the
knowledge of good and evil, he lost the knowledge of the one of whom knowledge
matters most.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 05 Mar 2014 14:00:00 -0500</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2014-03-05:2014/in-the-day-that-you-eat-of-it.html</guid><category>M. Div.</category><category>SEBTS</category></item><item><title>Sufficiency and Efficacy</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2014/sufficiency-and-efficacy.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;The extent of the atonement is one of the most debated topics in the history of
the church for centuries. Whether Jesus Christ&amp;rsquo;s death provided substition for
the sins of all people or just some has been the cause of many dissensions and
denominational splits in the Protestant world ever since the Reformation. Most
famously, Arminius and his followers were expelled from the Calvinistic churches
over this very issue and the way they worked out their stance in other areas of
doctrine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the most part, though, what is at issue is not whether Jesus&amp;rsquo; death was of
sufficient merit to save all people. Jesus the incarnate Son of God provided a
sacrifice of infinite worth, undoubtedly of sufficient worth to cover all the
sins of all mankind in all of history. Rather, the question is to whom the
atonement is applied and how&amp;mdash;or, to put it differently, to whom its benefits
are available. Thus, the phrases of &amp;ldquo;limited atonement&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;unlimited
atonement&amp;rdquo; are best understood as referring to the availability and effect of
the atonement, &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; to its value.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Second, it must be recognized that all orthodox Christians affirm that the
effects of the atonement are limited in at least one important sense: not all
people are redeemed, and therefore not all people benefit from the atonement of
Christ. To put it as many have before, all orthodox believers affirm that the
atonement was &amp;ldquo;sufficient for all, but efficient for some,&amp;rdquo; for if it was
&amp;ldquo;efficient&amp;rdquo; for all, then all would be saved. (To affirm any lesser effect is to
diminish the atonement. This is not to say that there may not be other, broader
effects of Christ&amp;rsquo;s death on the cross&amp;mdash;e.g. the notion of prevenient grace
enabling all to respond to the preached word&amp;mdash;only that the atonement itself is
not applied universally.) The question then is only who those &amp;ldquo;some&amp;rdquo; are and the
terms under which the atonement is available to them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The simplest answer is simply to say, &amp;ldquo;the elect!&amp;rdquo; and have done, leaving aside
the tendentious question of who is elect&amp;mdash;but this question is precisely where
the rubber meets the road on the issue of the atonement. After all, everyone
agrees that the only the sins of those who believe are actually removed in
Christ, regardless of how election works out. Thus, when people speak of
&amp;ldquo;limited&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;unlimited&amp;rdquo; atonement, they are usually speaking of the issue of
general or specific election. Does the work of Christ mean that all are equally
able to hear and respond to the gospel, or does it mean that only the elect are
enabled to hear and respond?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think the most faithful articulation of the matter is to speak of the
atonement in three ways. First, we affirm that Jesus&amp;rsquo; death was sufficient to
atone for the sins of the world&amp;mdash;&lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; the world. Second, we offer the
atonement freely to everyone. Although the only the elect will be saved (however
we understand that to play out), the Scriptures clearly enjoin us to proclaim
Christ&amp;rsquo;s subtitutionary death and justifying resurrection to sinners everywhere
and to urge everyone to repent and trust in him. Third, we affirm that the
saving work of the atonement is applied to the sins of those who confess Christ
as Savior and Lord and obey him. We need not perfectly understand or agree upon
the means by which people come to confess Christ as Lord to affirm that it is
only in that affirmation and obedience that one&amp;rsquo;s sins are covered in the
atonement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is thus most appropriate to speak of Jesus&amp;rsquo; atonement as unlimited in extent
but limited in effect.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 25 Feb 2014 08:30:00 -0500</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2014-02-25:2014/sufficiency-and-efficacy.html</guid><category>M. Div.</category><category>SEBTS</category></item><item><title>Like His Brothers in Every Way</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2014/like-his-brothers-in-every-way.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Whether Jesus could have sinned or not is a question to tangle the mind. On the
one hand, we affirm that he was fully human, and this affirmation binds us to
affirm that he could indeed sin: all humans are capable of sinning, and apart
from Jesus, all humans &lt;em&gt;have&lt;/em&gt; sinned. The author of Hebrews reminds us
forcefully that Jesus was made like his brothers&amp;mdash;which is to say, &lt;em&gt;us&lt;/em&gt;&amp;mdash;in
every respect, being tempted like them, yet without sin. On the other hand, we
recognize that the Godhead is sinless and that, as James reminds us, he neither
tempts nor can be tempted with evil. As with many issues relating to the
Incarnation, we face the challenge of holding together both Jesus&amp;rsquo; full deity
and his full humanity. When either is lost (or even simply diminished) in order
to emphasize or preserve the other, important aspects of our faith break in
serious ways.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Difficult (mysterious even) the question may be, but the author of Hebrews
leaves little doubt. Jesus was tempted like us in &lt;em&gt;every&lt;/em&gt; way&amp;mdash;not only in some
ways, but in every way. This is an essential affirmation for the Christian
faith. If Jesus could not sin, then he was not fully human, and his perfect life
is unsurprising and not particularly meaningful. If he &lt;em&gt;could&lt;/em&gt; sin, then his
perfect life is extraordinary and especially meaningful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the same time, we must integrate the things that Hebrews and James (and the
rest of the Scriptures) teach us. If the Godhead cannot be tempted by sin and
Jesus &lt;em&gt;was&lt;/em&gt; tempted by sin, does this make Jesus somehow &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; God? No, for this
misses the rest of the witness of the New Testament, including those selfsame
books. James himself calls Jesus Lord in terms that, set against a Jewish
background, can only be understood to refer to God himself (see especially James
5:11, perhaps the most direct quote of Exodus 34:6 in the whole New Testament
and an unmistakable reference to Yahweh God). Neither can we admit the notion
that James and Hebrews disagree with each other&amp;mdash;at least, not and maintain our
affirmation of the unity of Scripture, which is a non-negotiable from where I
stand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As with many things in the Trinity and the Incarnation, then, we are left making
a dual (and apparently conflicting affirmation). Jesus&amp;rsquo; humanity was perfectly
capable of sinning, and his divinity was incapable of sinning. The Incarnation
holds the two together in a single person, and so we affirm that Jesus could
have sinned, but did not. We note, too, that he did not precisely because he did
as all humans are called to do (and what glorified humans &lt;em&gt;will&lt;/em&gt; do) and
perfectly trusted the Father by obeying the Holy Spirit. Jesus&amp;rsquo; perfect life was
not the domination of his humanity by his divinity, but the submission of his
humanity to the divinity of the Trinity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thus we affirm that Jesus&amp;rsquo; not sinning on our behalf was a real moral victory,
not a hollow thing we can only look at bemusedly from afar. He lived as a real
second Adam, doing what the first Adam failed to do while beset by many more and
far greater temptations than the first Adam. He really did overcome the world&amp;mdash;
not only its powers, but its temptations. He really did demonstrate true and
perfect holiness that we might follow his example. He really did triumph over
every power of sin, that we might be transformed into his likeness. Though the
triune God is never tempted to sin, the triune God mysteriously partook of
everything it is to be human in the Incarnation, and that humanity &lt;em&gt;could&lt;/em&gt; be
tempted&amp;mdash;and he overcame.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 11 Feb 2014 08:30:00 -0500</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2014-02-11:2014/like-his-brothers-in-every-way.html</guid><category>M. Div.</category><category>SEBTS</category></item><item><title>The Mother of God</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2014/the-mother-of-god.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Is it right to call Mary the Mother of God? The historic, orthodox answer is a
resounding &amp;ldquo;yes&amp;rdquo;&amp;mdash;though a clearly qualified and well articulated &amp;ldquo;yes.&amp;rdquo; This
is not just the historic, orthodox position; it is the &lt;em&gt;right&lt;/em&gt; position. Mary
was indeed the &amp;ldquo;mother of God&amp;rdquo;. She was the mother of Jesus. Jesus was (and is)
fully God &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; fully man, completely and truly, both at once without loss of
the full measure of either. He did not cease being totally divine upon his
incarnation, but he did assume full humanity. The argument is as simple as it
first seems: Mary is the mother of Jesus, and Jesus is God, therefore Mary is
the mother of God.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Evangelicals tend to shy away from following the broader tradition and affirming
that Mary is the mother of God. There are many reasons for this, not least our
general discomfort with things having to do with Mary born of the over-
referencing of Mary in the Catholic tradition and the actual Mariolatry that is
too often evinced in Catholic lay practice throughout the world. However, our
response ought not be to reject this view, but to speak carefully and clearly
and reject what is mistaken while keeping what is true.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is true that we must be nuanced in our handling of this issue. The word
&amp;ldquo;mother&amp;rdquo; brings with it implications that we must avoid, and we must remember
Jesus&amp;rsquo; statements on what it meant to be his mother and brothers and sisters in
the gospels (i.e. that those who followed him were those really deserving of the
titles). However, simply to set aside the title is to lose important aspects of
the reality of the incarnation. If we say that Mary was &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; the mother of God,
we are really saying either that she was not truly the mother of Jesus, or that
Jesus was not fully God. Neither of these is a tolerable option.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, to those qualifications. When we say that Mary is the mother of God, we are
not saying that God in any sense has his source in her. All of the humanity of
Jesus finds its source equally in Mary and in the Spirit&amp;rsquo;s divine intervention
&amp;mdash;but Mary was created by the Son, rather than the Son originating in her. Mary
is the mother of God in Christ, but she is not to the Son exactly as ordinary
mothers are to ordinary sons, for Jesus was not an ordinary son.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nor do we mean that Mary has special prerogatives because of her relationship to
Jesus. As noted above, Jesus made clear that he was concerned above all with
obedience to the will of God (see e.g. Matthew 12:46&amp;ndash;50). Thus, the devotions
offered to Mary by our Catholic and Eastern Orthodox brothers and sisters is
misplaced, as is the notion that her prayers are somehow more effective in
touching Jesus&amp;rsquo; heart than are those of the ordinary saint who is seeking to
honor God.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These qualifications notwithstanding, we must still be willing and ready to
affirm that Mary was in fact the Mother of God. To do otherwise is to reduce in
one way or another the mystery of the incarnation. It is not so much that &lt;em&gt;Mary&lt;/em&gt;
is important here as that affirming her motherhood of God helps us affirm the
important points to which we must hold fast in terms the full deity and full
humanity of &lt;em&gt;Christ&lt;/em&gt;. Mary is important because Jesus humanity came by means of
Mary&amp;rsquo;s body. Everything that it is to be man, Jesus always was from conception,
and everything that it is to be God, Jesus always was from the moment of his
conception.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 04 Feb 2014 08:30:00 -0500</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2014-02-04:2014/the-mother-of-god.html</guid><category>M. Div.</category><category>SEBTS</category></item><item><title>Infant Guilt—Purest Speculation</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2014/infant-guilt-purest-speculation.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Whether people are born guilty of sin, or simply inherit a nature so predisposed
to sin that the actual act is inevitable has been a much debated topic for
generations. In my view, however, the question is impossible to answer. I do not
think Scripture speaks with sufficient clarity on the matter. We know on the one
hand that all are &amp;ldquo;by nature children of wrath&amp;rdquo; (Ephesians 2:3), and that &amp;ldquo;all
have sinned and fall short of the glory of God&amp;rdquo; (Romans 3:23). What neither of
these texts tell us, though, and what indeed &lt;em&gt;no&lt;/em&gt; text tells us, is whether
people are guilty at birth or whether they are simply sinful and become guilty.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We could reason to a conclusion that accords with our other theological
commitments with little difficulty. We know that God is just, and punishes for
the wrongs we commit, but we have no evidence that he punishes wrongs we &lt;em&gt;might&lt;/em&gt;
commit, and therefore we might conclude that he would therefore not find guilty
any newly conceived or newly born person. On the other hand, we also must reckon
with the reality that the Scriptures treat questions of progeny far differently
than do individually-minded modern Westerners.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Scripture points us to the God who &amp;ldquo;will by no means clear the guilty, visiting
the iniquity of the fathers on the children and the children&amp;rsquo;s children, to the
third and the fourth generation&amp;rdquo; (Exodus 34:7) as well as the God who proclaims
that &amp;ldquo;The soul who sins shall die. The son shall not suffer for the iniquity of
the father, nor the father suffer for the iniquity of the son&amp;rdquo; (Ezekiel 18:20).
Paul did write that &amp;ldquo;one trespass led to condemnation for all men,&amp;rdquo; but he
immediately follows up this provocative statement by arguing that &amp;ldquo;one act of
righteousness leads to justification and life for all men&amp;rdquo; (Romans 5:18)&amp;mdash;yet
we know that Paul does not (and cannot) here mean that all men are saved, for we
know that he believes that those who do not repent and believe the gospel perish
in their sins under the expectation of judgment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We cannot from the evidence that God has given us decide this question. We are
left without an answer. If we grant the sufficiency of Scripture, then we must
recognize that if there are questions God has in his wisdom opted not to answer,
it is for a reason, and we should cease with our speculations and be silent. We
may not know whether infants are &lt;em&gt;guilty&lt;/em&gt;, but we do know two other things that
are far more important than that: First, God is merciful and gracious and just.
We will not in the final reckoning find his justice lacking or his treatment of
(for example) those who died in infancy to be lacking. Second, all are born
under the dual curse of sin&amp;rsquo;s hold and death&amp;rsquo;s certainty.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These truths give us clear and straightforward points of application. First, we
must preach the gospel clearly to people of every age and intellectual ability,
for even little children sin and death is awaiting us all. Whether or not we are
born guilty, we &lt;em&gt;become&lt;/em&gt; guilty very quickly. Second, much of the speculation on
this question&amp;mdash;and many churches practices such as infant baptism&amp;mdash;seems to be
rooted in worry about the fate of those who die young, without having made a
credible profession of faith. Yet even if we &lt;em&gt;did&lt;/em&gt; know the answer to the
question of their guilt, we still might not know God&amp;rsquo;s response. Even did we
know the answer, still we would need learn to trust in the goodness and wisdom
of God in this matter.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 01 Feb 2014 08:30:00 -0500</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2014-02-01:2014/infant-guilt-purest-speculation.html</guid><category>M. Div.</category><category>SEBTS</category></item><item><title>What Was Their Sin?</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2014/what-was-their-sin.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;As Christians, we all recognize that Adam and Eve&amp;rsquo;s first sin in the garden of
Eden prompted the catastropic Fall of all humanity, and that their eating of the
fruit of the tree of the knowledge of good and evil was the &lt;em&gt;act&lt;/em&gt; of sin that
produced such horrific results in human history. What is perhaps less clear is
why that particular act was sinful. Was it disobedience? gaining knowledge?
pride? idolatry? The most straightforward reading of Genesis 3 makes it clear
that the act was sinful at the most basic level because it was disobedience, a
direct rejection of the stated will of God. God tells Adam that the consequences
he receives are because he ate of the tree from which he was commanded not to
eat (3:17).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perhaps the more interesting question, then, is why disobedience to God is a
sin. As Christians, we acknowledge that the Bible teaches us this truth. Digging
deeper is helpful in understanding many things about God and the nature of both
humanity and the shape of the world we inhabit. To describe why disobedience is
sinful, though, requires that we first define what sin &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt;. Sin is, at the most
basic level, failure&amp;mdash;missing the mark, as the Greek word would have it. The
next question, then, is: &lt;em&gt;Failure at what?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sin is failure to be what humans were (and still are) meant to be&amp;mdash;a mystery of
ages, to which we have the answer. Genesis tells us exactly who we humans are.
We are made in the image of God. We are to be small icons of divine glory. The
divinity we are meant to recapitulate in miniature exists in perfect harmony, is
completely wise and wholly good, and exercises utter sovereignty. Women and men
are meant likewise to exist in true harmony, to be wise in right measure and
truly good, and to exercise sovereignty in our appointed spheres. This is what
it &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; to be human: to do as God does in the ways he appoints in the world he
made.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thus, to &lt;em&gt;fail&lt;/em&gt; at that task is no small thing. It is to fail in the most
significant way possible. Worse still, to fail as Adam and Eve did (and as we
all have ever since) can only happen in a conscious act. Yes, our natures are
now so corrupted that we all sin incidentally, too. But we all of us sin on
purpose. Our first father and mother did not fail accidentally. They willfully
rejected the very reason for their existence and spat in the face of the author
of that existence. (Here is the source of the human struggle for existential
meaning and the dread of meaningless that plagues us.) They rejected both the
shape of reality and the one who made reality. They rebelled. They became
traitors against the universe&amp;rsquo;s God.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Their sin, then, was not only disobedience. There are times when disobedience
might be right: one &lt;em&gt;should&lt;/em&gt; reject unjust commands. This, however, was not such
a command. Their act of disobedience included both mistrust of most trustworthy
God and self-exaltation over and against the only exalted God. God does not only
demand our allegiance, he &lt;em&gt;deserves&lt;/em&gt; it. He requires our worship not because he
is vain, but because to worship anything else, however lovely, is to do injury
to the object of that worship, to ourselves, and to the Triune Godhead. Adam and
Eve&amp;rsquo;s eating of the fruit of the tree of the knowledge of good represented
precisely that offense. They rejected God&amp;rsquo;s sovereignty, his wisdom and
goodness, and even fellowship with him. They rejected their own sphere of
sovereignty, chose quick knowledge over wisdom, deceit over goodness, and
treachery over communion.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 25 Jan 2014 08:00:00 -0500</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2014-01-25:2014/what-was-their-sin.html</guid><category>M. Div.</category><category>SEBTS</category></item></channel></rss>