<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Chris Krycho - sermons</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/</link><description></description><lastBuildDate>Tue, 12 Apr 2016 19:15:00 -0400</lastBuildDate><item><title>God is With Us</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2016/god-is-with-us.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;i class="editorial"&gt;The only constraints on this sermon were that it be between 15 and 25 minutes long, and be on a text from the Old Testament. Audio is recorded with &lt;a href="https://geo.itunes.apple.com/us/app/ferrite-recording-studio/id1018780185?mt=8&amp;amp;at=1001l4KM"&gt;Ferrite&lt;/a&gt;, using an &lt;a href="http://www.apple.com/iphone-se/"&gt;iPhone SE&lt;/a&gt; placed on the podium.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section id="audio" class="level3"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Audio&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.podtrac.com/pts/redirect.m4a/cdn.chriskrycho.com/sermons/2016-03-08.m4a"&gt;Download&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;audio title="God Is With US" controls="controls" preload="metadata" src="http://www.podtrac.com/pts/redirect.m4a/cdn.chriskrycho.com/sermons/2016-04-12.m4a" type="audio/m4a"&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;Sorry; your browser doesn&amp;#39;t support m4a files. Try downloading the file
directly and playing it in iTunes or another media app.&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/audio&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="video" class="level3"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Video&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="iframe-wrapper four-to-three"&gt;
&lt;iframe src="https://player.vimeo.com/video/162628625" frameborder="0" webkitallowfullscreen mozallowfullscreen allowfullscreen&gt;
&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href="https://vimeo.com/162628625"&gt;God Is With Us (John 14:15–31)&lt;/a&gt; from &lt;a href="https://vimeo.com/chriskrycho"&gt;Chris Krycho&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;a href="https://vimeo.com"&gt;Vimeo&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="god-is-with-us" class="level1"&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;God Is With Us&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;section id="introduction" class="level2"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was recently reading a long article on President Obama’s foreign policy, and something caught my attention as I was reading through the article. There’s a great scene where they’re sitting on a plane in another country, and people are waiting for the President to get off the plane, and the reporter tries to prod him that it might be time to leave, and the President just keeps talking. And what struck me was that &lt;em&gt;relationship&lt;/em&gt;, where he could prod the President that &lt;em&gt;maybe it’s time to leave.&lt;/em&gt; You don’t get that kind of relationship by standing up in the middle of a White House press conference and demanding up-close and personal access. You get it because the President initiates it and invites you to have it with him.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There’s a fairly obvious analogy to our friendship with God here, and you may well have heard it before. But it rings true. And more than true, in this case: it’s as if the President came and said, “Hey, I’m going to make you a room in the White House. But in the meantime, I’m going to come live with &lt;em&gt;you&lt;/em&gt; and share everything I have with you.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As we read through the passage, look for two things, our two themes for this evening:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol type="1"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We love and obey God&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;God dwells with us&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Again: &lt;em&gt;we love and obey God&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;God dwells with us&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="body" class="level2"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Body&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Read with me, starting in verse 15, and on down through verse 31:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you love me, you will keep my commandments. And I will ask the Father, and he will give you another Helper, to be with you forever, even the Spirit of truth, whom the world cannot receive, because it neither sees him nor knows him. You know him, for he dwells with you and will be in you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I will not leave you as orphans; I will come to you. Yet a little while and the world will see me no more, but you will see me. Because I live, you also will live. In that day you will know that I am in my Father, and you in me, and I in you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whoever has my commandments and keeps them, he it is who loves me. And he who loves me will be loved by my Father, and I will love him and manifest myself to him.&amp;quot; Judas (not Iscariot) said to him, “Lord, how is it that you will manifest yourself to us, and not to the world?” Jesus answered him, “If anyone loves me, he will keep my word, and my Father will love him, and we will come to him and make our home with him. Whoever does not love me does not keep my words. And the word that you hear is not mine but the Father’s who sent me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“These things I have spoken to you while I am still with you. But the Helper, the Holy Spirit, whom the Father will send in my name, he will teach you all things and bring to your remembrance all that I have said to you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Peace I leave with you; my peace I give to you. Not as the world gives do I give to you. Let not your hearts be troubled, neither let them be afraid. You heard me say to you, ‘I am going away, and I will come to you.’ If you loved me, you would have rejoiced, because I am going to the Father, for the Father is greater than I. And now I have told you before it takes place, so that when it does take place you may believe. I will no longer talk much with you, for the ruler of this world is coming. He has no claim on me, but I do as the Father has commanded me, so that the world may know that I love the Father. Rise, let us go from here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;section id="i.-we-love-and-obey-god" class="level3"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;I. We love and obey God&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Throughout this passage, we see those two themes: we love and obey God, and he dwells with us. And they always seem to come in that order.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Look at verse 15:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you love me, you will keep my commandments. And I will ask the Father…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Or verse 21:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whoever has my commandments and keeps them, he it is who loves me. And he who loves me will be loved by the Father…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Or verse 23:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If anyone loves me, he will keep my word, and my Father will love him, and we will come to him, and make our home with him.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And by the same token:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whoever does not love me does not keep my words.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, our obedience doesn’t &lt;em&gt;bring about&lt;/em&gt; the Spirit filling us. Our obedience isn’t why God dwells with us. In fact, it’s Jesus’ obedience to the Father, going to die at the hands of the ruler of this world, down there in verse 30, and his resurrection, which we see in verses 18–20, which make fellowship with God possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But clearly, our obedience matters. It’s constantly tied to God’s dwelling with us in this passage. Jesus opens with it because he was talking with people who &lt;em&gt;did&lt;/em&gt; love him. This is &lt;em&gt;comfort&lt;/em&gt; in the midst of what is about to be a very difficult trial. When they might feel left alone like orphans, and needed to known they were his, and he would come back to them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So why obedience? Because it is a sign of love. We see that at the end of the passage, in Jesus’ love for the Father and his obedience flowing out of that. And we can see it in our own lives, too. If my daughters are dishonoring their mom by disobeying her, there is something wrong with their love for her. Sometimes when we are talking to or disciplining our three-year-old, we tell her, “Hey, your loves have gotten out of order.” She is loving good things, but in the wrong proportions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And we all do that. When we &lt;em&gt;don’t&lt;/em&gt; obey God, when we don’t keep his commandments, it is precisely because we our loves are disordered or mis-ordered. We love things in the wrong way, or we have love them with the wrong priority. Above all, we love other things more than our Father. Not like Jesus.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What does it look like when we &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt; love God?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol type="1"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For one, &lt;em&gt;knowing&lt;/em&gt; his words. You can’t keep them if you don’t know them!
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Read the Bible&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Talk about what Jesus said with friends and family, just as part of the ordinary course of your day.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Memorize Scripture, so it’s there in your mind as you go through life.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Practice daily obedience to his words—not just the flashy, exciting kind, but the ordinary ways we seek holiness.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Be kind to your neighbors.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Go to church.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Love your in-laws well.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tell others the good news of all that Jesus has done and will do.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Help your kids with their homework even when you’d rather be reading, and don’t be grumpy at them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Deal with your children graciously, kindly, and patiently, even when disciplining them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Give generously to support the church and missions work.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Give generously to those who are in need, period—to whomever asks.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Forgive others when they do you wrong.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tell others of this great hope and joy!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Live in community with other believers: be open to correction, and to encouragement—and give the same!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Repent of your sins, both privately and publicly.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Serve where there are needs.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Turn the other cheek and bless those who curse you.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do your work whole-heartedly, for the sake of the God who dwells in you, and not for man!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Be honest and truthful in your financial and professional dealings&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And remember, that’s not a list of ways to get into God’s good graces. It’s a list of ways we respond because we are are already in God’s good graces. Those are things we do because we are confident we are loved. We show him our love by our joyful obedience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But in truth, we find that hard. We need help, dealing our disordered and our mis-ordered loves. We forget that we are loved. We forget that we’re not alone, orphans in a cold world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="ii.-god-dwells-with-us" class="level3"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;II. God Dwells With Us&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But we’re not. God dwells with us. That’s the hope, and the help, that we need. God dwells with us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Look at that question there in the middle: Judas (not Iscariot) asks, “Lord, how is it that you will manifest yourself to us, and not to the world?” That’s a good question. And what Jesus does here is take his first answer, and carry it even further out of the realm of what Judas understood then.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jesus opens this passage, having just told them how he is going to go away to the Father and prepare a place for them, and he says, “I will ask the Father, and he will give you another helper” (another advocate, or a friend-in-court, someone to carry you through the trial) “to be with you forever.” The disciples were where, I think, any of us would be in their shoes. &lt;em&gt;Jesus says he’s ‘going to his Father’? What does that mean? Are we going to be alone?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A few weeks ago, I traveled for work, and I ended up being gone for about a week and a half. I have two little girls, and one of them was about nineteen months old then, and she was a &lt;em&gt;wreck&lt;/em&gt; after that. For weeks, every time I went &lt;em&gt;near&lt;/em&gt; the door—if I so much as went to take out the trash, she would &lt;em&gt;lose&lt;/em&gt; it. She didn’t understand where I had gone, or why, or when I was going to come back. And she loves me. She didn’t want me to leave again. She wanted me to be with her.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That’s where the disciples were. It makes sense. That’s why Jesus told them, “I’m not going to leave you as orphans. I will come to you.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But when Jesus explains &lt;em&gt;how&lt;/em&gt; he will come to them: “I will ask, and the Father will send you a Helper, and he will be with you. The world won’t see me, but I will show myself to &lt;em&gt;you&lt;/em&gt;,” you can see where Judas’ confusion comes from. Jesus’ answer, and really this whole passage, points us to &lt;em&gt;something&lt;/em&gt;…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I can’t fully capture all this passage says. I have wrestled with it for &lt;em&gt;weeks&lt;/em&gt;, and there is just so much here. I can’t capture it. Look at verse 23: “If anyone loves me,” Jesus says, “he will keep my word, and my Father will love him, and we will come to him and make our home with him.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I can’t give you a summary, but maybe a window, looking at an ocean.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;God dwells with us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;God… dwells… with us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I said “a window on an &lt;em&gt;ocean&lt;/em&gt;” because the depths here… More than an ocean, there is a &lt;em&gt;universe&lt;/em&gt; of depth here. There are depths here which we will never finish plumbing. We could, for eternity, dive deeper, and deeper into that reality. We &lt;em&gt;will&lt;/em&gt; for eternity dive deeper. But we will never exhaust its depths. We will never say, “Oh: that’s how deep the love of God goes; that’s where it stops.” And this mystery? There is more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;God dwells with us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you’re a believer, if you love God and keep his commands, this ocean is yours. And friend, listen: if you’re hearing this word and you &lt;em&gt;don’t&lt;/em&gt; yet love God—you’re &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; keeping Jesus’ words—&lt;em&gt;this&lt;/em&gt; is what is freely offered to you: in Jesus’ first dwelling with us in the Incarnation; in his life, obeying the Fathers’ plan all the way through to his death on our behalf; in his resurrection; in his asking the Father to send the Spirit—salvation offered freely to you. The God who has always been, the God who exists in eternal love in the Trinity, wants to dwell with you. So turn from your rebellion against God, and love God—and know that you are loved by him!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He promised them they would see him again (in verses 19–20), a pointer to the resurrection. But more than that, we see in his promise of peace, and even in his telling them ahead of time that he was leaving, preparation for the time when he would have ascended. Like now. We don’t see Jesus with these eyes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But we still need to know we’re not orphans. We still need peace, and not like the world gives it. We need God to be with us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Imagine there were a way I could tell my little girls, “I’m going away to do some work for you, but even while I’m gone, I will come to you.” Isn’t that what Jesus does here? “I’m going to my Father to prepare a place for you” but now, to your distress about that: “the Father and I will come to you.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How? “I will ask the Father,” Jesus says in verse 16, “and he will give you another Helper, to be with you forever, the spirit of Truth… he dwells with you, and will be in you.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Spirit of the living God: his breath; our helper, our advocate and friend-in-court; our teacher, who will remind us of everything Jesus said to us, who inspired these Scriptures and now applies them to us; the peace that we need.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because Jesus didn’t go away and leave them orphans. He didn’t leave &lt;em&gt;us&lt;/em&gt; orphans.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;God dwells with us, because his Spirit is with us and in us. And just as the Father and the Son are one (as we see both earlier in this chapter, and again here in verses 20 and 24) the Spirit is one with the Father and the Son. They act together, but it’s more than that. The way Jesus talks in this passage: “We will come to him, and make our home with him”; or the way Paul talks in Ephesians: “You are being built together into a dwelling place for God by the Spirit”. Where the Spirit is, the Father and the Son are, too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So when the Father does as the Son asks, and sends us the Spirit to dwell with us, he is giving us &lt;em&gt;himself&lt;/em&gt;. We have access in one Spirit to the Father. When someday we are glorified, and heaven has come down to earth, and the dwelling place of God is physically with man, when we can see the risen Lord with our own eyes—&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Spirit will still dwell with us. He is with us &lt;em&gt;forever&lt;/em&gt;. He is our union with God. Jesus is in the Father, and we are in him, and he is in us—through the &lt;em&gt;Spirit&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We somehow—again, depths beyond us—we participate, through the Spirit, in the life of God.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He, mystery of mysteries, he wants to dwell with us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="conclusionexhortation" class="level2"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Conclusion/Exhortation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As we close tonight, three things to take away.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol type="1"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Reflect.&lt;/strong&gt; John wants us to reflect on this mystery: God has made us his &lt;em&gt;home&lt;/em&gt;. God dwells with us.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Obey.&lt;/strong&gt; If we love him, we’re going to obey Jesus’ words. So remember that as we go out from here. Keep his word—not to persuade God to love you, but because he &lt;em&gt;already does&lt;/em&gt; love you, because he &lt;em&gt;already&lt;/em&gt; dwells with you, because you and I together are &lt;em&gt;his temple&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;his tabernacle&lt;/em&gt;. So keep his word. Demonstrate (like you would to a friend or a child or a spouse, but so much more) that you &lt;em&gt;love&lt;/em&gt; him.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Peace.&lt;/strong&gt; As we go out from here, we might think to say, “God be with you!” But perhaps better, in light of this passage, to say, “God &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; with you. Go in peace.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;div id="refs" class="references"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 12 Apr 2016 19:15:00 -0400</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2016-04-12:2016/god-is-with-us.html</guid><category>sermons</category><category>SEBTS</category><category>M. Div.</category></item><item><title></title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2016/2016-04-05-1341.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Few things are as encouraging when doing exegetical work for a sermon as finding that your thoughts aare &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; original, but stand in line with what the church has confessed about a passage before.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id="refs" class="references"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 05 Apr 2016 13:41:00 -0400</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2016-04-05:2016/2016-04-05-1341.html</guid><category>sermons</category></item><item><title></title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2016/2016-04-05-0800.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;One of the things that’s weird about writing sermons for a class is the requirement to turn in a summary of my preparation. Why, you ask? Because it tends to look like this…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src="//cdn.chriskrycho.com/images/sermon-notes.jpg" title="sermon notes with markup" /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;div id="refs" class="references"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 05 Apr 2016 08:00:00 -0400</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2016-04-05:2016/2016-04-05-0800.html</guid><category>writing</category><category>sermons</category><category>M. Div.</category><category>SEBTS</category></item><item><title>A Strange and Messy Deliverance</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2016/a-strange-and-messy-deliverance.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;i class="editorial"&gt;The only constraints on this sermon were that it be between 15 and 25 minutes long, and be on a text from the Old Testament. Video and its audio are from an old MacBook Pro pointed at the podium. Dedicated audio is from my iPhone in my shirt pocket.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section id="audio" class="level3"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Audio&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.podtrac.com/pts/redirect.m4a/cdn.chriskrycho.com/sermons/2016-03-08.m4a"&gt;Download&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;audio title="A Strange and Messy Deliverance" controls="controls" preload="metadata" src="http://www.podtrac.com/pts/redirect.m4a/cdn.chriskrycho.com/sermons/2016-03-08.m4a" type="audio/m4a"&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;Sorry; your browser doesn&amp;#39;t support m4a files. Try downloading the file
directly and playing it in iTunes or another media app.&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/audio&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="video" class="level3"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Video&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="iframe-wrapper four-to-three"&gt;
&lt;iframe src="https://player.vimeo.com/video/158279181" frameborder="0" webkitallowfullscreen mozallowfullscreen allowfullscreen&gt;
&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href="https://vimeo.com/158279181"&gt;A Strange and Messy Deliverance (Judges 3:7–31)&lt;/a&gt; from &lt;a href="https://vimeo.com/chriskrycho"&gt;Chris Krycho&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;a href="https://vimeo.com"&gt;Vimeo&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="prayer" class="level2"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Prayer&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let us pray. &lt;em&gt;Gracious Father: thank you for revealing yourself to us, especially in your Son, our Lord; and for filling us with your Spirit so that we may know you truly. As we come to your word tonight, help us know you more deeply and worship you more faithfully. In Christ’s name, amen.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="introduction" class="level2"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Please open your Bibles to Judges, chapter 3. And as you turn there, I want you to think about these words:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Boring exegesis &lt;em&gt;must&lt;/em&gt; be wrong when the texts are so obviously full of life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Again:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Boring exegesis &lt;em&gt;must&lt;/em&gt; be wrong when the texts are so obviously full of life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That’s N. T. Wright, speaking of the Pauline epistles. But I think, equally applicable whenever we come to God’s word—especially in preaching and teaching—and most especially when the texts are like this one: lively, to say the least; strange, even.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have two goals for this sermon. The first—always the first—is to show the grace of God clearly. As Bryan Chappell, the author &lt;em&gt;Christ-Centered Preaching&lt;/em&gt;, puts it, we want to see how God did for his people then what they could not do for themselves; and through that to be be reminded of what he has done for us, that we could not do for ourselves. That’s the point of this sermon: God’s grace in Christ.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But secondarily—thinking about boring exegesis; thinking about hard texts like Judges 3—I hope to encourage you that these texts, these strange texts, these sometimes difficult texts—they’re for us, and for our good. They’re for our people, and our people’s good. We don’t need to ashamed of them, or embarrassed by them, or intimidated by them. Rather, we can come away seeing how these texts magnify the grace of God, how these texts remind us to look to Christ.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="body" class="level2"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Body&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;section id="othniel-the-first-judge" class="level3"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Othniel: The first judge&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So let’s look and see. This is a long passage, with three judges—Othniel, Ehud, and Shamgar—so we’ll take each in turn. Read with me, starting in verse 7:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And the people of Israel did what was evil in the sight of the LORD. They forgot the LORD their God and served the Baals and the Asheroth. Therefore the anger of the LORD was kindled against Israel, and he sold them into the hand of Cushan-rishathaim king of Mesopotamia. And the people of Israel served Cushan-rishathaim eight years. But when the people of Israel cried out to the LORD, the LORD raised up a deliverer for the people of Israel, who saved them, Othniel the son of Kenaz, Caleb’s younger brother. The Spirit of the LORD was upon him, and he judged Israel. He went out to war, and the LORD gave Cushan-rishathaim king of Mesopotamia into his hand. And his hand prevailed over Cushan-rishathaim. So the land had rest forty years. Then Othniel the son of Kenaz died.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This first narrative is probably the easiest to understand. &lt;strong&gt;Othniel&lt;/strong&gt; is &lt;strong&gt;the first judge&lt;/strong&gt;. He is the prototype for all the other judges that follow. His story shows out the pattern for the whole book, the same one the author laid out back in chapter 2: sin, discipline, a cry for mercy, and God’s deliverance through a judge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Verse 7: Israel sins. They &lt;em&gt;forgot&lt;/em&gt; Yahweh their God. They served the Ba’als and the Asheroth instead of the God who had delivered them from Egypt.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That’s an interesting word choice: &lt;em&gt;forgot&lt;/em&gt;—and it’s an important word, not only in this passage, but throughout the Bible. After all the reminders in the covenant: Set up these stones so you remember! Teach your children, so they remember. Bind it on your hands and your forehead, so you remember! And they forgot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Othniel is Caleb’s brother, note. They forgot in the &lt;em&gt;first generation&lt;/em&gt; they were in the land.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When we forget, we get things wrong. You’ve seen it happen: a spouse forgets an anniversary, and spends some time “in the dog house.” Or parents who miss a school event for their children, and leave them feeling like they don’t matter. Forgetting a friend’s birthday: maybe you’re not as close as you thought.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And sometimes… we all forget who God is, what he has done for us, and what our relationship to him is as the covenant people of God. We find ourselves fixated on the approval of the people in the pews, on the applause of subscribers to our popular podcast, on the affirmation of our professional peers. We become idolaters—just like Israel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But he showed them mercy. How? “He sold them into the hand of Cushan-rishathaim, king of Mesopotamia”—not mercy the way we might be inclined to think of it, but real, deep mercy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because: see what happens? It had the intended effect. They remembered Yahweh and called out to him. And he delivered them—both from the pagan King, and from their idolatry, at least for a time! The Spirit came on Othniel, and he led Israel to war, and God delivered them from Cushan-rishathaim, and they had peace for forty years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;God delivered his people, and Othniel, this &lt;em&gt;first judge&lt;/em&gt;, was a good judge. He wasn’t a prophet like Moses; he didn’t give them lasting rest, any more than Joshua had (40 years is good, but it’s not &lt;em&gt;forever&lt;/em&gt;); and he didn’t circumcise their hearts. Not &lt;em&gt;the&lt;/em&gt; judge then. A good judge, but not &lt;em&gt;the&lt;/em&gt; judge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="ehud-the-assassin" class="level3"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Ehud: The assassin&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sadly, he was also the &lt;em&gt;best&lt;/em&gt; of the Judges. Things only go downhill from here. Who’s next? &lt;strong&gt;Ehud: the assassin.&lt;/strong&gt; Let’s read again, picking up in verse 12:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And the people of Israel again did what was evil in the sight of the LORD, and the LORD strengthened Eglon the king of Moab against Israel, because they had done what was evil in the sight of the LORD. He gathered to himself the Ammonites and the Amalekites, and went and defeated Israel. And they took possession of the city of palms. And the people of Israel served Eglon the king of Moab eighteen years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then the people of Israel cried out to the LORD, and the LORD raised up for them a deliverer, Ehud, the son of Gera, the Benjaminite, a left-handed man. The people of Israel sent tribute by him to Eglon the king of Moab. And Ehud made for himself a sword with two edges, a cubit in length, and he bound it on his right thigh under his clothes. And he presented the tribute to Eglon king of Moab. Now Eglon was a very fat man. And when Ehud had finished presenting the tribute, he sent away the people who carried the tribute. But he himself turned back at the idols near Gilgal and said, “I have a secret message for you, O king.” And he commanded, “Silence.” And all his attendants went out from his presence. And Ehud came to him as he was sitting alone in his cool roof chamber. And Ehud said, “I have a message from God for you.” And he arose from his seat. And Ehud reached with his left hand, took the sword from his right thigh, and thrust it into his belly. And the hilt also went in after the blade, and the fat closed over the blade, for he did not pull the sword out of his belly; and the dung came out. Then Ehud went out into the porch and closed the doors of the roof chamber behind him and locked them. When he had gone, the servants came, and when they saw that the doors of the roof chamber were locked, they thought, “Surely he is relieving himself in the closet of the cool chamber.” And they waited till they were embarrassed. But when he still did not open the doors of the roof chamber, they took the key and opened them, and there lay their lord dead on the floor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ehud escaped while they delayed, and he passed beyond the idols and escaped to Seirah. When he arrived, he sounded the trumpet in the hill country of Ephraim. Then the people of Israel went down with him from the hill country, and he was their leader. And he said to them, “Follow after me, for the LORD has given your enemies the Moabites into your hand.” So they went down after him and seized the fords of the Jordan against the Moabites and did not allow anyone to pass over. And they killed at that time about 10,000 of the Moabites, all strong, able-bodied men; not a man escaped. So Moab was subdued that day under the hand of Israel. And the land had rest for eighty years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We see the same pattern again here… sort of. We see Israel sin, and God discipline them. And we see Israel cry out to their covenant God, and we see him deliver them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But of course, Ehud’s story is more complicated than Othniel’s was. Some of the details here might initially perplex us. Why do we hear about how fat the king is? Why do we hear about the dung coming out after he gets stabbed? Why almost any of the extraneous-seeming details in this story?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, this is satire. (Which doesn’t make it untrue, of course.) The author plays up the ridiculous elements in this bit of history to make a point.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What do we see here?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A conquering king! …&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;who’s actually morbidly obese, not exactly a strapping warrior&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;who, so cunning he could forge an alliance with the Ammonites and Amalekites, gets fooled by a simple trick (“Oh king, I have secret message for you”)—he’s either hopelessly naive or profoundly overconfident; neither is good&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a man who so comically out of line with what a king should be that his servants don’t even notice when there’s a wretched stench and he takes a &lt;em&gt;looong&lt;/em&gt; time relieving himself&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Great king.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And his servants? They aren’t exactly top-drawer. They don’t even notice Ehud escaping after he assassinated their king…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If we read the story right, it’s humorous. The author is poking fun at the Moabites! “Those Moabites!”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Right?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But, wait… those Moabites conquered Israel. This ridiculous Moabite king?… Ehud was there to bring him tribute.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Israel&lt;/em&gt; is the real joke. The idolaters who got conquered by &lt;em&gt;this&lt;/em&gt; king. Ouch.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is what good satire does. It sneaks in, makes you laugh, and then hits you where it counts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And what about Ehud himself? What about this savior figure? He’s not good either. He’s a vicious assassin, a traitor who stabbed the man he was legally supposed to be serving.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This story is messy. Not just because of the dung coming out. But because while yes, God did deliver his people, and that is good—but Ehud isn’t the kind of deliverer we want, not the kind of deliverer we need.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not the brutal killer, but the one who was brutally killed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not the one who defeated a foreign king by stabbing him in the gut, but the one who overcame both the pagan oppressor and the idolatry that led to that oppression by &lt;em&gt;being&lt;/em&gt; stabbed, by taking the weapon to &lt;em&gt;his&lt;/em&gt; gut.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The book of Judges shows us over and over again what we’re like left to our own purposes. How even our human saviors are woefully insufficient. The covenant hope, proclaimed from the start of Genesis and made so clear in Deuteronomy… was still waiting to be fulfilled.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="shamgar-unifying-theme" class="level3"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Shamgar &amp;amp; Unifying Theme&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And then we come to the end of this chapter—to &lt;strong&gt;Shamgar: the man with an ox-goad&lt;/strong&gt; and his one verse: verse 31.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After him was Shamgar the son of Anath, who killed 600 of the Philistines with an oxgoad, and he also saved Israel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So if you’re like me, you’re wondering at least two things about this passage. One is: what in the world is an oxgoad? That’s the easy one: It’s a cattle prod. A long wooden pole with a point on the end. Makes for a decent improvised spear.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the other question, the bigger question, is &lt;em&gt;why does Ehud get paragraphs, with lurid details for a satire… and Shamgar gets just one sentence?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have a man who, based on his name, doesn’t even seem to be an Israelity, who shows up, kills 600 Philistines with an ox-goad, and then he’s gone. He gets one mention in Deborah’s song in chapter 5, but basically, this is it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So why mention him at all if he’s so seemingly unimportant? Why these proportions?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After all, this is the inspired word of God. And the author had a reason for giving us these stories, even &lt;em&gt;these proportions.&lt;/em&gt; He’s making a point.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We read this and I, for one, think, “Oh, that sounds interesting; how did he do that with a cattle pr—” “NO. That’s not the question.” He slams the door on that question.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Shamgar’s skill with an ox-goad is not the point, any more than Ehud’s skill as an assassin was the point, any more even than Othniel’s skill as a military leadership was the point. No more, I put it to you, than any of &lt;em&gt;us&lt;/em&gt; are the point.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“And he also saved Israel.” Those words tell us what we need to know. Who saved Israel? Shamgar… Ehud… Othniel… but really, in every case, Yahweh. The covenant-keeping God, who saved Israel not only from 600 Philistines, not only from a Moabite king worthy of derision, not only from a mighty king of Mesopotamia—but from her idolatry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="summary-and-exhortation" class="level2"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Summary and Exhortation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Someday—someday, after many judges, many kings, many priests, many prophets—there would come a deliverer—a judge, a prophet, a priest, a king—&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;who would give the land rest, who would give the people of God true rest, for more than just a generation; forever…&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;who would be a wise king&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;who would be gentle and gracious ruler&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;who would give God’s people circumcised hearts&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;who would fulfill the covenant hopes and take on himself the covenant curses of Deuteronony, of Exodus, of Genesis&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have that deliverer. We have Christ. “And he also saved Israel.” So when we read, when we teach, when we preach, let us look, every time, and see what God did for his people that they could not do for themselves. Let us, in every passage, in every picture of grace, find a reminder of what God has done for us in Christ, that we could not do for ourselves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have a deliverer. Don’t forget. Don’t let your people forget. We have a deliverer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Gracious Father: thank you for delivering us. Help us be faithful with your word. Help us remember, and help us remind your people, of how you have delivered us. In the name of Jesus, our savior, amen.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id="refs" class="references"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 08 Mar 2016 20:00:00 -0500</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2016-03-08:2016/a-strange-and-messy-deliverance.html</guid><category>SEBTS</category><category>M. Div.</category><category>sermons</category></item><item><title></title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2016/2016-02-23-2358.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Stayed up &lt;em&gt;way&lt;/em&gt; too late tonight, working on a sermon on Judges 3. Yes. Judges 3. Should be interesting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id="refs" class="references"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 23 Feb 2016 23:58:00 -0500</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2016-02-23:2016/2016-02-23-2358.html</guid><category>sermons</category></item><item><title></title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2016/2016-02-11-0900.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;I’ve set up a podcast feed specifically for any sermons I preach going forward. You can subscribe these places:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/podcast/sermons-by-chris-krycho/id1083193863?mt=2"&gt;&lt;i class="fa fa-fw fa-music"&gt;&lt;/i&gt; iTunes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://overcast.fm/p395569-ypBaG2"&gt;&lt;i class="fa fa-fw fa-play-circle"&gt;&lt;/i&gt; Overcast&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://pca.st/slox"&gt;&lt;i class="fa fa-fw fa-play-circle-o"&gt;&lt;/i&gt; Pocket Casts&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/sermons.xml"&gt;&lt;i class="fa fa-fw fa-rss"&gt;&lt;/i&gt; Direct&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As an aside: having done the starting-up dance for 4 podcasts now, it’s gotten pretty easy. 😉&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id="refs" class="references"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 11 Feb 2016 09:00:00 -0500</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2016-02-11:2016/2016-02-11-0900.html</guid><category>podcasting</category><category>sermons</category></item><item><title>A Humble, Selfless, Unity</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2016/a-humble-selfless-unity.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;i class="editorial"&gt;The only constraints on this sermon were that it be between 15 and 25 minutes long, and be on a text from an epistle. Video is from an old MacBook Pro pointed at the podium.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section id="audio" class="level3"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Audio&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.podtrac.com/pts/redirect.m4a/cdn.chriskrycho.com/sermons/2016-02-09.m4a"&gt;Download&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;audio title="A Humble, Selfless, Unity" controls="controls" preload="metadata" src="http://www.podtrac.com/pts/redirect.m4a/cdn.chriskrycho.com/sermons/2016-02-09.m4a" type="audio/m4a"&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;Sorry; your browser doesn&amp;#39;t support m4a files. Try downloading the file
directly and playing it in iTunes or another media app.&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/audio&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="video" class="level3"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Video&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="iframe-wrapper four-to-three"&gt;
&lt;iframe src="https://player.vimeo.com/video/154810219" frameborder="0" webkitallowfullscreen mozallowfullscreen allowfullscreen&gt;
&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href="https://vimeo.com/154810219"&gt;A Humble, Selfless Unity (Philippians 2:1–11)&lt;/a&gt; from &lt;a href="https://vimeo.com/chriskrycho"&gt;Chris Krycho&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;a href="https://vimeo.com"&gt;Vimeo&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Good evening. Let’s pray before we begin.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Gracious God, may your word be clear in our hearts. May your Spirit open our minds to see you more clearly and love as you have loved us. May we see you, and may I not obscure you. Thank you for revealing yourself to us.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="introduction" class="level2"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our text for this evening is Philippians 2:1–11. It might be a familiar passage to many of you, but I think it might also be a surprising passage to you. It was for me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don’t know if you’ve ever been walking along someplace familiar and had something prompt you to stop and notice something about your surroundings that you had never seen before. Maybe you went back to the house you grew up in, and the house is the same, but you aren’t—and you notice the little cracks in the ceiling. &lt;em&gt;Were those always there?&lt;/em&gt; You look at the wall in your older sister’s bedroom. &lt;em&gt;Was it always that color? I thought it was lighter than that.&lt;/em&gt; You go down the stairs into the basement, and “Yup, they always creaked like that,” your mother tells you. You start to ask about the way the basement smells and she just shakes her head at you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It had been a while since I read this passage, and it kind of felt like thinking you had grown up in a &lt;em&gt;really nice house&lt;/em&gt; and going back and discovering that it was &lt;em&gt;mansion&lt;/em&gt;. But whether you’ve read this passage a hundred times, or this your first time opening a Bible, God is inviting us into a beautiful mansion tonight.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="believers-called-to-humble-selfless-unity-215" class="level2"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;1. Believers called to humble, selfless, unity (2:1–5)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As we come to Philippians 2, Paul has just spent the first chunk of a letter to these Christians in Philippi—good friends to him, people who have supported his ministry—about his circumstances… which aren’t great, frankly. He wrote this letter from prison. But, one way or another, he has seen a great many people hear the good news about Jesus as a result of his in prison. But he also knows that the Philippians are having a hard time, and he knows that they need encouragement in their faith. He knew that when things get hard—whether that’s persecution, physical or mental illness, death among your friends or family, losing jobs—when life gets hard, we can turn on each other. And Paul called the Philippians, in the midst of their trials—God is calling us, tonight, in the midst of our trials—to something different: to a &lt;strong&gt;humble, selfless, unity&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s read:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;So if there is any encouragement in Christ, any comfort from love, any participation in the Spirit, any affection and sympathy, &lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;complete my joy by being of the same mind, having the same love, being in full accord and of one mind.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;section id="four-reasons" class="level3"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Four reasons&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Paul opens with four &lt;em&gt;reasons&lt;/em&gt; for people to live with this humble, selfless unity. “If there is any…”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol type="1"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;encouragement in Christ&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;comfort from love&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;participation in [which could also read fellowship in or with] the Spirit&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;affection and sympathy&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“If there is any,” he says. Is there any? Well, yes. There &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; encouragement in Christ. We &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt; find comfort from being loved, by God and by each other. As believers, we do have fellowship with the Spirit, and through him with Christ and the Father, and of course with each other too. We do have God-given affection and sympathy for each other, and even for non-believers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In other words, Paul is using that “if” to quietly point the Philippian believers to a &lt;em&gt;reality&lt;/em&gt;. When he asks them to complete his joy if these things are true, he’s saying, “Look, these four things &lt;em&gt;are&lt;/em&gt; true.” You &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt; encouragement; comfort; fellowship; affection and sympathy. And just as they did, so do we.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So given those four good reasons, Paul asks them to complete his joy. As he has told them already, earlier in the epistle, he already has great joy—in seeing the gospel go forth. He even rejoices when people preach the gospel in an attempt to make him jealous. But his joy isn’t complete without something else. If these four reasons are the foundation for that completion, the finished building is &lt;strong&gt;humble, selfless, unity&lt;/strong&gt;. But what we might ask: what is the structure of that finished building?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="three-ways" class="level3"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Three ways&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are three. Four foundation stones, and three pillars on that base. Paul told his friends they would complete his joy—they would fill it up—by:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol type="1"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;being of the same mind&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;having the same love&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;being in full accord and of one mind&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(If you’re worried about my counting: affection and sympathy go together, and so do “being in full accord and of one mind.” If you have true affection for someone, you will feel sympathy for her when she is struggling. If you’re in full accord with someone, it’s like you and he share a mind. So: four foundation stones, and these three pillars.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And what we see in these three pillars is that these three ways are really &lt;em&gt;one&lt;/em&gt; way. They’re one structure. And that &lt;em&gt;one way&lt;/em&gt;, is to be &lt;em&gt;one&lt;/em&gt;. That one way is &lt;em&gt;unity&lt;/em&gt;. Joy, for the apostle, and I think it is fair to say God’s joy in our fellowship, is complete when we are truly unified. Not identical, but unified.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But how? &lt;em&gt;How&lt;/em&gt; do we have the same mind? &lt;em&gt;How&lt;/em&gt; do we have the same love? &lt;em&gt;How&lt;/em&gt; can we be in full accord and of one mind? That seems rather abstract. If I sat down my three-and-a-half year old and my 20-month old and said, “Okay, Ellie and Kate, you need to have unity between you two,” they would just stare at me. Ellie, the older one, might say, “Yes, daddy!” just to be good, but they wouldn’t know what to do with it. Kate, the younger one, would probably yell “No!” because she’s a toddler and we’re working on that right now. And wherever you are: whether you’re saying, “Okay…” but you don’t really get it, or you’re saying “No, no way! Have you met these people?” Paul draws us forward. He gives us some help, makes it a little more concrete.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="two-contrasts" class="level3"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Two contrasts&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Paul gives us two pairs of contrasts to help us see a little more clearly what this kind of unity looks like. Capstones to match the foundation, if you will.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;Do nothing [, he says in v. 3,] from selfish ambition or conceit, but in humility count others more significant than yourselves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That’s the first capstone, the first contrast. Not selfish ambition, not conceit, but humility, and counting others more important than yourself. So we see first that this unity is &lt;em&gt;humble&lt;/em&gt; unity. It comes becomes I’m valuing you above me. I’m not trying to exalt myself. I’m thinking of how I can make you do well instead.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Verse 4 shows us the second contrast, the second capstone:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;sup&gt;4&lt;/sup&gt;Let each of you look not only to his own interests, but also to the interests of others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This unity, then, is also &lt;em&gt;selfless&lt;/em&gt;. When we’re healthy, we don’t just aim to get our own. “Looking out for number one!” No, instead, we help others accomplish their hopes. We give of our time; our money; our sleep; our space – to help others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So this is the church. This is the kind of building we’re supposed to be. As Paul puts it in Ephesians, we’re being built together into a temple for God—a temple of people known for their &lt;strong&gt;humble, selfless, unity&lt;/strong&gt;—their love.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have these four foundations: encouragement in Christ, comfort from love, fellowship with the Spirit, and affection and sympathy. We have three pillars of unity: being of the same mind, having the same love, being in full accord and of one mind. We have two capstones: calls to humility and selflessness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But you might be asking now, “How? I want that unity; I even want to be selfless and humble, even if that sounds kind of hard. But I don’t know &lt;em&gt;how&lt;/em&gt;.” And to that, Paul says, “Don’t worry; I’ll give you an example. In fact, here is &lt;em&gt;the&lt;/em&gt; example.” And he shows us Christ—verse 5: “Have this mind among yourselves, which was also in Christ Jesus…”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="the-foundation-of-humble-selfless-unity-2611" class="level2"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;2. The foundation of humble, selfless, unity (2:6–11)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The mind of Christ! That’s a heady thing to think about. But for Paul, it’s deeply practical, in fact. He gives us a very succinct summary of Jesus’ ministry. And what was Jesus like? He was humble. He was selfless. (And if you’re thinking, “But what about unity?” you’re right. Hold on to that thought. We’ll come back to it.) Let’s start by looking at Christ’s example.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section id="christ-humbled-himself" class="level3"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Christ humbled himself&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;sup&gt;6&lt;/sup&gt;who [Christ Jesus], though he was in the form of God, did not count equality with God a thing to be grasped [—something to be held onto—], &lt;sup&gt;7&lt;/sup&gt;but emptied himself, by taking the form of a servant, being born in the likeness of men. &lt;sup&gt;8&lt;/sup&gt;And being found in human form, he humbled himself by becoming obedient to the point of death, even death on a cross.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What we see here is one of the great mysteries our faith. God became man. We could take a dozen sermons on this point alone. But Paul has something very specific for us to see from the Incarnation here. Whatever prerogatives we might have—whatever money, whatever fame, whatever position or status—the Son had more. And Jesus Christ lived as a servant. He didn’t hold onto what was his (and it really was his, by right!). He came as one of us. When you read here, “in the likeness of man,” don’t think “he was kind of like us.” Hebrews tells us that he was &lt;em&gt;exactly&lt;/em&gt; was we are—yet without sin.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And that degradation goes down and down and down. He became a baby, who needed to be changed. He dealt, like my older daughter does, with younger siblings who tormented him. He was teased by other children. He went through puberty and had his voice go all scratchy. He worked for many years in obscurity. When he started his ministry, he was rejected as often as accepted, loved for his miracles and not for the God he revealed, mocked even by his own family, and wandered around without a home. Remember, the God of all the universe. And ultimately, he died. Died a sinner’s shameful death. He took our humiliation. And through all of it, he did not complain, he just served. So Christ is our model.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A convicting model, at least for me. Jesus, the real flesh-and-blood Jesus who was tempted just like us, is the perfect man. He is what it &lt;em&gt;means&lt;/em&gt; to be human rightly. And he served. He’s the rightful king! And he served. Do I serve like that? Do you? Or do we demand our rights?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="the-father-exalted-christ" class="level3"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;The Father exalted Christ&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, as we come into these final verses, we see what at first might seem like a bit of a strange turn. Paul is trying to teach us about this kind of &lt;strong&gt;humble, selflessness,&lt;/strong&gt;—and yes, &lt;strong&gt;unity&lt;/strong&gt;. Hmm. And we were tracking along, as we saw the concrete example of Jesus living and dying selflessly. Feeling conviction, even; I certainly was and am. But then we get to this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;sup&gt;9&lt;/sup&gt;Therefore God has highly exalted him and bestowed on him the name that is above every name, &lt;sup&gt;10&lt;/sup&gt;so that at the name of Jesus every knee should bow, in heaven and on earth and under the earth, &lt;sup&gt;11&lt;/sup&gt;and every tongue confess that Jesus Christ is Lord, to the glory of God the Father.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is, at first blush, a bit of a challenge. “Okay. I mean, it’s good that Jesus is exalted. But how does it fit? Am &lt;em&gt;I&lt;/em&gt; going to be exalted? Am I supposed to serve because Jesus was exalted? What’s going on here?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are two parts to this. One of them is, yes, that Jesus is Lord. We are citizens of his kingdom, and if his people lived like that, his people should &lt;em&gt;certainly&lt;/em&gt; live like that. So that is one part of it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But there is something else going on here, too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And this—oh, this! What do we see here? We see the Father exalting the son. He &lt;em&gt;highly&lt;/em&gt; exalted him. He gave him the name that is above every other name. The Father wants every one to say, “Jesus is Lord!” The Father wants everyone to bow down and worship Jesus. And Jesus, the Son—he’s doing all of this, he’s becoming a servant, taking on human nature, dying, on a cross to what end? To the glory of the Father!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have a little glimpse here into something… &lt;em&gt;awesome&lt;/em&gt;. We see the Father, saying to the Son, “Let me exalt you!” And Jesus says to the Father, “All the glory is yours!” And the Father to the Son, and the Son to the Father, back and forth, and back and forth, forever. This is the life of the trinity. This is the eternal life of the triune God: &lt;strong&gt;humble, selfless, unity&lt;/strong&gt;! Love!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And this is what we’re meant to be. This is what the church is for. This is what &lt;em&gt;humanity&lt;/em&gt; is for: men and women made in the image of God—&lt;strong&gt;humble, selfless, unity&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The life of the Trinity, in the life of the church. This is the building we’re meant to be. This is the temple. This is the mansion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Paul has taken our question: “How do I live like that?” and he’s answered it by showing us how the life of the triune God took on flesh, and lived among us. Was our servant. Died for us. He says: “How Christ lived is how we are meant to live.” And he reminds us, back there in v. 1: “If there is any encouragement in Christ, any comfort from love, any participation in the Spirit—any fellowship with the Spirit, remember; any affection and sympathy, complete my joy…” We have fellowship with the Spirit. That’s where our unity comes from: not common interests, not shared experiences, not being the same age, or sex, or ethnicity, or social standing, or economic status.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We’re meant to be a little picture, every day, of the Trinity. And the way we do that, is by living like Christ did. We choose, every day, to serve the people around us, instead of ourselves. We choose, every day, not to put ourselves first, but to put others first. We choose, every day, not to make ourselves look great, but to love others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="exhortation" class="level2"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Exhortation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Brothers and sisters, here is my challenge to you today. Fill up your joy, and fill up my joy, and fill out our Triune God’s joy in you!—by loving one another as he has loved us. This kind of &lt;strong&gt;humble, selfless, unity&lt;/strong&gt; is not a burden. It is what we are for. And yes, in this fallen world, it is hard sometimes. But we have the Spirit. We participate in God’s own love. Mystery— awesome mystery! Let us love one another. Let us count one another more important than ourselves. Let us look not only to our own interests, but to each other’s. Let us live in the &lt;strong&gt;humble, selfless, unity&lt;/strong&gt; of our King’s kingdom.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And friend, if you are &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; a believer, and you look at this picture, I hope you’re thinking, “Yes. That’s what the world ought to look like.” Because it is. And it’s beautiful. We’re not meant not for self-absorption. We’re meant to live like Christ did. So I challenge you: call Christ lord. Let his death be yours, and his resurrection, too—come walk after him with us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let us pray to our loving, selfless, humble God of unity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;God we praise you, who are love and light forever. Thank you for your love—for sharing it with us, humbly and selflessly; for drawing us into your love and restoring us to what you designed us for. Thank you for building us into a temple for your Spirit. Help us walk in this same humble, selfless unity. &lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id="refs" class="references"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 09 Feb 2016 18:40:00 -0500</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2016-02-09:2016/a-humble-selfless-unity.html</guid><category>SEBTS</category><category>M. Div.</category><category>sermons</category></item><item><title></title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2016/2016-02-06-1633.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Writing a sermon on Philippians 2:1–10 and listening to Howard Shore’s &lt;em&gt;The Lord of the Rings: The Two Towers – The Complete Recordings.&lt;/em&gt; Delightful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id="refs" class="references"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 06 Feb 2016 16:33:00 -0500</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2016-02-06:2016/2016-02-06-1633.html</guid><category>music</category><category>sermons</category></item><item><title>Power and Mercy</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2015/power-and-mercy.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;i class="editorial"&gt;The Bible exposition class for which I prepared this sermon involves &lt;em&gt;writing&lt;/em&gt; but not &lt;em&gt;delivering&lt;/em&gt; a sermon. If, at some point in the future, I actually deliver this sermon (e.g. in my sermon delivery course next semester), I will update this post with a link to the audio and/or video.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section id="introduction" class="level2"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recent estimates suggest that the United States of America currently spends about three times as much money on our military as the next biggest military spender out there, China. In fact, if you add up the military spending of China, Russia, Saudi Arabia, France, Great Britain, India, and Germany, we still spend more. And remember, China’s and India’s populations are both over four times larger than ours. What’s more, corruption and graft notwithstanding, our military-industrial complex is incredibly advanced. It’s fair to say that America has the most powerful, best equipped, most effective military apparatus in the whole world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And yet. And yet, as a country, we are very afraid. All of that power can’t protect us from everything. And we are very feared. For all of America’s lofty ideals, we have made a mess of things pretty often. We’ve gotten it wrong. Having power, it turns out, isn’t enough. Having enough power matters, but so does having the right kind of power, and so does how you use that power.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As we look at Mark 5:1–20, we’re going to see that play out. It’s not just having power that matters. It matters who has the power, and how they use it. Do they torment? Or do they show mercy?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ll give you a hint: we want power coupled with mercy. You can see, if you look at verse 19, how this whole passage hinges on that. When all is said and done, the man in the middle of this story gets to go tell all his friends and neighbors how much the Lord had done for him—how powerful God is—and how the Lord had shown him mercy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="exposition" class="level2"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Exposition&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;section id="context" class="level3"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Context&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So let’s see how Mark gets us there. As we come to our text, we read: “They came to the other side of the sea, to the country of the Gerasenes.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The other side of the sea from what?” you might be asking. Well, from Galilee, where Jesus had been teaching. Back at the beginning of chapter 4, Mark tells us about a series of parables that Jesus taught about his new kingdom. And those parables particularly emphasized people’s response as his kingdom comes. Some reject it entirely; some look excited about it at first, but ultimately aren’t a part of it; and some, a few, &lt;em&gt;really are&lt;/em&gt; citizens of the new kingdom.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then, back in 4:35, Mark switched to a series of narratives—four stories. This is Mark’s basic strategy: tell us what Jesus said, and then show us what he did. Why? Well, because the parables weren’t just cryptic things Jesus said to confuse people; he was telling his disciples, the ones who had ears to hear, how things really were. Each thing Jesus &lt;em&gt;did&lt;/em&gt; showed that what he &lt;em&gt;said&lt;/em&gt; was true.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;His kingdom wasn’t coming the way people thought, or even to the people who thought it was for them. And he wasn’t the kind of king they had in mind, either. He had authority not just over nations and troops, but (as Mark shows us in these four stories), over the sea and the sky, over demons—that’s today’s passage—over incurable illness, even over death. And in each of these events, we see that Jesus wasn’t just a &lt;em&gt;powerful&lt;/em&gt; king. He was also a &lt;em&gt;merciful&lt;/em&gt; king.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, within these four narratives, Mark breaks things down into two pairs of miracle stories which hang together: the storm and the demonized man, and the two healings back on the other side of the sea. Today, we find ourselves in the second half of that first pair. With the storm, the disciples could not save themselves, so Jesus rebuked the storm, and there was a great calm, and the disciples were afraid. We are going to see those same ideas here: someone who cannot save himself, Jesus rebuking something, a great calm as a result, and people being afraid. We will see Jesus’ power and mercy. And we will see a different response than fear—a better one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="beat-1-a-wild-man-516" class="level3"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Beat 1: A wild man – 5:1–6&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So let’s follow Mark on this journey. Verse 2 tells us that “when Jesus had stepped out of the boat, immediately there met him out of the tombs a man with an unclean spirit”. Verse 6 reiterates the point—“And when he saw Jesus from afar, he ran and fell down before him”—but first Mark wants us to know something about who this man was. Verses 3 through 5 tell us:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He lived among the tombs. And no one could bind him anymore, not even with a chain, for he had often been bound with shackles and chains, but he wrenched the chains apart, and he broke the shackles in pieces. No one had the strength to subdue him. Night and day among the tombs and on the mountains he was always crying out and cutting himself with stones.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In other words, this was not a man in need of a little help, an appointment with a counselor. No, here we have a man enslaved. Nothing anyone could do would help him.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What we have here is Mark establishing both the characters involved, and the “power curve” for the rest of the scene. If you’re reading a superhero comic or watching a superhero movie, you have a sense of how strong everyone is. And of course, this leads to all sorts of conundrums. Who would win in a fight? Next year’s &lt;em&gt;Batman vs. Superman: Dawn of Justice&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Captain America: Civil War&lt;/em&gt; both hinge on this. Who is stronger? Who will win? And of course, if you let the wrong characters in, the game just becomes pointless. I saw an interview with the writers behind &lt;em&gt;Captain America&lt;/em&gt;, where they explained why the Hulk wouldn’t be in the movie. You add in the Hulk, and it’s game over for the other team. There’s no tension in the conflict anymore. The Hulk just wins.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And that’s basically the picture Mark shows us in this passage. It’s pretty clear: the demons were stronger. Nothing anyone could do was effective. They couldn’t even keep this man imprisoned; verse 4 has him acting like, well, like the Hulk. They tried chaining him up hand and foot; he just ripped the chains on his wrists off and smashed the fetters on his feet. “No one,” Mark says, “had the strength to subdue him.” Healing him was out of the question. And the man himself was clearly totally under the demons’ control. The “super-villains” had the upper hand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, the Hulk can be kind of fun to watch, but that’s not what we have here. They made a mockery of this man. We shouldn’t take that lightly. They made him run around screaming, naked, cutting himself, in the midst of the tombs. There is a reason Mark describes him as having an &lt;em&gt;unclean&lt;/em&gt; spirit. The demons were doing everything in their power—short of killing this man—to defile what God had called “very good” and what he had promised to redeem: his humanity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So there’s the power curve when Jesus arrives on the scene; there are the characters. As soon as Jesus gets off the boat, this man comes out to meet him. And then, perhaps surprisingly, given that power curve—but then again, maybe not &lt;em&gt;so&lt;/em&gt; surprising given what Jesus has already done in this gospel—verse 6 tells us that the man falls down at his knees before Jesus. He goes prostrate. Flat on his face. The way you would kneel before someone absolutely more powerful than you. Jesus’ arrival is clearly a change from the status quo.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="beat-2-a-merciful-act-5713" class="level3"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Beat 2: A merciful act – 5:7–13&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;section id="setup" class="level4"&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Setup&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So Mark has set the scene for us: here is a man who has been tormented for who knows how long, and as soon Jesus steps off the boat, he man comes running up and throws himself down at Jesus’ feet. That’s quite the welcoming party. Put yourself in the disciples’ shoes for a moment. You’ve just seen Jesus go from sleeping in the back of a boat—in the middle of the kind of storm that scared the Galilean fishermen who are with you—to standing up and telling a storm to be quiet and it does. You’re afraid. And then you get to the other side, still more than a little in shock from that, and a naked man with cuts all over his body comes up to Jesus and throws himself at his feet and starts arguing with him, shouting at him. You might be afraid all over again. And for good reason. Notice that throughout the whole passage, the disciples are just onlookers. This is out of their league, too; so they just watch.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="beat-2a-jesus-power-5710" class="level4"&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Beat 2a: Jesus’ power – 5:7–10&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dealing with the man and his impure spirit is not, however, out of Jesus’ league. Verses 7–10 make it very clear that Jesus is absolutely and unquestionably the most powerful person in this encounter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Notice, too, that the demonized man is arguing with Jesus because Jesus is arguing with him. Verses 7 and 8 tell us:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He shouted at the top of his voice, “What do you want with me, Jesus, Son of the Most High God? In God’s name don’t torture me!” For Jesus had said to him, “Come out of this man, you impure spirit!”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jesus picked this fight, and it’s not going to go down well for the demons.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now we know from ancient records that there were both Greek and Jewish exorcists who made it their business to drive out evil spirits. You will find the same in many non-Western cultures today, and—as an aside—I think those cultures probably have the right of it more than we do. It has been said that the greatest trick the devil ever pulled was convincing people he didn’t exist, and that seems about right. How can you possibly fight something you don’t even believe exists? It’s a brilliant, devious strategic move. You can pull the North Korea strategy—try to constantly rattle your saber to keep everyone afraid of you. Or you can act like an assassin: keep a low profile, and if possible don’t even let your would-be opponents know you exist, until you’ve killed them and caused mayhem. In the hyper-secular West, that seems to be the satanic strategy of the hour, and I think it’s fair to say it’s been reasonably successful for our enemy—even if we know from passages like this one that Jesus’ ultimate victory is guaranteed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That &lt;em&gt;wasn’t&lt;/em&gt; the strategy of the day back then, though. And we know from those old records that the general strategy for dealing with demons was to try to use powerful command words and phrases, or to negotiate and bargain, or to use the demon’s name to get spiritual power over them, or to try to use other divine powers to bind them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But we don’t see any of that in this passage. The demons recognize Jesus’ power and authority right away. You can see it there in verse 7: as soon as Jesus tells them to leave, they plead with him not to torment them. And you don’t plead with someone not to torment you unless they &lt;em&gt;can&lt;/em&gt; torment you. By the time Jesus asks for a name in verse 9, the demons have already acknowledged Jesus’ power and authority in the situation. What’s more, they call him “Son of the Most High God” there in verse 7. Now, this title does double duty here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, it is another confirmation of Mark’s claim throughout his gospel: that Jesus is in fact the Son of God. And significantly, the early confessions to that effect all come on the lips of demons he exorcises. The spiritual forces know spiritual authority when they see it, even if the people don’t see it yet. So confirming that Jesus is “the Son of God” is the first thing this does.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second thing it does is establish that Jesus isn’t just another player in the spiritual game. Whatever other gods someone might worship, and whatever other claims to divine power someone might offer up, Jesus trumps them all. He is the son not just of &lt;em&gt;some&lt;/em&gt; god, but of &lt;em&gt;the Most High God&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The fact that there is a legion of demons, as they admit in verse 9, simply heightens the contrast. We knew already that the “impure spirit” was able to torment the man; now we know that it is &lt;em&gt;many&lt;/em&gt; demons. It doesn’t matter. They’re still reduced to begging and pleading with him: verse 10 tells us that the man—really, the spirits speaking through him—“begged Jesus again and again not to send them out of the area.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Again, the power curve: Jesus’ authority isn’t even in the same ballpark as anyone else in the story—not the demonized man, not the people who were unable to help him or even restrain him, not the silent disciples, and not even the multitude of demons. He exceeds them all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="beat-2b-jesus-focus-51113" class="level4"&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Beat 2b: Jesus’ focus – 5:11–13&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jesus’ power is only part of the story, though. As we come into vv. 11–13, we can see his &lt;em&gt;focus&lt;/em&gt; as well. And that focus is healing a man in need. Read with me, starting in verse 11:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A large herd of pigs was feeding on the nearby hillside. The demons begged Jesus, “Send us among the pigs; allow us to go into them.” He gave them permission, and the impure spirits came out and went into the pigs. The herd, about two thousand in number, rushed down the steep bank into the lake and were drowned.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, this confirms what we already know: they &lt;em&gt;need&lt;/em&gt; Jesus’ permission. He is in charge. But, second, it also tells us that between the man and the pigs, there wasn’t a contest for Jesus. Not because he didn’t care about pigs. We know from Colossians 1 that the eternal Son of God—who Mark is taking this whole book to tell us about—is the agent of God’s creation of the whole universe; and his powerful word is the reason that the whole universe keeps existing, pigs included. Pigs were part of what he called a “good” creation in Genesis 1. Speaking as a lover of bacon myself, I’m inclined to agree with God’s assessment: pigs are good.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But, and this is important: people are more important than pigs. You can find any number of modern commentators on this passage asking about the ethical implications of Jesus’ letting the demons destroy the pigs along with themselves in this way. Neither Mark nor Luke or Matthew seem bothered by this point. Neither does Jesus. Pigs matter. Pigs are good. But they don’t matter like people do. And while it is not clear from this passage why Jesus accepted the demons’ request, what is clear is that his mercy toward this man—his compassion on him—trumped any concern for the pigs. Jesus’ focus was healing and saving people. Here, we see clearly that his powerful word is not just for creation, but also for &lt;em&gt;salvation&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This tells us something about Jesus’ power and authority. It is &lt;em&gt;good&lt;/em&gt; power and authority. He is &lt;em&gt;merciful&lt;/em&gt;. And it is so important—&lt;em&gt;extraordinarily&lt;/em&gt; important—that the Son of the Most High God, the king bringing in his kingdom, be merciful. Because as Ephesians 2 tells us, before God intervenes in our lives, we’re all like this man was. We start off dead in our sins, slaves to our lusts and every desire gone wrong and totally unchecked, in the domain of darkness, following the prince of the power of the air, the spirit now at work in the children of disobedience. The demons, in other words. And then Jesus steps in. As the rightful king, he has the power to free us… and he’s a &lt;em&gt;merciful&lt;/em&gt; king, so he &lt;em&gt;does&lt;/em&gt; free us. That’s good news. That’s gospel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="beat-3-a-fearful-crowd-51417" class="level3"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Beat 3: A fearful crowd – 5:14–17&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, it doesn’t always &lt;em&gt;look&lt;/em&gt; like good news to everyone when Jesus shows up and starts healing people. Remember, Mark is showing us the truth of those parables from back in chapter 4. So we see here the good king who is bringing in his kingdom—in secret now, but someday in glorious light—but we also see those different kinds of soil from the parable of the sower and the seed: some fruitful, some &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; fruitful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Look at what happens in verses 14 through 17:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Those tending the pigs ran off and reported this in the town and countryside, and the people went out to see what had happened. When they came to Jesus, they saw the man who had been possessed by the legion of demons, sitting there, dressed and in his right mind; and they were afraid. Those who had seen it told the people what had happened to the demon-possessed man—and told about the pigs as well. Then the people began to plead with Jesus to leave their region.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I can imagine being one of the herdsmen, seeing the pigs drowned by demons, and being frightened—and maybe they were. But that’s not what Mark says. That’s not why these people were afraid. They were afraid because they saw this man who had been naked, clothed; who had been running and screaming, sitting calmly; who had been out of his mind, now in his right mind. &lt;em&gt;That&lt;/em&gt; was what made them afraid.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mark has created a sharp contrast here: between this scene and the one that preceded it, the calming of the storm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In both scenes, we see Jesus confronting something far more powerful than ordinary humans can handle: in the first, a terrible storm; in the second, a legion of demons.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In both scenes, we see him exercise his powerful word for mercy: in the first, to save his disciples from the storm; in the second, to save this man from the demons who tormented him.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In both scenes, we see the tumult of a broken world, and then calm and peace after Jesus acts.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;And in both scenes, we see people who are afraid after Jesus acts.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But there seems to be more than one way to be “afraid” when you see the power of God’s Spirit on display in the person of Jesus Christ. You can be afraid and still want to be with him, like the disciples. Or you can be afraid like these people were—they wanted him to leave.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Clearly, one of these is better than the other. Far better to be with Jesus even if his power is more than you can handle—even if you find that the Son of God is not at all safe. Because he &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; good.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="beat-4-an-effective-commission-51820" class="level3"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Beat 4: An effective commission – 5:18–20&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But Mark wants to take us even further than the disciples’ example. He wants us to see that we do not need to be afraid. Because Jesus’ &lt;em&gt;power&lt;/em&gt; is expressed in &lt;em&gt;mercy&lt;/em&gt; to his people. The disciples didn’t really understand who Jesus was yet, didn’t really grasp either his power or his mercy yet, but someone surprising in this story does: an unclean Gentile man who had been tortured by demons. The man Jesus healed. The one to whom he so very powerfully showed mercy. Look! Verse 18:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As Jesus was getting into the boat, the man who had been demon-possessed begged to go with him.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He begged! He is the third person to beg or plead in this story. The demons begged not to be destroyed yet—and Jesus surprisingly showed them mercy in that. The people pleaded with Jesus to leave—and Jesus surprisingly showed them mercy in that. And here—at last!—someone begs for the &lt;em&gt;right&lt;/em&gt; thing: to be with Jesus. The same phrase as when Jesus called the disciples to be with him. And Jesus surprisingly… shows mercy by saying &lt;em&gt;no&lt;/em&gt; to him. Verses 19 and 20:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jesus did not let him, but said, “Go home to your own people and tell them how much the Lord has done for you, and how he has had mercy on you.” So the man went away and began to tell in the Decapolis how much Jesus had done for him. And all the people were amazed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Go home to your own people”, verse 19 says—some translations say “to your friends”—“and tell them how much the Lord has done for you, and how he has mercy on you.” Precisely &lt;em&gt;because&lt;/em&gt; this man understood Jesus great power and his great mercy, he had somewhere to be that wasn’t &lt;em&gt;with Jesus&lt;/em&gt; yet. He knew how great God’s power was, and he knew how deep God’s mercy was. So Jesus gave him a commission, and it looks familiar: go tell the nations what God has done. The nations: this is a Gentile, not a Jew; he is in the Decapolis, Gentile country, not Jewish country. “Go tell them about God’s mercy,” Jesus says to him. Because the mercy of God is not just for the Jews. Jesus was not going to be a petty little messiah, king of a corner of Palestine. God’s mercy was for the healing of the nations. And here we see the first taste of that in Mark—because what happened? “…all the people were amazed.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mark doesn’t tell us here what came of this, what the fruit was. We don’t know how many of those who were amazed were just apparently fruitful soil, where the seed sprung up and soon withered. But it is clear that there was at least &lt;em&gt;one&lt;/em&gt; who was good soil. And if Jesus’ ministry in the Decapolis in chapter 7 is any indication, it seems the Spirit may well have been using this man’s seed-sowing to prepare a great harvest some day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One more thing to see here: a detail, but not a little thing. Unlike the disciples, who hadn’t &lt;em&gt;gotten it&lt;/em&gt; yet—this man proclaimed &lt;em&gt;exactly&lt;/em&gt; what he should have. Notice, Jesus tells him to say what “the Lord” had done for him. From a Jew, including Jesus, that meant “Yahweh,” the God of Israel. And in verse 20, “the man went away and began to tell… how much &lt;em&gt;Jesus&lt;/em&gt; had done for him.” And rightly so. The mercy of Yahweh, the God of Israel, is the mercy of Jesus, the Son of the &lt;em&gt;Most High God&lt;/em&gt;—the God over every pagan deity, over every demonic power, over every human heart, over &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; nations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="summation" class="level2"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Summation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A few years ago, John Piper was preaching a missions sermon, and he started with Mark 5:19. You can see why. It’s the heart of the gospel. And Piper summed up the heart of the gospel this way:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;God sent his Son into the world to save sinners from every nation so that they would glorify him for his mercy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And that’s right. This whole narrative is a microcosm, a little picture, of the gospel, and of the right response to the gospel. Here we have a story of a Gentile man—one of the nations, not a Jew—who was literally enslaved by the powers of hell, set free by Jesus. But not just set free; set free and given a commission. Look there at verse 19 again: “Go home to your friends and tell them how much the Lord has done for you, and how he has had mercy on you.” That commission tells us what this story is about. And the center of that commission is the center of Mark’s gospel. And in fact, it’s the center of the whole Bible. It’s the center of this &lt;em&gt;great&lt;/em&gt; story we are all part of. God’s power, expressed in mercy, to save people from every nation through Jesus Christ.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Look how much he has done for us &lt;em&gt;because of that mercy&lt;/em&gt;! He saves people like you and me, people from every nation who can’t save themselves, and he invites them into his kingdom, and he gives them a mission.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="invitation" class="level2"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Invitation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Which is to say, he gives &lt;em&gt;us&lt;/em&gt; a mission. If you are a Christian in this room—if you have said to Jesus, “Let me be with you”—then he has said to you, “Go and tell your friends how much the Lord has done for you and how he has shown mercy to you.” Every one of us should want others to know how God has saved us. If you aren’t doing that, I challenge you: tell the people around you! Tell your friends, your coworkers, your family members. If that’s hard for you—and I understand; it can be—then think back on your salvation. Think about how God has shown mercy to you. Pray for the Spirit to stir you up, to deepen your love for him and your joy in what he has done, so that your telling others isn’t out of guilt, but out of excitement. That’s a prayer he delights to answer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And friend, if you are in this room and you are &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; in the kingdom? We have a good king, who offers you a pardon for your rebellion. You can be a citizen with us; we were all rebels, too. Come to him. Ask to be with him. Join us as we follow him. He has shown us mercy; he will show you mercy, too. All you have to do is surrender. Lay down your weapons. Ask for mercy. And call him Lord. If that’s you, please: let us walk with you. Come talk with us before you leave.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s pray. Let’s pray to our powerful, merciful God.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id="refs" class="references"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 09 Dec 2015 12:30:00 -0500</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2015-12-09:2015/power-and-mercy.html</guid><category>SEBTS</category><category>M. Div.</category><category>sermons</category></item></channel></rss>