<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Chris Krycho - social media</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/</link><description></description><lastBuildDate>Sat, 11 Aug 2018 10:35:00 -0400</lastBuildDate><item><title>“Free Speech”</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2018/free-speech.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Every time there is a major controversy about large platforms blocking or delisting some controversial figure, something like the following exchange follows:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Person 1:&lt;/strong&gt; But what about free speech? You’re censoring this party!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Person 2:&lt;/strong&gt; [Twitter/Facebook/Youtube/etc.] is a private platform! Free speech guarantees the right not to be jailed for what you say, &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; the right to have it on every platform you want.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So far as it goes, this is true. XKCD’s explanation is completely right on the legal merits:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://xkcd.com/1357/"&gt;&lt;img src="http://www.explainxkcd.com/wiki/images/a/ae/free_speech.png" title="XKCD 1357: Free Speech" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But while this is all true in some sense, it also seems to me to be missing the larger and &lt;em&gt;much&lt;/em&gt; more important point. Namely: the whole reason we have these arguments—and the reason people tend to think as they do about the “free speech” question in these situations, legally nonsensical or not—is that we have outsourced the vast majority of our public discourse to these private platforms.&lt;a href="#fn1" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref1"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Twitter and Facebook have become the &lt;em&gt;de facto&lt;/em&gt; public fora of the 2010s, with Google’s search results and Wikipedia’s summaries taking similarly authoritative roles on what &lt;em&gt;exists&lt;/em&gt; and what &lt;em&gt;is true&lt;/em&gt;. Not that most people would put it that way, but it remains true: if something isn’t in Google search, it might as well not exist on the internet, and therefore for many people &lt;em&gt;at all&lt;/em&gt;. Likewise with Wikipedia’s summaries: the admonitions of every college professor in the world notwithstanding, what Wikipedia says has an undeniable authority. And when someone is blacklisted from Twitter or Facebook, their ability to be heard at all by internet users as a block is &lt;em&gt;dramatically&lt;/em&gt; curtailed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This centralization of discussion and information into a few private platforms has a great many downsides. But perhaps chief among them is that we have ceded major aspects of our public and civic life to private platforms, and their interests are not the interests of the public good. They are driven almost entirely by the profit motive, or (possibly even worse at times) by nebulous and chimeric ideologies that treat “connecting people [digitally]” or “organizing the world’s information” as inherent and superlative goods. So when someone has their page removed from Facebook, or their website blacklisted from Google, there is a real sense in which they &lt;em&gt;have&lt;/em&gt; been removed from public discourse and&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the purposes of this post, I could not care less what the major internet companies do or don’t show on their platforms. Instead, I worry about our practice both as individuals and also as communities-of-practice—churches, associations, and so on—of abdicating our responsibility to maintain real public and civic lives in our local places in favor of letting these corporate giants do the work for us. I worry about the costs of letting Google and Facebook replace genuine public fora in our lives. I worry about the long-term effect of letting supranational megacorporations driven by that toxic combination of profit motive and nonsensical ideologies set the terms of our lives. I worry about the whole set of underlying structural and systematic moves that have made delisting on one of those platforms seem like a violation of the ideal of free speech.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I’ve said for many years in this space: we should work hard at reclaiming our lives from the tangle of the corporations. We should limit the way we both use and think about these platforms. We should read books, old and new, rather than simply rely on the Google results and Wikipedia summaries. We should have painful, awkward conversations and indeed arguments with neighbors and colleagues and family members rather than merely all-caps shouting at each other on Facebook or Twitter. We should carve out our own spaces on the internet, &lt;a href="http://tumblr.austinkleon.com/post/37863874092"&gt;owning our own turf&lt;/a&gt;; but more than that we should remember that even that is no substitute for the thicker (and yes, more painful, frustrating, and awkward!) communities and interactions of a church or a neighborhood or a town hall meeting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section class="footnotes"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn1"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Given the context in which I’m writing this, it’s probably helpful to say that I think InfoWars is a font of demonic lies. I’m a Christian; I mean that literally.&lt;a href="#fnref1" class="footnote-back"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 11 Aug 2018 10:35:00 -0400</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2018-08-11:/2018/free-speech.html</guid><category>writing</category><category>ethics</category><category>politics</category><category>social media</category><category>Twitter</category><category>indie web</category></item><item><title>On Tweeting (Instead of Writing)</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2018/on-tweeting-instead-of-writing.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;I ended up spending about half an hour on Twitter this morning, a fair bit of it writing out tweets in response to things I’d bumped into. This is not a thing I do often, especially anymore. (There was a time, back in the days of App.net, when I spent a &lt;em&gt;lot&lt;/em&gt; of time conversing in a Twitter-like context.) And as I was thinking on it afterwards, I realized why I don’t often do it anymore: I come away from it dissatisfied. I’d have been &lt;em&gt;far&lt;/em&gt; happier working on the blog post I had started before opening Twitter (for something related to that post).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Twitter is an interesting medium, but I consistently find that if I attempt to have conversations on Twitter—especially about important topics—I come away frustrated with my inability to say clearly what I mean, and concerned by the very real possibility of being misunderstood by someone who has too little of the context.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because Twitter is like standing in the middle of the largest party on earth and &lt;span style="font-variant: small-caps; font-style: italic; font-weight: bold;"&gt;shouting at the top of your lungs&lt;/span&gt; to the person next to you. What you’re saying might make total sense in the context of that specific conversation, and if you could explain the context would make sense to the other people in the room, and yet be open to wild and massive misinterpretation or misunderstanding. Worse, because you are &lt;span style="font-variant: small-caps; font-style: italic; font-weight: bold;"&gt;shouting at the top of your lungs&lt;/span&gt; (not to mention limited in the weirdest way to 280-character blurbs strung together into something only vaguely resembling coherence), it’s difficult to communicate well even to the person you’re talking to.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wrote early this year that we should all &lt;a href="https://www.chriskrycho.com/2018/tweet-less-blog-more.html"&gt;tweet less and blog more&lt;/a&gt; and I was reminded forcefully of that. Tweetstorms are worse than blog posts. The fact that more people are apt to interact with them is a &lt;em&gt;downside&lt;/em&gt;, not an &lt;em&gt;upside&lt;/em&gt;, because people are apt to interact with your least articulate, least coherent, least contextualized version of an idea, and they’re encouraged by the medium to respond to it with snappy comebacks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m not quite at the point where I want to just get off of Twitter entirely—but I’m not far from it either. I have no longer any desire to &lt;em&gt;converse&lt;/em&gt; there, and find decreasing profit in reading anything there but links to interesting essays or blog posts. I’m seriously considering using it as a write-only medium and just piping the users with the highest signal of interesting links &lt;a href="https://feedbin.com/blog/2018/01/11/feedbin-is-the-best-way-to-read-twitter/" title="“Feedbin is the Best Way to Read Twitter”"&gt;right into my &lt;abbr&gt;RSS&lt;/abbr&gt; feed&lt;/a&gt; and having done with it.&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 03 May 2018 07:30:00 -0400</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2018-05-03:/2018/on-tweeting-instead-of-writing.html</guid><category>twitter</category><category>social media</category><category>writing</category><category>rss</category></item><item><title>The Value of Silence</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2017/the-value-of-silence.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Over the past year or so, I’ve increasingly become persuaded of the importance of times of silence for clear thinking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While I’ve spent the last several years listening to podcasts in much of my walking and running time, I’ve started blocking out times in which I’m &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; listening to things that way—times dedicated either to just instrumental music, or simply to silence. This goes for more than those walks and runs. I’ve also been thinking about driving time, which I likewise once filled with thought, but which in recent years I have, again, filled with podcasts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I used to take &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; my runs in silence. I often drove in silence or with only instrumental music. I moved away from that somewhat in my years in North Carolina, in part because I discovered a great many podcasts I enjoyed, and in part because it was a way of sustaining mental focus when I had run the same routes too many times. Soon, it bled into my pomodoro walks and into nearly all my drives as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But much of my best thinking happened in those silences.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I need that space for letting my mind tease out questions and issues I’m thinking on. So: while not eliminating podcasts, I have been intentionally carving out more and more time again for silence. Pomodoro walks, runs, drives. Times when I simply listen to interesting music and think.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The need for silence goes beyond merely podcasts for me. I’ve continued to think about the role of Twitter in my life, the amount of time I spend looking at RSS feeds, and even my enjoyment of times in e.g. Slack communities I participate in. Twitter I have long limited strictly—it’s &lt;a href="http://blog.ayjay.org/joe-posnanski-wises-up/"&gt;an enormous and often unproductive time sink&lt;/a&gt;—but even RSS (which is much better for thought in nearly every way!) and healthy Slack communities can be &lt;em&gt;connecting&lt;/em&gt; in ways that actually &lt;a href="https://pinboard.in/u:ayjay/b:c7d2be58b366"&gt;inhibit deep thought&lt;/a&gt;. We need a degree of solitude and silence to think well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thus, though each of those is often a good source of information, and I enjoy them, I am increasingly aware of the curious ways they interact with my ability to think clearly and deeply about things. And about the ways they shift the &lt;em&gt;arena&lt;/em&gt; of my thinking clearly and deeply about things. Pose me a question and I’m apt to answer it, but the way I answer it in a Slack chat is different from—and often worse than—the way I’d answer it if I took the time to write it up as a blog post, and that in turn different from how I would approach it if composing a medium-length essay.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I am sussing out where and how I want to draw those lines, where I want to &lt;a href="https://thefrailestthing.com/2017/11/18/the-ethics-of-technological-mediation/"&gt;pay my attention&lt;/a&gt;, because &lt;a href="http://iasc-culture.org/THR/channels/Infernal_Machine/2015/03/79-theses-on-technology-for-disputation/"&gt;attention is indeed something we pay&lt;/a&gt;. Fewer podcasts, less time in ephemeral media (even including blogging); more time in books and long essays and in writing itself as a means of coming to understanding. More time, indeed, scribbling notes in paper notebooks, for the ways that time spent thinking &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; disconnected from the internet shapes us. More time, when I’m writing in a digital form, with the wifi off. And hopefully, as a result, more and better thinking.&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 26 Nov 2017 19:30:00 -0500</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2017-11-26:/2017/the-value-of-silence.html</guid><category>writing</category><category>social media</category></item></channel></rss>