<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Chris Krycho - social media</title><link>http://v4.chriskrycho.com/</link><description></description><lastBuildDate>Mon, 04 Nov 2019 22:00:00 -0500</lastBuildDate><item><title>A Note on Attention</title><link>http://v4.chriskrycho.com/2019/a-note-on-attention.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;a href="https://v4.chriskrycho.com/2018/assumed-audiences.html"&gt;Assumed Audience&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/b&gt; written with an eye to folks willing to think a little bit harder about &lt;em&gt;attention&lt;/em&gt;—something we &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; need to get better at.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Walking through the airport this morning, I found that my attention itself had caught my attention. I have had &lt;a href="https://thefrailestthing.com/2018/08/03/spectrum-of-attention/"&gt;this bit&lt;/a&gt; from L. M. Sacasas bouncing around in my head for the last month or so:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The ability to take photographs expands (and limits) the hiker’s perceptive repertoire—it creates new possibilities, the landscape now appears differently to our hiker. Smartphone in hand, the hiker might now perceive the world as field of possible images. This may, for example, direct attention up from the path toward the horizon, causing even our experienced hiker to stumble. We may be tempted to say, consequently, that the hiker is no longer paying attention, that the device has distracted him. But this is, at best, only partly true. The hiker is still paying attention. In fact, he may be paying very close, directed attention, hunting for that perfect image. But his attention is of a very different sort than the “in the flow” attention of a hiker on the move. They are now missing some aspects of the surroundings, but picking up on others. Without the smartphone in hand, the hiker may not stumble, but they may not notice a particularly striking vista either.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://v4.chriskrycho.com/2019/photography-ing-again.html"&gt;Yesterday’s bit of history&lt;/a&gt; might give you to how I ended up walking through Denver International Airport with my camera in hand today, taking in the architecture with a rather different eye than I usually do. My normal path through the airport is &lt;em&gt;merely&lt;/em&gt; utilitarian: get to the gate, fill my water bottle, hit the bathroom, grab a seat and knock out some work while I wait to board. Today, though, I found myself considering the structures of the facility, its décor, the little touches architects and designers had put in place to (or at least, to attempt to) humanize what might otherwise be a terribly forbidding structure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(Airports are among the chief edifices of our modern, technological regime. They are not merely travel hubs, but miniature shopping malls. They require not only the massive infrastructure that supports aircraft themselves, but also the perhaps even greater infrastructure to support the cars we park there, the workers who cycle through, the food to be eaten, and so on. They are, I think, under-appreciated as signifiers of our default approach of technological mastery over the world. More on this, perhaps, another day.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The very act of carrying a camera with me changed my perceptual relationship to the airport. And why? Because the device around my neck prompted (that is: my choice to carry it with me prompted) a shift in my attention. I left Sacasas’ words above just as he wrote them, focused on the way a smartphone shifts the attention of his hypothetical hiker. The smartphone, by dint of its ubiquity and its versatility, does indeed (and &lt;em&gt;more especially&lt;/em&gt; than other devices) shift our attention. Not least, I think, because for most of us, there is no conscious choice to bring it with us, as there was for me with my camera this morning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The phone both draws our attention and diffuses it. For all that having the smartphone in my pocket may increase my attentiveness to the beautiful vista on a hike, it may also tempt me to disengage entirely from the hike: not only to consider the environment in a different light, but to send my mind across the world to other places, other activities entirely. The contrast with a dedicated device like the camera I brought with me is illuminating. Certainly a camera shifts my relationship to a hike, just as it does to a stroll through the airport. But it does so by way of &lt;em&gt;focusing&lt;/em&gt; my attention, and drawing it into aspects of the hike that I might otherwise miss. That focusing is a tradeoff: as Sacasas notes, it means there are things I notice which I might not have had I not had a camera in hand; but also that there are aspects of a hike that I do not enjoy as I would had I no camera to hand—precisely because my attention is focused by the device. But the difference between the way a single-purpose technology affects our attention and the way a device with greater versatility affects our attention is rather stark.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have an increasing degree of affection for an interest in devices dedicated to a single job. Some of this is simply that, as good as smartphones are at many tasks, a purpose-built piece can often serve better than a jack-of-all-trades production. As my friend &lt;a href="https://www.stephencarradini.com"&gt;Stephen&lt;/a&gt; has often lamented: the iPod was a better portable music player—in the sense of doing that one specific job—than any iPhone! I could say the same of my &lt;a href="https://us.kobobooks.com/collections/ereaders/products/kobo-aura-one-limited-edition"&gt;Kobo&lt;/a&gt;… and far more for a paper book! I find the experience of using those task-tailored technologies much more &lt;em&gt;enjoyable&lt;/em&gt; than our ubiquitous and flexible—and therefore ultimately &lt;em&gt;distracting&lt;/em&gt;—smartphones. They shape my attention very differently, and (I think), &lt;em&gt;better&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 04 Nov 2019 22:00:00 -0500</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:v4.chriskrycho.com,2019-11-04:/2019/a-note-on-attention.html</guid><category>attention</category><category>photography</category><category>social media</category><category>wisdom</category></item><item><title>From My Sent Folder: On Social Media Tradeoffs</title><link>http://v4.chriskrycho.com/2019/from-my-sent-folder-on-social-media-tradeoffs.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;a href="https://v4.chriskrycho.com/2018/assumed-audiences.html"&gt;Assumed Audience&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/b&gt; anyone &lt;em&gt;willing&lt;/em&gt; to think hard about social media and its place in our lives.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;I got a particularly thoughtful email from a friend about his family’s use of Facebook in response to &lt;a href="https://v4.chriskrycho.com/2019/breaking-up-with-social-media.html"&gt;yesterday’s essay&lt;/a&gt;. I’ve reproduced most of my response here because I think it’s a helpful extension on that essay.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I (a) totally hear where you’re coming from, and deeply sympathize; and (b) deeply disagree about the notion that they’re “just tools – not good or evil in themselves.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I agree in the strictest sense that the tools are not evil in and of themselves. But I think that particular framing is actually extremely misleading. Tools have &lt;em&gt;shapes&lt;/em&gt;, and those shapes form us in ways that may prove out to be particular bad. The usual example is: use a hammer for hours a day every day, and you’ll end up with calluses and quite possibly some hilariously out-of-proportion forearms if you don’t figure out how to be ambidextrous at least for hammering. That tools are not inherently moral does not mean they’re &lt;em&gt;neutral&lt;/em&gt;. (I also am not persuaded that tools are themselves always &lt;em&gt;morally&lt;/em&gt; neutral, but that’s another discussion and a subtler one.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the case of the social media tools, I &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt; think there are differences in both degree (the extent to which they shape us) and kind (the particular shapes they press us into as we use them). Thus my willingness to work for LinkedIn and my &lt;em&gt;un&lt;/em&gt;willingness to work for Twitter or Facebook! And with that in mind, I do agree that the tradeoffs around Facebook can look very different than those around Twitter today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What’s more, I’d go so far as to say that a service much like Facebook but retooled in certain very important ways could be a much-less-alloyed good in the world! (There are no unalloyed goods in our fallen reality, of course.) A service that was less interested in &lt;em&gt;driving user attention&lt;/em&gt; and therefore constantly working in ways that actively undermine people’s self-control and ability to disengage could have most (probably all!) the upsides Facebook offers you and your family today, with few of the horrid downsides we’re seeing with it at the macro scale and few (if any) of the downsides I have felt with it personally at the micro scale. It’s those vicious little loops driving me to check obsessively that I want out of—not the ability to have geographically distributed people able to stay in touch and indeed even to connect, of the sort you and I have benefited from so much.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;None of that is an argument for everyone to get off of Facebook. I certainly think you and your family have very &lt;em&gt;good&lt;/em&gt; reasons to be there. Rather, it’s more that the more of us who make the kinds of moves I’m making, the more it opens back up the &lt;em&gt;possibility&lt;/em&gt; that those communities could form in other spaces, and creates the &lt;em&gt;reminder&lt;/em&gt; for others that in fact many people are &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; in those spaces. It’s a very long play, for sure, but, you know: &lt;a href="https://winningslowly.org"&gt;winning slowly&lt;/a&gt; and all that jazz.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In that regard it’s not so different from my rejection of Amazon: I’m under no misapprehension that I’m going to have any meaningful effect on the company itself, and in fact I have friends who I think are &lt;em&gt;very wise&lt;/em&gt; to continue using it because e.g. Prime eliminates needless frictions from their very challenging lives. It’s that my opting out allows me to support &lt;em&gt;other&lt;/em&gt;—healthier!—businesses and hopefully keep them going.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All of which is kind of a long way of saying: these are &lt;em&gt;wisdom&lt;/em&gt; questions, and I think that wisdom not only allows but indeed &lt;em&gt;dictates&lt;/em&gt; different courses for different people.&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 14 Jun 2019 08:30:00 -0400</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:v4.chriskrycho.com,2019-06-14:/2019/from-my-sent-folder-on-social-media-tradeoffs.html</guid><category>social media</category><category>from my sent folder</category><category>ethics</category><category>wisdom</category></item><item><title>Breaking Up With Social Media</title><link>http://v4.chriskrycho.com/2019/breaking-up-with-social-media.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;a href="https://v4.chriskrycho.com/2018/assumed-audiences.html"&gt;Assumed Audience&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/b&gt; anyone &lt;em&gt;willing&lt;/em&gt; to think hard about social media and its place in our lives.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section id="i.-the-itch" class="level2"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;I. The Itch&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I began writing this post from our vacation bedroom in Jamaica, about five days before I could possibly publish it: before we left, I shut down the machines which can generate new versions of my site. I wished, as I started this post, that I had an equally effective measure for cutting off access to social media on this trip.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I tried, of course. Before we left on June 1, I removed Slack and Discord from my iPad (I had long since taken them off my phone). I likewise removed email from my phone, and I have also mostly been leaving my phone in our room. I kept an email client on my iPad, but I have checked my email only once a day or so—mostly in the interest of clearing my inbox, but also because the newsletters I subscribe to make for very good reading materials.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All of this preparation was good. It worked well. The first few days of our vacation were filled, blissfully, with mental silence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then I signed into Twitter on June 3, as news started breaking from Apple’s &lt;a href="https://developer.apple.com/wwdc19/"&gt;&lt;abbr title="World Wide Developer Conference"&gt;WWDC&lt;/abbr&gt;&lt;/a&gt; event. It was fun seeing people’s reactions, and I learned a fair bit about &lt;a href="https://developer.apple.com/xcode/swiftui/"&gt;news which excites me a great deal&lt;/a&gt;—people were already digging into the new tools and tweeting about them! But it also flipped back on the part of my brain that has been trained (by 14 years of using first Facebook and then Twitter) to &lt;em&gt;obsessively check social media&lt;/em&gt;. Mid-afternoon on June 7, I recognized the difference this was making in my mental life. (Yes, it took me most of a week to see it clearly; social media’s effects are insidious.) I signed back out of Twitter’s web client and committed not to sign back in until after our vacation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have felt throughout the ensuing days—especially the first—what I can only describe as a mental &lt;em&gt;itch&lt;/em&gt;: and it can be scratched only by signing into Twitter, and skimming down through the things people have said, and clicking the little heart button on some of them, and seeing if anyone has interacted with any of my own posts along the way, and trying to say something clever or interesting to elicit more such responses, and refreshing the feed, and skimming down through the things people have said, and…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I dislike the feeling intensely. The itch itself is a distraction, and scratching the itch would produce only more (and worse) distraction. As Craig Mod &lt;a href="https://craigmod.com/roden/027/"&gt;described it&lt;/a&gt; recently:&lt;a href="#fn1" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref1" role="doc-noteref"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Something fires off in the back of the skull, and then again. No conscious complicity, all autonomous, micro-stimulations. Triggered by: A scroll, a reload, a pull to refresh, a like, a share, the right headline. I can now pinpoint this sequence of involuntary response to be the tiny &lt;em&gt;physio&lt;/em&gt;logical loop my body runs through when using Twitter or Instagram.…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I find the tiny loop problem to be terrifying. Tiny loops tend to be perfectly designed to satisfy the id’s raw impulses. That raw id is great fuel for creativity. The concern I have coming back and feeling the loops again for the first time in a long time is: if you’re not careful, tweets and their ilk can burn all your fuel with nothing to show.…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This pain is a withdrawal symptom. But if you get over that compulsion for info-stimulation, you are presented with an opportunity to replace the tiny loops with much more rewarding activities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="ii.-the-costs" class="level2"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;II. The Costs&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have long observed that my use of Twitter hijacks my mental habits in many other contexts.&lt;a href="#fn2" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref2" role="doc-noteref"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; I find myself responding to a book’s ideas not with consideration but with ideas for clever or snarky tweets. (This happened to me multiple times on this trip, including after I had already drafted and repeatedly revised this post!) It is not only Twitter which can have this effect, of course: I have experienced it with blogging as well. But I find that this particularly twisted, &lt;em&gt;distracted&lt;/em&gt; form of thinking increases in direct proportion to the amount I use Twitter, and much less so with other forms of writing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Twitter misaligns my mind even when I am away from it. It discourages &lt;em&gt;thought&lt;/em&gt;. As Mod put it, “if you’re not careful, tweets and their ilk can burn all your fuel with nothing to show.” Exactly that. I spend time on Twitter and come out feeling like I have done &lt;em&gt;something&lt;/em&gt; but in reality the cycles spent there are pure waste. No thought. No writing. No learning.&lt;a href="#fn3" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref3" role="doc-noteref"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; No time spent with my family or friends. Nothing but more fodder for the &lt;a href="https://stratechery.com/2018/data-factories/"&gt;data factory&lt;/a&gt; and the advertisement money it generates.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The counter-arguments mount up, of course—as they do whenever we think of eliminating a pleasurable vice:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;But how would I interact with other people in the Rust and Swift communities around ideas or questions I have?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Wouldn’t it be a waste of slowly-built-up influence in the Rust and Ember and TypeScript communities to be absent from that space?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;…but it turns out, those are the only questions. Both of them are easily answered, too. The aforementioned communities exist, &lt;em&gt;and exist in much richer ways&lt;/em&gt;, in contexts besides Twitter—forums, chat, etc. Those other contexts have their own dysfunctions (chat particularly so), but those I will address in their own ways. I can use what influence I do have in those communities more effectively by writing here, answering questions elsewhere, and building software or writing docs or the like. There is simply no sense in which I &lt;em&gt;must&lt;/em&gt; be on Twitter for professional reasons.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moreover, very little of what happens on Twitter is of any lasting import. There is a great deal of Thought Leading,&lt;a href="#fn4" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref4" role="doc-noteref"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;4&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; but the medium discourages careful, rich, context-sensitive writing: just what is necessary for real work (and not just screaming mobs or fanboying). This is equally as true of software development as of theology. The medium dominates the message. Twitter threads, as I have &lt;a href="https://v4.chriskrycho.com/2018/on-tweeting-instead-of-writing.html"&gt;noted before&lt;/a&gt; (and see also &lt;a href="https://v4.chriskrycho.com/2018/tweet-less-blog-more.html"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://v4.chriskrycho.com/2017/the-value-of-silence.html"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;), are much worse than something like a blog post for their intended purpose. The defining feature of Twitter—the &lt;em&gt;reply&lt;/em&gt;—is a bug and not a feature. I &lt;em&gt;love&lt;/em&gt; thoughtful replies to my writing… which is &lt;em&gt;precisely why I don’t have comments here but encourage people to email me instead&lt;/em&gt;—and Twitter has a far, far worse signal-to-noise ratio than do blog comments. Where’s the upside?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mod again:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think we’ll look back with shock on many “fundamentals” of the internet as it exists today. I’m still amazed that any private organization would allow unfiltered public commenting. I remain totally unconvinced of its benefits. Twitter, in this sense, is just insanity — an endless stream of public comment posturing and signaling and, largely, screaming. Dumb dumb. Basic ’net folly 101.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If I still feel a bit &lt;a href="https://thefrailestthing.com/2019/06/08/devils-bargain/"&gt;the way L. M. Sacasas does&lt;/a&gt;,&lt;a href="#fn5" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref5" role="doc-noteref"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;5&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; too—&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ditching the platform and going indie, as it were, works better when you’ve already got a large audience that is going to follow you where ever you go or an established community (a convivial society, I’d dare say), online and off, with which to sustain your intellectual life. I’m pretty sure I don’t quite have the former, and I’ve struggled to find that latter, making my way as an independent scholar of sorts these last several years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But again, this is not to say that Alan is wrong, only that my counting the cost is a more conflicted affair.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;—well, so be it. For as he notes himself, the toll &lt;em&gt;will&lt;/em&gt; be paid, one way or another:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In any case, I can feel Twitter working on me as I’ve begun to use it more frequently of late and allowed myself to tweet as well as read. I can feel it working on me in much the same way that, in Tolkien’s world, the wearer’s of the Ring can feel it working on them. It leaves one feeling weary, thin, exposed, morally compromised, divided, etc., while deeply distorting one’s view of reality. And, as far as I’m concerned, there are no Tom Bombadil’s, immune to the ring’s power, among us in this case.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="iii.-complicity" class="level2"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;III. Complicity&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Counting the cost is complicated in another way for me, too: To what extent can I do this &lt;em&gt;because&lt;/em&gt; of my use of Twitter? This site’s audience includes readers who first encountered me and my work &lt;em&gt;there&lt;/em&gt;. Even my freedom to leave social media benefits from having used those tools. I cannot escape a degree of complicity in the degradations and distortions that social media have wrought in our culture and our public and our civic life. The best I can say for myself is that I have consciously chosen to eschew click-driven writing for half a decade, whether using Twitter or no. As regards that inescapable complicity, all any of us can do is acknowledge our faults—or, as &lt;a href="https://biblehub.com/james/5-16.htm"&gt;my faith&lt;/a&gt; would &lt;a href="https://biblehub.com/1_john/1-9.htm"&gt;have it&lt;/a&gt;, confess and repent of our sins—and seek to make amends.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And there is yet more at stake here. Twitter (like Facebook) is more than merely &lt;em&gt;complicit&lt;/em&gt; in the transformation of our world into an attention economy. They have &lt;em&gt;driven&lt;/em&gt; it. Their technocratic, restraint-less approach to the world is foolish—at best. And they are unrepentant; “wicked” may thus be not too strong a word.&lt;a href="#fn6" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref6" role="doc-noteref"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;6&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; Continuing to use these services only further cements their primacy. As Alan Jacobs &lt;a href="https://blog.ayjay.org/to-put-the-point-plainly/"&gt;put it&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The decision to be on Twitter (or Facebook, etc.) is not simply a personal choice. It has run-on effects for you but also for others. When you use the big social media platforms you contribute to their power and influence, and you deplete the energy and value of the open web. You make things worse for everyone. I truly believe that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even insofar as I do get value from being on Twitter—being able to throw out a question about Rust or Swift or Ember or TypeScript, confident that I will get a knowledgeable answer—I increasingly wonder about the power and social dynamics in play. Is it &lt;em&gt;good&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;right&lt;/em&gt; that, because I have blogged, have worked on open source projects, and have run a successful podcast, I have a greater degree of access? While I have worked hard at those projects, my success in them does not make my questions or interests &lt;em&gt;more important&lt;/em&gt; than anyone else’s. Put more bluntly: I do not &lt;em&gt;deserve&lt;/em&gt; the attention of Swift compiler developers or Rust or Ember core team members or the TypeScript &lt;abbr title="product manager"&gt;PM&lt;/abbr&gt;. But I can get that attention, and easily, on Twitter. Some of this is ordinary human social dynamics: earned social trust and so on. But I wonder if Twitter does not &lt;em&gt;heighten&lt;/em&gt; the effect. Certainly it seems to me that it may.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="iv.-the-end-and-a-new-beginning" class="level2"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;IV. The End, and a New Beginning&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Leaving Twitter myself will not begin to undo all of that. But I can undercut, in some small way, the pressure so many other people&lt;a href="#fn7" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref7" role="doc-noteref"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;7&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; feel to be on Twitter for professional reasons. Insofar as my own public work succeeds without Twitter, I hope that success helps others come to feel the same freedom. Something more like the &lt;a href="http://tantek.com/2010/281/b1/what-is-the-open-web"&gt;open web&lt;/a&gt; and the old indie blogger network ethos is a step in the right direction—not in spite of its frictions; rather &lt;a href="https://blog.ayjay.org/scale-is-the-enemy/"&gt;&lt;em&gt;because&lt;/em&gt; it does not scale&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And more than that: getting &lt;a href="https://buttondown.email/chriskrycho/archive/the-slow-web-and-the-limits-of-solutions/"&gt;offline entirely&lt;/a&gt; at times and for seasons. Remembering the rhythms of life common to all human beings up till a few short years ago. Quietly reading books and talking with friends. It’s time for many more of us to embrace the kind of social media monasticism &lt;a href="https://thefrailestthing.com/2018/03/27/vows-of-digital-poverty/"&gt;Sacasas outlined&lt;/a&gt; in the midst of the #DeleteFacebook movement (and which Stephen and I have talked about so much &lt;a href="https://winningslowly.org/season-7.html"&gt;this season of Winning Slowly&lt;/a&gt;). I want my attention back, but even more importantly I want to show that &lt;i&gt;this is not all that can or should be&lt;/i&gt;. There are alternative paths we might yet take.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So: I have deleted all my tweets save one: a link to this post. I am doing much the same with Facebook and LinkedIn.&lt;a href="#fn8" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref8" role="doc-noteref"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;8&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; I hope you’ll consider doing something similar!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Going forward, I will be doing much more writing here. I will also continue to publish &lt;a href="https://buttondown.email/chriskrycho"&gt;my newsletter&lt;/a&gt;, normally on a weekly basis. I will still be &lt;a href="https://v4.chriskrycho.com/podcasts"&gt;podcasting&lt;/a&gt;. I hope (and expect) to be writing more full-on essays—the area more than any other where I have felt the drain from social media’s interference. And I will be working on &lt;a href="https://buttondown.email/rewrite"&gt;rewrite&lt;/a&gt;! And if you’d like to get in touch, you can always &lt;a href="mailto:hello@chriskrycho.com"&gt;email me&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn1" role="doc-endnote"&gt;&lt;p&gt;in a newsletter he published after I had already written two full drafts of this post: it was confirmation, not inspiration.&lt;a href="#fnref1" class="footnote-back" role="doc-backlink"&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn2" role="doc-endnote"&gt;&lt;p&gt;So do a number of other platforms, whose use I am reconsidering as well—mostly anything &lt;em&gt;chat&lt;/em&gt;-like.&lt;a href="#fnref2" class="footnote-back" role="doc-backlink"&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn3" role="doc-endnote"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Not &lt;em&gt;truly&lt;/em&gt; learned. A new fact found, perhaps, but facts acquired are not the same as learning done. More rarely, a link to a place I &lt;em&gt;can&lt;/em&gt; learn something. But such links exist in many places!&lt;a href="#fnref3" class="footnote-back" role="doc-backlink"&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn4" role="doc-endnote"&gt;&lt;p&gt;and, worse but in far greater quantity, &lt;em&gt;wannabe&lt;/em&gt; Thought Leading&lt;a href="#fnref4" class="footnote-back" role="doc-backlink"&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn5" role="doc-endnote"&gt;&lt;p&gt;in a post, I note, which I had not seen when I wrote the &lt;em&gt;first&lt;/em&gt; draft of this post! There is something in the air right now, and I’m glad of it.&lt;a href="#fnref5" class="footnote-back" role="doc-backlink"&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn6" role="doc-endnote"&gt;&lt;p&gt;conclusions I have drawn the more starkly through thinking-out-loud about it with my friend &lt;a href="https://stephencarradini.com"&gt;Stephen&lt;/a&gt; throughout &lt;a href="https://winningslowly.org"&gt;Winning Slowly&lt;/a&gt; seasons &lt;a href="https://winningslowly.org/season-6.html"&gt;6&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://winningslowly.org/season-7.html"&gt;7&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;a href="#fnref6" class="footnote-back" role="doc-backlink"&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn7" role="doc-endnote"&gt;&lt;p&gt;I initially wrote “everyone” instead of “so many other people” here, but I noticed that that’s simply (very!) wrong: it’s central to the vicious cycle of pressure that social media &lt;em&gt;creates&lt;/em&gt;. “Everyone is here; you’ll miss out on such important things!” is &lt;em&gt;the&lt;/em&gt; lie of these platforms.&lt;a href="#fnref7" class="footnote-back" role="doc-backlink"&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn8" role="doc-endnote"&gt;&lt;p&gt;While I do have reservations about LinkedIn, they are different both in kind and in degree than my concerns about other social media platforms—as my taking a job there just a few months ago should indicate! I would &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; have taken a job with Facebook or Twitter. I will probably elaborate on this at some point, as I think it’s worth tracing out how and why I see these as meaningfully different!&lt;a href="#fnref8" class="footnote-back" role="doc-backlink"&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 13 Jun 2019 15:15:00 -0400</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:v4.chriskrycho.com,2019-06-13:/2019/breaking-up-with-social-media.html</guid><category>social media</category><category>writing</category><category>attention</category><category>ethics</category></item><item><title>Social Media, Remote Work, and Vocation</title><link>http://v4.chriskrycho.com/2019/social-media-remote-work-and-vocation.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;a href="https://v4.chriskrycho.com/2018/assumed-audiences.html"&gt;Assumed Audience&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/b&gt; Anyone interested in changing dynamics around work, especially “remote” work as enabled by the internet.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I spent the week with a bunch of internet friends at &lt;a href="https://emberconf.com"&gt;EmberConf&lt;/a&gt;—and I have been mulling (yet more) on the dynamics of social media, embodiment, attention, and presence. This is the content of my &lt;a href="https://buttondown.email/chriskrycho"&gt;email newsletter&lt;/a&gt; for the week—not my normal habit, but this piece lives in both worlds, I think.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I spend a non-trivial part of my day every work day in “closed” social media spaces: a handful of community Slack organizations and my work Slack, a couple of open source software Discord communities, and a Twist subscription where Stephen and I coordinate our &lt;a href="https://winningslowly.org"&gt;Winning Slowly&lt;/a&gt;. I still use Twitter—but decreasingly so: I pop on once or twice a day, skim through my feed, and close it out. I almost never use Facebook at all: it simply stopped being useful &lt;em&gt;at all&lt;/em&gt; in the last few years. I check LinkedIn… mostly because my day job is to support that app. I never use &lt;em&gt;any&lt;/em&gt; other social media anymore—Instagram I dropped years ago; others are dead (App.net) or never caught on for me past an initial experiment (Ello).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Going to EmberConf highlighted for me both the deep value of those platforms and their stark limitations. The deep value, because I spent a lot of time this week with people I have come to consider colleagues and indeed friends. Their stark limitations, because for all that we spend a great deal of time conversing with each other online—planning, arguing, helping each other, joking—there is something profoundly different, profoundly &lt;em&gt;better&lt;/em&gt;, about standing or sitting by from someone and hearing their words (not merely reading them). We are embodied beings and disembodied interactions simply are not the same.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am increasingly a proponent, and a loud one, for remote work. I have worked remotely myself for over six years now: over half my career to date. I have said often in the past few years that remote work is now a non-negotiable for me: it is too important in my family life for me to do otherwise. Remote work is profoundly empowering in many ways. It enables me to collaborate with peers around the country and around the world. It gives me more time, by way of eliminating a commute. It affords me the ability to simply turn off the distractions and work deeply.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perhaps most valuable of all to me, it allows me to be present with my family—to have been there as my daughters learned to walk and to speak; to be able, when my dear wife needed a break from the potty-training, to &lt;em&gt;give her that break&lt;/em&gt;; to give both my wife and my daughters my attention when they need it (and not only in hours deemed convenient by an employer)—in short to give those I love most what they deserve from me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I will not willingly give up those benefits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But notice: it is precisely a matter of my &lt;em&gt;presence&lt;/em&gt; that is at issue here. The difference is not in whether my embodied nature matters, but where it matters most. I am grateful for my various remote employers these past few years, and I aim (and have aimed) always to honor my employers by doing my best work for them. But I owe no employer the hours or the attention that belong first of all to my family.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We speak sometimes of “vocation”—but mean by it almost always “our mode of employment.” The word means more than that. My callings are manifold and pluriform, and so are yours. I am first of all a follower of Jesus: the calling that shapes all the others. I am then one of God’s people, then a husband, then a father, then a son and brother, then a friend, then an employee. (If that ordering seems odd, well, it always has: even to Jesus’ first followers.) My vocations are broader and deeper than merely “a man who writes software for LinkedIn” (glad though I am of that one)—and the others, rightly understood, demand much more of me than does my career.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am glad, therefore, of Slack and Discord, and to some degree even of Twitter (and, at times in the past, Facebook also). I have made friends there and done good work there. I am likewise grateful for the tools that make remote work possible. But I must not mistake those social media and tools for the truer goods for which they cannot substitute: sharing good food and drink with each other, and living out &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; our callings in the places where we find ourselves.&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 23 Mar 2019 16:25:00 -0400</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:v4.chriskrycho.com,2019-03-23:/2019/social-media-remote-work-and-vocation.html</guid><category>vocation</category><category>remote work</category><category>social media</category><category>embodiment</category></item><item><title>“Free Speech”</title><link>http://v4.chriskrycho.com/2018/free-speech.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Every time there is a major controversy about large platforms blocking or delisting some controversial figure, something like the following exchange follows:&lt;a href="#fn1" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref1" role="doc-noteref"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Person 1:&lt;/strong&gt; But what about free speech? You’re censoring this party!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Person 2:&lt;/strong&gt; [Twitter/Facebook/Youtube/etc.] is a private platform! Free speech guarantees the right not to be jailed for what you say, &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; the right to have it on every platform you want.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So far as it goes, this is true. XKCD’s explanation is completely right on the legal merits:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://xkcd.com/1357/"&gt;&lt;img src="http://www.explainxkcd.com/wiki/images/a/ae/free_speech.png" title="XKCD 1357: Free Speech" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But while this is all true in some sense, it also seems to me to be missing the larger and &lt;em&gt;much&lt;/em&gt; more important point. Namely: the whole reason we have these arguments—and the reason people tend to think as they do about the “free speech” question in these situations, legally nonsensical or not—is that we have outsourced the vast majority of our public discourse to these private platforms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Twitter and Facebook have become the &lt;em&gt;de facto&lt;/em&gt; public fora of the 2010s, with Google’s search results and Wikipedia’s summaries taking similarly authoritative roles on what &lt;em&gt;exists&lt;/em&gt; and what &lt;em&gt;is true&lt;/em&gt;. Not that most people would put it that way, but it remains true: if something isn’t in Google search, it might as well not exist on the internet, and therefore for many people &lt;em&gt;at all&lt;/em&gt;. Likewise with Wikipedia’s summaries: the admonitions of every college professor in the world notwithstanding, what Wikipedia says has an undeniable authority. And when someone is blacklisted from Twitter or Facebook, their ability to be heard at all by internet users as a block is &lt;em&gt;dramatically&lt;/em&gt; curtailed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This centralization of discussion and information into a few private platforms has a great many downsides. But perhaps chief among them is that we have ceded major aspects of our public and civic life to private platforms, and their interests are not the interests of the public good. They are driven almost entirely by the profit motive, or (possibly even worse at times) by nebulous and chimeric ideologies that treat “connecting people [digitally]” or “organizing the world’s information” as inherent and superlative goods. So when someone has their page removed from Facebook, or their website blacklisted from Google, there is a real sense in which they &lt;em&gt;have&lt;/em&gt; been removed from public discourse and their speech “silenced”—even if not in an illegal sense.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the purposes of this post, though, I could not care less what the major internet companies do or don’t show on their platforms. Instead, I worry about our practice both as individuals and also as communities-of-practice—churches, associations, and so on—of abdicating our responsibility to maintain real public and civic lives in our local places in favor of letting these corporate giants do the work for us. I worry about the costs of letting Google and Facebook replace genuine public fora in our lives. I worry about the long-term effect of letting supranational megacorporations driven by that toxic combination of profit motive and nonsensical ideologies set the terms of our lives. I worry about the whole set of underlying structural and systematic moves that have made delisting on one of those platforms seem like a violation of the ideal of free speech.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I’ve said for many years in this space: we should work hard at reclaiming our lives from the tangle of the corporations. We should limit the way we both use and think about these platforms. We should read books, old and new, rather than simply rely on the Google results and Wikipedia summaries. We should have painful, awkward conversations and indeed arguments with neighbors and colleagues and family members rather than merely all-caps shouting at each other on Facebook or Twitter. We should carve out our own spaces on the internet, &lt;a href="http://tumblr.austinkleon.com/post/37863874092"&gt;owning our own turf&lt;/a&gt;; but more than that we should remember that even that is no substitute for the thicker (and yes, more painful, frustrating, and awkward!) communities and interactions of a church or a neighborhood or a town hall meeting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn1" role="doc-endnote"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Given the context in which I’m writing this, it’s probably helpful to say that I think InfoWars is a font of demonic lies. I’m a Christian; I mean that literally.&lt;a href="#fnref1" class="footnote-back" role="doc-backlink"&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 11 Aug 2018 10:35:00 -0400</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:v4.chriskrycho.com,2018-08-11:/2018/free-speech.html</guid><category>writing</category><category>ethics</category><category>politics</category><category>social media</category><category>Twitter</category><category>indie web</category></item><item><title>On Tweeting (Instead of Writing)</title><link>http://v4.chriskrycho.com/2018/on-tweeting-instead-of-writing.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;I ended up spending about half an hour on Twitter this morning, a fair bit of it writing out tweets in response to things I’d bumped into. This is not a thing I do often, especially anymore. (There was a time, back in the days of App.net, when I spent a &lt;em&gt;lot&lt;/em&gt; of time conversing in a Twitter-like context.) And as I was thinking on it afterwards, I realized why I don’t often do it anymore: I come away from it dissatisfied. I’d have been &lt;em&gt;far&lt;/em&gt; happier working on the blog post I had started before opening Twitter (for something related to that post).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Twitter is an interesting medium, but I consistently find that if I attempt to have conversations on Twitter—especially about important topics—I come away frustrated with my inability to say clearly what I mean, and concerned by the very real possibility of being misunderstood by someone who has too little of the context.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because Twitter is like standing in the middle of the largest party on earth and &lt;span style="font-variant: small-caps; font-style: italic; font-weight: bold;"&gt;shouting at the top of your lungs&lt;/span&gt; to the person next to you. What you’re saying might make total sense in the context of that specific conversation, and if you could explain the context would make sense to the other people in the room, and yet be open to wild and massive misinterpretation or misunderstanding. Worse, because you are &lt;span style="font-variant: small-caps; font-style: italic; font-weight: bold;"&gt;shouting at the top of your lungs&lt;/span&gt; (not to mention limited in the weirdest way to 280-character blurbs strung together into something only vaguely resembling coherence), it’s difficult to communicate well even to the person you’re talking to.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wrote early this year that we should all &lt;a href="https://v4.chriskrycho.com/2018/tweet-less-blog-more.html"&gt;tweet less and blog more&lt;/a&gt; and I was reminded forcefully of that. Tweetstorms are worse than blog posts. The fact that more people are apt to interact with them is a &lt;em&gt;downside&lt;/em&gt;, not an &lt;em&gt;upside&lt;/em&gt;, because people are apt to interact with your least articulate, least coherent, least contextualized version of an idea, and they’re encouraged by the medium to respond to it with snappy comebacks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m not quite at the point where I want to just get off of Twitter entirely—but I’m not far from it either. I have no longer any desire to &lt;em&gt;converse&lt;/em&gt; there, and find decreasing profit in reading anything there but links to interesting essays or blog posts. I’m seriously considering using it as a write-only medium and just piping the users with the highest signal of interesting links &lt;a href="https://feedbin.com/blog/2018/01/11/feedbin-is-the-best-way-to-read-twitter/" title="“Feedbin is the Best Way to Read Twitter”"&gt;right into my &lt;abbr&gt;RSS&lt;/abbr&gt; feed&lt;/a&gt; and having done with it.&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 03 May 2018 07:30:00 -0400</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:v4.chriskrycho.com,2018-05-03:/2018/on-tweeting-instead-of-writing.html</guid><category>twitter</category><category>social media</category><category>writing</category><category>rss</category></item><item><title>The Value of Silence</title><link>http://v4.chriskrycho.com/2017/the-value-of-silence.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Over the past year or so, I’ve increasingly become persuaded of the importance of times of silence for clear thinking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While I’ve spent the last several years listening to podcasts in much of my walking and running time, I’ve started blocking out times in which I’m &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; listening to things that way—times dedicated either to just instrumental music, or simply to silence. This goes for more than those walks and runs. I’ve also been thinking about driving time, which I likewise once filled with thought, but which in recent years I have, again, filled with podcasts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I used to take &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; my runs in silence. I often drove in silence or with only instrumental music. I moved away from that somewhat in my years in North Carolina, in part because I discovered a great many podcasts I enjoyed, and in part because it was a way of sustaining mental focus when I had run the same routes too many times. Soon, it bled into my pomodoro walks and into nearly all my drives as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But much of my best thinking happened in those silences.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I need that space for letting my mind tease out questions and issues I’m thinking on. So: while not eliminating podcasts, I have been intentionally carving out more and more time again for silence. Pomodoro walks, runs, drives. Times when I simply listen to interesting music and think.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The need for silence goes beyond merely podcasts for me. I’ve continued to think about the role of Twitter in my life, the amount of time I spend looking at RSS feeds, and even my enjoyment of times in e.g. Slack communities I participate in. Twitter I have long limited strictly—it’s &lt;a href="http://blog.ayjay.org/joe-posnanski-wises-up/"&gt;an enormous and often unproductive time sink&lt;/a&gt;—but even RSS (which is much better for thought in nearly every way!) and healthy Slack communities can be &lt;em&gt;connecting&lt;/em&gt; in ways that actually &lt;a href="https://pinboard.in/u:ayjay/b:c7d2be58b366"&gt;inhibit deep thought&lt;/a&gt;. We need a degree of solitude and silence to think well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thus, though each of those is often a good source of information, and I enjoy them, I am increasingly aware of the curious ways they interact with my ability to think clearly and deeply about things. And about the ways they shift the &lt;em&gt;arena&lt;/em&gt; of my thinking clearly and deeply about things. Pose me a question and I’m apt to answer it, but the way I answer it in a Slack chat is different from—and often worse than—the way I’d answer it if I took the time to write it up as a blog post, and that in turn different from how I would approach it if composing a medium-length essay.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I am sussing out where and how I want to draw those lines, where I want to &lt;a href="https://thefrailestthing.com/2017/11/18/the-ethics-of-technological-mediation/"&gt;pay my attention&lt;/a&gt;, because &lt;a href="http://iasc-culture.org/THR/channels/Infernal_Machine/2015/03/79-theses-on-technology-for-disputation/"&gt;attention is indeed something we pay&lt;/a&gt;. Fewer podcasts, less time in ephemeral media (even including blogging); more time in books and long essays and in writing itself as a means of coming to understanding. More time, indeed, scribbling notes in paper notebooks, for the ways that time spent thinking &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; disconnected from the internet shapes us. More time, when I’m writing in a digital form, with the wifi off. And hopefully, as a result, more and better thinking.&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 26 Nov 2017 19:30:00 -0500</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:v4.chriskrycho.com,2017-11-26:/2017/the-value-of-silence.html</guid><category>writing</category><category>social media</category></item></channel></rss>