<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Chris Krycho</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/</link><description></description><atom:link href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/feeds/software-development.xml" rel="self"></atom:link><lastBuildDate>Mon, 07 Sep 2015 11:55:00 -0400</lastBuildDate><item><title>Rust and Swift (iii)</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2015/rust-and-swift-iii.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;i class="editorial"&gt;I am reading through the Swift book, and comparing it to Rust, which I have also been learning over the past month. As with the other posts in this series, these are off-the-cuff impressions, which may be inaccurate in various ways. I’d be happy to hear feedback! Note, too, that my preferences are just that: preferences. Your tastes may differ from mine.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I just hit operators in the Swift book. First question: are operators special syntax, or are they sugar for &lt;code&gt;protocol&lt;/code&gt;s? (Every modern language I use or even have played with handles them as sugar for another language construct—Python, Ruby, Io, Elixir, and Rust, to name just a few ranging over a substantial variety of ages and styles.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Oh. I did the requisite digging, and operators are functions (which is okay) defined in the global namespace (&lt;em&gt;:sigh:&lt;/em&gt;). I say “okay” rather than good because the justification offered is that this is the only way to make the operators work as binary operators between existing instances of types. But that elides the fact that, if that’s the case, it is so because of other language design decisions. This seems like a perfect place to use a &lt;code&gt;protocol&lt;/code&gt;, but perhaps (unlike Rust’s &lt;code&gt;trait&lt;/code&gt;) they’re not sufficiently capable to handle this? That’s an open question; I have no idea about the answer.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Interestingly, Rust has several fewer operators than Swift, even apart from those mentioned in my &lt;a href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2015/rust-and-swift-ii.html"&gt;previous post&lt;/a&gt;. It drops the pre- and post-increment operators entirely (as does Python), since their results can always be accomplished in other ways with less potential for confusion. Swift keeps them, no doubt in part because most (Objective) C programs are deeply familiar with them and with idioms associated with them.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I learned a few new things about Rust’s operators as well: the Boolean &lt;code&gt;||&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;&amp;amp;&amp;amp;&lt;/code&gt; operators and its bit wise &lt;code&gt;|&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;&amp;amp;&lt;/code&gt; operators differ not only in that the former are &lt;em&gt;short-circuit&lt;/em&gt; operators and the latter are not. Obviously you can also do things like bit-wise flag operations with the latter, but the reference emphasizes the short-circuiting behavior. This makes perfect sense, but it wasn’t something I’d ever considered explicitly before.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;There is no ternary operator in Rust, because of how it handles the relationship between expressions and statements. Swift keeps it. That’s an interesting reflection of differences in design: Rust dropped it because &lt;code&gt;if&lt;/code&gt; blocks are expressions, so it’s redundant, and they have had a goal of removing unnecessary features. (See the discussion on dropping the ternary operator—with an interesting aside from Brendan Eich on JavaScript—&lt;a href="https://github.com/rust-lang/rust/issues/1698"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;). Note that this is not a criticism of Swift, just an observation, though I do really like Rust’s expression-driven approach.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The &lt;code&gt;??&lt;/code&gt; “nil coalescing operator”, on the other hand, I actively dislike. This seems like shorthand for the sake of shorthand, partly necessitated by the existing drive toward shorthand with optional types in Swift. Sometimes brevity can lead to decreased clarity. Eliding too much, or subsuming it into shorthand, makes the language harder to hold in your head and requires you to slow down more for parsing each line.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Nothing surprising (or different) between the standard boolean operators in the two languages.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I wonder how many times the word “concise” (or synonyms of it) appear in the Swift book? It’s increasingly clear to me reading that brevity is one of the primary design goals. Maybe it’s just me, but that actually seems a little weird. Brevity is good so far as it goes, but &lt;em&gt;legibility&lt;/em&gt; is much better.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;div class="references"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 07 Sep 2015 11:55:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2015-09-07:2015/rust-and-swift-iii.html</guid><category>software development</category><category>listicles</category></item><item><title>Rust and Swift (ii)</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2015/rust-and-swift-ii.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;i class="editorial"&gt;I am reading through the Swift book, and comparing it to Rust, which I have also been learning over the past month. As with the other posts in this series, these are off-the-cuff impressions, which may be inaccurate in various ways. I’d be happy to hear feedback! Note, too, that my preferences are just that: preferences. Your tastes may differ from mine.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;At first blush, I find the extra syntax around optionals in Swift more confusing than helpful. I think this comes down to my preference for a more Python-like approach: “Explicit is better than implicit” and “There should be one– and preferably only one –obvious way to do it” both militate against the multiple different ways you can handle optional values in Swift. Optional types are created in one of two ways:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;with the &lt;code&gt;?&lt;/code&gt; operator on a type definition, creating an explicitly wrapped type which must be checked in some way.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;with the &lt;code&gt;!&lt;/code&gt; operator on a type definition, creating an “implicitly unwrapped optional” by forcibly unwrapping it (and creating a runtime error if the optional is empty)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After creating an optional, you can get at its contents by:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;using the &lt;code&gt;if let&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;while let&lt;/code&gt; constructs to bind the optional value’s non-&lt;code&gt;nil&lt;/code&gt; value for a block&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;using the &lt;code&gt;!&lt;/code&gt; operator on a variable name, explicitly unwrapping it (and creating a runtime error if the optional is empty)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By contrast, in Rust you always have to explicitly unwrap the item, using the &lt;code&gt;unwrap&lt;/code&gt; method or pattern matching. There are no implicitly unwrapped types. Moreover, there is no special syntax around creating optional types in Rust: you just declare them with an &lt;code&gt;Option&lt;/code&gt; type or another type that &lt;code&gt;impl&lt;/code&gt;s the &lt;code&gt;Option&lt;/code&gt; behavior. The “shortcut” behavior around error handling, &lt;code&gt;try!&lt;/code&gt;, isn’t special syntax, but application of another standard language construct (in this case, a macro).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The discussion of &lt;code&gt;assert&lt;/code&gt; in the Swift book re-raises the question about the global namespace:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“You write an assertion by calling the global &lt;code&gt;assert(_:_:)&lt;/code&gt; function.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This continues to suggest strongly that Swift does in fact have a true global namespace, &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; an automatically-imported prelude. That can make a big difference for applications in certain spaces (e.g. systems programming), when you might have good reason to want to replace the standard library’s approach with a different one. (See Rust’s &lt;a href="https://doc.rust-lang.org/book/no-stdlib.html"&gt;&lt;code&gt;#[no_std]&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt; docs and the &lt;a href="https://github.com/rust-lang/rfcs/blob/master/text/1184-stabilize-no_std.md"&gt;related RFC&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;In Rust, &lt;code&gt;assert!&lt;/code&gt; is a macro, not a function, which is an interesting but perhaps not &lt;em&gt;especially&lt;/em&gt; important distinction in this particular case. (It might be, though; I’d have to see the implementation of each to see how they play out differently.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;In any case, this also highlights another large difference between the two: testing is &lt;a href="https://doc.rust-lang.org/stable/book/testing.html"&gt;front and center&lt;/a&gt; in Rust, and barely receives a mention so far in the Swift book (and isn’t in the table of contents). Having language-level support for testing is a big deal.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Language tour and first chapter of the language guide down, my sense is that Swift is a substantially better language than C or C++ (and presumably than Objective C, but since I don’t know that language I can’t speak to it) for app design, but that Rust is a better language yet. Both a far more modern than their predecessors, but they approach the same problems in surprisingly different ways, relatively similar syntax notwithstanding. So far, I like the Rust approach better.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;In particular, more syntax is not my preferred way to tackle these things. Providing good language constructs and primitives on which to build seems better in &lt;em&gt;many&lt;/em&gt; ways:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It substantially reduces the cognitive load for the developer, by keeping the number of constructs small and simply varying how they are applied.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It increases the quality of those primitives, because it forces the language deadness to make sure they actually address the full problem space.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It lets developers approach the same problem in ways the language design team may not have anticipated, and over time the community may find shared conventions that improve on the &lt;code&gt;std&lt;/code&gt; approach, and nothing has to change in the language spec (or the compiler!) to adopt those changes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In general, then, it makes change much easier to manage, and change can be community-driven rather than requiring the language design team to manage it.&lt;a href="#fn1" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref1"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;div class="references"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;section class="footnotes"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn1"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This may of course be intentional on Apple’s part with Swift. Maintaining tight control over its tooling is very typical of modern Apple.&lt;a href="#fnref1"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 06 Sep 2015 10:20:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2015-09-06:2015/rust-and-swift-ii.html</guid><category>software development</category><category>listicles</category></item><item><title>Rust and Swift (i)</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2015/rust-and-swift-i.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;i class=editorial&gt;I started writing these responses in a Slack channel of developers I participate in as I worked through the &lt;a href="https://developer.apple.com/swift/"&gt;Swift&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://developer.apple.com/library/ios/documentation/Swift/Conceptual/Swift_Programming_Language/"&gt;book&lt;/a&gt;. I realized after a bit that it would make a better blog post than chat room content, so here we are. This is all entirely off-the-cuff: me just thinking out loud as I read; this is by no means expert opinion.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;..&amp;lt;&lt;/code&gt; – seriously?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That has to be one of the most annoying operators I’ve ever seen. It ends up with cognitive noise because &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;name&lt;/code&gt; initially processes as “starting a generic” and you have to re-parse it visually and mentally.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;After the first chapter of the Swift book, my impression is “a poor man’s Rust”; my gut feel based on that first pass and everything I’ve seen and read about Swift over the past two years is that it’s roughly what you would get if you took Rust’s syntax and replaced Rust’s hard safety goals with the aim of mapping to ObjC semantics. (To be fair to Apple, that interoperability was probably necessary.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;An example that jumps out at me as immediately illustrative of the difference in approach the languages take is the way you pass structures by reference vs. copy. In Swift, that’s done via two completely distinct language constructs, &lt;code&gt;struct&lt;/code&gt;s and &lt;code&gt;class&lt;/code&gt;es respectively.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Rust, there is just the &lt;code&gt;struct&lt;/code&gt; type to handle both of those. They’re immutable unless you declare them with &lt;code&gt;mut&lt;/code&gt;, and you can pass them via copy simply by implementing the &lt;code&gt;Copy&lt;/code&gt; &lt;code&gt;trait&lt;/code&gt; (which seems roughly analogous to Swift’s &lt;code&gt;protocol&lt;/code&gt;, but I’ve not yet dig deeply enough to see how they differ). Those things aren’t baked into the language, but use simpler language building blocks to define behavior into he library.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I saw someone do a write up a while back arguing that Go isn’t a &lt;em&gt;bad&lt;/em&gt; language, it just isn’t a &lt;em&gt;good&lt;/em&gt; language. My first impression of Swift, after having spent the last month with Rust, is very much along those lines.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Huh. Here’s something that I appreciate about Rust, Haskell, and others now that I didn’t before: there’s a difference between implicitly/automatically importing a prelude or a given set of standard library functions, and having actually global functions. Does Swift actually have functions like &lt;code&gt;print&lt;/code&gt; in a global namespace, as the book seems to imply, or they being imported automatically &lt;em&gt;a la&lt;/em&gt; Rust/Haskell/etc.? (edited)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Hmm. Why have &lt;code&gt;Double&lt;/code&gt; &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; &lt;code&gt;Float&lt;/code&gt;—just for ObjC interop, I guess?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Extending the above note on &lt;code&gt;class&lt;/code&gt;es and &lt;code&gt;struct&lt;/code&gt;s and &lt;code&gt;protocol&lt;/code&gt;s vs. Rust’s approach: the same thing is true about &lt;code&gt;extension&lt;/code&gt;, which is a distinct concept from implementing a &lt;code&gt;protocol&lt;/code&gt;; again, in Rust these are both just handled with a single language construct, &lt;code&gt;impl&lt;/code&gt;. That’s not because &lt;code&gt;impl&lt;/code&gt; is overloaded, but rather because the underlying language machinery is the same for the two things. (edited)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;(I’ve a feeling learning Swift is going to turn me into even more of a Rust fanboy.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reading the two books in close sequence like this is proving really productive mentally for thinking about how the two handle the same issues. I’ve never done anything quite like this before, and it’s fascinating.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I have an increased appreciation for Rust’s use of semi-colons to turn expressions into statements, and thereby to distinguish clearly between the two (among other things, allowing for implicit return of anything that’s an expression).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Another interesting comparison: Rust’s &lt;code&gt;match&lt;/code&gt; and Swift’s &lt;code&gt;switch&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;case&lt;/code&gt; fill the same role of pattern matching. I’m curious to see how they differ. Does Swift do matching on arbitrary expressions?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also, I see where the syntax choices came from in both, and while I slightly prefer Rust’s, I think both make reasonably good sense; Swift’s will understandably be more familiar to C and ObjC programmers, and that’s a perfectly defensible approach. Seen that way, it is expanding on the C-style construct (even if it’s actually doing something substantially more sophisticated than that under the hood by being a form of actual pattern matching).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;div class="references"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 04 Sep 2015 22:59:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2015-09-04:2015/rust-and-swift-i.html</guid><category>listicles</category><category>software development</category></item><item><title>2015-09-02 08:07</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2015/2015-09-02-0807.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;I’m writing a bunch of C that &lt;em&gt;needs&lt;/em&gt; to handle error returns. I’m really wishing I had Rust’s &lt;code&gt;#[must_use]&lt;/code&gt; annotation right now. For that matter, I just want Rust’s &lt;code&gt;Result&amp;lt;T, E&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; type available.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="references"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 02 Sep 2015 08:07:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2015-09-02:2015/2015-09-02-0807.html</guid><category>software development</category></item><item><title>2015-09-01 06:51</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2015/2015-09-01-0651.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;What are you using to track software development issues these days? JIRA, YouTrack, FogBugz, RedMine, or something else?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="references"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 01 Sep 2015 06:51:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2015-09-01:2015/2015-09-01-0651.html</guid><category>software development</category></item><item><title>2015-08-27 06:13</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2015/2015-08-27-0613.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Flame war time: I’ve basically concluded that &lt;em&gt;for the tasks I use them for&lt;/em&gt;, I prefer Vim’s modal editing style to Emacs’ not-modal editing style.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’d still rather use Atom/Sublime or IntelliJ IDEA for almost everything, though.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="references"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 27 Aug 2015 06:13:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2015-08-27:2015/2015-08-27-0613.html</guid><category>software development</category></item><item><title>2015/08/19 16:33</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2015/20150819-1633.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Sometimes it is tempting as a designer to think that users are stupid. Don’t. If the software is not working for users, that implies stupidity in another party entirely: the one that designed the software. 😉&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="references"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 19 Aug 2015 16:33:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2015-08-19:2015/20150819-1633.html</guid><category>design</category><category>software development</category></item><item><title>2015-08-18 17:49</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2015/2015-08-18-1749.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Ugh. I just discovered that a support email address has been sitting unattended for eight months. (Totally my fault.) Not a &lt;em&gt;lot&lt;/em&gt; of problems… but any unanswered emails for that long are the worst user experience. So frustrated with myself right now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="references"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 18 Aug 2015 17:49:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2015-08-18:2015/2015-08-18-1749.html</guid><category>software development</category></item><item><title>2015-08-17 17:40</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2015/2015-08-17-1740.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;I’ve been using &lt;a href="http://input.fontbureau.com"&gt;Input&lt;/a&gt; for &lt;a href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2015/2015-08-07-2137.html"&gt;about ten days now&lt;/a&gt;. It grew on me slowly, but I &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; like it. Using it everywhere now!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="references"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 17 Aug 2015 17:40:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2015-08-17:2015/2015-08-17-1740.html</guid><category>typography</category><category>software development</category></item><item><title>2015-08-17 06:33</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2015/2015-08-17-0633.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;It turns out browsers render CSS transitions for &lt;em&gt;positioning&lt;/em&gt; much more nicely than they do those for the &lt;em&gt;box model&lt;/em&gt; (perhaps unsurprisingly, on reflection). Use &lt;code&gt;position&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;top&lt;/code&gt; instead of &lt;code&gt;margin&lt;/code&gt; to smoothly animate an item moving within its container.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="references"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 17 Aug 2015 06:33:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2015-08-17:2015/2015-08-17-0633.html</guid><category>software development</category><category>design</category></item><item><title>2015-08-13 20:01</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2015/2015-08-13-2001.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;It’s nice when you evaluate a potential product’s market more closely and find your idea might actually be viable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="references"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 13 Aug 2015 20:01:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2015-08-13:2015/2015-08-13-2001.html</guid><category>software development</category><category>business</category></item><item><title>2015-08-12 08:40</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2015/2015-08-12-0840.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Where do you like to set your &lt;code&gt;--prefix&lt;/code&gt; when configuring personal development tooling setups? Somewhere under ~? Or somewhere else?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="references"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 12 Aug 2015 08:40:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2015-08-12:2015/2015-08-12-0840.html</guid><category>software development</category></item><item><title>2015-08-11 20:13</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2015/2015-08-11-2013.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;If you’re delivering images over the web, you &lt;em&gt;need&lt;/em&gt; to be using something like &lt;a href="https://imageoptim.com"&gt;ImageOptim&lt;/a&gt;. No excuses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="references"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 11 Aug 2015 20:13:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2015-08-11:2015/2015-08-11-2013.html</guid><category>software development</category></item><item><title>2015-08-10 15:06</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2015/2015-08-10-1506.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Tradeoffs time: whether ’tis better to drop in an off-the-shelf open source solution for this particular problem, and bring in all the extra weight it includes, or do it myself and pay in the time spent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="references"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 10 Aug 2015 15:06:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2015-08-10:2015/2015-08-10-1506.html</guid><category>software development</category></item><item><title>2015/08/09 22:16</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2015/20150809-2216.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Tonight, Jaimie said that she thought Rust had turned me into a bit of a fanboy. Don’t tell anyone, but I think she’s basically right…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="references"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 09 Aug 2015 22:16:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2015-08-09:2015/20150809-2216.html</guid><category>software development</category></item><item><title>2015-08-08 18:11</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2015/2015-08-08-1811.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;I can think of no more effective an argument for &lt;a href="http://www.rust-lang.org/"&gt;Rust&lt;/a&gt; and its &lt;a href="http://blog.rust-lang.org/2015/04/10/Fearless-Concurrency.html"&gt;memory safety guarantees&lt;/a&gt; than the time I spent this weekend hunting down bugs caused by buffer overruns in decades-old C code.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="references"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 08 Aug 2015 18:11:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2015-08-08:2015/2015-08-08-1811.html</guid><category>software development</category></item><item><title>2015-08-08 15:33</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2015/2015-08-08-1533.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;I found a &lt;code&gt;CEditDlg&lt;/code&gt; instance and went looking for it in the MSDN docs, and was a bit nonplussed not to find it. Oh. It’s a &lt;code&gt;CFileDialog&lt;/code&gt; subclass, and never mind the semantic ambiguity arising from the existence of a native &lt;code&gt;CEdit&lt;/code&gt; class. 😐&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="references"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 08 Aug 2015 15:33:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2015-08-08:2015/2015-08-08-1533.html</guid><category>software development</category></item><item><title>2015-08-07 21:37</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2015/2015-08-07-2137.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Thinking about setting &lt;a href="http://input.fontbureau.com"&gt;Input&lt;/a&gt; as my typeface for doing my development for a week or two, see how it goes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anybody tried it? Bugs or problems to report?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="references"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 07 Aug 2015 21:37:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2015-08-07:2015/2015-08-07-2137.html</guid><category>software development</category><category>typography</category></item><item><title>High- and Low-Level Programming Languages</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2015/high-and-low-level-programming-languages.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;It occurred to me while listening to &lt;a href="https://edwinb.wordpress.com"&gt;Edwin Brady&lt;/a&gt; talk about &lt;a href="http://www.idris-lang.org"&gt;Idris&lt;/a&gt; on the &lt;a href="http://typetheorypodcast.com"&gt;Type Theory Podcast&lt;/a&gt;,&lt;a href="#fn1" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref1"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; having just spent a few weeks starting to learn &lt;a href="https://www.rust-lang.org"&gt;Rust&lt;/a&gt;: “low-level” has at least two meanings in software. One is whether something has manual memory management or is garbage collected, reference counted, or otherwise manages memory itself. This is what people often mean when they talk about C, C++, etc. as being “low-level” and languages like Python or Ruby or C♯ being high-level.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But then you toss in a language like &lt;a href="https://www.rust-lang.org"&gt;Rust&lt;/a&gt;, and things start to get a little more complicated. Rust can do the same kind of direct memory management that makes C or C++ a good language for things like writing operating system kernels. [&lt;a href="https://github.com/torvalds/linux"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;,&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Architecture_of_Windows_NT"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;,&lt;a href="http://www.opensource.apple.com/source/xnu/xnu-2782.10.72/"&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;] But it is also memory-safe, at least in ordinary usage. Like C♯, you have to be explicit about any unsafe code, with the &lt;code&gt;unsafe&lt;/code&gt; keyword on any blocks that do memory management that isn’t safe. And the vast majority of Rust code &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; safe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More than that, though, Rust &lt;em&gt;feels&lt;/em&gt; like a high-level language. It gives you higher-kinded functions, generics, traits-based composition of types, hygienic macros, and the implementation of many important parts the essentials of the language in the library. If you need to patch something, or extend something, you can do that in a straightforward way. In short, it gives you lots of good abstractions like you would expect in a high-level language.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rust is low-level in that you can write (and people are writing) systems-level programs in it. It is high-level in that it lets you express things in ways normally associated with languages like Haskell or OCaml or Python or Ruby. To put it simply: it’s &lt;em&gt;low-level&lt;/em&gt; in its ability to address the computer, and &lt;em&gt;high-level&lt;/em&gt; in the abstractions it hands to a programmer. That’s a powerful combination, and I hope more languages embrace it in the years to come.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="references"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;section class="footnotes"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn1"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Yes, I know that’s insanely nerdy. What did you expect?&lt;a href="#fnref1"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 07 Aug 2015 20:00:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2015-08-07:2015/high-and-low-level-programming-languages.html</guid><category>software development</category></item><item><title>2015-08-07 18:20</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2015/2015-08-07-1820.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Quote of the week (3-year-old Ellie talking to her mom, who has been learning Python): “Mommy! I have a function for you!”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="references"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 07 Aug 2015 18:20:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2015-08-07:2015/2015-08-07-1820.html</guid><category>ellie</category><category>software development</category><category>jaimie</category></item><item><title>2015-08-06 17:33</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2015/2015-08-06-1733.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;☑ Finished reading the &lt;a href="http://rustbyexample.com"&gt;Rust by Example&lt;/a&gt; book.&lt;br /&gt;
☑ Submitted a couple &lt;a href="https://github.com/rust-lang/rust-by-example/pull/628"&gt;pull requests&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;br /&gt;
☑ Concluded that I &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; like this language.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="references"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 06 Aug 2015 17:33:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2015-08-06:2015/2015-08-06-1733.html</guid><category>software development</category></item><item><title>2015-08-05 21:05</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2015/2015-08-05-2105.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Hooked up my digital piano to Logic Pro X tonight and wrote &lt;a href="https://soundcloud.com/chriskrycho/theme-for-sappy-no-vocals"&gt;the theme&lt;/a&gt; for a podcast we’re doing together on learning to program. It’s so good!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="references"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 05 Aug 2015 21:05:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2015-08-05:2015/2015-08-05-2105.html</guid><category>podcast</category><category>music</category><category>Jaimie</category><category>software development</category></item><item><title>2015-08-03 07:58</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2015/2015-08-03-0758.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Whoa! After years of demand, Confluence &lt;em&gt;finally&lt;/em&gt; added support for importing Markdown-formatted content in its “Markup” box. It’s not native support for editing in Markdown… but it &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; a step forward. Good work, Atlassian.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="references"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 03 Aug 2015 07:58:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2015-08-03:2015/2015-08-03-0758.html</guid><category>software development</category></item><item><title>2015-08-02 18:03</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2015/2015-08-02-1803.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Just recorded the first episode of a new, short, weekly podcast I’m working on. Audio should be live in about a week!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="references"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 02 Aug 2015 18:03:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2015-08-02:2015/2015-08-02-1803.html</guid><category>software development</category><category>podcast</category></item><item><title>2015-08-01 08:33</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2015/2015-08-01-0833.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;People often point to &lt;a href="https://xkcd.com/627/"&gt;this (&lt;em&gt;hilariously accurate&lt;/em&gt;) flowchart&lt;/a&gt; to explain how to solve tech problems… but it leaves something &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; important out: we “techies” know the right questions to ask. That makes a big difference.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="references"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 01 Aug 2015 08:33:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2015-08-01:2015/2015-08-01-0833.html</guid><category>software development</category></item><item><title>2015-07-30 20:28</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2015/2015-07-30-2028.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Another little feature of Rust I quite like: the use of &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Trait_(computer_programming)"&gt;&lt;code&gt;trait&lt;/code&gt;s&lt;/a&gt; instead of inheritance to share behavior. All the benefits of inheritance, and a few more besides, but none of the drawbacks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="references"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 30 Jul 2015 20:28:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2015-07-30:2015/2015-07-30-2028.html</guid><category>software development</category></item><item><title>2015-07-29 20:47</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2015/2015-07-29-2047.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;I just realized that one of the reason &lt;a href="http://www.rust-lang.org/"&gt;Rust&lt;/a&gt; so strongly appeals to me is that its design embodies one of my favorite traits from &lt;a href="https://www.python.org/dev/peps/pep-0020/"&gt;the Zen of Python&lt;/a&gt;: &lt;em&gt;explicit is better than implicit&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="references"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 29 Jul 2015 20:47:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2015-07-29:2015/2015-07-29-2047.html</guid><category>software development</category></item><item><title>2015-07-29 10:42</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2015/2015-07-29-1042.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Courtesy of &lt;em&gt;something&lt;/em&gt; in my stack not playing right, I’ve now been reduced to pushing and pulling changes between OS X and my Windows VM through Bitbucket, rather than just having a mapped drive locally. This feels silly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="references"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 29 Jul 2015 10:42:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2015-07-29:2015/2015-07-29-1042.html</guid><category>software development</category></item><item><title>2015-07-29 10:20</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2015/2015-07-29-1020.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Hmm, this may be telling of the future… &lt;a href="https://www.sourcetreeapp.com"&gt;SourceTree&lt;/a&gt; now introduces itself as a Git tool. No mention of Hg at all. 😟&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="references"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 29 Jul 2015 10:20:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2015-07-29:2015/2015-07-29-1020.html</guid><category>software development</category></item><item><title>2015-07-04 19:57</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2015/2015-07-04-1957.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;My dear &lt;a href="http://jaimiekrycho.com"&gt;wife&lt;/a&gt; has started teaching herself Python as a hobby. She has &lt;em&gt;the&lt;/em&gt; essential skill required to succeed as a programmer: the willingness to persevere even when it isn’t making sense to her. I’m extremely impressed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="references"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 04 Jul 2015 19:57:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2015-07-04:2015/2015-07-04-1957.html</guid><category>Jaimie</category><category>software development</category></item><item><title>2015-06-27 14:11</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2015/2015-06-27-1411.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Playing with CSS transforms and transitions while I listen to a lecture on Romans for my New Testament class. Keep myself awake…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="references"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 27 Jun 2015 14:11:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2015-06-27:2015/2015-06-27-1411.html</guid><category>software development</category></item><item><title>2015-06-26 14:03</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2015/2015-06-26-1403.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;I cannot wait till I can switch to ES2015. Got bit by the stupid var scoping issue again. You’d think I’d be past that by now…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="references"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 26 Jun 2015 14:03:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2015-06-26:2015/2015-06-26-1403.html</guid><category>software development</category></item><item><title>2015-06-25 21:06</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2015/2015-06-25-2106.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Reading JavaScript Allongé. Just got to combinatorial logic (kestrel and idiot bird, for those in the know). Then he destructured a list with them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mind. Blown.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="references"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 25 Jun 2015 21:06:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2015-06-25:2015/2015-06-25-2106.html</guid><category>software development</category></item><item><title>2015-06-25 09:10</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2015/2015-06-25-0910.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;One of the things that annoys me most when writing C is how difficult (really, almost impossible) it is to do anything generically. The same operation for different items in a struct? Good luck. It’s possible, but rarely worth the work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="references"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 25 Jun 2015 09:10:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2015-06-25:2015/2015-06-25-0910.html</guid><category>software development</category></item><item><title>HTML5 Location, &lt;base&gt;, and SVG</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2015/html5-location-base-and-svg.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;For quite some time, I have been frustrated by a bug in HolyBible.com: Firefox would not render SVGs using the &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;use xlink:xhref=&amp;quot;#some-SVG-ID&amp;quot;&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/use&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; pattern. Today, I set aside my ongoing work on new user-facing functionality and dedicated what working time I had to hunting down the cause of this and fixing it at last.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was surprised to find the culprit: the &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;base&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; tag. If you don’t know what the &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;base&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; tag is, you’re not alone. It is &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; used all that much in general, and I had never actually seen it on a site before starting on this project last year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So what went wrong? How do these two things play together?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am using (and reusing) SVG items throughout the HolyBible.com interface, taking advantage of the ability to define symbols and reference them with the &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;use&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; tag, like so:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="html"&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;svg version=&amp;quot;1.1&amp;quot; xmlns=&amp;quot;http://www.w3.org/2000/svg&amp;quot; xmlns:xlink=&amp;quot;http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink&amp;quot; xmlns:ev=&amp;quot;http://www.w3.org/2001/xml-events&amp;quot; style=&amp;quot;display: none&amp;quot;&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;symbol id=&amp;quot;logo-shape&amp;quot; viewBox=&amp;quot;0 0 256 256&amp;quot;&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;title&amp;gt;Logo&amp;lt;/title&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;desc&amp;gt;The HolyBible.com logo: sunrise breaking over an open book (the Bible).&amp;lt;/desc&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;path id=&amp;quot;logo-light&amp;quot; d=&amp;quot;M172.1 116.3l5.1-4.1-12.5-.5 32-26.3-41.4 18.4 11-20.1L148 96l12.2-37.5L138.8 91l.1-36.2-10.3 34.4L114 36.1l4.3 54.9-22.2-34.9 13 39.9-18.3-12.4 11 20.1-42.5-19.2 32.8 26.9-10.4.8 4.4 3.9c13.1-1.6 27.4-2.7 42.4-2.7 15.4 0 30.1 1.2 43.6 2.9z&amp;quot;/&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;path id=&amp;quot;logo-book&amp;quot; d=&amp;quot;M199.9 219.9c-47.4-9.8-96.4-9.8-143.8 0-6-28.9-12-57.7-17.9-86.6 59.3-12.3 120.4-12.3 179.7 0-6 28.9-12 57.8-18 86.6z&amp;quot;/&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;/symbol&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;/svg&amp;gt;

&amp;lt;!-- somewhere else on the page --&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;svg&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;use xlink:href=&amp;quot;#logo-shape&amp;quot;&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/use&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;/svg&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Throughout all my early prototyping, this worked perfectly across all modern browsers. (For more, see &lt;a href="https://css-tricks.com/svg-sprites-use-better-icon-fonts/"&gt;CSS Tricks&lt;/a&gt;.) Now, when I started moving from the prototype phase into actually building the application in Angular last fall, I learned that you have to set the base URL for the application using the &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;base&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; tag to use the HTML5 Location API with Angular 1.x. If you want URL-based, rather than &lt;code&gt;#&lt;/code&gt;-based navigation in an Angular app, you need this. Following the recommendation of whatever documentation and tutorials I found, I set it so:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="html"&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;base href=&amp;quot;/&amp;quot;&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Again, this was the recommendation I saw in every bit of documentation and every tutorial, so I assumed it would have no problems. As it turns it, that’s not the case. (This is a &lt;a href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2015/how-to-build-a-single-page-app-api-right.html"&gt;recurring theme&lt;/a&gt; in my experience with Angular.) In Chrome, Safari, and IE9+, this works exactly as expected. In Firefox, however, it does &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt;. The use of the &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;base&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; tag changes the behavior of &lt;code&gt;#&lt;/code&gt;-based URLs on a page. Specifically, it makes it so that if you’re at a URL that &lt;em&gt;isn’t&lt;/em&gt; the base route, anchor links don’t behave as expected. In order to make the &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;use&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; tag as expected, we would have to use the same URL as the base tag. Among other things, this would require making sure that any place we used the &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;use&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; tag, we would have to set that—not exactly a good idea, given that it would entail an awful lot of changes if the base URL were ever changed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What if, instead, we did this?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="html"&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;script&amp;gt;document.write(&amp;#39;&amp;lt;base href=&amp;quot;&amp;#39; + document.location.origin + &amp;#39;&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;&amp;#39;);&amp;lt;/script&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This way, when the page renders, it writes the document location based on the &lt;em&gt;current&lt;/em&gt; location. The URL history still behaves as expected with Angular, but the relative URLs for IDs behave as expected in Firefox again, while not breaking the behavior in any other browsers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But… then you’ll navigate to another page, and Firefox will be back to not working.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="https://github.com/angular/angular.js/issues/8934#issuecomment-56568466"&gt;solution&lt;/a&gt;, it turns out, only came into being after I’d done the initial implementation, and I have no idea how much later it found its way into the Angular docs. However, even though it now &lt;em&gt;exists&lt;/em&gt; in the docs, it’s by no means obvious why you should do it this way, and certainly no mention of SVG! This might not seem odd to you… but it should, given that the only reason that Angular introduced this API change was to account for &lt;em&gt;exactly this issue&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;a href="#fn1" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref1"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As the Angular docs note, leaving out the &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;base&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; tag means all your URLs have to be absolute if you want to use HTML5 location and the &lt;code&gt;$locationProvider&lt;/code&gt;. If you want to use SVGs with &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;use&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; and Firefox, though, that’s what you have to do (and therefore that’s what I’m doing).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fun times, right?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="references"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;section class="footnotes"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn1"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The closest it gets is this reference:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Links that only contain a hash fragment (e.g. &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;a href=&amp;quot;#target&amp;quot;&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;) will only change &lt;code&gt;$location.hash()&lt;/code&gt; and not modify the url otherwise. This is useful for scrolling to anchors on the same page without needing to know on which page the user currently is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even this, however, only &lt;em&gt;hints&lt;/em&gt; at the root of the SVG issue.&lt;a href="#fnref1"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 02 Jul 2015 22:00:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2015-06-20:2015/html5-location-base-and-svg.html</guid><category>software development</category></item><item><title>2015-06-18 21:54</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2015/2015-06-18-2154.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;To my great delight, and thanks to a &lt;a href="https://alpha.app.net/jnm/post/61270949"&gt;suggestion&lt;/a&gt; from App.net friend &lt;a href="https://alpha.app.net/jnm/"&gt;@jnm&lt;/a&gt;, I was able to &lt;a href="http://www.linuxjournal.com/content/downloading-entire-web-site-wget"&gt;get a static copy&lt;/a&gt; of my 2012–2013-era site archived this evening. That in turn means I’ll be able to replace my WordPress install with static HTML pages over the next few weeks. &lt;em&gt;Victory.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="references"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 18 Jun 2015 21:54:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2015-06-18:2015/2015-06-18-2154.html</guid><category>software development</category></item><item><title>How to Build a Single-Page App API Right</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2015/how-to-build-a-single-page-app-api-right.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;When I was first working on HolyBible.com, I struggled for quite a while to wrap my head around the right way to structure its API—and in truth, I actually didn’t come up with what I would call the &lt;em&gt;right&lt;/em&gt; solution. I came up with a &lt;em&gt;working&lt;/em&gt; solution, and the site performs all right, most of the time. However, our goal as developers shouldn’t be “all right, most of the time.” It should be “really well, all the time.” A big part of what I did wrong came from the bad advice I found in reading up on the issue along the way. This is my shot at helping you, dear reader, avoid making the same mistake.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section id="the-challenge" class="level2"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The challenge&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When building a client-side application, we need to get the data for each view so that we can render it. In the case of HolyBible.com, that means everything from actual Bible text to study Bible notes, about pages, etc. The question is &lt;em&gt;how&lt;/em&gt; to do this: we need to be able to load an actual page from our server, and we need a way to request data (rather than whole pages) from the server.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(More experienced developers already know where this is going: that last sentence there has the key to this whole thing. I know. But the internet &lt;em&gt;doesn’t.&lt;/em&gt; I learned this the hard way.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section id="the-mistake" class="level3"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;The mistake&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here’s the mistake I made: I built the Bible data API as (essentially) a &lt;em&gt;single&lt;/em&gt; endpoint. When I went looking for advice on how to build this in Angular and Node/Express, every single tutorial or blog post I found outlined the same basic solution: routes for your data endpoints, and catch-all route that returns the basic frame page for everything else. So, for HolyBible.com, that would come out with route matchers for e.g. &lt;code&gt;/data/gen.1.1&lt;/code&gt;, and for any other specific routes needed (for other views, static resources, etc.), with a default behavior of just dropping a static, basically empty template at the catchall &lt;code&gt;*&lt;/code&gt; route. Then, once the application has loaded, it can inspect the URL and load the relevant data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This works. It’s exactly what I did on HolyBible.com, in fact. But it’s &lt;em&gt;slow&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don’t get me wrong: the time until the initial page load is actually relatively quick (though I plan to improve it substantially over the next couple months). The real problem is that the initial page load &lt;em&gt;doesn’t include any content&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I &lt;em&gt;hate&lt;/em&gt; this. That’s why people are on the site: not to see my neat skills with JavaScript, just to read the Bible. And they have to wait, because once the page &lt;em&gt;does&lt;/em&gt; load, Angular has to spin up the full application, see what content &lt;em&gt;should&lt;/em&gt; have been loaded, and request it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="the-solution" class="level3"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;The solution&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don’t write &lt;em&gt;one&lt;/em&gt; API. Write &lt;em&gt;two&lt;/em&gt;. They should be structured nearly identically, but one of them will be a &lt;em&gt;page&lt;/em&gt; API endpoint, and one will be a &lt;em&gt;data&lt;/em&gt; API endpoint. In the context of HolyBible.com, here’s how that would play out.&lt;a href="#fn1" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref1"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; One endpoint would be based purely on the standard URL, something like &lt;code&gt;holybible.com/jhn.3.16&lt;/code&gt;. The other would be to retrieve a set of &lt;em&gt;data&lt;/em&gt; associated with a given address, like &lt;code&gt;holybible.com/data/jhn.3.16&lt;/code&gt;. This is only a little different from the approach suggested above, but that small difference matters—in fact, it matters a &lt;em&gt;lot&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instead of having the &lt;code&gt;/jhn.3.16&lt;/code&gt; route get handled by a catchall &lt;code&gt;*&lt;/code&gt; route on the back end, it gets its own API endpoint, which looks for URLS of this shape and hands back a full page. That API endpoint is responsible to actually render the content of the page appropriately—in this case, with something like the whole chapter of John 3.&lt;a href="#fn2" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref2"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;em&gt;That&lt;/em&gt; gets handed back to the browser, so the very first thing the user sees is not a blank page while the JavaScript framework spins up and requests data, but rather &lt;em&gt;the Bible text they asked for in the first place&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, the JavaScript framework &lt;em&gt;can&lt;/em&gt; spin up, and load any required session data, etc. and start managing the UI like normal. Once we get to this point, the framework can go ahead and request a data payload from the &lt;code&gt;/data/&amp;lt;reference&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; endpoint. So, for example, if there is a navigation control on the page (as on HolyBible.com and indeed most sites), clicking to navigate to Job 14 could, instead of requesting &lt;code&gt;/job.14.4&lt;/code&gt;, fetch the data from the other endpoint by running an AJAX request to &lt;code&gt;/data/job.14.4&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The backend thus supplies &lt;em&gt;both&lt;/em&gt; a &lt;code&gt;/&amp;lt;resource&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; and a &lt;code&gt;/data/&amp;lt;resource&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; route. This might seem redundant, but we’ve just seen why it isn’t, Moreover, if you have any logic that needs to be in place—in our example here, a Bible reference parser, for example, to decide what content should be supplied—you can easily reuse it between the two routes. The differences is simply in the form of the data returned: is it a fully-rendered template, or just the data?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="so-what" class="level2"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;So what?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This approach has two big advantages over the catch-all approach that was frequently recommended in e.g. Angular SPA tutorials I read.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol type="1"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;It’s &lt;em&gt;progressive enhancement&lt;/em&gt;. If the JavaScript fails, or the user has it disabled, or it fails to load because it’s loaded asynchronously, the user still gets the page they asked for. Moreover, as long as the page content is build carefully (links built appropriately for other content, and so on), the entire application could continue to work even if the JavaScript &lt;em&gt;never&lt;/em&gt; becomes available.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;It’s &lt;em&gt;performant&lt;/em&gt;. Loading the content this way will be &lt;em&gt;much&lt;/em&gt; faster than the standard approach recommended for single-page apps. As noted above, it gets the content to the user immediately, then lets the JavaScript UI bits come into play. Since future page loads can take advantage of both caching and smaller data payloads, the whole thing can actually be faster than either a pure client-side &lt;em&gt;or&lt;/em&gt; a pure server-side approach. That is, once the client-side application is running, it can just update its views with data delivered via AJAX, rather than reloading the whole page. But &lt;em&gt;before&lt;/em&gt; that, the user doesn’t have to wait to see something useful until the JavaScript framework spins up.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s not often an approach gives you progressive enhancement and actually increases the performance of an application, but this one does. Better yet, you can apply this in just about any framework: it’s equally applicable to AngularJS with ExpressJS, Backbone with Rails, Ember with Django, Aurelia with Phoenix, or any other combination you come up with.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="references"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section class="footnotes"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn1"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Note: this is &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; the actual API structure of HolyBible.com, or even particularly close to it. Remember, I learned everything I’m writing here by doing it &lt;em&gt;wrong&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;a href="#fnref1"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn2"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Or possibly a section which constitutes a semantic block of data. I have some thoughts on chunking Bible data semantically rather than by chapter and verse for this kind of thing. That’s another post for another day, though.&lt;a href="#fnref2"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 09 Jun 2015 22:16:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2015-06-09:2015/how-to-build-a-single-page-app-api-right.html</guid><category>software development</category></item><item><title>2015-06-09 10:46</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2015/2015-06-09-1046.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Tip: if you’re using Mercurial’s bookmarks to track lightweight branches, somewhat analogous to Git’s branches, use Mercurial’s special &lt;code&gt;@&lt;/code&gt; tag to track whatever you want to treat as the tip of a &lt;code&gt;master&lt;/code&gt; branch. That way, any clone will check that out by default.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="references"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 09 Jun 2015 10:46:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2015-06-09:2015/2015-06-09-1046.html</guid><category>software development</category></item><item><title>2015-06-06 11:46</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2015/2015-06-06-1146.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;I just taught Jaimie how to use GitHub for Mac (as she is helping a friend with his Jekyll-powered website), and explained the basics of distributed version control. She is totally a boss. And GitHub for Mac is a pretty good app.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="references"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 06 Jun 2015 11:46:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2015-06-06:2015/2015-06-06-1146.html</guid><category>software development</category></item><item><title>2015-05-29 09:38</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2015/2015-05-29-0938.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;One of (many) irritations with using Angular: every search turns up Bootstrap solutions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m not using Bootstrap.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;:sigh:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="references"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 29 May 2015 09:38:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2015-05-29:2015/2015-05-29-0938.html</guid><category>software development</category></item><item><title>Python Enums, ctypes.Structures, and DLL exports</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2015/ctypes-structures-and-dll-exports.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;For one of my contracts right now, I’m writing a &lt;code&gt;ctypes&lt;/code&gt; Python interface to existing C code. I got stuck and confused for quite a while on getting the interface to a given function to build correctly, and along the way had to try to understand the &lt;code&gt;from_param&lt;/code&gt; class method. The official docs are… fine… but the examples provided don’t cover the most common/basic use case: defining a simple, &lt;em&gt;non-ctypes&lt;/em&gt; data type as an argument to a DLL-exported function.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s say you have a C function exported from a DLL; for convenience we’ll make it something rather silly but easy to understand:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="c"&gt;&lt;code&gt;/** my_exported.h */
#include &amp;quot;exports.h&amp;quot;

typedef enum {
    ZERO,
    ONE,
    TWO
} MyEnum;

MY_API int getAnEnumValue(MyEnum anEnum);&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The implementation just gives back the integer value of the function:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="c"&gt;&lt;code&gt;int getAnEnumValue(MyEnum anEnum) {
    return (int)anEnum;
}&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I said, a &lt;em&gt;very&lt;/em&gt; silly example. Note that you don’t technically need the &lt;code&gt;(int)&lt;/code&gt; cast there; I’ve just put it in to be explicit about what we’re doing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How would we use this from Python? Assuming we have a DLL named &lt;code&gt;my_dll&lt;/code&gt; which exports the &lt;code&gt;getAnEnumValue&lt;/code&gt; function, we’d load it up roughly like this:&lt;a href="#fn1" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref1"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="python"&gt;&lt;code&gt;import ctypes as c

my_dll = c.cdll.LoadLibrary(&amp;#39;my_dll&amp;#39;)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then, we bind to the function like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="python"&gt;&lt;code&gt;get_an_enum_value = my_dll.getAnEnumValue&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, when you do this, you usually also supply the &lt;code&gt;argtypes&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;restype&lt;/code&gt; values for these functions. If you’re like me, you’d think, “Oh, an enum—a perfect opportunity to use the &lt;code&gt;Enum&lt;/code&gt; type in Python 3.4+!” and then you’d do something like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="python"&gt;&lt;code&gt;import ctypes as c
from enum import IntEnum

class MyEnum(IntEnum):
    ZERO = 0
    ONE = 1
    TWO = 2

my_dll = c.cdll.LoadLibrary(&amp;#39;my_dll&amp;#39;)
get_an_enum_value = my_dll.getAnEnumValue
get_an_enum_value.argtypes = [MyEnum]
get_an_enum_value.restype = c.c_int&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That seems sensible enough, but as it is, it won’t work: you’ll get an error:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;TypeError: item 1 in _argtypes_ has no from_param method&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is because &lt;code&gt;argtypes&lt;/code&gt; values &lt;em&gt;have&lt;/em&gt; to be either existing &lt;code&gt;ctypes&lt;/code&gt; types&lt;a href="#fn2" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref2"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; or supply either:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a &lt;code&gt;from_param&lt;/code&gt; classmethod, or&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;an &lt;code&gt;_as_parameter_&lt;/code&gt; attribute&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can use &lt;code&gt;ctypes.Structure&lt;/code&gt; subclasses natively that way, because the &lt;code&gt;Structure&lt;/code&gt; class supplies its &lt;code&gt;from_param&lt;/code&gt; classmethod. The same is &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; true of our custom enum class, though. As the docs put it:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you have defined your own classes which you pass to function calls, you have to implement a &lt;code&gt;from_param()&lt;/code&gt; class method for them to be able to use them in the argtypes sequence. The &lt;code&gt;from_param()&lt;/code&gt; class method receives the Python object passed to the function call, it should do a typecheck or whatever is needed to make sure this object is acceptable, and then return the object itself, its &lt;code&gt;_as_parameter_&lt;/code&gt; attribute, or whatever you want to pass as the C function argument in this case. Again, the result should be an integer, string, bytes, a &lt;code&gt;ctypes&lt;/code&gt; instance, or an object with an &lt;code&gt;_as_parameter_&lt;/code&gt; attribute.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, to make the enum type work, we need to add a &lt;code&gt;from_param&lt;/code&gt; class method or an &lt;code&gt;_as_parameter_&lt;/code&gt; attribute to it. Thus, either of these options will work:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="python"&gt;&lt;code&gt;class MyEnum(IntEnum):
    ZERO = 0
    ONE = 1
    TWO = 2

    # Option 1: set the _as_parameter value at construction.
    def __init__(self, value):
        self._as_parameter = int(value)

    # Option 2: define the class method `from_param`.
    @classmethod
    def from_param(cls, obj):
        return int(obj)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the constructor-based option, the &lt;code&gt;value&lt;/code&gt; argument to the constructor is the value of the &lt;code&gt;Enum&lt;/code&gt; instance. Since the value of anan &lt;code&gt;IntEnum&lt;/code&gt; is always the same as the integer to whcih it is bound, we can just return &lt;code&gt;int(value)&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;code&gt;from_param&lt;/code&gt; approach works a little differently, but with the same results. The &lt;code&gt;obj&lt;/code&gt; argument to the &lt;code&gt;from_param&lt;/code&gt; method is the object instance, in this case the enumerated value itself. &lt;em&gt;Any&lt;/em&gt; &lt;code&gt;Enum&lt;/code&gt; with an integer value can be directly cast to &lt;code&gt;int&lt;/code&gt; (though it is possible for &lt;code&gt;Enum&lt;/code&gt; instances to have other values, so be careful), and since we have an &lt;code&gt;IntEnum&lt;/code&gt; here, we can again just return &lt;code&gt;int(obj)&lt;/code&gt; directly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, let’s say we want to apply this pattern to more than a single &lt;code&gt;IntEnum&lt;/code&gt; class, because our C code defines more than one enumeration. Extracting it to be common functionality is simple enough: just create a class that implements the class method, and inherit from it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="python"&gt;&lt;code&gt;class CtypesEnum(IntEnum):
    &amp;quot;&amp;quot;&amp;quot;A ctypes-compatible IntEnum superclass.&amp;quot;&amp;quot;&amp;quot;
    @classmethod
    def from_param(cls, obj):
        return int(obj)


class MyEnum(CtypesEnum):
    ZERO = 0
    ONE = 1
    TWO = 2&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our final (working!) Python code, then, would be:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="python"&gt;&lt;code&gt;# Import the standard library dependencies
import ctypes as c
from enum import IntEnum


# Define the types we need.
class CtypesEnum(IntEnum):
    &amp;quot;&amp;quot;&amp;quot;A ctypes-compatible IntEnum superclass.&amp;quot;&amp;quot;&amp;quot;
    @classmethod
    def from_param(cls, obj):
        return int(obj)


class MyEnum(CtypesEnum):
    ZERO = 0
    ONE = 1
    TWO = 2


# Load the DLL and configure the function call.
my_dll = c.cdll.LoadLibrary(&amp;#39;my_dll&amp;#39;)
get_an_enum_value = my_dll.getAnEnumValue
get_an_enum_value.argtypes = [MyEnum]
get_an_enum_value.restype = c.c_int

# Demonstrate that it works.
print(get_an_enum_value(MyEnum.TWO))&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The output will be &lt;code&gt;2&lt;/code&gt;, just as you’d expect!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An important note: The type definition we’ve provided here will work for &lt;code&gt;argtypes&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;restype&lt;/code&gt; assignments, but &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; as one of the members of a custom &lt;code&gt;ctypes.Structure&lt;/code&gt; type’s &lt;code&gt;_fields_&lt;/code&gt; value. (Discussing how you’d go about doing that is beyond the scope of this post; the most direct approach is just to use a &lt;code&gt;ctypes.c_int&lt;/code&gt; and note that it is intended to be used with a given &lt;code&gt;IntEnum&lt;/code&gt;/&lt;code&gt;CtypesEnum&lt;/code&gt; type.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks to &lt;a href="https://alpha.app.net/oluseyi"&gt;@oluseyi&lt;/a&gt; for being my &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rubber_duck_debugging"&gt;rubber ducky&lt;/a&gt; while I was working this out earlier this week!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="references"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;section class="footnotes"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn1"&gt;&lt;p&gt;I’m leaving out the part where we build the DLL, and also the part where we locate the DLL, and only using the Windows convention. If you’re on a *nix system, you should use &lt;code&gt;'my_dll.so'&lt;/code&gt; instead, and in any case you need to make sure the DLL is available in the search path.&lt;a href="#fnref1"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn2"&gt;&lt;p&gt;I &lt;em&gt;love&lt;/em&gt; the redundancy of “&lt;code&gt;ctypes&lt;/code&gt; types,” don’t you?&lt;a href="#fnref2"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 28 May 2015 18:00:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2015-05-28:2015/ctypes-structures-and-dll-exports.html</guid><category>software development</category></item><item><title>2015-05-25 20:06</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2015/2015-05-25-2006.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;That &lt;a href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2015/2015-05-22-2330.html"&gt;project&lt;/a&gt; I started on the other day? It’s still going… and swimmingly. I’ve now gotten it not only working at the most basic level (as it was before) but also to do a bit more complex work. You can see it (and any other scripts I build) &lt;a href="https://github.com/chriskrycho/tilde"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="references"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 25 May 2015 20:06:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2015-05-25:2015/2015-05-25-2006.html</guid><category>software development</category></item><item><title>2015-05-23 15:30</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2015/2015-05-23-1530.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Currently on my mind: how to chunk up the Bible text with semantic blobs and chapter/verse trees in corresponding data structures, in order to present meaningful sections of content (paragraphs, etc.) without resorting to delivering a whole book.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="references"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 23 May 2015 15:30:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2015-05-23:2015/2015-05-23-1530.html</guid><category>software development</category><category>design</category></item><item><title>2015-05-22 23:30</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2015/2015-05-22-2330.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;This post brought to you by a brand new script, which automatically generates the file needed—YAML header and all!—to create a new microblog post on chriskrycho.com. Python for the win.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="references"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 22 May 2015 23:30:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2015-05-22:2015/2015-05-22-2330.html</guid><category>software development</category></item><item><title>Open Source is Neat</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2015/open-source-is-neat.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;I confess: my &lt;em&gt;first&lt;/em&gt; response to seeing &lt;a href="//andrewcamenga.com/"&gt;this page&lt;/a&gt; was a flash of anger: &lt;em&gt;Hey, he didn’t just learn from my site configuration, he actually stole my site &lt;/em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;design&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;!&lt;/em&gt; And then I remembered: I open-sourced the design precisely so people could do that. This was just the first time I’ve ever actually had someone reuse something I did and shared like this. It was a strange (but ultimately wonderful) feeling. I hope to have it again many more times.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In any case, I rather like the tweaks Andrew Comenga made to my design to make it his own; &lt;a href="//andrewcamenga.com/"&gt;go take a look&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="references"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 17 May 2015 22:52:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2015-05-17:2015/open-source-is-neat.html</guid><category>links</category><category>software development</category><category>design</category></item><item><title>These Are My People</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2015/these-are-my-people.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;At the end of April, I flew out to Seattle to &lt;a href="//www.chriskrycho.com/2015/tolle-lege.html"&gt;give a talk&lt;/a&gt; at &lt;a href="//bibletechconference.com"&gt;BibleTech&lt;/a&gt;, a conference hosted by Faithlife (the company that owns Logos Bible Software). What I found was not only a bunch of interesting content—though there was certainly plenty of that, and props to the Logos/Faithlife people for putting on a great event—but also an awful lot of people &lt;em&gt;a lot like me&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Those of you who know me well know this is rare. Finding people who share &lt;em&gt;one&lt;/em&gt; of my primary interests &lt;em&gt;and approach it the same way I do&lt;/em&gt; is relatively rare. Finding people who share an interest is not especially hard, but that qualification is extraordinarily important: I know lots of people interested in programming, and lots of people interested in theology, and not many at all who approach either the same way I do. Finding people who are interested in both software &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; theology (still less also music and linguistics and so on) has been so rare as to be a point of quiet but significant and ongoing frustration in my life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And then I went to BibleTech, and met a lot of amazing people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was reflecting on the experience today—thinking about why I’ve so deeply enjoyed not only the conference itself but &lt;a href="//bibletechnology-slack.herokuapp.com/"&gt;the community&lt;/a&gt; that has sprung out of it—I realized: &lt;em&gt;These are my people.&lt;/em&gt; They share a passion for software development, theology, linguistics, and in many cases even music. There may not be many of us in the world, but a substantial number were assembled in Seattle April 30–May 1, 2015. That’s no small thing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have no idea what the future holds for me—whether it will continue to include writing software for the Bible specifically or not—but I &lt;em&gt;can&lt;/em&gt; say that this phase of my life has been enormously beneficial in this one way if in no others. It is nice to find kindred spirits in the world, and to know that, even if I am pretty strange, there are other strange people out there, too, and that we can keep working in our strange ways to make the Word of God more available and more useful to people every day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Good work, BibleTech.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="references"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 17 May 2015 22:25:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2015-05-17:2015/these-are-my-people.html</guid><category>software development</category><category>joy</category></item><item><title>A Modern Python Development Toolchain</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2015/a-modern-python-development-toolchain.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Most of my development time these days—and especially the majority of my happiest time!—is spent working in Python. As such, I’ve experimented off and on over the last few years with the best workflow, and have settled down with a set of tools that is &lt;em&gt;very&lt;/em&gt; effective and efficient for me. I’m sure I’m not the only one who’s had to wrestle with some of the issues particular to this toolchain, and I know that information like this can be valuable especially for people just starting off, so I thought I would document it all in one place.&lt;a href="#fn1" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref1"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note: when talking about a given program, I will italicize it, like &lt;em&gt;brew&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;git&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;python&lt;/em&gt;. When talking about things to type, I will make them a code block like &lt;code&gt;git clone &amp;lt;a repository&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;. For any extended samples, I will make them full-on code blocks:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="python"&gt;&lt;code&gt;import re

def a_neat_function():
    my_string = &amp;quot;Isn&amp;#39;t it cool?&amp;quot;
    if re.match(r&amp;quot;i\w+&amp;quot;, my_string, flags=re.I):
        print(my_string)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The main tools I use are: a good text editor (I like all of &lt;a href="//www.sublimetext.com"&gt;Sublime Text&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="//atom.io"&gt;Atom&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="//github.com/textmate/textmate"&gt;TextMate&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href="//chocolatapp.com"&gt;Chocolat&lt;/a&gt;; each has its own strengths and weaknesses) or sometimes &lt;a href="https://www.jetbrains.com/pycharm/"&gt;a full IDE&lt;/a&gt;, version control software (I appreciate and use both &lt;a href="http://www.git-scm.com"&gt;Git&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="http://mercurial.selenic.com"&gt;Mercurial&lt;/a&gt;), and three dedicated tools to which the rest of this post is devoted: &lt;em&gt;pyenv&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;pip&lt;/em&gt;, and virtual environments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Everyone is going to have their own preferences for version control tools and an editor; but the recommendations I make regarding Python installations, package management, and workspaces/virtual environments should be fairly standard for anyone doing Python development on a Unix-like system in 2015.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section id="python-proper" class="level2"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Python Proper&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First up: Python itself. OS X ships with a built-in copy of Python 2; in the latest version of Yosemite, it’s running Python 2.7.6. The latest version of Python 2 is 2.7.9, so that isn’t &lt;em&gt;terribly&lt;/em&gt; far behind—but it is still behind. Moreover, OS X does &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; ship with Python 3, and since I do all of my development in Python 3&lt;a href="#fn2" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref2"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; I need to install it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section id="homebrew" class="level3"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Homebrew&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For a long time, I managed all my Python installations with &lt;a href="http://brew.sh"&gt;&lt;em&gt;homebrew&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. If you’re not familiar with it, &lt;em&gt;homebrew&lt;/em&gt; is a package manager that lets you installed tools on the command line, similar to what you get from &lt;em&gt;aptitude&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;yum&lt;/em&gt; on Ubuntu or Fedora respectively.&lt;a href="#fn3" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref3"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; If you’re not using &lt;em&gt;homebrew&lt;/em&gt; yet, I highly recommend it for installing command-line tools. (If you’re not using command-line tools yet, then the rest of this post will either bore you to death, or prove extremely enlightening!) If you haven’t started yet, now’s a good time: &lt;a href="http://brew.sh"&gt;go install it!&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While &lt;em&gt;homebrew&lt;/em&gt; is great for installing and managing packages in general, I can’t say this loud enough: &lt;em&gt;don’t manage Python with homebrew&lt;/em&gt;. It’s finicky, and really isn’t meant for all the things you have to do to manage more than one version of Python at a time.&lt;a href="#fn4" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref4"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;4&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (There’s a reason there’s a whole &lt;a href="https://github.com/Homebrew/homebrew/blob/master/share/doc/homebrew/Homebrew-and-Python.md"&gt;troubleshooting section&lt;/a&gt; devoted to it.) If you think it’s crazy that I might want more than one copy of Python installed a time, well… let’s just say I suspect you’ll change your mind after doing a bit more development. (At the most basic, most people will end up wanting both Python 2 and 3 installed, and will want to upgrade them as bug fixes and the like come out.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="pyenv" class="level3"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;pyenv&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instead of installing via &lt;em&gt;homebrew&lt;/em&gt;, use it to install &lt;a href="https://github.com/yyuu/pyenv"&gt;&lt;em&gt;pyenv&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, and use that to manage your installations. &lt;em&gt;pyenv&lt;/em&gt; is a dedicated tool for managing your “Python environment,” and it excels at that. If you were on a Mac with &lt;em&gt;homebrew&lt;/em&gt; installed, your setup process to add the latest version of Python might look something like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="shell"&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ brew install pyenv
$ echo &amp;#39;eval &amp;quot;$(pyenv init -)&amp;quot;&amp;#39; &amp;gt;&amp;gt; ~.profile
$ source ~/.profile
$ pyenv install 3.4.3&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Line by line, that (a) installs &lt;em&gt;pyenv&lt;/em&gt;, (b) adds a hook to your shell profile,&lt;a href="#fn5" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref5"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;5&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (c) updates your current session using the updated profile, and (d) installs the latest version of Python (as of the time I’m writing this). Now you have a full version of Python 3.4.3 alongside the system install of Python 2.7.6. If you wanted to install 2.7.9, or 2.2.3, or the development version of PyPy3, you could easily do that as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition, &lt;em&gt;pyenv&lt;/em&gt; lets you specify which version to use globally (&lt;code&gt;pyenv global &amp;lt;name&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;) and which version to use in a given directory structure (&lt;code&gt;pyenv local &amp;lt;name&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;). So if you prefer to use Python 3 in general, but need to use Python 2 on one project, you can just navigate to the root of that project and set it:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="shell"&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ pyenv global 3.4.3
$ cd path/to/my/project
$ pyenv local 2.7.9&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This will create a simple plain text file, &lt;code&gt;.python-version&lt;/code&gt;, whose contents will be just &lt;code&gt;2.7.9&lt;/code&gt;—but for everything under &lt;code&gt;path/to/my/project&lt;/code&gt;, typing &lt;code&gt;python&lt;/code&gt; will launch Python 2.7.9, while typing it &lt;em&gt;outside&lt;/em&gt; that folder will launch Python 3.4.3. (If you want, you can just create the &lt;code&gt;.python-version&lt;/code&gt; file yourself manually and give it the name of a version. There’s nothing special about it all; it’s just the place &lt;code&gt;pyenv&lt;/code&gt; looks to know which Python version to use.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="managing-python-packages" class="level2"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Managing Python Packages&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are four basic approaches to managing Python packages:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;installing them manually&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;using a system-level package manager like &lt;em&gt;homebrew&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;yum&lt;/em&gt;, or &lt;em&gt;aptitude&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;using &lt;em&gt;easy_install&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;using &lt;em&gt;pip&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The vast majority of the time, the right choice is using &lt;em&gt;pip&lt;/em&gt;. Over the last few years, &lt;em&gt;pip&lt;/em&gt; has become the default install tool for Python packages and it now ships natively with it on every platform. Suffice it to say: if you need to install a package, do not install it not with &lt;em&gt;homebrew&lt;/em&gt; (or &lt;em&gt;aptitude&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;yum&lt;/em&gt;). Install it with &lt;em&gt;pip&lt;/em&gt;. It integrates with Python better, it always has access both to the latest versions of Python packages (including those only available in e.g. development repositories on GitHub or Bitbucket or wherever else) and to all previously released versions, and it’s the community’s main tool for the job.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That said, occasionally it makes sense to install packages manually by downloading them and running &lt;code&gt;python setup.py install&lt;/code&gt; or to use a system-level package manager. On the other hand, given &lt;em&gt;pip&lt;/em&gt;’s ability to do everything &lt;em&gt;easy_install&lt;/em&gt; does, and its ability to do quite a few more things as well, there really isn’t a time to use &lt;em&gt;easy_install&lt;/em&gt;. Using the language-supplied tools keeps everything playing nicely together. Perhaps just as importantly, it is the only way to make sure everything behaves the way it should when you start using…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="virtual-environments" class="level2"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Virtual Environments&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When working with a variety of different clients, or simply on different projects, it is common not only to end up with different versions of Python but also with different sets of packages or—tricker still!—different versions of the same package required for different projects. Virtual environments provide a solution: they reuse the main Python executable (by creating links on the file system to it), but create isolated “workspaces” for the various packages you might install.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That way, in one workspace, you might have version 1.2 of a package installed, and in another you might have version 3.3 installed—because those are the required dependencies for something &lt;em&gt;else&lt;/em&gt; you’re doing. This isn’t a hypothetical situation. For quite a while with one of my clients, we had pinned a particular version of the Python documentation package we use because it broke our use case after an update—but I still wanted to have the latest version of that tool in my &lt;em&gt;other&lt;/em&gt; projects. Setting up virtual environments neatly solves that problem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section id="venv-and-virtualenv" class="level3"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;venv and virtualenv&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you have Python 3.3 or later, you have a built-in tool for this called &lt;a href="https://docs.python.org/3/library/venv.html"&gt;&lt;em&gt;pyvenv&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;; if you have Python 3.4 or later, it supports &lt;em&gt;pip&lt;/em&gt; right out of the gate so you don’t have to install it yourself. If you’re on older versions, you can install &lt;a href="https://virtualenv.pypa.io/en/latest/"&gt;&lt;em&gt;virtualenv&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;code&gt;pip install virtualenv&lt;/code&gt;) and get the same basic tooling: &lt;em&gt;pyvenv&lt;/em&gt; was inspired by &lt;em&gt;virtualenv&lt;/em&gt;. Then you can create virtual environments with the &lt;code&gt;pyvenv&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;virtualenv&lt;/code&gt; commands, and use those to isolate different setups from each other. If you haven’t started using virtual environments yet, start now!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="pyenv-with-virtualenv" class="level3"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;pyenv with virtualenv&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I know, the similarity of names for &lt;em&gt;pyenv&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;pyvenv&lt;/em&gt; is unfortunate. If it helps, you can call the latter as &lt;code&gt;venv&lt;/code&gt; rather than &lt;code&gt;pyvenv&lt;/code&gt;. But, more importantly, one of the areas &lt;em&gt;pyenv&lt;/em&gt; is much better than &lt;em&gt;homebrew&lt;/em&gt; is its support for managing virtual environments. Install &lt;a href="https://github.com/yyuu/pyenv-virtualenv"&gt;&lt;em&gt;pyenv-virtualenv&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="shell"&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ brew install pyenv-virtualenv
$ echo &amp;#39;eval &amp;quot;$(pyenv virtualenv-init -)&amp;quot;&amp;#39; &amp;gt;&amp;gt; ~/.profile&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now you’re off to the races: you’ll never have to type &lt;code&gt;pyvenv &amp;lt;path to a virtual environment&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;, because instead you can just type &lt;code&gt;pyenv virtualenv &amp;lt;version&amp;gt; &amp;lt;name&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;em&gt;pyenv&lt;/em&gt; will take care of setting it up for you. Even better: all the nice tricks I listed above about setting directory-specific and global preferences for which Python version to use work equally well with virtual environments managed via &lt;em&gt;pyenv&lt;/em&gt;. In other words, you can do something like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="shell"&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ pyenv install 2.7.9
$ pyenv install 3.4.3
$ pyenv global 3.4.3
$ pyenv virtualenv 2.7.9 my-virtual-environment
$ cd path/to/my/project
$ pyenv local my-virtual-environment&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;code&gt;.python-version&lt;/code&gt; file will contain &lt;code&gt;my-virtual-environment&lt;/code&gt;. The Python version will be 2.7.9. The environment will be isolated, just as if you had run &lt;code&gt;pyvenv&lt;/code&gt; to set up a virtual environment. Everything works together beautifully! Moreover, you can easily reuse virtual environments this way, because you can set the &lt;code&gt;local&lt;/code&gt; value in more than one place. For example, I use the same virtual environment for this site and &lt;a href="//www.winningslowly.org/" title="A podcast: taking the long view on technology, religion, ethics, and art."&gt;Winning Slowly&lt;/a&gt;, because they have slightly different site configurations but all the same Python dependencies. Creating it was simple:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="shell"&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ pyenv install 3.4.3
$ pyenv virtualenv 3.4.3 pelican
$ cd ~/Sites/chriskrycho.com
$ pyenv local pelican
$ cd ~/Sites/winningslowly.org
$ pyenv local pelican&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I named the virtual environment after &lt;a href="//docs.getpelican.com/"&gt;the tool I use to generate the sites&lt;/a&gt;, and reused it in both sites. Both now have a &lt;code&gt;.python-version&lt;/code&gt; file that reads &lt;code&gt;pelican&lt;/code&gt;. Now, anytime I’m working anywhere under &lt;code&gt;~/Sites/chriskrycho.com&lt;/code&gt; &lt;em&gt;or&lt;/em&gt; &lt;code&gt;~/Sites/winningslowly.org&lt;/code&gt;, I have the same tooling in place.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="summary" class="level2"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The combination of &lt;em&gt;pip&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;pyenv&lt;/em&gt; and virtual environments makes for a very simple, straightforward process to manage Python environments these days:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Install Python versions with &lt;em&gt;pyenv&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Install Python packages with &lt;em&gt;pip&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Set up virtual environments with &lt;em&gt;pyenv-virtualenv&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you stick to those basic rules, Python itself shouldn’t give you any trouble at all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="references"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section class="footnotes"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn1"&gt;&lt;p&gt;All the usual caveats apply, of course: this may or may not work well for you; it’s just what works for me, and I make no claim or warranty on the tools below—they’re working well for &lt;em&gt;me&lt;/em&gt;, but I don’t maintain them, so if they break, please tell the people who maintain them! Also, because I do nearly all my development on a Mac (I test on Windows, but that’s it), the following is necessarily &lt;em&gt;fairly&lt;/em&gt; specific to OS X. You can readily adapt most of it to Linux, though, or even to a &lt;a href="https://www.cygwin.com"&gt;Cygwin&lt;/a&gt; install on Windows—I do just that when I have cause. But my main tool is a Mac, so that’s what I’ve specialized for.&lt;a href="#fnref1"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn2"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Lucky me, I know!&lt;a href="#fnref2"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn3"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Yes, I know that those are wrappers around Debian and Arch, and I know about &lt;em&gt;apt-get&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;rpm&lt;/em&gt;. No, that information isn’t especially relevant for the rest of this post.&lt;a href="#fnref3"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn4"&gt;&lt;p&gt;For example, if you upgrade your Python installation using homebrew and then cleanup the old version (e.g., by running the typical &lt;code&gt;brew update &amp;amp;&amp;amp; brew upgrade &amp;amp;&amp;amp; brew cleanup&lt;/code&gt; sequence)—say, from 3.4.2 to 3.4.3—and you have virtual environments which depended on 3.4.2… well, you’re in a bad spot now. A &lt;em&gt;very&lt;/em&gt; bad spot. Have fun getting back to a working state!&lt;a href="#fnref4"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn5"&gt;&lt;p&gt;You can of course drop it directly in &lt;code&gt;.zshrc&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;.bash_profile&lt;/code&gt; or wherever else. &lt;a href="//github.com/chriskrycho/profile"&gt;My setup&lt;/a&gt; puts all common handling in &lt;code&gt;.profile&lt;/code&gt; and runs &lt;code&gt;source .profile&lt;/code&gt; as the first action in any other shell configurations.&lt;a href="#fnref5"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 16 May 2015 22:40:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2015-05-16:2015/a-modern-python-development-toolchain.html</guid><category>Software Development</category></item><item><title>2015-05-16 19:30</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2015/2015-05-16-1930.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Updated the websites today. Did a bunch of back end work that &lt;em&gt;should&lt;/em&gt; be basically invisible or make a change seamlessly on the front end for both &lt;a href="//www.chriskrycho.com"&gt;chriskrycho.com&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="//www.winningslowly.org"&gt;winningslowly.org&lt;/a&gt;. Very satisfying day; nice to be working on things just because I can.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="references"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 16 May 2015 19:30:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2015-05-16:2015/2015-05-16-1930.html</guid><category>software development</category><category>design</category></item><item><title>2015-05-06 07:37</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2015/2015-05-06-0737.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Microsoft Visual Studio: bringing you links in error messages… that aren’t clickable!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="references"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 06 May 2015 07:37:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2015-05-06:2015/2015-05-06-0737.html</guid><category>software development</category></item><item><title>2015-05-06 07:22</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2015/2015-05-06-0722.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;I’m &lt;a href="https://github.com/chriskrycho/euler-elixir"&gt;doing Project Euler with Elixir&lt;/a&gt; as a way of keeping myself sane while I try to get a project that worked fine in Visual Studio 2015 Technical Preview to build in Visual Studio 2015 Release Candidate. &lt;em&gt;sigh&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="references"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 06 May 2015 07:22:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2015-05-06:2015/2015-05-06-0722.html</guid><category>software development</category></item><item><title>Lessons Learned</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2015/lessons-learned.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Since mid July 2015, I have been working on a complete redesign and re-build of &lt;a href="//holybible.com"&gt;HolyBible.com&lt;/a&gt;. The good folks at &lt;a href="//prts.edu"&gt;Puritan Reformed Theological Seminary&lt;/a&gt; who own the site wanted to replace its previous content with a Bible reading tool. While there’s still a lot to wrap up, the project is &lt;em&gt;nearing&lt;/em&gt; its conclusion, and I thought I’d note a few things I’ve learned (in some cases, learned &lt;em&gt;again&lt;/em&gt;) along the way. I want to say up front, lest these be taken the wrong way: I’m extremely proud of the work I’ve done, and the application I’ve delivered &lt;em&gt;does&lt;/em&gt; work to the specifications I was hired to meet. More than that, it does it well. But, of course, it could do it &lt;em&gt;better&lt;/em&gt;. The following thoughts are therefore not, “How I failed” but rather “How I will do this &lt;em&gt;even better&lt;/em&gt; next time around.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol type="1"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Single page apps are great, but not always the right choice.&lt;/em&gt; I made the decision, based on my expectations and understandings of what I would need, to develop the site as a single-page web application. This was a mistake. Not the worst mistake ever: it has its upsides, including performance &lt;em&gt;once the app spins up&lt;/em&gt;, but for the kind of content I have here, I would take a different tack today. Better in this case to deliver static content and &lt;em&gt;update&lt;/em&gt; it dynamically as appropriate than to try to load all the content dynamically every time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At a technical level, that would probably mean supplementing standard HTML with &lt;a href="//backbonejs.org"&gt;Backbone&lt;/a&gt; instead of developing it as a single-page app in &lt;a href="//angularjs.org"&gt;Angular&lt;/a&gt;. For the backend, while I did it in Node.js and that would work fine, I’d probably do a straight Django app (especially with a few of the goals I learned about &lt;em&gt;after&lt;/em&gt; the project was well along in development).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Progressive enhancement or graceful degradation are hard in web applications, but they still matter.&lt;/em&gt; In the past, I’ve always taken a hard line on making sure things either degrade gracefully or are simply enhanced by JavaScript content. In the architecture decisions I made for this app, I failed to take that into account (largely because I thought it would just &lt;em&gt;need&lt;/em&gt; to work as a web app, but see above). I regret that enormously at this point; it would be much better in this particular case to have content available even if the additional functionality doesn’t work. Even if you &lt;em&gt;are&lt;/em&gt; doing something where you are building an &lt;em&gt;app&lt;/em&gt;, finding ways to make it work on poor connections, older browsers, etc. matters. I’m still thinking a &lt;em&gt;lot&lt;/em&gt; about the best way to do this in the future.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;More popular doesn’t mean better.&lt;/em&gt; Angular has a ton of traction and uptake, and that was deceptive early on. I won’t so easily be fooled in the future. Angular is so very popular in part because Google can put serious money behind its development—and its marketing. But it’s &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; the best for many applications; if you’re not in the business of developing your own custom framework, it’s not even &lt;em&gt;close&lt;/em&gt; to the best. Use Ember or Knockout or any number of other full-stack frameworks rather than a meta-framework.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How to avoid making that mistake? Well, for my part since then, I’ve learned to look not just as the &lt;em&gt;quantity&lt;/em&gt; of material in a given community, but its &lt;em&gt;quality&lt;/em&gt;. For example, &lt;a href="//emberjs.com"&gt;Ember&lt;/a&gt; has &lt;em&gt;incredible&lt;/em&gt; documentation (far better than Angular’s), and they also have a much clearer vision and a more dependable approach to development (strict semantic versioning, etc.). Had I taken the time to read &lt;em&gt;both&lt;/em&gt; sets of docs more carefully and think through the consequences of their designs more thoroughly, I could have recognized this before starting. Next time, I will do just that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I will also look at the way the community behaves. The Ember community is &lt;em&gt;far&lt;/em&gt; friendlier for newcomers from what I’ve seen than the Angular community—no slam meant on the Angular crowd, but the Ember folks are just doing that really well. That matters, too. (I can’t speak for other communities, of course; these are just the groups I’ve watched the most.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All in all, Ember would have been the better fit between these two (even though, as noted above, it also wouldn’t have been the &lt;em&gt;best&lt;/em&gt; fit).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Unit tests really are the best.&lt;/em&gt; I did a vast majority of this project with unit tests—the first time I’ve ever been able to do that for a whole project. In other projects, I’ve been able to do it for parts, but never this much. It saved my bacon a &lt;em&gt;lot&lt;/em&gt;. Where I got in a hurry and felt like I didn’t have time to write the tests, I (inevitably and predictably!) ended up spending a lot of time chasing down hard-to-isolate bugs—time I could have avoided by writing well-tested (and therefore better-factored) code in the first place. Lesson learned &lt;em&gt;very&lt;/em&gt; thoroughly. Server- and client-side unit tests are &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; good. They’re also sometimes &lt;em&gt;hard&lt;/em&gt;; getting mocks set up correctly for dealing with databases, etc. can take a while. That difficulty pays for itself, though.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Unit tests &lt;strong&gt;really&lt;/strong&gt; don’t replace API documentation.&lt;/em&gt; I have seen people advocate test-driven-development as a way of obviating the need to do major documentation of an API. This is, in a word, ridiculous. Having to read unit tests if you want to remember how you structured an API call is a pain in the neck. Don’t believe it. Design your API and document it, &lt;em&gt;then&lt;/em&gt; do test-driven development against that contract.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sometimes ‘good enough’ is enough.&lt;/em&gt; There is always more to be done, and inevitably you can see a thousand things that could be improved. But ‘good’ shipping code is far more valuable than ‘perfect’ code that never ships. You should never ship &lt;em&gt;bad&lt;/em&gt; code, but sometimes you do have to recognize ‘good enough’ and push it out the door.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Full-stack development is fun, but it’s also really hard.&lt;/em&gt; I wrote every scrap of code in HolyBible.com proper (though of course it relies on a lot of third-party code). It was very, very difficult to manage that all by myself; it’s a lot to hold in one’s head. (One of the reasons I chose Node was because keeping my implementation and testing all in one language helped reduce that load somewhat.) Would I do it again? Sure. But very much chastened about the difficulties involved. It has been enormously rewarding, and I &lt;em&gt;like&lt;/em&gt; being a full-stack developer. But it’s a lot of work, and now I know more clearly just how much.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I could say a great deal more about the technical side of things especially, but my biggest takeaway here is that a lot of the hardest and most important work in developing software has nothing to do with the code itself. Architecture and approach shape &lt;em&gt;far&lt;/em&gt; more than the implementation details (even if those details still matter an awful lot). And popularity is not at all the same as either &lt;em&gt;quality&lt;/em&gt; or (especially) &lt;em&gt;suitability for a given task&lt;/em&gt;. In the future, I will be better equipped for the necessary kinds of evaluation, and will hopefully make still better decisions accordingly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="references"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 12 Apr 2015 13:49:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2015-04-12:2015/lessons-learned.html</guid><category>software development</category></item><item><title>Unsurprisingly, In Flux</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2015/unsurprisingly-in-flux.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;i class="editorial"&gt;This started as a &lt;a href="https://alpha.app.net/chriskrycho/post/57102562"&gt;series of posts&lt;/a&gt; on App.net. I &lt;a href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2014/a-few-theses-on-blogging.html"&gt;resolved&lt;/a&gt; a while ago that if I was tempted to do that, I should just write a blog post instead. I failed at that resolution, but at a friend’s &lt;a href="https://alpha.app.net/jws/post/57108281"&gt;suggestion&lt;/a&gt;, am adapting it into a blog post anyway. You can see the posts that prompted it &lt;a href="https://alpha.app.net/keita/post/57096585"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://alpha.app.net/jws/post/57096838"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The state of JavaScript frameworks today is a scale, really, from not-at-all-monolithic to totally-monolithic, in roughly this order: Backbone – React &amp;amp; Angular – Ember – Meteor.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Backbone and related library Underscore are really collections of common JS tools and patterns you can use to write apps, but they’re not &lt;em&gt;frameworks&lt;/em&gt;, per se. You’ll write all your own boilerplate there.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;React and Angular supply much &lt;em&gt;more&lt;/em&gt; of the functionality, but Angular is a “meta-framework” that aims to do &lt;em&gt;some&lt;/em&gt; boilerplate but let you construct your own custom app framework.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Angular is very powerful, but it’s kind of like Git: wires are exposed; you have to understand a &lt;em&gt;lot&lt;/em&gt; about the internals to get it to do what you want. Its routing functionality is pretty limited out of the box, too—so much so that there’s a near-standard third-party router.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;React, as I understand it, supplies a paradigm and associated tools oriented primarily at view state management, though with capabilities via extensions for routing, etc. These tools are &lt;em&gt;extremely&lt;/em&gt; powerful for performance in particular. It’s not a full framework, and the docs expressly note that you can &lt;em&gt;just&lt;/em&gt; use React for the view layer with other tools if you want.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;In any case, Angular and React do &lt;em&gt;different&lt;/em&gt; things from each other, but both do substantially more than Backbone.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ember is a full framework, strongly emphasizing shared conventions (with a lot of common developers from Rails). It’s perhaps less adaptable than React or Angular, but is much more full-featured; you have very little boilerplate to do.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Meteor is like Ember, but does server-side Node as well as client-side stuff, with the goal being to minimize code duplication, sharing assets as much as possible.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Of all of those, Ember has easily (easily!) the best-explained roadmap, most articulate leadership, and best development path. They are also aggressively adopting the best features of other frameworks wherever it makes sense.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Angular is currently in flux, as Google has announced Angular 2.0 will be basically a completely different framework; there will be &lt;em&gt;no&lt;/em&gt; direct migration path for Angular 1.x apps to Angular 2.0+. Total rewrite required.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ember uses a steady 6-week release schedule with very careful regression testing and semantic versioning, with clear deprecation notices and upgrade paths, and is therefore both rapidly iterating &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; relatively stable for use.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;If you just need a set of tools for enhance functionality on otherwise relatively static pages, Backbone+Underscore is a great combo. If you already have a bunch of things in place but want a dedicated view layer, React is good.&lt;a href="#fn1" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref1"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;If you’re writing a new, full-on web &lt;em&gt;application&lt;/em&gt; (SPA, or organized in whatever other way), I think Ember is the very clear winner at this point. I have good confidence in their leadership and they’re firing on all cylinders.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Regarding Angular, &lt;a href="https://alpha.app.net/mikehoss"&gt;@mikehoss&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://alpha.app.net/mikehoss/post/57105656"&gt;posted&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the record they are doing that to make it more mobile-friendly. The Ang1 has abysmal performance on mobile. Besides a time machine, this maybe the best option. And Miško is a bit of a jerk.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I can’t speak to his comment about Miško (Miško Hevery, one of the leads on AngularJS), but I agree about Angular itself: the rewrite needs to happen. Angular 1.x is a mess—as are its docs. It’s just not a good time to be using 1.x for any new projects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ll add to these points that I’ve used Angular for the last 9 months on HolyBible.com development. As I noted: the documentation is pretty rough, and in a lot of cases you really do have to understand what the framework is doing and how before you can get it to do the things you want. This is, in one sense, exactly the &lt;em&gt;opposite&lt;/em&gt; of what I’m looking for in a framework—but it makes sense given Angular’s goal of being a meta-framework.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rather like Git, though, which was originally going to be infrastructure for version control systems which would have their own interface, but eventually just had a “good enough” interface that we’re all now stuck with, Angular is being used &lt;em&gt;as&lt;/em&gt; a framework, not just as a &lt;em&gt;meta-framework&lt;/em&gt;, and it’s unsurprisingly not great for that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;i class="editorial"&gt;Take this for what it’s worth: not the final word (by a long stretch) on JavaScript frameworks, but rather the perspective of one guy who notably &lt;em&gt;hasn’t used all of the frameworks&lt;/em&gt;, but has spent some time looking at them. Moreover, I haven’t particularly edited this; it’s more a summary in the kind of short-form posts that I originally created than a detailed analysis. The only things I’ve done are expand some of the notes on Angular and React, and add the footnote on React.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="references"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;section class="footnotes"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn1"&gt;&lt;p&gt;I &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; don’t know a ton about React, but I do think a lot of what I do know about it is cool from a programming perspective. From a designer perspective, however, it’s a bit of a pain: React’s “JSX” domain-specific language is &lt;em&gt;much&lt;/em&gt; less friendly to developers than standard HTML, and therefore than either Ember or Angular, both of which implement their templating via HTML templating languages. There’s a substantil tradeoff there: React’s model is interesting not only academically but in practice because of the performance results it produces. It’s worth note, though, that others have recognized this and are adopting it to varying degrees; notably, Ember is incorporating the idea of minimizing changes to the DOM by keeping track of state and updating only differences, rather than refreshing the whole tree, in the new rendering engine (HTMLBars) they’re rolling out over the past several and future several releases.&lt;a href="#fnref1"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 28 Aug 2015 19:50:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2015-04-08:2015/unsurprisingly-in-flux.html</guid><category>software development</category></item><item><title>The Joy of Good Tools</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2015/joy-good-tools.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;i class="editorial"&gt;Note: This started out as a &lt;a href="https://alpha.app.net/chriskrycho/post/47820144"&gt;series of posts on App.net&lt;/a&gt;, but as I realized that it was growing a bit, I decided to &lt;a href="/2014/a-few-theses-on-blogging.html"&gt;take my own advice&lt;/a&gt; and turn it into a short blog post. (The first four paragraphs of this post are the same as the posts that spawned it.) And then, as so often happens with my writing, it rather took on a life of its own. So much for short.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After wrestling with Bitbucket issues again all day, I think I’ve finally hit the breaking point. Time to go ahead and drop the money on GitHub and migrate my private repos there. (Yes, GitLab is neat, but tool integrations matter, too.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think I’m also probably going to spring for a small subscription to Pivotal Tracker. It’s cheaper to do GitHub+PivotalTracker at my scale than to host GitLab and run YouTrack on a VPS. And that’s &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; counting my time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The big thing with Pivotal is that I &lt;em&gt;need&lt;/em&gt; the ability to estimate more effectively even than something like Trello affords (and I don’t want to spend time wrangling with Chrome plugins), and it gives me that. Totally worth the cost in saved pain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And as for GitHub as compared to the free GitLab… well, honestly, the F/OSS-copycat model bothers me on a lot of levels. The fact that their strategy is “copy GitHub as closely as possible, and charge for it” is not my idea of “winning slowly”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(“Winning slowly” is more than just the name of my &lt;a href="//www.winningslowly.org"&gt;podcast&lt;/a&gt;. In fact, it’s the opposite: we named the podcast that because it’s one of the core commitments in our lives.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I’m going to pay for Pivotal and GitHub. My time is worth something, and the quality of the tools I use matters, too. Ongoing irritation and frustration adds up over time. Good tools can make us happier. Bad tools can make work more frustrating than it needs to be. Given just how frustrating work can be anyway, the last thing in the world I want to do is unnecessarily spend my time being even more frustrated by my tools. And you know what? $7/month for each of those tools is absolutely worth more than the frustration of wrestling with tools that do the job less well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m actually really excited by this. Pivotal Tracker will help me avoid making the painful mistake of underestimation in the future, by helping me see how long things actually take and giving me a way to plan out major projects with that data immediately available. GitHub will be simultaenously more functional and much lovelier than Bitbucket—no strategy tax holding it back!—and will be much nicer to use.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the end of the day, it comes down to this: I’m happy to pay for good tools that make my work more enjoyable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To my surprise and amusement, this leads me to a closely related point I had been writing up in a separate blog post: the value of tools that &lt;em&gt;delight&lt;/em&gt;. It is not merely that bad tools make work unpleasant. Good tools can make work a &lt;em&gt;joy&lt;/em&gt;. Indeed, because my vocations is such a significant part of my life, few things bring me as much simple pleasure as a tool that does its job well, is pleasant to use, and is beautiful, all at once.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The latest example of this for me is &lt;a href="//www.neat.io/bee/index.html"&gt;Bee&lt;/a&gt;, a tool designed to make working with issue trackers like JIRA, GitHub Issues, and FogBugz easier and more pleasant. I use JIRA for one of my long-term contracts—I actually set it up for the company—and I have a love-hate relationship with it. JIRA’s power is great, but the web interface is slow and cluttered.&lt;a href="#fn1" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref1"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have used other desktop tools with JIRA before, and they were even worse than the web interface. I stumbled across Bee the other day (I cannot even remember how!), decided to try it out, and fell in love. It is simple, fast, and &lt;em&gt;elegant&lt;/em&gt;. That is a killer combination. I have been using it daily for over a week, and strange though it might be to say of a desktop client for issue trackers, I get genuine pleasure out of using it. (Yes, I know: that is a bit strange.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have the same experience with a number of other tools I use—&lt;a href="//www.git-tower.com"&gt;Tower&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="//bywordapp.com"&gt;Byword&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href="//www.jetbrains.com/idea/"&gt;IntelliJ IDEA&lt;/a&gt; to name just a few. This very post is written in Byword, and I’m &lt;em&gt;happy&lt;/em&gt; about it. I wish I felt that way about every tool I use.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And this goes beyond software. I have had the same experience driving a car. The Mazda3 I drove in and after college was a delight. The MUV&lt;a href="#fn2" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref2"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; we drive right now is sufficient. The Chevy Malibu we rented for driving to and from Texas in December was &lt;em&gt;irritating&lt;/em&gt;, with an inordinate number of small failures to consider how the thing would actually be used. I would buy another Mazda3 in a heartbeat; I would contentedly take another Lexus RX300-alike; I would avoid a Chevy Malibu like the plague.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Every&lt;/em&gt; category of tool is like this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The difference between a poor or mediocre tool and a good tool can make the difference between frustration and satisfaction. The difference between a good tool and a &lt;em&gt;great&lt;/em&gt; tool can make the difference between satisfaction and delight. That inspires me: it makes me want to make things so that they do more than &lt;em&gt;suffice&lt;/em&gt;—so that they &lt;em&gt;excel&lt;/em&gt;, so that they delight and energize their audience. Whether that is someone using a web application I write or someone listening to a piece of music I composed, I want them to experience more than good-enough. I want them to feel joy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is something profound here, I think, something that goes even deeper than just the experience of being happy enough with a good tool to pay money to use it. I think human beings are meant for that profound joy—meant for it in every breath. That these kinds of delights are rare, and so often marred even at their best by little failures, is a mark of the imperfection—and, in human terms at least, the &lt;em&gt;imperfectibility&lt;/em&gt;—of the world in which we live. But the fact that such moments will be rare until the eschaton neither undoes nor diminishes the imperative to strive after them—especially for those of us who, as Christians, affirm the goodness and the &lt;em&gt;telos&lt;/em&gt; of the created world. Quite the contrary. We have a responsibility and a charge as subcreators always to be able to say of the work we have done, “It is good.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am not there yet. I hope very much, though, that the work I do this year will be—for at least one person—a little sip from that deep well of delight. Whether I succeed or no, at least the bar is set where it ought to be.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="references"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;section class="footnotes"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn1"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Atlassian’s designers seem to be shooting for the kind of “flat” minimalism that is in right now… and missing the mark entirely. &lt;em&gt;All&lt;/em&gt; of their tools are a cluttered mess in the UI/X department.&lt;a href="#fnref1"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn2"&gt;&lt;p&gt;A “Mom Utility Vehicle”, my wry term for “SUV”-type vehicles sitting on standard car chasses.&lt;a href="#fnref2"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 09 Jan 2015 18:00:00 -0500</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2015-01-09:2015/joy-good-tools.html</guid><category>software development</category><category>design</category><category>joy</category></item><item><title>Growing Up Together</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2014/growing-up-together.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;A few years ago, you might have caught me in a grumpy moment grousing about JavaScript. I distinctly did &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; like writing it. Every time I sat down to deal with it, I found myself in a tangled mess of plain JavaScript, jQuery, and DOM manipulations that inevitably left me tearing my hair out.&lt;a href="#fn1" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref1"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; I found it difficult to write in the first place, and even harder to maintain in the long run. I could not come up with good ways to organize it, especially because so much of what I was doing was so thoroughly &lt;em&gt;ad hoc&lt;/em&gt; in nature. Cobble this together over here; scrounge together those things over there; hope nothing collides in the middle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the last four months, I have written several thousand lines of JavaScript, and I have &lt;em&gt;loved&lt;/em&gt; it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For my latest major project, relaunching &lt;a href="https://holybible.com"&gt;HolyBible.com&lt;/a&gt;, I wrote the front end in &lt;a href="https://angularjs.org"&gt;AngularJS&lt;/a&gt; and the back end as an &lt;a href="http://expressjs.com"&gt;Express&lt;/a&gt; app (the most popular &lt;a href="http://nodejs.org"&gt;NodeJS&lt;/a&gt; web framework). I’ve written gobs of tests in &lt;a href="http://jasmine.github.io"&gt;Jasmine&lt;/a&gt; (using &lt;a href="https://github.com/mhevery/jasmine-node"&gt;jasmine-node&lt;/a&gt; for server-side tests) and drawn on tons of other open-source packages.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And I have &lt;em&gt;loved&lt;/em&gt; it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A small example: a moment ago, looking up the link for Jasmine, I noted that the latest version released today. My response was, “Ooh—cool!”&lt;a href="#fn2" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref2"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What changed? Well, mostly I changed, but also JavaScript changed a bit. We both grew up over the last four years. On the JavaScript side of things, a lot of good design patterns and tools have come into play in that span. I’m sure there were plenty of good, disciplined web developers writing clear, careful, well-organized client-side JavaScript four years go. But in the interval, that kind of JavaScript got a lot more prominent, in part because it has had help from the rapid rise of server-side JavaScript in the form of Node.js and its flourishing ecosystem of components and tools. Build tools like &lt;a href="http://browserify.org"&gt;Browserify&lt;/a&gt; and development tools like &lt;a href="http://livereload.com"&gt;LiveReload&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://incident57.com/codekit/"&gt;Codekit&lt;/a&gt; have combined with best practices learned from those long years of jQuery/DOM-manipulation hell so that these days, good JavaScript is a lot like good programming in any other language: highly modular, carefully designed, and well-organized.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the same period of time, I have matured enormously as a developer (just enough to see how far I still have to go, of course). At the point where I most hated JavaScript, I also really struggled to see the utility of callbacks. Frankly, it took me the better part of a month just to get my head around it—most of the tutorials out there just assumed you understood them already, and, well: I didn’t. Functions as first-class members of a language was new to me at that point. Fast-forward through several years of full-time Python development, lots of time spent reading about software development and some harder computer science concepts, and my perspective on JavaScript has shifted more than a little. Closures are beautiful, wonderful things now. Functions as arguments to other functions are delightful and extremely expressive. Prototypal inheritance—trip me up though it sometimes still does—is a fascinating variation on the idea of inheritance and one that I think I like rather better than classical inheritance.&lt;a href="#fn3" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref3"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are still things I don’t love about JavaScript. Its syntax owes far too much to the C family of languages to make me happy; I quite like the way that CoffeeScript borrows from Python (white-space-delimited blocks, use of equality words like &lt;code&gt;is&lt;/code&gt; and boolean rules like &lt;code&gt;and&lt;/code&gt; rather than &lt;code&gt;===&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;&amp;amp;&amp;amp;&lt;/code&gt; respectively, etc.). And I am looking forward to a number of features coming in the next version of JavaScript—especially generators and the &lt;code&gt;const&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;let&lt;/code&gt; keywords, which will allow for &lt;em&gt;much&lt;/em&gt; saner patterns.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But all of that is simply to say that I am now starting to know JavaScript enough to know that its &lt;em&gt;real&lt;/em&gt; issues aren’t the surface-level differences from the other languages with which I’m familiar. They’re not even the warts I noted here. They’re things like the mix of classical and prototypal inheritance in the way the language keywords and object instantiation work. But I don’t mind those. Every language has tradeoffs. Python’s support for lambdas is pretty minimal, despite the utility of anonymous functions, for example. But I &lt;em&gt;like&lt;/em&gt; the tradeoffs JavaScript makes.&lt;a href="#fn4" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref4"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;4&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In other words, I discovered the same thing so many other people have over the last few years: JavaScript isn’t just a good choice for utilitarian reasons. Beneath that messy exterior is a gem of a language. I’m having a lot of fun with it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="references"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;section class="footnotes"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn1"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Thus the early balding starting by my temples.&lt;a href="#fnref1"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn2"&gt;&lt;p&gt;My wife’s bemused response: “Is that &lt;em&gt;another&lt;/em&gt; language?” Take that as you will.&lt;a href="#fnref2"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn3"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The couple weeks I got to spend &lt;a href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2014/a-little-crazy.html"&gt;playing&lt;/a&gt; with &lt;a href="http://iolanguage.org"&gt;Io&lt;/a&gt; certainly helped! Io’s prototypal inheritance is semantically “purer” than JavaScript’s, which is quite an improvement in my view. JavaScript’s &lt;code&gt;new&lt;/code&gt; keyword and the pseudo-classical object pattern it brings along can go rot in a bog.&lt;a href="#fnref3"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn4"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Truth be told, I like them even better from the perspective of CoffeeScript, which hides a lot of the rough edges of JavaScript and, as noted above, brings in quite a few things I like from Python. For my part, I intend to write as much CoffeeScript as possible going forward.&lt;a href="#fnref4"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 15 Nov 2014 00:30:00 -0500</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2014-11-15:2014/growing-up-together.html</guid><category>software development</category></item><item><title>A Ridiculous Situation</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2014/a-ridiculous-situation.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;One of the pieces of code I’m maintaining has an &lt;em&gt;absurd&lt;/em&gt; situation in its build structure—honestly, I’m not sure how it ever compiled. For simplicity’s sake, let us assume the four following files:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;main.c&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;secondary.c&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;writer.h&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;calculator.h&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The project has many more files than this, of course, but these are the important ones for demonstrating this particular piece of insanity (which shows up &lt;em&gt;many&lt;/em&gt; places in the codebase).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m reproducing here some dummy code representing an &lt;em&gt;actual set of relationships in the codebase&lt;/em&gt;. The functions and module nameshave been changed; the relationships between the pieces of code have not.&lt;a href="#fn1" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref1"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; When I started trying to build the program that included what I am representing as &lt;code&gt;main.c&lt;/code&gt; below, this is the basic structure I found:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section id="main.cpp" class="level3"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;code&gt;main.cpp&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the main module of the program. In the actual code in which I found this particular morass, it was actually code generated by the UI builder in Visual Studio 6&lt;a href="#fn2" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref2"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and then turned into an unholy mess by a developer whose idea of good programming involved coupling the various parts of the code as tightly as possible.&lt;a href="#fn3" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref3"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="c"&gt;&lt;code&gt;#include &amp;quot;calculator.h&amp;quot;
#include &amp;quot;secondary.h&amp;quot;

int a=0, int b=0;

int addNumbers(a, b) {
    return a+b;
}

void doBadThingsWithGlobals(int * someNumber) {
    a = 6;
    *someOtherNumber = 5;
}

#include &amp;quot;writer.h&amp;quot;

void main() {
    a = 3;
    doBadThingsWithGlobals(&amp;amp;b);
    addNumbers(a, b);
    doStuffWithNumbers(a,b);
    subtractNumbers(b, a);
}

// More insanity follows...&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yes, the main function and the &lt;code&gt;doBadThingsWithGlobals&lt;/code&gt; function are both modifying global state, and yes, there is an include statement midway down through the module. (Just wait till you see what it does.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="secondary" class="level3"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;“secondary”&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is a secondary module which has been somewhat cleaned up. It has normal relationships between header and source files, and includes all its dependency headers at the top of the file. It has a header which defines the public API for the module, and that even has inclusion guards on it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section id="secondary.h" class="level4"&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;&lt;code&gt;secondary.h&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;pre class="c"&gt;&lt;code&gt;#ifndef SECONDARY_H
#define SECONDARY_H

int doStuffWithNumbers();

#endif SECONDARY_H&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="secondary.c" class="level4"&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;&lt;code&gt;secondary.c&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;code&gt;doStuffWithNumbers&lt;/code&gt; function here calls &lt;code&gt;addNumbers&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="c"&gt;&lt;code&gt;#include &amp;quot;secondary.h&amp;quot;
#include &amp;quot;calculator.h&amp;quot;

int doStuffWithNumbers(int x, int y) {
    addNumbers(x, y);
}&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;But wait!&lt;/em&gt; you say, &lt;em&gt;That function isn’t defined here!&lt;/em&gt; Ah, and you would be right, except that it doesn’t refer to the &lt;code&gt;addNumbers&lt;/code&gt; function in &lt;code&gt;main.c&lt;/code&gt;. It refers to a function implementation in &lt;code&gt;calculator.h&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="calculator.h" class="level3"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;code&gt;calculator.h&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;pre class="c"&gt;&lt;code&gt;int addNumbers(int p, int q) {
    return p + q;
}

int subtractNumbers(int r, int s) {
    return r - s;
}&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Strangely, this &lt;code&gt;addNumbers&lt;/code&gt; function is identical to the one in &lt;code&gt;main.c&lt;/code&gt;. Even &lt;em&gt;more&lt;/em&gt; strangely, it is defined—not merely declared, actually defined—in the header file! Nor is this the only such function. Look at the details of &lt;code&gt;writer.h&lt;/code&gt;, which was mysteriously included above in the middle of the main module.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="writer.h" class="level3"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;code&gt;writer.h&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;pre class="c"&gt;&lt;code&gt;void writeStuff() {
    fprintf(stdout, &amp;quot;a: %d, b: %d&amp;quot;, a, b);
}&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once again, we have a full-fledged implementation in the header file. Why, you ask? Presumably because the developer responsible for writing this code never quite got his head around how C’s build system works. The entirety of one of the central components of this software—an element that in any normal build would be a common library—was a single, approximately 2,000-line &lt;em&gt;header file&lt;/em&gt;. (Say hello to &lt;code&gt;calculator.h&lt;/code&gt; up there; that’s what I’m abstracting away for this example.)&lt;a href="#fn4" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref4"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;4&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Worse: it is printing the values of &lt;code&gt;a&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;b&lt;/code&gt;, and no, I am not skipping some part of &lt;code&gt;writer.h&lt;/code&gt;. It is getting those from &lt;code&gt;main.c&lt;/code&gt;, because it was included after they were defined, and the build process essentially drops this header inline into &lt;code&gt;main.c&lt;/code&gt; before it compilation.&lt;a href="#fn5" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref5"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;5&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; So here we have a header file with the implementation of a given piece of code, included in a specific location and defined in such a way that if you change where it is included, it will no longer function properly (since the variables will not have been defined!)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Worse, there are conflicting definitions for one of the functions used in &lt;code&gt;main.c&lt;/code&gt;, and because of its dependency on &lt;em&gt;other&lt;/em&gt; functions in &lt;code&gt;calculator.h&lt;/code&gt; (e.g. &lt;code&gt;subtractNumbers&lt;/code&gt; in this mock-up), it cannot be removed! Moreover, given the many places &lt;code&gt;calculator.h&lt;/code&gt; is referenced throughout the code base, it is non-trivial to refactor it.&lt;a href="#fn6" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref6"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;6&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If this sounds insane… that’s because it is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you’re curious how I dealt with it, well… I renamed the &lt;code&gt;addNumbers()&lt;/code&gt; function in &lt;code&gt;main.c&lt;/code&gt; to &lt;code&gt;_addNumbers()&lt;/code&gt; and put a loud, angry &lt;code&gt;TODO&lt;/code&gt; on it for the current release, because the only way to fix it is to refactor this whole giant mess.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The takeaway of the story, if there is one, is that people will do crazier, weirder, worse things than you can possibly imagine when they don’t understand the tools they are using and just hack at them till they can make them work. The moral of the story? I’m not sure. Run away from crazy code like this? Be prepared to spend your life refactoring?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How about: try desperately &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; to leave this kind of thing for the person following you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="references"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section class="footnotes"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn1"&gt;&lt;p&gt;That’s actually not &lt;em&gt;wholly&lt;/em&gt; true, because these pieces of code are also duplicated in numerous places throughout the codebase. We’ve eliminated as many as possible at present… but not all of them, courtesy of the crazy dependency chains that exist. Toss in a dependency on Visual Studio 6 for some of those components, and, well… suffice it to say that we’re just happy there are only two versions floating around instead of the seven that were present when I started working with this codebase two and a half years ago.&lt;a href="#fnref1"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn2"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Yes, &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Microsoft_Visual_Studio#Visual_Studio_6.0_.281998.29"&gt;&lt;em&gt;that&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; Visual Studio 6. The one from 1998. Yes, that’s insane. No, we haven’t managed to get rid of it yet, though we’re close. So close.&lt;a href="#fnref2"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn3"&gt;&lt;p&gt;I am not joking. Multi-thousand line functions constituting the entirety of a program are not just &lt;em&gt;normal&lt;/em&gt;, they are pretty much the only way that programmer ever wrote. When you see the code samples below, you will see why: someone was lacking an understanding of C’s build system.&lt;a href="#fnref3"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn4"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Also, that’s the piece of code of which I found seven different versions in various places when I started. Seven!&lt;a href="#fnref4"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn5"&gt;&lt;p&gt;I once ran into some code working on a different project for an entirely different client where there had been a strict 1,000-line limit to C source files, as part of an attempt to enforce some discipline in modularizing the code. Instead of embracing modularity, the developers just got in the habit of splitting the source file and adding &lt;code&gt;#include&lt;/code&gt; statements at the end of each file so that they could just keep writing their non-modular code.&lt;a href="#fnref5"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn6"&gt;&lt;p&gt;I have tried. Twice. I’m hoping that the third time &lt;em&gt;will&lt;/em&gt; be the charm.&lt;a href="#fnref6"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 07 Nov 2014 21:00:00 -0500</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2014-11-07:2014/a-ridiculous-situation.html</guid><category>software development</category></item><item><title>The Next Generation of Version Control</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2014/next-gen-vcs.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;The current state of affairs in version control systems is a mess. To be sure, software development is &lt;em&gt;far&lt;/em&gt; better with &lt;em&gt;any&lt;/em&gt; of the distributed version control systems in play—the three big ones being &lt;a href="http://git-scm.com"&gt;Git&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://mercurial.selenic.com"&gt;Mercurial&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;code&gt;hg&lt;/code&gt;), and &lt;a href="http://bazaar.canonical.com/en/"&gt;Bazaar&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;code&gt;bzr&lt;/code&gt;), with a few other names like &lt;a href="http://www.fossil-scm.org"&gt;Fossil&lt;/a&gt; floating around the periphery—than it ever was in a centralized version control system. There are definitely a few downsides for people converting over from some standard centralized version control systems, notably the increased number of steps in play to accomplish the same tasks.&lt;a href="#fn1" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref1"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; But on the whole, the advantages of being able to commit locally, have multiple complete copies of the repository, and share work without touching a centralized server far outweigh any downsides compared to the old centralized system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That being so, my opening statement remains true, I think: &lt;em&gt;The current state of affairs in version control is a mess.&lt;/em&gt; Here is what I mean: of those three major players (Git, Hg, and Bazaar), each has significant downsides relative to the others. Git is famously complex (even arcane), with a user interface design philosphy closely matching the UI sensibilities of Linus Torvalds—which is to say, all the wires are exposed, and it is about as user-hostile as it could be.&lt;a href="#fn2" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref2"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; It often outperforms Hg or Bazaar, but it has quirks, to say the very least. Hg and Bazaar both have &lt;em&gt;much&lt;/em&gt; better designed user interfaces. They also have saner defaults (especially before the arrival of Git 2.0), and they have better branching models and approaches to history.&lt;a href="#fn3" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref3"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; They have substantially better documentation—perhaps especially so with Bazaar, but with either one a user can understand how to use the tool &lt;em&gt;without having to understand the mechanics of the tool&lt;/em&gt;. This is simply not the case with Git, and while I &lt;em&gt;enjoy&lt;/em&gt; knowing the mechanics of Git because I find them interesting, &lt;em&gt;having&lt;/em&gt; to understand the mechanics of a tool to be able to use it is a problem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the other systems have their downsides relative, to Git, too. (I will focus on Hg because I have never used Bazaar beyond playing with it, though I have read a good bit of the documentation.) Mutable history in Git is valuable and useful at times; I have rewritten whole sequences of commits when I realized I committed the wrong things but hadn’t yet pushed.&lt;a href="#fn4" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref4"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;4&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; Being able to commit chunks instead of having to commit whole files at a go is good; I feel the lack of this every time I use Hg.&lt;a href="#fn5" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref5"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;5&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (Needing to understand the &lt;em&gt;file system&lt;/em&gt; that Git invented to make sure you do not inadvertently destroy your repository is… not so good.) A staging area is nice,&lt;a href="#fn6" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref6"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;6&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (even if &lt;em&gt;having&lt;/em&gt; to stage everything manually can be in the pain in the neck&lt;a href="#fn7" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref7"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;7&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In short, then, there was no clear winner for this generation. Each of the tools has significant upsides and downsides relative to the others. Git has become the &lt;em&gt;de facto&lt;/em&gt; standard, but &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; because of its own superiority over the alternatives. Rather, it won because of other forces in the community. Mostly I mean &lt;a href="https://github.com"&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt;, which is a &lt;em&gt;fantastic&lt;/em&gt; piece of software and easily the most significant driving factor in the wider adoption of Git as a tool. The competition (&lt;a href="https://bitbucket.org"&gt;Bitbucket&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://launchpad.net"&gt;Launchpad&lt;/a&gt;) are nowhere near the same level of sophistication or elegance, and they certainly have not managed to foster the sorts of community that GitHub has. The result has been wide adoption of Git, and a degree of Stockholm Syndrome among developers who have adopted it and concluded that the way Git works is the way a distributed version control system &lt;em&gt;should&lt;/em&gt; work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is not. Git is complicated to use and in need of tools for managing its complexity; the same is true of Hg and Bazaar, though perhaps to a slightly lesser extent because of their saner branching models. This is what has given rise to the &lt;a href="http://nvie.com/posts/a-successful-git-branching-model/"&gt;plethora&lt;/a&gt; of &lt;a href="http://scottchacon.com/2011/08/31/github-flow.html"&gt;different&lt;/a&gt; formal &lt;a href="https://about.gitlab.com/2014/09/29/gitlab-flow/"&gt;workflows&lt;/a&gt; representing various attempts to manage that complexity (which have been &lt;a href="https://bitbucket.org/yujiewu/hgflow/wiki/Home"&gt;applied&lt;/a&gt; to other systems &lt;a href="https://andy.mehalick.com/2011/12/24/an-introduction-to-hgflow"&gt;as well&lt;/a&gt;). Managing branching, linking that workflow to issues, and supplying associated documentation for projects have also cropped up as closely associated tasks— thus the popularity of GitHub issues and Bitbucket wikis, not to mention &lt;a href="http://www.fossil-scm.org"&gt;Fossil’s&lt;/a&gt; integration of both into the DVCS tool itself. None of the tools handle differences between file systems very elegantly (and indeed, it took &lt;em&gt;years&lt;/em&gt; for Git even to be useable on Windows). All of them especially struggle to manage symlinks and executable flags.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So there is an enormous opportunity for the &lt;em&gt;next&lt;/em&gt; generation of tools. Git, Hg, and so on are huge steps forward for developers from CVS, Visual SourceSafe, or SVN. But they still have major weaknesses, and there are many things that not only can but should be better. In brief, I would love for the next-generation version control system to be:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;distributed (this is now a non-negotiable);&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;fast;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;well-documented—&lt;em&gt;at least&lt;/em&gt; as well as Hg is, and preferably as well as Bazaar is;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;well-designed, which is to say having a user interface that is actually a user-interface (like Hg’s) and not an extremely leaky abstraction around the mechanics;&lt;a href="#fn8" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref8"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;8&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;fast;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;file-system oriented, &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; diff-oriented: this is one of Git’s great strengths and the reason for a lot of its performance advantages;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;extensible, with a good public API so that it is straightforward to add functionality like wikis, documentation, social interaction, and issue tracking in a way that actually integrates the tool;&lt;a href="#fn9" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref9"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;9&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;and last but not least, truly cross-platform.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That is a non-trivial task, but the first DVCS that manages to hit even a sizeable majority of these desires will gain a lot of traction in a hurry. The second generation of distributed version control has been good for us. The third could be magical.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="references"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;section class="footnotes"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn1"&gt;&lt;p&gt;A point that was highlighted for me in a conversation a few months ago with my father, a programmer who has been using SVN for a &lt;em&gt;long&lt;/em&gt; time and found the transition to Git distinctly less than wonderful.&lt;a href="#fnref1"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn2"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Anyone who feels like arguing with me on this point should go spend five minutes laughing at the &lt;a href="http://git-man-page-generator.lokaltog.net"&gt;fake man pages&lt;/a&gt; instead.&lt;a href="#fnref2"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn3"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Few things are as hotly debated as the relative merits of the different systems’ branching models and approaches to history. At the least, I can say that Hg and Bazaar’s branching models are &lt;em&gt;more to my taste&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;a href="#fnref3"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn4"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Yes, there are extensions that let you do this with Hg, but they are fragile at best in my experience, and substantially less capable than Git’s.&lt;a href="#fnref4"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn5"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Yes, I know about Hg’s record extension. No, it is &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; quite the same, especially because given the way it is implemented major GUI tools cannot support it without major chicanery.&lt;a href="#fnref5"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn6"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Yes, I know about Hg’s queue extension, too. There is a reason it is not turned on by default, and using it is substantially more arcane than Git’s staging are. Think about that for a minute.&lt;a href="#fnref6"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn7"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Yes, there is the &lt;code&gt;-a&lt;/code&gt; flag. No, I do not want to have to remember it for every commit.&lt;a href="#fnref7"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn8"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Let’s be honest: if Git’s abstraction were a boat, it would sink. It’s just that leaky.&lt;a href="#fnref8"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;GitHub does all of this quite well… but they have had to write heaps and gobs of software &lt;em&gt;around&lt;/em&gt; Git to make it work.&lt;a href="#fnref9"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 20 Oct 2014 07:25:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2014-10-16:2014/next-gen-vcs.html</guid><category>software development</category></item><item><title>Pushing Into C's Corner Cases</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2014/pushing-into-cs-corner-cases.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;I’m working on a project that is all in C because of its long history and legacy. We’re slowly modernizing the codebase and writing all our new code in Python (using NumPy, C extensions, and so on for performance where necessary). Occasionally, I just want to bang my head against the wall because there are things we can do so simply in any modern language that you just can’t do in any straightforward way in C. For example, I have file writers that all work &lt;em&gt;exactly&lt;/em&gt; the same way, with the single exception that the format string and the data that you put into it vary for each file.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Python, this would be straightforward to handle with the class machinery: you could simply specify the format string in each inheriting class and define the data points to be supplied at the top of an overriding function, call the parent function with &lt;code&gt;super()&lt;/code&gt; and be done.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To do something similar in pure C is nearly impossible. You can supply a format string with each function (or module, or however you separate out the code), and if you feel especially clever you could convert all your data types to strings and pass them as a list to be printed by the standard function. The net result would be &lt;em&gt;longer&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;less maintainable&lt;/em&gt; than simply having a set of essentially-duplicate functions, though.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="references"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 12 Aug 2014 09:00:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2014-08-12:2014/pushing-into-cs-corner-cases.html</guid><category>software development</category></item><item><title>The Long Race</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2014/the-long-race.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;It has been too long since I have written anything—too long not for my audience (small as it is), but for my soul. The last few weeks of class were of course even busier than the rest of the semester, courtesy of a couple major assignments I wrapped up and studying for and taking finals, all while doing my normal work as a software developer on the side. Writing simply fell by the wayside, alas. Even my devotions posts simply didn’t happen. And that is all right; there are seasons for all of these things, and it is not as if I didn’t write many thousands of words in late April and early May. They simply were not &lt;em&gt;blogging&lt;/em&gt; words.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So here I am tonight, writing simply to unwind. I spent much of the day working on various software projects—a pattern I expect to carry throughout the summer. In addition to my regular work for Quest Consultants Inc. back in Norman, I am picking up various web design and development jobs over the summer. God has been gracious in answering prayers for opportunities to pick up extra contracting work, and I have several really excellent opportunities to supplement my 20 hours a week for Quest with other work. That is nice not only financially, but also intellectually. The change of pace between different kinds of work helps me stay fresh on all of them. My own personal &lt;a href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2014/a-little-crazy.html"&gt;side projects&lt;/a&gt; are coming along slowly, but that is all right. Slow but steady is the best way to go about those kinds of projects anyway.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That lesson is one I have learned more and more from my ongoing and ever-increasing delight in running. So far in May I have run about 125 miles; I expect to run over 150 miles this month in total (though of course all such plans are always subject to revision, and never more so than when one’s wife is 37 weeks pregnant). I am now running easy, aerobic miles ten to fifteen seconds faster per mile than I could manage in my personal best half marathon time a few years ago. I run so (relatively) quickly now not because of any particular innate athleticism—quite the contrary, as anyone who has known me since high school can attest. I can run as far and fast as I do only because I have stuck with it and used a &lt;a href="http://markallenonline.com/maoArticles.aspx?AID=2" title="Working Your Heart"&gt;smart training plan&lt;/a&gt;. And really, as in most parts of life, it is that sticking-with-it that leads to getting somewhere. Of course, sticking with it is no guarantee that things will work out. It is usually a requisite step along the way, though—a necessary-though-insufficient condition. That is simply the way God built the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Little Ellie is quickly wrapping up her second year of life in this big world. She is saying lots of words (at last!), whining until she has driven Jaimie a bit crazy (in too-typical toddler fashion), and growing up in big ways and small. We are having a great deal of fun watching her start to be more socially aware and active, even if it is a little strange to have a daughter old enough that she has friends whom she loves and who love her in turn. She has also discovered a deep love of &lt;em&gt;Star Wars&lt;/em&gt;—no surprise for a daughter of ours, though the intensity of her delight in the movies, for a girl who is not yet two years old, did surprise both Jaimie and me a bit. You should hear her try to say “Darth Vader” or “Dark Side” or “Star Wars.” It is impossibly adorable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jaimie is, as noted above, some 37 weeks pregnant and quite ready to be done carrying our second little gal on the inside. She is still plugging away slowly at the &lt;a href="http://jaimiekrycho.com/shaking-epheria-pt-1/" title="Bloodlines: The Shaking of Epheria, Part I"&gt;second novella&lt;/a&gt; in her &lt;a href="http://www.amazon.com/Bloodlines-Epheria-The-Trilogy-ebook/dp/B00HY478QO/" title="Get Bloodlines of Epheria on Kindle!"&gt;Bloodlines&lt;/a&gt; fantasy trilogy. She manages to keep Ellie entertained—no small feat—and does a remarkable job taking care of things around the house so that I can focus on work and school. Her struggle with &lt;a href="http://2012-2013.chriskrycho.com/theology/marriage-depression/" title="Marriage and Depression"&gt;depression&lt;/a&gt; has not diminished, but God has given us grace to carry on and she and I have both learned to respond in better, healthier, more helpful ways when the slumps come.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As for the future, we really have no idea what the next several yeras will hold. I plan to finish my Master of Divinity—Lord willing, around December 2016. In the meantime, we will keep raising our little girls, I will keep writing software, and we will keep exploring and seeing what we want to do and how best to pursue those desires in a way that honors God. Who knows what those years will hold? God only, and certainly not us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="references"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 24 May 2014 00:07:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2014-05-24:2014/the-long-race.html</guid><category>software development</category><category>family</category><category>fitness</category></item><item><title>A Little Crazy</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2014/a-little-crazy.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;I’m going to do something a little crazy, I’ve decided. I’m going to go ahead and do like I wrote &lt;a href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2014/doing-it-myself.html"&gt;a bit back&lt;/a&gt;, and make &lt;a href="http://step-stool.io"&gt;Step Stool&lt;/a&gt; actually a thing over the course of the rest of the year. Not so crazy. What is a bit nuts is the way I’ve decided to go about that process. In short: as close to the hardest way possible as I can conceive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over the last couple weeks, I’ve been spending a fair bit of time toying with &lt;a href="http://iolanguage.org"&gt;Io&lt;/a&gt;. It’s a neat little language, very different in its approach to a &lt;em&gt;lot&lt;/em&gt; of things than the languages I’ve used previously. My programming language history is very focused on the “normal” languages. The vast majority of real- world code I’ve written has been in one of C, PHP, or Python. I’ve done a good bit of Javascript along the way, more Fortran than anyone my age has any business having done, and a little each of Java and Ruby. Like I said: the normal ones. With the exception of Javascript, all of those are either standard imperative, object-oriented, or mixed imperative and object-oriented languages. Python and Ruby both let you mix in a fair bit of functional-style programming, and Javascript does a &lt;em&gt;lot&lt;/em&gt; of that and tosses in prototypal inheritance to boot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But still: they’re all pretty mainstream, “normal” languages. Io isn’t like that at all. For one thing, it’s hardly popular in any sense at all. Well-known among the hackers&lt;a href="#fn1" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref1"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; I know, perhaps, but not popular by any measure. It’s small. And it’s very &lt;em&gt;alien&lt;/em&gt; in some ways. It’s &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Prototype-based_programming"&gt;prototypal inheritance&lt;/a&gt;, not normal inheritance. Courtesy of &lt;a href="https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Web/JavaScript/Guide/Inheritance_and_the_prototype_chain"&gt;Javascript&lt;/a&gt;, I have a &lt;em&gt;little&lt;/em&gt; familiarity with that, but it’s definitely still not my default way of thinking about inheritance. Python’s inheritance model (the one I use most frequently) is &lt;em&gt;essentially&lt;/em&gt; the same as that in C++, Java, PHP, and so on—it’s normal class-driven inheritance. Io goes off and does full-blown prototypal inheritance; even just the little I’ve played with it has been fun.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Io also does a bunch of other things a &lt;em&gt;lot&lt;/em&gt; different from the other languages I’ve used. First, there are no keywords or—formally speaking—even operators in the language. Every action (including ones like &lt;code&gt;+&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;for&lt;/code&gt;) is simply a message. Every value is an object (so &lt;code&gt;1.0&lt;/code&gt; is just as fully an object as an arbitrarily-defined &lt;code&gt;Person&lt;/code&gt;). The combination means that writing &lt;code&gt;1 + 2&lt;/code&gt; is actually just interpreted as the object &lt;code&gt;1&lt;/code&gt; receiving the &lt;code&gt;+&lt;/code&gt; message carrying as its “argument” the &lt;code&gt;2&lt;/code&gt; object (really just the message contents). This is &lt;em&gt;completely&lt;/em&gt; different at a deep paradigm level from the normal object-oriented approach with object methods, even in a language like Python where all elements are objects (including functions). The net result isn’t necessarily particularly different from calling methods on objects, but it is a &lt;em&gt;little&lt;/em&gt; different, with have some interesting consequences. Notably (though trivially—or at least, so it seems to me at this point), you can pass a message to the null object without it being an error. More importantly, the paradigm shift is illuminating.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Io also has far more capabilities in terms of concurrency than any of the other languagues with which I’m familiar, because it actively implements the &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Actor_model"&gt;Actor Model&lt;/a&gt;, which means its implementation of messaging instead of object method calls can behave in concurrent ways. (I’d say more if I understood it better. I don’t yet, which is one of the reasons I want to study the language. Concurrency is very powerful, but it’s also fairly foreign to me.) It’s also like Lisp in that its code can be inspected and modified at runtime. I’ve wanted to learn a Lisp for several years for this kind of mental challenge, but the syntax has always just annoyed me too much ever to get there. Io will give me a lot of its benefits with a much more pleasant syntax. It has coroutines, which are new to me, and also helpful for concurrency.&lt;a href="#fn2" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref2"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The long and short of it is that the language has a ton of features not present in the languages I have used, and—more importantly—is &lt;em&gt;paradigmatically&lt;/em&gt; different from them. Just getting familiar with it by writing a goodly amount of code in it would be a good way to learn in practice a bunch of computer science concepts I never had a chance to learn formally.&lt;a href="#fn3" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref3"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By now, as long as I’ve rambled about Io, you’ve probably figured out where I was going in that first paragraph. I’ve decided to stretch my brain a bit and write Step Stool in Io. There are bunches of static site generators out there in Python already, many of them quite mature. (This site is running on &lt;a href="https://github.com/getpelican"&gt;one of them&lt;/a&gt; as of the time I write this post—it’s quite solid, even its quirks and limitations occasionally annoy me.) The point of Step Stool has always been twofold, though. First, I’ve wanted to get to a spot where I was really running my own software to manage my site, letting me do whatever I want with it and guaranteeing I always understand it well enough to make those kinds of changes. Second, I’ve just wanted to &lt;em&gt;learn&lt;/em&gt; a whole bunch along the way. Third, it’s right there in the website link: &lt;a href="http://step-stool.io"&gt;step-stool.io&lt;/a&gt;! How could I pass up such an opportunity?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is that second goal that has pushed me to do this crazy project this crazy way. It’s crazier than just teaching myself a language in order to do the static site generator itself, too, because there are a few other pieces missing that I’ll need to write to make this work… like a Markdown implementation and an HTML templating language. I’ve never written anything remotely like either before, so I’m going to take the chance to learn a &lt;em&gt;lot&lt;/em&gt; of new things. For the Markdown implementation, rather than relying on regular expression parsing (like most Markdowns do), I’m going to use a Parsing Expression Grammar. That will certainly be more efficient and reliable, but—more importantly—it is also outside my experience. I have yet to start thinking through how to tackle the HTML templating language implementation (though I know I am going to make it an Io implementation of &lt;a href="http://slim-lang.com"&gt;Slim&lt;/a&gt;, which I quite like).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In any case, I’m going to be taking a good bit longer to get Step Stool finished. That is all right: I am going to learn a ton along the way, and I am quite sure I will have a blast doing it. And that is &lt;em&gt;exactly&lt;/em&gt; what these kinds of projects are for.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ll post updates as I go, with the things I’m learning along the way. Hopefully they’ll be interesting (or at least entertaining).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="references"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;section class="footnotes"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn1"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Hackers in the original sense of the world. Not “crackers”, but people who like hacking on code, figuring things out the hard way.&lt;a href="#fnref1"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn2"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Python 3.5 is actually adding coroutines, and I’m excited about that. I’ll feel much more comfortable with them there having used them in Io, I’m sure!&lt;a href="#fnref2"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn3"&gt;&lt;p&gt;I got here backwards, as it were—by way of an undergraduate degree in physics. I don’t regret that for a second: I got a much broader education than I could have managed while getting an engineering degree, and most importantly learned &lt;em&gt;how to learn&lt;/em&gt;: easily the most important skill anyone gains from any engineering degree.&lt;a href="#fnref3"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 29 Apr 2014 19:30:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2014-04-29:2014/a-little-crazy.html</guid><category>software development</category></item><item><title>Learning QML, Part 1</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2014/learning-qml-part-1.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;For part of my work with Quest Consultants, I’ve been picking up Qt’s QML toolkit to use in building out the UI. The declarative syntax and ability to define one’s own model in non-C++- or Python-specific ways is quite nice. That said, the learning process has had more than a few bumps along the way. I decided to go ahead and write those up as I go, both for my own reference and in the hope that it may prove useful to others as I go.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;QML is a &lt;em&gt;Javascript-like&lt;/em&gt; language for &lt;em&gt;declarative programming&lt;/em&gt; of a user interface. So it’s a Javascript-based language that sort of behaves like HTML. In fact, it behaves like Javascript in terms of how you define, access, and update properties, and you can embed full-featured (mostly) Javascript functions and objects in it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But when you have nested QML Types, you end up with them behaving more like HTML.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The weirdest bit, and the thing that I’m having the hardest time adjusting to, is that you can only edit properties of root Types when you’re working with an instance of that Type. And those Types are defined by &lt;em&gt;documents&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, to give the simplest possible example, let’s say I defined a new type called &lt;code&gt;Monkey&lt;/code&gt;, in the &lt;code&gt;Monkey.qml&lt;/code&gt; file, like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;// Monkey.qml
import QtQuick 1.1

Item {
    id: monkey_root
    property int monkey_id: -1
    property string monkey_name: &amp;quot;I don&amp;#39;t have a name!&amp;quot;

    Item {
        id: monkey_foot
        property string monkey_foot_desc: &amp;quot;The monkey has a foot!&amp;quot;
    }
}&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I can use that in another file. If they’re in the same directory, it’s automatically imported, so I can just do something like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;//main.qml
import QtQuick 1.1

// Rectangle is exactly what it sounds like. Here we can display things.
Rectangle {
    id: the_basic_shape
    height: 400
    width: 400
    color: green

    Monkey {
        id: monkey_instance
        monkey_id = 42
        monkey_name = &amp;quot;George&amp;quot;  // he&amp;#39;s kind of a curious little guy
    }

    Text {
        text: monkey_instance.monkey_name
        color: &amp;quot;red&amp;quot;
    }
}&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That creates a (really ugly) rectangle that prints the &lt;code&gt;Monkey&lt;/code&gt;’s name in red text on a green background. It’s impossible to access directly the &lt;code&gt;monkey_foot&lt;/code&gt; element, though, which means that composing more complex objects in reusable ways is difficult. In fact, I haven’t come up with a particularly good way to do it yet. At least, I should say that I haven’t come up with a good way to create high-level reusable components yet. I can see pretty easily how to create low-level reusable components, but once you start putting them together in any &lt;em&gt;specific&lt;/em&gt; way, you can’t recompose them in other ways.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From what I’ve gotten my head around so far, this ends up being less flexible than either HTML templating languages (which are, or at least can be, completely declarative) or normal Javascript (which is obviously &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; declarative). Mind you, it’s all sorts of &lt;em&gt;interesting&lt;/em&gt;, and I have a pretty decent idea what I’m going to do to implement our UI with it, but it’s taken me most of the day to get a good handle on that, and my head still feels a bit funny whenever I’m trying to see how best to create composable components.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note, too, that this is the &lt;em&gt;only&lt;/em&gt; way to create a new basic type of object in QML: it has to be the root level object in a QML document. I would &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; like to be able to access internal declarations—to have named internal types/objects. Unfortunately, QML doesn’t let you do this. I suspect this has to do with how the QML type system works: it actually binds these types to C++ objects behind the scenes. This is a non-trivially helpful decision in terms of the performance of the application, but it certainly makes my brain a little bit twitchy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are two basic consequences of this structure. First, any types you need to be able to use in other QML objects have to be defined in their own QML documents. Second, it is (as near as I can see so far, at least) difficult to create good generic QML types of more complex structures that you can then use to implement specific variations. For example: if you want to create accordions, you can create a fair number of the low-level elements in generic ways that you can reuse, but once you get to the relationships between the actual model, delegate, and view elements, you will need to create them in custom forms for each distinct approach.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is more like creating HTML documents than Javascript, which makes sense, &lt;em&gt;if&lt;/em&gt; you remember that QML is Javascript-based but &lt;em&gt;declarative&lt;/em&gt;. You just have to remember that while you can define some reusable components, the full-fledged elements are like full HTML pages with a templating system: you can include elements, but not override their internal contents. In QML, you can override &lt;em&gt;some&lt;/em&gt; of their contents, which is nice—but that is not the primary way to go about it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="references"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 11 Apr 2014 15:30:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2014-04-11:2014/learning-qml-part-1.html</guid><category>software development</category></item><item><title>Feels Right</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2014/feels-right.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;I had spent most of the last week and a half working on getting &lt;a href="http://www.firebirdsql.org"&gt;FirebirdSQL&lt;/a&gt; configured and ready to use for a project I’m working on with &lt;a href="http://www.questconsult.com"&gt;Quest Consultants&lt;/a&gt;. It was slow going. The tool is decent, but the documentation is spotty and it felt like everything was just a bit of a slog—to get it working correctly, to get it playing nicely with other pieces of the development puzzle, to get it working across platforms.&lt;a href="#fn1" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref1"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; Then, because I had done something a &lt;em&gt;little&lt;/em&gt; bit silly in my eagerness to get up and going last week and written code without a testable configuration, I hit a wall today. The queries weren’t working. I had made a &lt;a href="http://stackoverflow.com/questions/22865573/sqlalchemy-successful-insertion-but-then-raises-an-exception"&gt;bug&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I spent a substantial part of the day chasing down that bug, and then a conversation with user &lt;em&gt;agronholm&lt;/em&gt; on the &lt;a href="http://docs.sqlalchemy.org/en/rel_0_9/"&gt;SQLAlchemy&lt;/a&gt; IRC channel (&lt;a href="irc://irc.freenode.net/sqlalchemy"&gt;freenode/#sqlalchemy&lt;/a&gt;) got me thinking. The Firebird team describes one of their options as an “embedded” server, but &lt;em&gt;agronholm&lt;/em&gt; pointed out that what they really mean is &lt;em&gt;portable&lt;/em&gt;. It’s running a standalone server and client, but it’s not part of the same thread/process (like SQLite is). Then &lt;em&gt;agronholm&lt;/em&gt; very helpfully asked—my having mentioned my preference for &lt;a href="http://www.postgresql.org"&gt;PostgreSQL&lt;/a&gt; earlier—“Does Postgres not have a portable version?” Two minutes later, we had both found &lt;a href="http://sourceforge.net/projects/postgresqlportable/"&gt;PostgreSQL Portable&lt;/a&gt;, and I rejoiced.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It took me less than half an hour to get it downloaded and set up and to confirm that it would work the way we need for this particular piece of software. (Firebird had taken me a good three hours, what with digging through badly organized and not terribly clear documentation.) It took me less than half an hour more to get PostgreSQL to the same point that I’d finally gotten Firebird to after multiple hours working with it. And I was so &lt;em&gt;very&lt;/em&gt; happy. What had been an especially frustrating work day now had me quietly smiling to myself constantly for the last two and a half hours as I &lt;a href="http://stackoverflow.com/questions/22865573/sqlalchemy-successful-insertion-but-then-raises-an-exception/22872598#22872598"&gt;finished&lt;/a&gt; tracking down the bug that had set me on this path in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Several years ago, when I first started doing web development, I got my feet wet in database work with MySQL—probably the single most common starting point for anyone going that route, courtesy of the ubiquity of the standard Linux-Apache- MySQL-PHP stack.&lt;a href="#fn2" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref2"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; A year after that, I picked up some work that was already using PostgreSQL and fell in love almost immediately.&lt;a href="#fn3" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref3"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; Something just felt &lt;em&gt;better&lt;/em&gt; about running &lt;code&gt;psql&lt;/code&gt; than running &lt;code&gt;mysql&lt;/code&gt; on the command line. Postgres’ implementation of the SQL standard felt more natural. Even the tiniest little details like the way tables display when you query them in &lt;code&gt;psql&lt;/code&gt; was nicer. In less than a week, I was sold and haven’t looked back. While I’ve used MySQL out of convenience on shared hosting from time to time, PostgreSQL is unquestionably my preferred database target.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today’s experience brought that all home again. That grin on my face all afternoon felt a bit silly, but it highlights the difference that really good software design makes. I am not just talking about how it looks here—though, to be sure, PostgreSQL is prettier than FirebirdSQL—but how it works. PostgreSQL feels responsive, its command set makes a lot of sense and is easy to use, and it is &lt;em&gt;extremely&lt;/em&gt; well documented. In fact, I would go so far as to say that it is the best documented open source software I have ever used, as well as among the very most robust. (The only other open source software I find to be as incredibly rock-solid and reliable as PostgreSQL is the Linux kernel. I am by no means an expert on either, or on open source software in general, but the Linux kernel is an unarguably amazing piece of work. So is PostgreSQL.) All those tiny little details add up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s a good reminder for me as I write software that yes, the things I care about—the small matters that would be so easy to overlook when customers express no interest in them—really do matter. People may not know that things like typography make a difference in their experience, but those subtle, often imperceptible things matter. They may not consciously notice the differences in your interface design (even a command line interface), but it will change their experience of the software. Do it poorly, or even in a just-good-enough-to-get- by fashion, and you’ll annoy or simply bore them. Do it well, and you might just delight them—even if they can’t tell you why.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;section id="examples" class="level2"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Examples&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To make my point a little more visible, I thought it might be useful to post samples of SQL to accomplish the same task in the two different database dialects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section id="firebirdsql4" class="level3"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;FirebirdSQL:&lt;a href="#fn4" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref4"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;4&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;CREATE TABLE projects (
  id INT NOT NULL PRIMARY KEY,
  title VARCHAR(32) NOT NULL,
  file_name VARCHAR(32) NOT NULL,
  file_location VARCHAR(256) NOT NULL,
  CONSTRAINT unique_file UNIQUE (file_name, file_location)
);
CREATE SEQUENCE project_id_sequence;
SET TERM + ;
CREATE TRIGGER project_id_sequence_update
  ACTIVE BEFORE INSERT OR UPDATE POSITION 0
  ON projects
AS
BEGIN
  IF ((new.id IS NULL) OR (new.id = 0))
    THEN new.id = NEXT VALUE FOR project_id_sequence;
END+
SET TERM ; +&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="postgresql" class="level3"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;PostgreSQL&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;CREATE TABLE projects (
  id SERIAL NOT NULL PRIMARY KEY,
  title VARCHAR(32) NOT NULL,
  file_name VARCHAR(32) NOT NULL,
  file_location VARCHAR(256) NOT NULL,
  CONSTRAINT unique_file UNIQUE (file_name, file_location)
);&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is not just that the PostgreSQL example is shorter and clearer—it is that it is shorter and clearer because its designers and developers have taken the time to make sure that the shorter, cleaner way works well, and have documented it so you can know how to use that shorter cleaner way without too much difficulty.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="references"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section class="footnotes"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn1"&gt;&lt;p&gt;I do most of my development on a Mac, but do all the testing on the target platform (Windows) in a VM.&lt;a href="#fnref1"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn2"&gt;&lt;p&gt;At this point, I would only use one of those by default if I were building a web app: Linux. I’d use &lt;a href="http://wiki.nginx.org/Main"&gt;nginx&lt;/a&gt; instead of Apache, &lt;a href="http://www.postgresql.org"&gt;PostgreSQL&lt;/a&gt; instead of MySQL, and &lt;a href="https://www.python.org"&gt;Python&lt;/a&gt; (though &lt;a href="https://www.ruby-lang.org/"&gt;Ruby&lt;/a&gt;, Javascript via &lt;a href="http://nodejs.org"&gt;node.js&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/vstudio/hh341490"&gt;C# and the .NET stack&lt;/a&gt;, or just about anything &lt;em&gt;but&lt;/em&gt; PHP would do fine).&lt;a href="#fnref2"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn3"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Almost&lt;/em&gt; immediately because at that point configuration on OS X was a bit of a pain. That is &lt;a href="http://postgresapp.com" title="Postgres.app"&gt;no longer the case&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;a href="#fnref3"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn4"&gt;&lt;p&gt;To be perfectly fair to Firebird, it is improving. The upcoming 3.0 series release will make these two a lot more similar than they are at present, and clean up a number of other issues. What it won’t do is get the &lt;em&gt;feel&lt;/em&gt; of using Firebird more like that of using Postgres, or make the installation procedure smoother or easier, or make the documentation more complete.&lt;a href="#fnref4"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 04 Apr 2014 21:30:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2014-04-04:2014/feels-right.html</guid><category>software development</category><category>design</category></item><item><title>FirebirdSQL and IntelliJ IDEA (etc.)</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2014/firebirdsql-and-intellij-idea-etc.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Setting up IntelliJ IDEA’s built-in database tools to work with FirebirdSQL requires a particular setup configuration, which I’m documenting here for public consumption.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These setup tools &lt;em&gt;should&lt;/em&gt; be applicable to any of JetBrains’ other Java-based IDEs which include database support (e.g. PyCharm, RubyMine, WebStorm, etc.). &lt;em&gt;Note:&lt;/em&gt; the following apply to IntelliJ IDEA 12 and the associated platforms, but &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; to the IDEA 13 platform, which made substantial changes to how databases are configured. The underlying details are consistent, but the interface has changed. I have tested on PyCharm 3.1 to confirm that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was all done on OS X 10.9, so I also make no guarantees that this works on other platforms, though the likelihood that it behaves the same on Linux is fairly good. I will update the post if and when I have confirmed that it does.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Steps to configuring a database correctly for use with IDEA/etc. Note that steps 1–3 are fairly obvious; the real point of interest is in steps 4 and 5, which took me the longest time to figure out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol type="1"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Download the latest version of the Firebird &lt;a href="http://www.firebirdsql.org/en/jdbc-driver/"&gt;Java drivers&lt;/a&gt; for your operating system and your Java version. (You can check your Java version by running &lt;code&gt;java -version&lt;/code&gt; at the command line.) Extract the downloaded zip file. The extracted folder should include a file named &lt;code&gt;jaybird-full-&amp;lt;version&amp;gt;.jar&lt;/code&gt; (&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;version&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; is currently 2.2.4).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;In IDEA, in the database view, add a new data source: in the Database view (accessible via a menu button on the right side of the screen), right click and choose &lt;strong&gt;New -&amp;gt; Data Source&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Under &lt;strong&gt;JDBC driver files&lt;/strong&gt;, browse to the location where you extracted the Jaybird driver files and select &lt;code&gt;jaybird-full-&amp;lt;version&amp;gt;.jar&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Under &lt;strong&gt;JDBC driver class&lt;/strong&gt;, choose &lt;code&gt;org.firebirdsql.jdbc.FBDriver&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Under &lt;strong&gt;Database URL&lt;/strong&gt;, specify &lt;code&gt;jdbc:firebirdsql://localhost:3050/&lt;/code&gt; followed by &lt;em&gt;either&lt;/em&gt; the full path to the database in question or a corresponding alias.&lt;a href="#fn1" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref1"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; A full path might look like this on Windows:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;jdbc:firebirdsql://localhost:3050/C:/my_project/the_database.db&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With an alias, you would instead have:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;jdbc:firebirdsql://localhost:3050/the_alias&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then specify valid values for the &lt;strong&gt;User&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;Password&lt;/strong&gt; fields from your existing configuration of the database.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Click the &lt;strong&gt;Test Connection&lt;/strong&gt; button and make sure the configuration works.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That should do it. Note that the driver choice and path configuration both matter. On OS X, I found that only the &lt;code&gt;FBDriver&lt;/code&gt; with this (and one other, older-style and therefore not recommended) path setup worked successfully.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Observations, corrections, additional information, and miscellaneous comments welcomed on &lt;a href="https://alpha.app.net/chriskrycho"&gt;App.net&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href="https://www.twitter.com/chriskrycho"&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="references"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;section class="footnotes"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn1"&gt;&lt;p&gt;I strongly recommend configuring an alias in the aliases.conf file in the Firebird home directory (usually set as &lt;code&gt;$FIREBIRD_HOME&lt;/code&gt; during installation on *nix systems). This lets you move the database around at will, update just the configuration file, and not have to update any references to the database file whatsoever.&lt;a href="#fnref1"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 28 Mar 2014 09:00:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2014-03-28:2014/firebirdsql-and-intellij-idea-etc.html</guid><category>Software Development</category></item><item><title>The End of Surfing</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2014/the-end-of-surfing.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Sometime in the last few months it occurred to me that I no longer “surf” the internet. I read, to be sure, and every once in a long while I even go on a spree where I follow links from one site to another (or just in a long trail on Wikipedia). In general, however, I no longer surf. I suspect I am not alone in this: if we took a straw poll I would venture that most of my friends offline and acquaintances online alike spend rather less time in “browsing” mode than they do reading Facebook or Twitter or Instagram. Motion from link to link has been replaced by individual hops out onto Buzzfeed or a viral cat picture website.&lt;a href="#fn1" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref1"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The obvious explanation for all of this is already there in what I’ve written: Facebook and Twitter and all the rest of the social media web. To be sure, the advent of social media and the increasing degree to which social media have captured user attention on the web are a significant factor in the end of the old surfing/browsing behavior. This is a dream come true for those social media giants which have found ways to deliver ads to their many millions of users and thereby turn enormous profits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the same time, I think there is an oft-overlooked factor in the shifting nature of the web over the last decade: the browser. In fact, if there is any single cause behind the death of old-fashioned surfing, I would point to Firefox 1.0: the browser which popularized tabbed browsing to increasingly large sections of the internet-using public.&lt;a href="#fn2" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref2"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; The open-source browser steadily ate away at Internet Explorer’s then absurd levels of dominance, until Internet Explorer 8 included of tabs itself. By the time that Chrome came on the scene, tabbed browsing had long since become a given.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So why do I think that &lt;em&gt;tabbed browsing&lt;/em&gt; of all things contributed to the end of “browsing” and “surfing” as our dominant mode of reading the internet? Simply put: it broke linearity. Previously,&lt;a href="#fn3" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref3"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; one’s experience of the web was single- stranded, leaping from one point to another in a line that however contorted was always connected by the forward and backward buttons on the browser. The moment tabbed browsing came on the scene, that line was broken. Following a link might mean it opened in a new tab instead of moving the whole view forward to it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Surfing as I remember it in the late ’90s and early ’00s was inherently the experience of getting lost along that timeline, finding myself dozens of links along the chain and wondering how I had ended up there, and then being able to trace my way back. With tabs, that traceability was gone. With it went the inherent tension that we faced with every link: to follow, or not? To get sucked down into &lt;em&gt;this&lt;/em&gt; vortex or &lt;em&gt;that&lt;/em&gt;? Because in all likelihood, we knew, we were not going to be coming back to this page. With tabs, though, I could open both of those pages without ever leaving this one. I could start new journeys without ending the old. But there was a hidden cost: that newly opened tab had no history. It was a clean slate; before that newly opened link there was only a blank page. If I closed the original from which I had opened it, there was no going back.&lt;a href="#fn4" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref4"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;4&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; If I closed this new tabs, there was no going forward to them. The line was broken.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From there it was only a short step to the idea of a single site being the center from which one ventured out to other points on the web before returning: the Facebooks and Twitters of the world. In some sense, Facebook’s entire model is predicated on the idea that it is natural to open a new tab with that juicy Buzzfeed content while keeping Facebook itself open in a background tab. Would it work in that old linear model? Sort of. Would it feel natural? Never.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All of this because of tabs. Invention’s most significant results are rarely those the minds behind it expect. When we are designing things—whether a piece of furniture or a piece of the web—we have to remember that design decisions all have repercussions that we may not see. Technology is never neutral. Particular innovations may or may not be &lt;em&gt;morally&lt;/em&gt; significant, but they always produce changes in people’s behavior. Design has consequences.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="references"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;section class="footnotes"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn1"&gt;&lt;p&gt;For the record, lots of that hopping from link to link was on Buzzfeed- like and viral-cat-picture-like sites, too. I am not concerned with the &lt;em&gt;kind&lt;/em&gt; of content being read here, so much as the way it is being read.&lt;a href="#fnref1"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn2"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Note that I am not crediting Firefox 1.0 with &lt;em&gt;creating&lt;/em&gt; the tabbed browser—only with popularizing it. That distinction matters.&lt;a href="#fnref2"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn3"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Excepting having multiple browser windows open, which I am sure people did—but to a much lesser extent.&lt;a href="#fnref3"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn4"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Yes, yes, browser history and re-open closed tab commands. But the &lt;em&gt;experience&lt;/em&gt; of those is different, and that’s what we’re talking about here.&lt;a href="#fnref4"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 26 Mar 2014 20:00:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2014-03-26:2014/the-end-of-surfing.html</guid><category>design</category><category>software development</category></item><item><title>Doing It Myself</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2014/doing-it-myself.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Last summer, I started work on a project I named &lt;a href="http://step-stool.io"&gt;Step Stool&lt;/a&gt;—aiming to make a static site generator that would tick of all the little boxes marking my desires for a website generator. In due time, the project got put on hold, as I started up classes again and needed to focus more on my family than on fun side projects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Come the beginning of 2014, I was ready to bit WordPress farewell once and for all, though. While &lt;a href="https://ghost.org"&gt;Ghost&lt;/a&gt; looks interesting, since I do all my writing in Markdown files, there is something tempting about the canonical version of the documents being the version on my computer (and thus also on my iPad and iPhone and anywhere I have Dropbox and/or Git access). I did not have time at the beginning of the year to finish writing Step Stool, and I knew as much,&lt;a href="#fn1" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref1"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; so instead I moved to &lt;a href="http://docs.getpelican.com/en/3.3.0/"&gt;Pelican&lt;/a&gt; as a stop-gap. There were lots of good reasons to pick Pelican: it has an active development community, fairly thorough documentation,&lt;a href="#fn2" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref2"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and it’s in Python and uses Jinja2 templates—the same basic approach I had taken with Step Stool, and the same toolset.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, while I have been glad to be away from WordPress, my experience with Pelican so far has only reinforced my desire to get Step Stool done. There are &lt;em&gt;lots&lt;/em&gt; of little things that it does in ways that just annoy me. Many of them have to do with configuration and documentation. On the latter, while the documentation is &lt;em&gt;fairly&lt;/em&gt; complete, there are quite a few holes and gaps. (Yes, yes, open source software and anyone can add to the docs. That’s great—it really is—but if I’m going to use someone else’s solution, it had better &lt;em&gt;just work&lt;/em&gt;. Otherwise, I’d rather spend my time getting my own going.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, if you want to see how the pagination actually works, good luck figuring it out from the documentation. You’ll need to go looking at the way the sample themes (yes, both of them) are implemented to start getting a feel for it. Along the same lines, many of the objects that get handed to the templates are not fully documented, so it is difficult to know what one can or cannot do. I do not particularly want to spend my time adding debug print statements to my templates just to figure out what options I have available.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The same kinds of things hold true for configuration options. Moreover, the configuration is done through a Python module. While that makes the module easier to integrate on the code side of things, it makes its actual content much less transparent than one might hope. Python is not really well optimized for writing configuration files—nor is any normal programming language. Configuration is inherently declarative, rather than imperative.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is not to say that Pelican is bad software. It is not. It is, however, a fairly typical example of open source software implemented by committee. It has holes (some of them serious), bumps, and quirks. Here is the reality: so will Step Stool, though they will be the quirks that come from an individual developer’s approach rather than a group’s. But the one thing I can guarantee, and the reason I am increasingly motivated to get back to working on Step Stool. And yes, I do have a couple other projects on my plate as well—contributions to the Smartypants and Typogrify modules, my own &lt;a href="https://bitbucket.org/chriskrycho/spacewell"&gt;Spacewell typography project&lt;/a&gt;, and quite possibly a &lt;a href="https://bitbucket.org/chriskrycho/markdown-poetry/"&gt;Markdown Poetry extension&lt;/a&gt;. But I would like very much to just get back to doing this myself. There is freedom in rolling my own solution to things. I will not always have time to do these kinds of things; I figure I should do them when I can.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So here’s to &lt;a href="http://step-stool.io"&gt;Step Stool&lt;/a&gt;, and—more importantly—to writing your own software just to scratch that itch.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="references"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;section class="footnotes"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn1"&gt;&lt;p&gt;I spent quite a bit of time tweaking my friend Vernon King’s &lt;a href="http://www.vernonking.org"&gt;Jekyll-powered site&lt;/a&gt;, I got Winning Slowly off the ground, including designing the site from scratch and implementing it (also in Pelican), and I did some substantial redesign work on this site. That was more than enough for my three week break—as evidenced by the fact that I didn’t get to the sort of 1.0 version of this site until just a week or so ago.&lt;a href="#fnref1"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn2"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Emphasis on “fairly.” More on &lt;em&gt;that&lt;/em&gt; in a moment as well.&lt;a href="#fnref2"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 21 Mar 2014 22:14:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2014-03-21:2014/doing-it-myself.html</guid><category>software development</category></item></channel></rss>