<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Chris Krycho - static site generators</title><link>http://v4.chriskrycho.com/</link><description></description><lastBuildDate>Fri, 31 Aug 2018 18:30:00 -0400</lastBuildDate><item><title>Once More Around The Wheel</title><link>http://v4.chriskrycho.com/2018/once-more-around-the-wheel.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;I very much wish my publishing needs were not so… complicated. Academic writing—though that’s done for a while—poetry, code, and a strong preference for semantic HTML to be generated by it along with an equally strong preference for plain text authoring…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nothing works for me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The only Markdown parser out there which does the right thing with all of those is &lt;a href="http://pandoc.org"&gt;Pandoc&lt;/a&gt;. The options for using Pandoc directly are not great. Shelling out to it via &lt;a href="https://getpelican.com"&gt;Pelican&lt;/a&gt; (my current strategy) works but is &lt;em&gt;slow&lt;/em&gt;. The implemented-in-Rust &lt;a href="https://www.getgutenberg.io"&gt;Gutenberg&lt;/a&gt; generator looks like &lt;em&gt;exactly&lt;/em&gt; what I want performance-wise, but its &lt;a href="https://github.com/google/pulldown-cmark" title="pulldown-cmark"&gt;underlying Markdown engine&lt;/a&gt; doesn’t support citations &lt;em&gt;or&lt;/em&gt; poetry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I keep coming back to the conclusion that I’m basically going to have to build whatever I want myself, if I want my desired publishing flow to exist. I don’t really &lt;em&gt;want&lt;/em&gt; to do that, though. It’s a boatload of work, even “just”—just!—to do something like (a) learn Haskell well enough to build on top of Pandoc directly or (b) build a good C-based API wrapper in Rust so that I can do it &lt;em&gt;that&lt;/em&gt; way or (c) extend &lt;a href="https://github.com/google/pulldown-cmark"&gt;pulldown-cmark&lt;/a&gt; to support poetry and citation management.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For lots of reasons (c) is probably what I’ll ultimately end up doing; I want that for more than just blogging. More on that eventually, I hope.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But in the meantime I really just… want someone else to have the same weird needs I do and build this for me. I just know full well at this point that that’s not going to happen, and accordingly am basically resigned to muddling along with Pelican and Pandoc until such a time as I can actually buckle down and build what I want and need.&lt;a href="#fn1" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref1" role="doc-noteref"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;em&gt;C’est la vie.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn1" role="doc-endnote"&gt;&lt;p&gt;As an aside: the prospect of buckling down and building things like that in my spare time is &lt;em&gt;much&lt;/em&gt; less appealing given my current &lt;a href="https://v4.chriskrycho.com/burnout/"&gt;struggles with burnout&lt;/a&gt;, and as I’ll write about at some point in the future I feel a (perhaps-surprising to you, my reader) lack of confidence about my &lt;em&gt;ability&lt;/em&gt; to accomplish those things.&lt;a href="#fnref1" class="footnote-back" role="doc-backlink"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 31 Aug 2018 18:30:00 -0400</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:v4.chriskrycho.com,2018-08-31:/2018/once-more-around-the-wheel.html</guid><category>writing</category><category>blogging</category><category>static site generators</category></item></channel></rss>