<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Chris Krycho</title><link href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/feeds/tech.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://www.chriskrycho.com/</id><updated>2014-02-24T15:20:00-05:00</updated><entry><title>Goodbye, Chrome</title><link href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2014/goodbye-chrome.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-02-24T15:20:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Chris Krycho</name></author><id>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2014-02-24:2014/goodbye-chrome.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Last week, Chrome crossed the line for me. I deleted it from my system to clean
up its many hooks into my system&amp;#8212;I searched out every trace of it I could
find&amp;#8212;and will put it back on my system only for testing websites. Why? Because
it&amp;#8217;s just too creepy&amp;nbsp;now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;#8217;s the story: two weekends ago, I was sitting at a coffee shop working on a
friend&amp;#8217;s website, when up popped a series of Google Now &lt;span class="caps"&gt;OS&lt;/span&gt; X desktop
notifications from Chrome, informing me of the weather, a package having
recently shipped, and so&amp;nbsp;on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There were just two problems with&amp;nbsp;this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I never gave Chrome permission to do anything of the&amp;nbsp;sort.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I was not signed into Chrome or any Google service at the&amp;nbsp;time.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Number 1 is bothersome. Number 2 is so far beyond bothersome that I took the
nuclear option. Let&amp;#8217;s walk through&amp;nbsp;them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Google apparently decided to start opting people into Google Now on the Chrome
33 Beta. Opting people into anything new is nearly always a bad idea in my view;
opting someone into something that actively integrates with email, calendar,
etc. without asking them is just creepy. Now, full disclosure: I had previously
granted Google access to some of this data for Google Now on my Android phone
(though I have since moved to an iPhone). However, as is usual for Google these
days, the company took that permission in one context and treated it as global
permission in all&amp;nbsp;contexts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No doubt the box I checked when I gave them access to that data in the first
place legally allowed them to continue touching it. That did not particularly
bother me. Rather, it was the assumption that I wanted the same kind of
interactions from the service in a different context. This is typical of Google
&amp;#8212;typically un-human-friendly, that is. People do different things with their
phones than with their browsers, and have different expectations of what each
will do. More importantly, though, even if we might &lt;em&gt;want&lt;/em&gt; our browsers to start
supplying us the kinds of sometimes-valuable information that we get from Google
Now (or Apple or Microsoft&amp;#8217;s similar tools), we generally want the opportunity
to make that decision. Increasingly, Google is making that decision for its
users, leaving them to opt out and turn it off if they so desire. That is not a
policy I particularly like. So: strike one. Or rather: strike several dozen, of
the sort that had me moving away from Google&amp;#8217;s services for quite some time&amp;#8212;
but it probably still wouldn&amp;#8217;t have pushed me across the line to this kind of
hard kill-it-with-fire&amp;nbsp;mentality.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What did? That would be the part where Chrome started sending me desktop Google
Now notifications. Without asking me. In a browser to which I was not logged in,
nor logged into any Google&amp;nbsp;services.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I will say that again to be clear: I was not signed into Chrome. I was not
signed into any Google services in the browser. I had not allowed the browser to
create desktop notifications. And it started sending me Google Now notifications
for my main Google account. Worse: nothing I could do with the browser itself
changed that behavior. (Unsurprising: there was no way Chrome should have been
able to do that in the first place, logged out of all Google services as I&amp;nbsp;was.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Goodbye, Chrome. You&amp;#8217;re just too&amp;nbsp;creepy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was not the first time I have seen Chrome engage in behavior that does not
respect its users. I have repeatedly run into cases where clearing the cache and
deleting browsers&amp;#8230; doesn&amp;#8217;t. Cookies sometimes still stick around. Private
browsing sessions inherit cookies from the main window (and sometimes vice
versa). Closing a private session and launching a new one would sometimes still
include cookies and cache from a previous session (bank accounts still logged
in, etc.). Chrome had thus long been untrustworthy to me. But this was a bridge
too far. This was not just slightly unnerving. It was&amp;nbsp;creepy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Call it a bug if you like. It is likely that it was, in fact, a bug. So, most
likely, were the other cases I saw above. But these are the kinds of bugs that
make a browser fundamentally untrustworthy, and they are the kinds of bugs that
are that much creepier coming from a company whose profit comes almost entirely
from selling advertising&amp;#8212;that is, from selling user information to advertising
companies. The deal was that we trusted Google not to abuse that information.
Unfortunately, that deal just keeps getting worse all the time. (Pray they do
not alter it&amp;nbsp;further.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I will have a copy of the browser on my system for testing purposes, but for
nothing else. Goodbye, Chrome. And for that matter: goodbye, Google services.
Over the course of the rest of this year, I will be moving myself completely off
of all Google services (mail, calendar, etc.), with the sole exception of (non-
logged-in) search. You&amp;#8217;re just too creepy&amp;nbsp;now.&lt;/p&gt;</summary></entry></feed>