<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Chris Krycho</title><link href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/feeds/tech.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://www.chriskrycho.com/</id><updated>2014-03-26T20:00:00-04:00</updated><entry><title>The End of Surfing</title><link href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2014/the-end-of-surfing.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-03-26T20:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Chris Krycho</name></author><id>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2014-03-26:2014/the-end-of-surfing.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Sometime in the last few months it occurred to me that I no longer &amp;#8220;surf&amp;#8221; the internet. I read, to be sure, and every once in a long while I even go on a spree where I follow links from one site to another (or just in a long trail on Wikipedia). In general, however, I no longer surf. I suspect I am not alone in this: if we took a straw poll I would venture that most of my friends offline and acquaintances online alike spend rather less time in &amp;#8220;browsing&amp;#8221; mode than they do reading Facebook or Twitter or Instagram. Motion from link to link has been replaced by individual hops out onto Buzzfeed or a viral cat picture website.&lt;sup id="fnref:1"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:1" rel="footnote"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The obvious explanation for all of this is already there in what I&amp;#8217;ve written: Facebook and Twitter and all the rest of the social media web. To be sure, the advent of social media and the increasing degree to which social media have captured user attention on the web are a significant factor in the end of the old surfing/browsing behavior. This is a dream come true for those social media giants which have found ways to deliver ads to their many millions of users and thereby turn enormous&amp;nbsp;profits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the same time, I think there is an oft-overlooked factor in the shifting nature of the web over the last decade: the browser. In fact, if there is any single cause behind the death of old-fashioned surfing, I would point to Firefox 1.0: the browser which popularized tabbed browsing to increasingly large sections of the internet-using public.&lt;sup id="fnref:2"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:2" rel="footnote"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; The open-source browser steadily ate away at Internet Explorer&amp;#8217;s then absurd levels of dominance, until Internet Explorer 8 included of tabs itself. By the time that Chrome came on the scene, tabbed browsing had long since become a&amp;nbsp;given.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So why do I think that &lt;em&gt;tabbed browsing&lt;/em&gt; of all things contributed to the end of &amp;#8220;browsing&amp;#8221; and &amp;#8220;surfing&amp;#8221; as our dominant mode of reading the internet? Simply put: it broke linearity. Previously,&lt;sup id="fnref:3"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:3" rel="footnote"&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; one&amp;#8217;s experience of the web was single-stranded, leaping from one point to another in a line that however contorted was always connected by the forward and backward buttons on the browser. The moment tabbed browsing came on the scene, that line was broken. Following a link might mean it opened in a new tab instead of moving the whole view forward to&amp;nbsp;it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Surfing as I remember it in the late &amp;rsquo;90s and early &amp;rsquo;00s was inherently the experience of getting lost along that timeline, finding myself dozens of links along the chain and wondering how I had ended up there, and then being able to trace my way back. With tabs, that traceability was gone. With it went the inherent tension that we faced with every link: to follow, or not? To get sucked down into &lt;em&gt;this&lt;/em&gt; vortex or &lt;em&gt;that&lt;/em&gt;? Because in all likelihood, we knew, we were not going to be coming back to this page. With tabs, though, I could open both of those pages without ever leaving this one. I could start new journeys without ending the old. But there was a hidden cost: that newly opened tab had no history. It was a clean slate; before that newly opened link there was only a blank page. If I closed the original from which I had opened it, there was no going back.&lt;sup id="fnref:4"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:4" rel="footnote"&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; If I closed this new tabs, there was no going forward to them. The line was&amp;nbsp;broken.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From there it was only a short step to the idea of a single site being the center from which one ventured out to other points on the web before returning: the Facebooks and Twitters of the world. In some sense, Facebook&amp;#8217;s entire model is predicated on the idea that it is natural to open a new tab with that juicy Buzzfeed content while keeping Facebook itself open in a background tab. Would it work in that old linear model? Sort of. Would it feel natural?&amp;nbsp;Never.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All of this because of tabs. Invention&amp;#8217;s most significant results are rarely those the minds behind it expect. When we are designing things&amp;#8212;whether a piece of furniture or a piece of the web&amp;#8212;we have to remember that design decisions all have repercussions that we may not see. Technology is never neutral. Particular innovations may or may not be &lt;em&gt;morally&lt;/em&gt; significant, but they always produce changes in people&amp;#8217;s behavior. Design has&amp;nbsp;consequences.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the record, lots of that hopping from link to link was on Buzzfeed-like and viral-cat-picture-like sites, too. I am not concerned with the &lt;em&gt;kind&lt;/em&gt; of content being read here, so much as the way it is being read.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:2"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note that I am not crediting Firefox 2.0 with &lt;em&gt;creating&lt;/em&gt; the tabbed browser&amp;#8212;only with popularizing it. That distinction matters.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:2" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 2 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:3"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Excepting having multiple browser windows open, which I am sure people did&amp;#8212;but to a much lesser extent.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:3" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 3 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:4"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yes, yes, browser history and re-open closed tab commands. But the &lt;em&gt;experience&lt;/em&gt; of those is different, and that&amp;#8217;s what we&amp;#8217;re talking about here.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:4" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 4 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary><category term="design"></category><category term="software development"></category></entry><entry><title>Doing It Myself</title><link href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2014/doing-it-myself.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-03-21T22:14:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Chris Krycho</name></author><id>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2014-03-21:2014/doing-it-myself.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Last summer, I started work on a project I named &lt;a href="http://step-stool.io"&gt;Step Stool&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#8212;aiming to
make a static site generator that would tick of all the little boxes marking my
desires for a website generator. In due time, the project got put on hold, as I
started up classes again and needed to focus more on my family than on fun side&amp;nbsp;projects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Come the beginning of 2014, I was ready to bit WordPress farewell once and for
all, though. While &lt;a href="https://ghost.org"&gt;Ghost&lt;/a&gt; looks interesting, since I do all my writing
in Markdown files, there is something tempting about the canonical version of
the documents being the version on my computer (and thus also on my iPad and
iPhone and anywhere I have Dropbox and/or Git access). I did not have time at
the beginning of the year to finish writing Step Stool, and I knew as much,&lt;sup id="fnref:1"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:1" rel="footnote"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;
so instead I moved to &lt;a href="http://docs.getpelican.com/en/3.3.0/"&gt;Pelican&lt;/a&gt; as a stop-gap. There were lots of good
reasons to pick Pelican: it has an active development community, fairly thorough
documentation,&lt;sup id="fnref:2"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:2" rel="footnote"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; and it&amp;#8217;s in Python and uses Jinja2 templates&amp;#8212;the same basic
approach I had taken with Step Stool, and the same&amp;nbsp;toolset.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, while I have been glad to be away from WordPress, my experience
with Pelican so far has only reinforced my desire to get Step Stool done. There
are &lt;em&gt;lots&lt;/em&gt; of little things that it does in ways that just annoy me. Many of
them have to do with configuration and documentation. On the latter, while the
documentation is &lt;em&gt;fairly&lt;/em&gt; complete, there are quite a few holes and gaps. (Yes,
yes, open source software and anyone can add to the docs. That&amp;#8217;s great&amp;#8212;it
really is&amp;#8212;but if I&amp;#8217;m going to use someone else&amp;#8217;s solution, it had better &lt;em&gt;just
work&lt;/em&gt;. Otherwise, I&amp;#8217;d rather spend my time getting my own&amp;nbsp;going.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, if you want to see how the pagination actually works, good luck
figuring it out from the documentation. You&amp;#8217;ll need to go looking at the way the
sample themes (yes, both of them) are implemented to start getting a feel for
it. Along the same lines, many of the objects that get handed to the templates
are not fully documented, so it is difficult to know what one can or cannot do.
I do not particularly want to spend my time adding debug print statements to my
templates just to figure out what options I have&amp;nbsp;available.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The same kinds of things hold true for configuration options. Moreover, the
configuration is done through a Python module. While that makes the module
easier to integrate on the code side of things, it makes its actual content much
less transparent than one might hope. Python is not really well optimized for
writing configuration files&amp;#8212;nor is any normal programming language.
Configuration is inherently declarative, rather than&amp;nbsp;imperative.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is not to say that Pelican is bad software. It is not. It is, however, a
fairly typical example of open source software implemented by committee. It has
holes (some of them serious), bumps, and quirks. Here is the reality: so will
Step Stool, though they will be the quirks that come from an individual
developer&amp;#8217;s approach rather than a group&amp;#8217;s. But the one thing I can guarantee,
and the reason I am increasingly motivated to get back to working on Step Stool.
And yes, I do have a couple other projects on my plate as well&amp;#8212;contributions
to the Smartypants and Typogrify modules, my own &lt;a href="https://bitbucket.org/chriskrycho/spacewell"&gt;Spacewell typography project&lt;/a&gt;,
and quite possibly a &lt;a href="https://bitbucket.org/chriskrycho/markdown-poetry/"&gt;Markdown Poetry extension &lt;/a&gt;. But I would like
very much to just get back to doing this myself. There is freedom in rolling my
own solution to things. I will not always have time to do these kinds of things; 
I figure I should do them when I&amp;nbsp;can.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So here&amp;#8217;s to &lt;a href="http://step-stool.io"&gt;Step Stool&lt;/a&gt;, and&amp;#8212;more importantly&amp;#8212;to writing your own
software just to scratch that&amp;nbsp;itch.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I spent quite a bit of time tweaking my friend Vernon King&amp;#8217;s &lt;a href="http://www.vernonking.org"&gt;Jekyll-powered site&lt;/a&gt;, I got Winning Slowly off the ground,
including designing the site from scratch and implementing it (also in Pelican),
and I did some substantial redesign work on this site. That was more than enough
for my three week break&amp;#8212;as evidenced by the fact that I didn&amp;#8217;t get to the sort
of 1.0 version of this site until just a week or so ago.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:2"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Emphasis on &amp;#8220;fairly.&amp;#8221; More on &lt;em&gt;that&lt;/em&gt; in a moment as well.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:2" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 2 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary><category term="software development"></category></entry><entry><title>Why Is American Internet So Slow?</title><link href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2014/why-is-american-internet-so-slow.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-03-07T19:55:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Chris Krycho</name></author><id>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2014-03-07:2014/why-is-american-internet-so-slow.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Pretty damning of the current (lack of a) regulatory regime, if you ask&amp;nbsp;me:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;According to a recent study by Ookla Speedtest, the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;U.S.&lt;/span&gt; ranks a shocking 31st
in the world in terms of average download speeds. The leaders in the world are
Hong Kong at 72.49 Mbps and Singapore on 58.84 Mbps. And America? Averaging
speeds of 20.77 Mbps, it falls behind countries like Estonia, Hungary,
Slovakia, and&amp;nbsp;Uruguay.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</summary><category term="links"></category></entry><entry><title>Goodbye, Chrome</title><link href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2014/goodbye-chrome.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-02-24T15:20:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Chris Krycho</name></author><id>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2014-02-24:2014/goodbye-chrome.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Last week, Chrome crossed the line for me. I deleted it from my system to clean
up its many hooks into my system&amp;#8212;I searched out every trace of it I could
find&amp;#8212;and will put it back on my system only for testing websites. Why? Because
it&amp;#8217;s just too creepy&amp;nbsp;now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;#8217;s the story: two weekends ago, I was sitting at a coffee shop working on a
friend&amp;#8217;s website, when up popped a series of Google Now &lt;span class="caps"&gt;OS&lt;/span&gt; X desktop
notifications from Chrome, informing me of the weather, a package having
recently shipped, and so&amp;nbsp;on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There were just two problems with&amp;nbsp;this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I never gave Chrome permission to do anything of the&amp;nbsp;sort.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I was not signed into Chrome or any Google service at the&amp;nbsp;time.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Number 1 is bothersome. Number 2 is so far beyond bothersome that I took the
nuclear option. Let&amp;#8217;s walk through&amp;nbsp;them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Google apparently decided to start opting people into Google Now on the Chrome
33 Beta. Opting people into anything new is nearly always a bad idea in my view;
opting someone into something that actively integrates with email, calendar,
etc. without asking them is just creepy. Now, full disclosure: I had previously
granted Google access to some of this data for Google Now on my Android phone
(though I have since moved to an iPhone). However, as is usual for Google these
days, the company took that permission in one context and treated it as global
permission in all&amp;nbsp;contexts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No doubt the box I checked when I gave them access to that data in the first
place legally allowed them to continue touching it. That did not particularly
bother me. Rather, it was the assumption that I wanted the same kind of
interactions from the service in a different context. This is typical of Google
&amp;#8212;typically un-human-friendly, that is. People do different things with their
phones than with their browsers, and have different expectations of what each
will do. More importantly, though, even if we might &lt;em&gt;want&lt;/em&gt; our browsers to start
supplying us the kinds of sometimes-valuable information that we get from Google
Now (or Apple or Microsoft&amp;#8217;s similar tools), we generally want the opportunity
to make that decision. Increasingly, Google is making that decision for its
users, leaving them to opt out and turn it off if they so desire. That is not a
policy I particularly like. So: strike one. Or rather: strike several dozen, of
the sort that had me moving away from Google&amp;#8217;s services for quite some time&amp;#8212;
but it probably still wouldn&amp;#8217;t have pushed me across the line to this kind of
hard kill-it-with-fire&amp;nbsp;mentality.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What did? That would be the part where Chrome started sending me desktop Google
Now notifications. Without asking me. In a browser to which I was not logged in,
nor logged into any Google&amp;nbsp;services.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I will say that again to be clear: I was not signed into Chrome. I was not
signed into any Google services in the browser. I had not allowed the browser to
create desktop notifications. And it started sending me Google Now notifications
for my main Google account. Worse: nothing I could do with the browser itself
changed that behavior. (Unsurprising: there was no way Chrome should have been
able to do that in the first place, logged out of all Google services as I&amp;nbsp;was.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Goodbye, Chrome. You&amp;#8217;re just too&amp;nbsp;creepy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was not the first time I have seen Chrome engage in behavior that does not
respect its users. I have repeatedly run into cases where clearing the cache and
deleting browsers&amp;#8230; doesn&amp;#8217;t. Cookies sometimes still stick around. Private
browsing sessions inherit cookies from the main window (and sometimes vice
versa). Closing a private session and launching a new one would sometimes still
include cookies and cache from a previous session (bank accounts still logged
in, etc.). Chrome had thus long been untrustworthy to me. But this was a bridge
too far. This was not just slightly unnerving. It was&amp;nbsp;creepy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Call it a bug if you like. It is likely that it was, in fact, a bug. So, most
likely, were the other cases I saw above. But these are the kinds of bugs that
make a browser fundamentally untrustworthy, and they are the kinds of bugs that
are that much creepier coming from a company whose profit comes almost entirely
from selling advertising&amp;#8212;that is, from selling user information to advertising
companies. The deal was that we trusted Google not to abuse that information.
Unfortunately, that deal just keeps getting worse all the time. (Pray they do
not alter it&amp;nbsp;further.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I will have a copy of the browser on my system for testing purposes, but for
nothing else. Goodbye, Chrome. And for that matter: goodbye, Google services.
Over the course of the rest of this year, I will be moving myself completely off
of all Google services (mail, calendar, etc.), with the sole exception of (non-
logged-in) search. You&amp;#8217;re just too creepy&amp;nbsp;now.&lt;/p&gt;</summary></entry></feed>