<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Chris Krycho</title><link href="http://chriskrycho.com/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://chriskrycho.com/feeds/theology.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://chriskrycho.com/</id><updated>2014-02-11T08:30:00-05:00</updated><entry><title>Like His Brothers in Every Way</title><link href="http://chriskrycho.com/2014/like-his-brothers-in-every-way/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-02-11T08:30:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Chris Krycho</name></author><id>tag:chriskrycho.com,2014-02-11:2014/like-his-brothers-in-every-way/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Whether Jesus could have sinned or not is a question to tangle the mind. On the one hand, we affirm that he was fully human, and this affirmation binds us to affirm that he could indeed sin: all humans are capable of sinning, and apart from Jesus, all humans &lt;em&gt;have&lt;/em&gt; sinned. The author of Hebrews reminds us forcefully that Jesus was made like his brothers&amp;#8212;which is to say, &lt;em&gt;us&lt;/em&gt;&amp;#8212;in every respect, being tempted like them, yet without sin. On the other hand, we recognize that the Godhead is sinless and that, as James reminds us, he neither tempts nor can be tempted with evil. As with many issues relating to the Incarnation, we face the challenge of holding together both Jesus&amp;#8217; full deity and his full humanity. When either is lost (or even simply diminished) in order to emphasize or preserve the other, important aspects of our faith break in serious&amp;nbsp;ways.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Difficult (mysterious even) the question may be, but the author of Hebrews leaves little doubt. Jesus was tempted like us in &lt;em&gt;every&lt;/em&gt; way&amp;#8212;not only in some ways, but in every way. This is an essential affirmation for the Christian faith. If Jesus could not sin, then he was not fully human, and his perfect life is unsurprising and not particularly meaningful. If he &lt;em&gt;could&lt;/em&gt; sin, then his perfect life is extraordinary and especially&amp;nbsp;meaningful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the same time, we must integrate the things that Hebrews and James (and the rest of the Scriptures) teach us. If the Godhead cannot be tempted by sin and Jesus &lt;em&gt;was&lt;/em&gt; tempted by sin, does this make Jesus somehow &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; God? No, for this misses the rest of the witness of the New Testament, including those selfsame books. James himself calls Jesus Lord in terms that, set against a Jewish background, can only be understood to refer to God himself (see especially James 5:11, perhaps the most direct quote of Exodus 34:6 in the whole New Testament and an unmistakable reference to Yahweh God). Neither can we admit the notion that James and Hebrews disagree with each other&amp;#8212;at least, not and maintain our affirmation of the unity of Scripture, which is a non-negotiable from where I&amp;nbsp;stand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As with many things in the Trinity and the Incarnation, then, we are left making a dual (and apparently conflicting affirmation). Jesus&amp;#8217; humanity was perfectly capable of sinning, and his divinity was incapable of sinning. The Incarnation holds the two together in a single person, and so we affirm that Jesus could have sinned, but did not. We note, too, that he did not precisely because he did as all humans are called to do (and what glorified humans &lt;em&gt;will&lt;/em&gt; do) and perfectly trusted the Father by obeying the Holy Spirit. Jesus&amp;#8217; perfect life was not the domination of his humanity by his divinity, but the submission of his humanity to the divinity of the&amp;nbsp;Trinity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thus we affirm that Jesus&amp;#8217; not sinning on our behalf was a real moral victory, not a hollow thing we can only look at bemusedly from afar. He lived as a real second Adam, doing what the first Adam failed to do while beset by many more and far greater temptations than the first Adam. He really did overcome the world&amp;#8212;not only its powers, but its temptations. He really did demonstrate true and perfect holiness that we might follow his example. He really did triumph over every power of sin, that we might be transformed into his likeness. Though the triune God is never tempted to sin, the triune God mysteriously partook of everything it is to be human in the Incarnation, and that humanity &lt;em&gt;could&lt;/em&gt; be tempted&amp;#8212;and he&amp;nbsp;overcame.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="M.&amp;hairsp;Div."></category></entry><entry><title>Joy Comes… After Pleading</title><link href="http://chriskrycho.com/2014/joy-comes-after-pleading/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-02-10T22:50:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Chris Krycho</name></author><id>tag:chriskrycho.com,2014-02-10:2014/joy-comes-after-pleading/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;In addition to the devotional reading I have been recording here, I have been working through large stretches of the Old Testament in my second Old Testament survey class, which covers everything after Job in your English Bible&amp;#8212;the Psalms, the Wisdom literature, and all the Prophets. To cover all that ground in a single semester requires moving quickly&amp;#8212;so quickly that I both skip over details  I might otherwise be attentive to, and pick up on overarching themes I might otherwise miss. This is particularly evident in the Psalms, and having just gone through them at a high pace makes the flow and the context of each individual Psalm more apparent as I come to them for the details again in my ordinary devotional reading. Reading large chunks and then coming back through the same section more slowly is such a helpful practice that I expect I shall try to keep it&amp;nbsp;up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Coming to Psalm 40, I am right in the middle of the Psalms of David&amp;#8212;a whole stretch focusing on&lt;sup id="fnref:attr"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:attr" rel="footnote"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; David&amp;#8217;s life and circumstances. Reading this particular Psalm on its own is illuminating in its own ways, of course. It is easy to come away with a sense of the joy of salvation from the exultant verses here. The poem leaps from one triumphant note to another, rejoicing in how Yahweh delivers his people and his anointed one. Hallelujah to&amp;nbsp;that!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Psalm&amp;#8217;s meaning is much, much richer when situated in the broader context of the book, though. When we turn back a single song and look at Psalm 39, we see that not every moment is so rosy and joyful. As I noted in my &lt;a href="/2014/with-confidence/"&gt;last post&lt;/a&gt;, the prayer in Psalm 39 is bold and leans hard on God&amp;#8212;because David &lt;em&gt;needed&lt;/em&gt; God profoundly. He needed salvation from his sins; he recognized the brevity of his own life and especially its fragility before the almighty maker of heaven and earth;&lt;sup id="fnref:rm"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:rm" rel="footnote"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; he knew that only Yahweh could accomplish what he needed. The (Spirit-inspired!) editor of the Psalms took these two poems on David&amp;#8217;s life and set them next to each other to teach us something about the contours of a life devoted to Yahweh. Not every moment is either sorrowful &lt;em&gt;or&lt;/em&gt; rejoicing. More often, each one leads into the other as the seasons of our life ebb and&amp;nbsp;flow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This ebb and flow is &lt;em&gt;good&lt;/em&gt;. We see the beauty of our salvation the more clearly because it is set against the backdrop of our great need for salvation. All too often, we recognize that need only because we have been forced to by our circumstances&amp;#8212;by the travails of human life that range from parenting a teething toddler to staring death full in its cancerous face (and we ought not make little or too much of either, different scales though they be). We sometimes find the joy of our salvation sweeter and more savory when we have wrestled through the pain of loss and the wrestling with God that ensues. We sometimes treasure God&amp;#8217;s answer more when has required us to wait for it&amp;#8212;to wait for &lt;em&gt;him&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is not to say that every trial is aimed at this end. It is to say that the contrast between Psalms 39 and 40 helps us see that &lt;em&gt;sometimes&lt;/em&gt; our trials work out to deepen our joy in salvation. That in turn helps us hold on to God all the more in the face of those trials, because it stands as one more picture of his goodness and wisdom, and thus of his&amp;nbsp;trustworthiness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:attr"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whether written &lt;em&gt;by&lt;/em&gt; or written &lt;em&gt;about&lt;/em&gt;&amp;#8212;the grammar in the headings is a bit ambiguous; &amp;#8220;of&amp;#8221; here can mean &amp;#8220;about&amp;#8221; or &amp;#8220;by&amp;#8221;.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:attr" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:rm"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why, yes, that is a reference to the creed, and no, I can&amp;#8217;t think of those words without hearing Rich Mullins sing them.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:rm" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 2 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary><category term="devotions"></category></entry><entry><title>With Confidence</title><link href="http://chriskrycho.com/2014/with-confidence/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-02-08T23:27:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Chris Krycho</name></author><id>tag:chriskrycho.com,2014-02-08:2014/with-confidence/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The Psalms simultaneously model for us and teach us. They show us how we ought to approach God, and teach us who God is. Psalm 39 is no exception: it does both, through and through. David opens the Psalm by expressing a sentiment we have all shared at some time or another: holding our tongue around those who are actively causing us grief or harm, lest we sin, and finally coming to a point when we can hold back our frustration no longer. Unlike my typical response, though, David did not lash out at those who frustrated him. As is typical of the response the Psalms record, David turned instead to God. It is a striking&amp;nbsp;turn:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;As I mused, the fire burned
    then I spoke with my tongue:
O Yahweh…
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The rest of the Psalm is addressed not to David&amp;#8217;s enemies (mentioned in verse 1) as a rebuke, but to the one who can deliver him from those enemies and from his own sin. It is not a quiet, passive Psalm, but a loud and forceful request (though not, notably, a demand) that Yahweh be gracious and deliver David from his own transgressions. There is acknowledgement, to be sure, of fault, but also bold importuning of the sovereign God of the universe to act in a certain way in David&amp;#8217;s life &lt;em&gt;when David had sinned&lt;/em&gt;. Even to those of us who stand on this side of the cross&amp;#8212;we who are enjoined to come confidently before the throne of grace (Hebrews 4:16)&amp;#8212;this kind of boldness is a bit&amp;nbsp;shocking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Psalms are full of this kind of thing&amp;#8212;and frankly, it tends to make most of us uncomfortable. The idea that we could thus address God seems out of line or inappropriate. It seems remarkably bold to say to God, &amp;#8220;Hear my prayer, O &lt;span class='smcp'&gt;Lord&lt;/span&gt;, / and give ear to my cry; / hold not your peace at my tears!&amp;#8221; More: it seems on the verge of untrusting, not to recognize that God always has his right and wise reasons for acting as he does and allowing (even ordaining) the things we experience. David has no qualms about this, though; in fact, it typifies the way he and the other Psalmists address God in the midst of&amp;nbsp;trouble.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wonder if perhaps we struggle with these kinds of prayers precisely because &lt;em&gt;we&lt;/em&gt; do not know or trust God as we ought. (And that we? It points mostly at me here.) David could come beseech God to be merciful and kind to him by delivering him from his own sin because he knew God to be merciful and gracious. He could plead boldly with God because he knew that God is both all-good and all-wise, and that God&amp;#8217;s answer would be &lt;em&gt;right&lt;/em&gt;. In short, he could come boldly before the throne of Yahweh Almighty because he &lt;em&gt;knew&lt;/em&gt; Yahweh Almighty. How much more can we who have seen Yahweh&amp;#8217;s mercy writ large in the grotesque humiliations of the incarnation, death, and resurrection of Jesus be confident in his goodness and wisdom and mercy toward us? When we see our own sin, and when we taste discipline for that sin, are we able to go to our Father in heaven and plead for deliverance from our own folly with this kind of&amp;nbsp;confidence?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If not, it is only because we do not know him or trust him as we&amp;nbsp;ought.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="devotions"></category></entry><entry><title>Imperatives and Indicatives</title><link href="http://chriskrycho.com/2014/imperatives-and-indicatives/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-02-07T21:30:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Chris Krycho</name></author><id>tag:chriskrycho.com,2014-02-07:2014/imperatives-and-indicatives/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Paul&amp;#8217;s typical format for his letters is to lay out a series of doctrinal statements in the first half of the epistle and then follow it up with a series of exhortations flowing out of those truths in the second half. This is not a hard rule with him. He has letters like 1 and 2 Corinthians in which the content moves back and forth more freely between the two kinds of material, and he also mixes imperatives in with indicatives and vice versa in all his letters. On the whole, though Colossians follows this pattern fairly closely: chapter 1 and the first part of chapter 2 are statements of theological truth (and among the highest and weightiest such in Scripture), and the rest of the book moves into the Christian response to these&amp;nbsp;truths.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a mere 44 verses (fewer if one leaves out the introduction), Paul traverses enormous depths of theology. Christ is the author of Creation, the one in whom all things hold together. He is before all things. He is the head of the church. He is the image of the invisible God. He is the heir (&amp;#8220;firstborn&amp;#8221;) of creation; it belongs to him in its entirety. He is the firstborn (and heir) of the resurrection from the&amp;nbsp;dead.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is no surprise, then, that the consequences range over all aspects of human life. There is nothing that goes untouched: not our family life, nor our economic behavior, nor our religious activity, nor our thoughts or actions in any area. Paul enjoined the Colossians to set aside all &amp;#8220;sexual immorality, impurity, passion, evil desire, and covetousness, which is idolatry&amp;#8230;. anger, wrath, malice, slander, and obscene talk from your mouth&amp;#8221; (Colossians 3:5,8). As Abraham Kuyper put it of culture, there is no part of life over which Christ does not shout, &amp;#8220;Mine!&amp;#8221; So it is in our lives as well: we are his wholly and utterly, fight it though we often do at times. We may foolishly cling to our sins, or we may seek to be sanctified in every area of our&amp;nbsp;lives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note well the constant return to the foundational truths on which that call to holiness is built. Paul not only lays out these exhortations as following the indication of all Christ has already done, but points again and again to the reality that sanctifiaction can happen only as we are joined with Christ. We died with Christ (2:20) and have been raised with Christ (3:1). He is our life (3:4) and our life is hidden with God in Christ (3:3). Christ is all, and in all (3:11). His peace rules in our hearts (3:15); his word dwells in us richly in the context of song and psalm&amp;nbsp;(3:16).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These are not small things, or light matters. These are magnificent and holy, and they call us to be holy likewise. God is very great&amp;#8212;very far beyond us&amp;#8212;but he draws us near in his loving kindness and calls us out of our selfishness and sin and into his holy ways.&amp;nbsp;Hallelujah.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="devotions"></category></entry><entry><title>The Wicked Perish</title><link href="http://chriskrycho.com/2014/the-wicked-perish/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-02-06T22:41:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Chris Krycho</name></author><id>tag:chriskrycho.com,2014-02-06:2014/the-wicked-perish/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;It is apparent to me that one of the reasons I sometimes struggle with passages speaking of God&amp;#8217;s judgment on the wicked is because I do not face persecution or active hostility from those who hate God. I might get called names or insulted occasionally (though only occasionally), but I have never been at risk of loss of property, much less of health or life, because I follow Christ. Believers in other places and other times are not so at ease among those who do not follow God. For those who are not so at ease, the prosperity and success of those who oppress them are much larger concerns&amp;#8212;much nearer to home, and much more urgently in need of&amp;nbsp;justice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thus, in both of Paul&amp;#8217;s letters to the Thessalonians, he encourages them to remain steadfast in part by pointing to God&amp;#8217;s future judgment on the enemies of Christ. He points them to the future return of Jesus not to remove the believers from this world, but to judge those who reject God and to rule in righteousness over the world. That is a cause for rejoicing for believers: all of us want to see the world put right, with an end to poverty and war, cancer and rape, tornadoes and abortion, Alzheimers and murder, oppression and death. Nearly &lt;em&gt;everyone&lt;/em&gt; wants this kind of world, in theory. But in practice, we are either children of God or people who &amp;#8220;refused to love the truth and so be saved&amp;#8221; (2 Thessalonians 2:10). And those who refuse to love the truth and be saved oppress and murder the people of God (and everyone else, but &lt;em&gt;especially&lt;/em&gt; the people of&amp;nbsp;God).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our fellow believers in Saudi Arabia and Iran and North Korea are not reading these passages of judgment and wondering how God could judge so harshly. They are reading them and holding fast to the hope that this day will come &lt;em&gt;soon&lt;/em&gt;, when those who grind underfoot the poor, the widow, and the orphan, who throw Jesus&amp;#8217; followers in jail and execute their pastors, will get justice at the hands of God. Many of our fellow believers look forward to the day when &lt;em&gt;they&lt;/em&gt; will get justice from God, because in this present life injustice has often been their&amp;nbsp;lot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;In just a little while, the wicked will be no more;
    though you look carefully at his place, he will not be there.
But the meek shall inherit the land
    and delight themselves in abundant peace.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This points me forward in several ways. First, it reminds me that this is an area in which I need to be sanctified. Contrary to everything the surrounding world says, a lack of judgment on the part of God would be grotesquely unrighteous. We can see this clearly in the most egregious cases: none of us think it would be right for Charles Manson or Stalin to get off without punishment. But God&amp;#8217;s justice is deeper than ours, and truer, and that is &lt;em&gt;good&lt;/em&gt;. Lord willing, I will come to understand more and more the goodness of his doing justice and righteousness on the earth, not least as I understand that his &lt;em&gt;shalom&lt;/em&gt; will not come&amp;#8212;could not come&amp;#8212;apart from his doing justice. And his doing justice means crushing&amp;nbsp;evil.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Second, it reminds me (again) that we Westerners, much though we have to offer to our brothers and sisters around the world, also have much to learn from them. The persecuted church is not so easily led astray in this area as we in our comfort are. Likewise, we have much to learn from those who have gone before us. Whatever their faults, many of our forebears in the faith got &lt;em&gt;this&lt;/em&gt; right where we get it wrong. We would do well to listen more humbly to our fellow saints of every age and every tribe&amp;#8212;and not to arrogate to ourselves the right to judge God&amp;#8217;s&amp;nbsp;justice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Third, it reminds me to pray for God to work his justice in the world: to deliver suffering saints in lands hostile to the gospel, and to end the oppression of the wicked either by saving them from their sins or by ruining them. This is not a comfortable prayer, but it is a good and right prayer. It reminds me, too, to pray all the more fervently: &amp;#8220;Lord, come&amp;nbsp;soon!&amp;#8221;&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="devotions"></category></entry><entry><title>Big Enough for Mystery</title><link href="http://chriskrycho.com/2014/big-enough-for-mystery/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-02-05T22:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Chris Krycho</name></author><id>tag:chriskrycho.com,2014-02-05:2014/big-enough-for-mystery/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Ecclesiastes is challenging book, to be sure. Like the rest of the Scriptures, though, it does yield its treasures as we seek the face of God there. Remembering that Scripture is the self-revelation of one who wants to be known helps us situate the hard passages and find their meaning. We are not left wandering in the dark; we can see God here. This is no less true of the pages of Zechariah than of the letters of Paul. The latter, it is true, may be more direct and explicit&amp;#8212;but the fact that Ecclesiastes gets at the character of God sideways, as it were, tells us something about God. It tells us that not everything about him can be learned from looking straight on, from direct&amp;nbsp;propositions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sometimes it is only in travail, in the &amp;#8220;dark night of the soul&amp;#8221; that we learn who our Maker really is. Sometimes it is only in poetry. Sometimes it is when the pursuit of wisdom turns to folly that we learn that wisdom is not some reified artifact to be apprehended, but a living person who is always Other and&amp;nbsp;Above&amp;#8212;Holy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Solomon went running after every kind of good in this world and for answers to all his questions. The more he searched, the more he gained, the more lost he was and the more he lost. The problem was not seeking the goods of this world, nor in seeking answers to questions. It was partly in seeking them where they could never be found, and partly in failing to be silent before the face of God who has not chosen to answer every question, and partly in succumbing to the notion that the depths of reality can be plumbed. Some things are forever out of our grasp; some knowledge is always too high for&amp;nbsp;us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That does not mean we ought not seek after wisdom. It means we ought to seek Wisdom himself, to go after the one who has become to us wisdom from God along with righteousness and peace. It means we ought to revel in what can be known, and revel too where God says, &amp;#8220;This is mystery. Trust me.&amp;#8221; The world is big enough for mystery. Humans, too, are big enough for mystery. Too often we shrink ourselves down, shrink down the world around us, shrink down God himself, so that we may all fit in conveniently sized packages with regular shapes. But God is always bursting out of our bounds, surprising us with his fierce love and his sharply tender&amp;nbsp;grace.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Solomon&amp;#8217;s conclusion in chapter 5&amp;#8212;like the conclusion to which he eventually comes in the end of the book&amp;#8212;is simpler than we might expect, given the travails of his&amp;nbsp;heart.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Behold, what I have seen to be good and fitting is to eat and drink and find enjoyment in all the toil with which one toils under the sun the few days of his life that God has given him, for this is his lot. Everyone also to whom God has given wealth and possessions and power to enjoy them, and to accept his lot and rejoice in his toil—this is the gift of God. For he will not much remember the days of his life because God keeps him occupied with joy in his heart. (Ecclesiastes&amp;nbsp;5:18&amp;#8211;20)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Small things, these: to eat and drink and find enjoyment in all our toil. Or perhaps not so small, when we look at them again. For Solomon has already told us that these are vanity when not given and received as gifts from God. They will not satisfy. They are just wind and emptiness. But then God fills them up, and they are suddenly good. God brings joy in these simple things. Is this not what all of us desire? Is it not what Solomon chased and failed to find (the confession of the preceding and following chapters of the book)? Is it not the original promise of the world: to work it and enjoy the fruit of one&amp;#8217;s labor as a gift from God&amp;#8217;s hand? No, these are not small things. They are very great. And they come from God, with joy.&amp;nbsp;Hallelujah.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="devotions"></category></entry><entry><title>The Mother of God</title><link href="http://chriskrycho.com/2014/the-mother-of-god/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-02-04T08:30:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Chris Krycho</name></author><id>tag:chriskrycho.com,2014-02-04:2014/the-mother-of-god/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Is it right to call Mary the Mother of God? The historic, orthodox answer is a resounding &amp;#8220;yes&amp;#8221;&amp;#8212;though a clearly qualified and well articulated &amp;#8220;yes.&amp;#8221; This is not just the historic, orthodox position; it is the &lt;em&gt;right&lt;/em&gt; position. Mary was indeed the &amp;#8220;mother of God&amp;#8221;. She was the mother of Jesus. Jesus was (and is) fully God &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; fully man, completely and truly, both at once without loss of the full measure of either. He did not cease being totally divine upon his incarnation, but he did assume full humanity. The argument is as simple as it first seems: Mary is the mother of Jesus, and Jesus is God, therefore Mary is the mother of&amp;nbsp;God.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Evangelicals tend to shy away from following the broader tradition and affirming that Mary is the mother of God. There are many reasons for this, not least our general discomfort with things having to do with Mary born of the over-referencing of Mary in the Catholic tradition and the actual Mariolatry that is too often evinced in Catholic lay practice throughout the world. However, our response ought not be to reject this view, but to speak carefully and clearly and reject what is mistaken while keeping what is&amp;nbsp;true.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is true that we must be nuanced in our handling of this issue. The word &amp;#8220;mother&amp;#8221; brings with it implications that we must avoid, and we must remember Jesus&amp;#8217; statements on what it meant to be his mother and brothers and sisters in the gospels (i.e. that those who followed him were those really deserving of the titles). However, simply to set aside the title is to lose important aspects of the reality of the incarnation. If we say that Mary was &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; the mother of God, we are really saying either that she was not truly the mother of Jesus, or that Jesus was not fully God. Neither of these is a tolerable&amp;nbsp;option.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, to those qualifications. When we say that Mary is the mother of God, we are not saying that God in any sense has his source in her. All of the humanity of Jesus finds its source equally in Mary and in the Spirit&amp;#8217;s divine intervention&amp;#8212;but Mary was created by the Son, rather than the Son originating in her. Mary is the mother of God in Christ, but she is not to the Son exactly as ordinary mothers are to ordinary sons, for Jesus was not an ordinary&amp;nbsp;son.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nor do we mean that Mary has special prerogatives because of her relationship to Jesus. As noted above, Jesus made clear that he was concerned above all with obedience to the will of God (see e.g. Matthew 12:46&amp;#8211;50). Thus, the devotions offered to Mary by our Catholic and Eastern Orthodox brothers and sisters is misplaced, as is the notion that her prayers are somehow more effective in touching Jesus&amp;#8217; heart than are those of the ordinary saint who is seeking to honor&amp;nbsp;God.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These qualifications notwithstanding, we must still be willing and ready to affirm that Mary was in fact the Mother of God. To do otherwise is to reduce in one way or another the mystery of the incarnation. It is not so much that &lt;em&gt;Mary&lt;/em&gt; is important here as that affirming her motherhood of God helps us affirm the important points to which we must hold fast in terms the full deity and full humanity of &lt;em&gt;Christ&lt;/em&gt;. Mary is important because Jesus humanity came by means of Mary&amp;#8217;s body. Everything that it is to be man, Jesus always was from conception, and everything that it is to be God, Jesus always was from the moment of his&amp;nbsp;conception.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="M.&amp;hairsp;Div."></category></entry><entry><title>Resolved to Pray</title><link href="http://chriskrycho.com/2014/resolved-to-pray/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-02-04T07:40:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Chris Krycho</name></author><id>tag:chriskrycho.com,2014-02-04:2014/resolved-to-pray/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Paul&amp;#8217;s letters all open with a common pattern: he gives the typical introduction of his era with his own name and those of his co-authors, and then proceeds to explain how he prays for the people to whom he is writing. I read once of someone who went through and looked at all the things Paul prays for people in his epistles and used those as a basis for his own prayers for others. That seems a remarkably good idea to me. Paul&amp;#8217;s heart for each and every church to which he ministered is readily&amp;nbsp;apparent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hope and pray that as I step more and more into ministry, my own heart would be so dedicated to the good of those whom I serve, and that I would be so faithful as Paul was to pray regularly for them. I have a long way to go in this; I do not pray as much even for my own family and friends as I would like. Jaimie and I have made prayer a regular part of our lives by sitting down as a family together to pray every night before we put Elayne to bed, and I pray at times throughout the day. These are good things. I am glad we have taken these steps to make prayer a regular part of our lives. Even so, I am much less dedicated and disciplined in prayer than many I know and especially than the many heroes of the faith who distinguished themselves in large part through the faithfulness of their prayers and their trust that God would&amp;nbsp;answer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The content of Paul&amp;#8217;s prayers is just as important as their frequency, though. Reading 1 Thessalonians 1 reminded me of the &lt;em&gt;kinds&lt;/em&gt; of things I ought to be praying, as well as &lt;em&gt;that&lt;/em&gt; I ought to be praying. In this particular introduction, Paul is above all grateful to God for the Thessalonians&amp;#8217; &amp;#8220;work of faith  and labor of love and steadfastness of hope in our Lord Jesus Christ.&amp;#8221; This faithfulness before God resounded throughout the early church; these believers had a reputation for their perseverance in the face of persecution and their love of God. What a thing to start praying for the believers I know, and especially for my church and the missionaries we have sent out: that we would be known for our faith, love, and steadfast hope in Jesus Christ; that we would persevere in the face of challenges to our faith and even outright persecution; that the testimony of our deeds would go forth and be an encouragement to the rest of the&amp;nbsp;Church.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Resolved, then: to pray more faithfully for my fellow saints, first of all at First Baptist Church of Durham and then in the other churches I know and love and then throughout the world as I hear of them; and to pray more thoughtfully and wisely for God to make of us all the kinds of people over whom Paul was rejoicing in these early verses of this letter.&amp;nbsp;Amen.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="devotions"></category></entry><entry><title>The Horror of Sin</title><link href="http://chriskrycho.com/2014/the-horror-of-sin/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-02-03T22:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Chris Krycho</name></author><id>tag:chriskrycho.com,2014-02-03:2014/the-horror-of-sin/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Matthew 26:3&amp;#8211;7 contains one of the most horrifying illustrations of human depravity anywhere in the Bible. It is such a simple passage, but the human wickedness on display is profound. The scene is this: Jesus has already been condemned by the Jews. Judas&amp;#8212;expecting &lt;em&gt;some&lt;/em&gt; other outcome than Jesus&amp;#8217; death, or simply turned back from the plan to which he had previously agreed&amp;#8212;comes, seeking to make right what he had done wrong. The priests respond by rejecting him, and he throws the money down on the floor before he goes and hangs&amp;nbsp;himself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The priests then note that it would be &lt;em&gt;wrong&lt;/em&gt; to put the money in the temple treasury, since it was after all blood money. Here these men were, having just plotted the death of a man they knew to be innocent, a man they could condemn only on trumped up charges after a farce of a trail, worried about whether they should put a few pieces of silver in the treasury or not. Their conclusion, that the money could not be used for the temple because it was &amp;#8220;blood money&amp;#8221;, still did not make them realize the horror of their sin&amp;#8212;that they had bought a man&amp;#8217;s life! That they should do this with &lt;em&gt;any&lt;/em&gt; man is a horror; that they would do it with their long-awaited Messiah, the incarnate Son of God, is a horror beyond words. That they could not see the disjunction between their scruples about where the money was used and the very reason they had the money should put the fear of sin in us&amp;nbsp;all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is human depravity. We can look our sin square in the face and not see it for what it is sometimes. We become inured to its power and its hold on us. We think we can just deal with it in some way or another&amp;#8212;and we are profoundly wrong. We cannot deal with our sin apart from the saving work of Chris ton our behalf. We cannot even see it clearly without the illuminating power of the Holy Spirit. No divine intervention means no holiness on our part; without the work of God we would remain forever trapped in the darkness that shrouds our eyes from seeing our sin aright and from seeing our great and awesome God as he&amp;nbsp;is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yet this is also the hand of God at work. So often God takes what men meant for evil and works it for good. Often we cannot see his means &lt;em&gt;or&lt;/em&gt; his ends, but we know from the gospels that the greatest evil ever perpetrated by men&amp;#8212;the only innocent man dead at the hands of hardenered human hearts&amp;#8212;was used of God to accomplish the greatest good ever provided to men. This lets us trust that God is likewise at work in our own lives. We know that he is all-wise and all-good. We do not know what he aims to accomplish with every act (nor indeed with many of his acts), but we know that those aims will be for the good of all those who love him and (most importantly) are loved by&amp;nbsp;him.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hallelujah.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="devotions"></category></entry><entry><title>Vanity! Vanity!</title><link href="http://chriskrycho.com/2014/vanity-vanity/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-02-02T22:15:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Chris Krycho</name></author><id>tag:chriskrycho.com,2014-02-02:2014/vanity-vanity/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Ecclesiastes is one of the most interpretively challenging books in the whole Bible. &lt;a href="/2014/ordinary-means-the-silence-of-god/"&gt;Like Esther&lt;/a&gt;, its inclusion in the canon was much debated. Unlike Esther, the book mentions God plenty&amp;#8212;but its approach to theology is challenging, to say the least. The author, generally understood to be Solomon, is not exactly a cheerful fellow and is his approach to life can be summed up in the single word that is the refrain of the whole book:&amp;nbsp;&amp;#8220;Vanity!&amp;#8221;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chapter 2 gives us this bleak outlook applied to pleasure and possessions on the one hand and vocation on the other. In both cases, the Preacher (Heb. &lt;em&gt;qoheleth&lt;/em&gt;) comes to the same conclusion: &amp;#8220;Then I considered all tha tmy hands had done and the toil I had expended in doing it, and behold, all was vanity and a striving after wind, and there was nothing to be gained under the sun&amp;#8221; (Ecclesiastes 2:11). This is so bleak as to border on despair, and therefore no few Christians of my acquaintance find the book difficult to integrate with their&amp;nbsp;theology.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The problem, as near as I can tell, is one of genre.&lt;sup id="fnref:genre"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:genre" rel="footnote"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Ecclesiastes is wisdom literature, and it serves as an extended meditation on the world that Solomon found around him. And taken without the context of redemptive history, Solomon&amp;#8217;s proclamation that everything is vanity is perfectly accurate. Life is a grind. We cannot keep the things we earn or buy, no matter how magnificent. If we are perfectly wise in our dealings, we will nonetheless die and leave everything we have to others, and who knows whether they will be geniuses, mediocrities, or idiots? We can have a thousand pleasures at our command, and we will find them all unsatisfactory in the end. We can work hard, and have nothing to show for it when we return to&amp;nbsp;dust.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But all these things are observations of the world as it is&amp;#8212;not statements on what it ought to be. It is easy to mistake description for prescription. The Preacher never suggests that life in this world &lt;em&gt;should&lt;/em&gt; be mere vanity. To the contrary: the very fact that he was asking the questions he asked is indicative of the real shape of reality. We all ask the same questions with him at some point or another: Does my work matter? Would I be satisfied if I had every material thing I could desire? Would having (functionally) infinite sexual choice&lt;sup id="fnref:sex"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:sex" rel="footnote"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; bring me contentment? Solomon discovered the answer:&amp;nbsp;no.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And there we leave it, for chapter 2. But my other reading tonight was in Matthew and in Psalms, and they do &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; leave it there. Psalm 33 points us to the ways that Yahweh works justice in the world and calls us to rejoice in him, not in the things of this age. Matthew 22&amp;#8211;25 reminds us that the kingdom of heaven is &lt;em&gt;coming&lt;/em&gt;; it is not here yet. The age to come will be so &lt;em&gt;very&lt;/em&gt; much better than this one. No more will our existence be nothing but vanity.&amp;nbsp;Hallelujah.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:genre"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am looking forward to seeing this covered in my Old Testament &lt;span class="caps"&gt;II&lt;/span&gt; class this semester, as I suspect that the coverage there will prove illuminating. It certainly was helpful for my grasp of Job!&amp;#8212;but  more on that another time.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:genre" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:sex"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Think about the fact that Solomon is reported to have had some 1,000 wives and concubines (see 1 Kings 11:3). This may not be infinite in the strictest sense of the word&amp;#8230; but it is close enough.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:sex" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 2 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary><category term="devotions"></category></entry><entry><title>Infant Guilt—Purest Speculation</title><link href="http://chriskrycho.com/2014/infant-guilt-purest-speculation/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-02-01T08:30:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Chris Krycho</name></author><id>tag:chriskrycho.com,2014-02-01:2014/infant-guilt-purest-speculation/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Whether people are born guilty of sin, or simply inherit a nature so predisposed to sin that the actual act is inevitable has been a much debated topic for generations. In my view, however, the question is impossible to answer. I do not think Scripture speaks with sufficient clarity on the matter. We know on the one hand that all are &amp;#8220;by nature children of wrath&amp;#8221; (Ephesians 2:3), and that &amp;#8220;all have sinned and fall short of the glory of God&amp;#8221; (Romans 3:23). What neither of these texts tell us, though, and what indeed &lt;em&gt;no&lt;/em&gt; text tells us, is whether people are guilty at birth or whether they are simply sinful and become&amp;nbsp;guilty.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We could reason to a conclusion that accords with our other theological commitments with little difficulty. We know that God is just, and punishes for the wrongs we commit, but we have no evidence that he punishes wrongs we &lt;em&gt;might&lt;/em&gt; commit, and therefore we might conclude that he would therefore not find guilty any newly conceived or newly born person. On the other hand, we also must reckon with the reality that the Scriptures treat questions of progeny far differently than do individually-minded modern&amp;nbsp;Westerners.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Scripture points us to the God who &amp;#8220;will by no means clear the guilty, visiting the iniquity of the fathers on the children and the children&amp;#8217;s children, to the third and the fourth generation&amp;#8221; (Exodus 34:7) as well as the God who proclaims that &amp;#8220;The soul who sins shall die. The son shall not suffer for the iniquity of the father, nor the father suffer for the iniquity of the son&amp;#8221; (Ezekiel 18:20). Paul did write that &amp;#8220;one trespass led to condemnation for all men,&amp;#8221; but he immediately follows up this provocative statement by arguing that &amp;#8220;one act of righteousness leads to justification and life for all men&amp;#8221; (Romans 5:18)&amp;#8212;yet we know that Paul does not (and cannot) here mean that all men are saved, for we know that he believes that those who do not repent and believe the gospel perish in their sins under the expectation of&amp;nbsp;judgment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We cannot from the evidence that God has given us decide this question. We are left without an answer. If we grant the sufficiency of Scripture, then we must recognize that if there are questions God has in his wisdom opted not to answer, it is for a reason, and we should cease with our speculations and be silent. We may not know whether infants are &lt;em&gt;guilty&lt;/em&gt;, but we do know two other things that are far more important than that: First, God is merciful and gracious and just. We will not in the final reckoning find his justice lacking or his treatment of (for example) those who died in infancy to be lacking. Second, all are born under the dual curse of sin&amp;#8217;s hold and death&amp;#8217;s&amp;nbsp;certainty.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These truths give us clear and straightforward points of application. First, we must preach the gospel clearly to people of every age and intellectual ability, for even little children sin and death is awaiting us all. Whether or not we are born guilty, we &lt;em&gt;become&lt;/em&gt; guilty very quickly. Second, much of the speculation on this question&amp;#8212;and many churches practices such as infant baptism&amp;#8212;seems to be rooted in worry about the fate of those who die young, without having made a credible profession of faith. Yet even if we &lt;em&gt;did&lt;/em&gt; know the answer to the question of their guilt, we still might not know God&amp;#8217;s response. Even did we know the answer, still we would need learn to trust in the goodness and wisdom of God in this&amp;nbsp;matter.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="M.&amp;hairsp;Div."></category></entry><entry><title>Not Simple</title><link href="http://chriskrycho.com/2014/not-simple/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-01-31T20:55:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Chris Krycho</name></author><id>tag:chriskrycho.com,2014-01-31:2014/not-simple/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Sometimes, I hate the heading markers in my Bible. While they can be helpful for some people at some times, I find more and more that they simply distract. They make it difficult to see&amp;#8212;or to remember&amp;#8212;that the books are &lt;em&gt;books&lt;/em&gt;. Nowhere is this more distracting than in the gospels. The gospels are coherent books. They are not mere collections of stories, arranged haphazardly or tossed together willy-nilly; the authors had a point and purpose in what they were doing, and that point and purpose is hard to see for the constant interruptions in the text. These interruptions, not present in the original, mask the way the pieces fit together&amp;#8212;and they mask the surprising ways they do &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; obviously fit together,&amp;nbsp;too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because these are the kinds of questions we should be asking as we read through the book: Why does Matthew transition from Jesus&amp;#8217; rather shocking encounter with his family&amp;#8212;the one where he proclaims that his disciples are his family in a way that his biological family is not&amp;#8212;to the death of John the Baptist? And why from there to the feeding of the five thousand? And why thence to interactions with the scribes and Pharisees? He is going somewhere with this narrative; where? What does he want us to&amp;nbsp;see?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In John 14, Jesus leaves the crowds behinds to seek respite on hearing of the death of his cousin and fellow servant of Yahweh, John the Baptizer. But then a crowd finds him, and he has compassion on them; he goes out of his way to care for them. Then, a few hundred words later, he compares a Canaanite woman to a dog, using the racially charged language of the Jews. (This should shock the reader, given how Matthew has already had Jesus praise outsiders and proclaim that the kingdom will be composed of those who were far off as well as of those who were near.) But then he blesses her for her faith. Then Matthew follows this story with another case of his feeding a multitude because of his compassion for them. Scattered through all these narratives are his interactions with the Pharisees, whom he repeatedly criticizes in the harshest&amp;nbsp;terms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why these particular stories? Why these particular&amp;nbsp;contrasts?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think it is because Matthew aims to confound his readers in precisely the ways the disciples (Matthew himself included) were confounded. We see that they were often confused. We see that they failed to understand who he was, and then even as they began to grasp that he was the Messiah (14:32, 16:16), they continued to misunderstand what he was about. His teachings confused them, and they had to learn over and over again the same lessons. Matthew has structured his narrative so that the reader is faced with the same kinds of confounding contrasts that the disciples faced. We, too, must wrestle with this Son of Man who both overflows with compassion on the crowds and repeatedly evinces his frustration with the faithlessness of the people. We, too, must come to terms with a king who planned from the first to die rather than than to conquer. We, too, must read the riddles rightly&amp;#8212;and marvel though we do at the disciples who did not understand his parables, if we are honest we must admit how we struggle to interpret them&amp;nbsp;ourselves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jesus is not simple. He never was. We too often try to fit him into a neat box: the social revolutionary, or the the compsassionate healer, or the righteous firebrand, or the gentle savior. Take your pick, according to your social and political preferences. But he will not be so boxed in. He is all of these and more, and he is none of these insofar as none of them circumscribe him. He is righteousness and justice and peace&lt;sup id="fnref:rjs"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:rjs" rel="footnote"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;#8212;which means that he thunders forth judgment, and he tenderly comforts those in need. It means that he offers sharp edges and delighted praise to the same people. It means that he marveled at the faith and the faithlessness of people whose hearts he knew before they spoke. It means that he is a mystery even as he reveals himself plainly. It means that he cannot be comprehended, but invites us to know&amp;nbsp;him.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:rjs"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A trio I borrowed from J. Clinton McCann Jr.&amp;#8217;s description of Yahweh&amp;#8217;s &amp;#8220;anointed one&amp;#8221; (that is, &amp;#8220;messiah&amp;#8221;) in the Psalms. See Chapter 12: Hearing the Psalter in &lt;cite&gt;Hearing the Old Testament&lt;/cite&gt;, eds. Craig G. Bartholomew &lt;span class="amp"&gt;&amp;amp;&lt;/span&gt; David &lt;span class="caps"&gt;J. H.&lt;/span&gt; Beldman.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:rjs" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary><category term="devotions"></category></entry><entry><title>Basic Human Folly</title><link href="http://chriskrycho.com/2014/basic-human-folly/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-01-30T08:15:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Chris Krycho</name></author><id>tag:chriskrycho.com,2014-01-30:2014/basic-human-folly/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Psalm 30 stands as one of the most evocative pictures of our human propensity for self-congratulatory folly in all of Scripture. It is a splendid poetic demonstration of an arc we have all traced out. David opens the Psalm by telling us where he is going. The first two stanzas declare that Yahweh saves and enjoins his saints to praise him, &amp;#8220;For his anger is but for a moemnt,  / and his favor is for a lifetime. / Weeping may tarry for the night, / but joy comes with the morning&amp;#8221; (Psalm&amp;nbsp;30:5).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then David tells us how he got there. I cannot do better in summing up the third stanza than simply quoting&amp;nbsp;it:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As for me, I said in my prosperity,
&amp;#8220;I shall never be moved.&amp;#8221;
By your favor, O &lt;span class='smcp'&gt;Lord&lt;/span&gt;,
you made my mountain stand strong;
you hid your face;
I was&amp;nbsp;dismayed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is one of the most basic human follies. As God cares for us and provides for us, we take credit for it ourselves. But it was &lt;em&gt;Yahweh&lt;/em&gt; who made David&amp;#8217;s &amp;#8220;mountain stand strong&amp;#8221;&amp;#8212;not David. The moment Yahweh took away his presence, David was in ruin. How often do we all fall prey to exactly this sort of nonsense? How often do I trust in my own capabilities or my own wisdom, and credit my own hard work and talents for where I stand in life? Certainly, I am too clever to do so openly, even to myself: I know that I should not be resting on my own merits. But deep down, we all make that dreadful move&amp;nbsp;sometimes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The other significant point of interest in this third stanza is what it was that dismayed David. He does not emphasize here whatever external consequences he may have experienced in his pride (though the next stanza suggests that there were some). Rather, he points to the Yahweh&amp;#8217;s withdrawal of his presence: &amp;#8220;you hid your face&amp;#8221; (Psalm 30:7b) as the basis for his dismay. Would that I were so sensitive to God that I recognized his presence as far more important than any other situational reality. We are offered the privilege of fellowship with the divine, and so often we&amp;#8212;so often &lt;em&gt;I&lt;/em&gt;&amp;#8212;turn away from it for other, lesser things. So often, we are more frustrated by the difficulties of our trials than we are by a lack of relationship with our heavenly Father. David has the right of it,&amp;nbsp;though.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is much that could be said of the fourth stanza on questions of theological development, Old Testament understandings of death, and so on. More interesting to me&amp;#8212;in a devotional context, at least!&amp;#8212;is the point of the stanza: a simple plea for help from Yahweh. Again, David&amp;#8217;s response is a model for us. When faced with the removal of God&amp;#8217;s presence and the looming consequences, he prayed for salvation. The result, coming in the fifth and final stanza, is the restoration of David&amp;#8217;s state. Yahweh moved him from the ritual death of lament (&amp;#8220;mourning&amp;#8221; and &amp;#8220;sackloth&amp;#8221;) to ritual life (&amp;#8220;dancing&amp;#8221; and &amp;#8220;gladness&amp;#8221;).&lt;sup id="fnref:ritual"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:ritual" rel="footnote"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Importantly, David does not make again the mistake that took him down this road in the first place. He recognizes that Yahweh had restored him for a&amp;nbsp;reason:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;that my glory may sing your praise and be not silent,
O &lt;span class='smcp'&gt;Lord&lt;/span&gt; my God, I will give thanks to you&amp;nbsp;forever!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;His &amp;#8220;glory&amp;#8221;&amp;#8212;his mountain standing strong&amp;#8212;was not for his own pleasure, but for the honor of the one who made him stand&amp;nbsp;strong.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:ritual"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This insight courtesy of Dr. Heath Thomas, who has pointed out similar motifs in Job. Matters of ritual state are important in all cultures, but were much more explicit in the Ancient Near East than they are in modern western societies. More on this some other time.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:ritual" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary><category term="devotions"></category></entry><entry><title>You Must Be Perfect</title><link href="http://chriskrycho.com/2014/you-must-be-perfect/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-01-29T08:14:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Chris Krycho</name></author><id>tag:chriskrycho.com,2014-01-29:2014/you-must-be-perfect/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;It is common right now in some circles of evangelicalism to so emphasize the dialectic of law and gospel that every moral exhortation or command in the Bible is turned into mere evidence of our inability and God&amp;#8217;s grace toward us. This is a&amp;nbsp;tragedy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I was reading through Matthew 5&amp;#8211;9 this morning, I was struck again by the force of Jesus&amp;#8217; moral teaching here. He takes major categories of sin and intensifies the Old Testament&amp;#8217;s teaching on it: murder, adultery, penury, and self-righteousness all come in for his condemnation here. Now, it is true that the standard he sets is perfection: &amp;#8220;You therefore must be perfect, as your heavenly Father is perfect,&amp;#8221; he says (Matthew 5:48, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;ESV&lt;/span&gt;). To be sure, none of us can measure up to this standard. In one sense, then, those who point out that this teaching shows us our need for Christ&amp;#8217;s salvation are absolutely&amp;nbsp;right.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, there is more going on here than merely highlighting our need for Christ. There is a picture of kingdom ethics that we are too quick to step over. &amp;#8220;Ah,&amp;#8221; we say, &amp;#8220;I can never be perfect, but thank God for covering my imperfections!&amp;#8221; and we move along through our lives. This is &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; what the text requires of us; it is not what God requires of us. The resurrection of Christ was like the first crack in a piece of glass, and our participation in his resurrection is like the spidering of that crack out until the whole glass is shattered completely. The old world has not yet passed away, but the new one is pushing its way through the cracks, visible more and more in our lives as we pursue holy&amp;nbsp;Christlikeness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At least, that is how it ought to be. But this in-breaking of the new age is hard work, and it is far easier to empty the Sermon on the Mount of its binding force on our lives. It is easier to look at the moral instruction of Scripture and see only one use of the Law: condemning sinners where they stand so they will look to Christ. Yet the Law does more than this. It also teaches us what God is like, and what his people ought to be like. So when Jesus says to us that we must put aside our anger at our brothers and sisters, that we must do whatever it takes to deal with lust, that we must not retaliate but instead go above and beyond in serving those who do us harm, we must &lt;em&gt;obey&lt;/em&gt;. When he tells us how to pray, how to fast, how to give to the needy (and, for that matter, that we &lt;em&gt;are&lt;/em&gt; to give generously to the needy), we must &lt;em&gt;obey&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jesus said&amp;nbsp;both:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="dquo"&gt;&amp;#8220;&lt;/span&gt;For I tell you, unless your righteousness exceeds that of the scribes and Pharisees, you will never enter the kingdom of heaven.&amp;#8221; (Matthew&amp;nbsp;5:20)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;and&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="dquo"&gt;&amp;#8220;&lt;/span&gt;Not everyone who says to me, &amp;#8216;Lord, Lord,&amp;#8217; will enter the kingdom of heaven, but the one who does the will of my Father who is in heaven.&amp;#8221; (Matthew&amp;nbsp;7:21)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Sermon on the Mount both tells us of our need for Christ because we cannot be perfect, and requires us to genuinely pursue perfection to honor our&amp;nbsp;Savior.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="devotions"></category></entry><entry><title>The New Testament Needs the Old (and So Do You)</title><link href="http://chriskrycho.com/2014/the-new-testament-needs-the-old-and-so-do-you/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-01-28T22:10:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Chris Krycho</name></author><id>tag:chriskrycho.com,2014-01-28:2014/the-new-testament-needs-the-old-and-so-do-you/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Having just finished reading through the Chronicles, it is readily apparent how Matthew self-consciously situated himself against the backdrop of the Old Testament as he began composing his gospel. Just as the Old Testament carefully preserved the lineages of the people&amp;#8212;most notably in Numbers and Chronicles&amp;#8212;so Matthew carefully laid out the descent of Christ, showing that his (adoptive) father&amp;#8217;s line ran true back through David.&lt;sup id="fnref:synoptic"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:synoptic" rel="footnote"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; If, as some scholars of the canon have speculated, Matthew&amp;#8217;s Old Testament canon concluded with Chronicles,&lt;sup id="fnref:canon"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:canon" rel="footnote"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; this beginning seems especially fitting, but in any case Matthew was clearly interested in establishing continuity between his work and the Hebrew&amp;nbsp;Bible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We pick up this same thread in his constant use of the word &amp;#8220;fulfill.&amp;#8221; The way Matthew uses the word has been much discussed among scholars, since many of the passages he quotes are clearly &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; talking about the Messiah in particular. While some see this as evidence of either Matthew&amp;#8217;s exegetical failure or the validity of purely allegorical readings, I think&lt;sup id="fnref:Beale"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:Beale" rel="footnote"&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; the solution is simpler. Matthew is using the word in a &lt;em&gt;simpler&lt;/em&gt; fashion. He means not &amp;#8220;fulfill&amp;#8221; in the sense in which we use the word of formal prophecies, but &amp;#8220;fill up&amp;#8221;. The Greek word &lt;em&gt;pleróō&lt;/em&gt; (πληρόω) covers both.&lt;sup id="fnref:semantic-range"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:semantic-range" rel="footnote"&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; When Matthew says that some event &amp;#8220;fulfills&amp;#8221; something from the Old Testament, he is not arguing that the Old Testament bit he references was originally written about Jesus, but rather that Jesus takes that original thing and fills it up with &lt;em&gt;more&lt;/em&gt; meaning than it originally&amp;nbsp;had.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The combination of these two things, in any case, is to point us to the Jewishness and the Old Testament background against which Jesus did his entire ministry, and in which the church was born. Last semester and this semester, I have been taking survey classes of the Old Testament, and I find them extremely valuable. The Old Testament is underpreached in most churches, because (I think) it is undervalued in most churches. Whether because of a simplistic and misguided notion that the Old Testament has only law and the New Testament only grace, or because the texts are harder to read for propositionally oriented Westerners,&lt;sup id="fnref:proposition"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:proposition" rel="footnote"&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; or simply because of unfamiliarity on the part of many pastors, we skip over the Old Testament. We might draw on it for moral statements from time to time, or to give some extra explanation for the atonement&amp;#8212;but when was the last time you heard someone preach through Isaiah, or Malachi, or 2&amp;nbsp;Chronicles?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a catastrophic loss to th echurch. Paul wrote that &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; Scripture was breathed out by God and is profitable for us&amp;#8212;and the only canon he had at the time was the Old Testament; he and his fellow apostles were still in the process of composing the pieces that became the New Testament! The early church&amp;#8217;s Bible, the texts from which they read, sang, and preached week in and week out, were those of the Old Testament. They read the Psalms together, learned from the Proverbs, chewed on Job, sought to imitate the saints of old, and above all looked for the many ways their Messiah had been proclaimed and prefigured in the pages of their book. They found there ample instruction in walking with God and worshipping their risen Lord. Matthew found there the ground of his entire gospel. Perhaps we would do well to do better in our love of the Old Testament,&amp;nbsp;too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:synoptic"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is much argument about the differing genealogies in Luke and Matthew. This is an interesting discussion&amp;#8230; for something besides a devotional post. Contrary to many a scholar, evangelical and dissenting alike, the so-called synoptic problem comes &lt;em&gt;after&lt;/em&gt; dealing with each book on its own terms.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:synoptic" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:canon"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All the same books would have been present, just in a different order.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:canon" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 2 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:Beale"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Following an article by &lt;span class="caps"&gt;G. K.&lt;/span&gt; Beale from several decades ago, a link to which I do not have at hand at the moment and which would undoubtedly bore the vast majority of you to stupor in any case.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:Beale" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 3 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:semantic-range"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is an important issue here for issues of translation, and especially for the idea of &amp;#8220;word studies&amp;#8221;: namely, that they&amp;#8217;re basically unhelpful. Words in different languages have different ranges of meanings. We can see this at the most basic level in the Spanish word &amp;#8220;mesa&amp;#8221;, which partly overlaps with the English word &amp;#8220;table&amp;#8221;, but extends to include things (like bluffs) which the English word does not include. This happens all the time, and accordingly just looking up all the places where a particular Greek word is used can often produce more heat than light&amp;#8212;it will make you think that authors mean the same thing in places where the context demands that they do not. I really, really recommend that you avoid word studies for this reason.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:semantic-range" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 4 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:proposition"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A factor undergoing rapid change in many parts of the West, as story becomes central again in large parts of the population.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:proposition" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 5 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary><category term="devotions"></category></entry><entry><title>Ordinary Means: The Silence of God</title><link href="http://chriskrycho.com/2014/ordinary-means-the-silence-of-god/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-01-27T08:05:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Chris Krycho</name></author><id>tag:chriskrycho.com,2014-01-27:2014/ordinary-means-the-silence-of-god/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Esther is one of the most unusual books in the Old Testament&amp;#8212;so much so that it was one of several books that almost did not end up in the canon. As has often been noted, it includes no mention of God, nor even a reference to prayer. The closest one comes to typical Jewish religious observance is the practice of fasting under dire circumstances and the tearing of clothes and donning sackloth and ashes in their place. But these were hardly unique to the worship of Yahweh; they were common practice throughout the Ancient Near East. Moreover, the book endorsed the practice of a feast beyond those listed in the Mosaic law: a questionable practice at &lt;em&gt;best&lt;/em&gt; from the perspective of many observant&amp;nbsp;Jews.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yet here it is, in most Jewish and all Christian canons.&lt;sup id="fnref:canon"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:canon" rel="footnote"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Again: as many commentators have noticed, Yahweh may not be mentioned by name, but his handiwork is evident throughout the book. He is not mentioned, but he is still present. His sovereignty is clear even in the absence of a prophetic declaration of his intent or activity. Indeed, for this reason I think that the book is also one of the most important books for understanding how God&amp;#8217;s actions in ordinary life play&amp;nbsp;out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Scriptures are filled with records of God&amp;#8217;s speech to his people, and of his miraculous intervention in their lives. From this, it can be easy to draw the notion that this is the normal and ordinary course of affairs. In other words, we might after reading through the histories of Israel conclude that we should expect God to be sending prophetic messages and miracles our way on a regular basis. Indeed,  large parts of the charismatic movement today are built around that very expectation. When life remains ordinary, we are inevitably disappointed. When we do not hear distinct, prophetic messages from God, we inevitably go looking for substitutes, whether in the pronouncements of famous Christians or our own &amp;#8220;inner sense&amp;#8221; of the Spirit&amp;#8217;s actions&amp;#8212;neither of which are reliable guides, as I have &lt;a href="http://2012-2013.chriskrycho.com/theology/will-of-god/"&gt;argued before&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the one hand, it is helpful to remember the circumstances under which those prophets spoke and those miracles happened. Always, they were associated with specific events in the redemptive history of the nation. Though they occasionally impinged on the life of ordinary people (like the family with whom Elisha repeatedly interacted, from miraculously overflowing oil to the resurrection of a dead child), for the most part they involved the spiritual and political leadership of the people of God. All this is true&amp;#8212;but true &lt;em&gt;statements&lt;/em&gt; do not always communicate in the same way as do true &lt;em&gt;stories&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is this gap that Esther fills.&lt;sup id="fnref:gap"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:gap" rel="footnote"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Here we have a story of God&amp;#8217;s saving his people with no divine speech, and no obvious miraculous intervention. In their place are ordinary people doing as best they can with the wisdom they have in the (dreadful) circumstances they face. Here was a moment in redemptive history, no less, with the fate of thousands of men and women hanging in the balance&amp;#8230; where all the sorts of things we sometimes erroneously expect for the not-so-significant moments in our own lives were simply&amp;nbsp;absent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is not that God was absent; we see from the outcomes that his concern for his people remained (he saved them) and his judgment on their enemies remained (he destroyed them). We even see that &amp;#8220;many from the peoples of the country declared themselves Jews, for the fear of the Jews had fallen on them&amp;#8221; (Esther 8:17b, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;ESV&lt;/span&gt;)&amp;#8212;not exactly a typical event in Jewish history, but certainly part of the end for which Yahweh had set them among the nations! Yet in all this, God remains behind the scenes. So it most often is in our own lives. God&amp;#8217;s silence does not imply his absence; nor does the ordinary nature of our lives imply his uninvolvement. Quite the contrary: most of the time, in most people&amp;#8217;s lives, in most places, God works by ordinary rather than extraordinary means. We get up, go about our day, honoring him as best we may in our various vocations, and he works &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; things to the praise of his glory and the good of those who love&amp;nbsp;him.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thank God for Esther and&amp;nbsp;Mordecai.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:canon"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The existence of various canons is less troubling than many critics would suggest&amp;#8212;not least because the core of all these canons is the same, and the extra material in them rarely leads to significant doctrinal variations. This is not to say that the distinctions are entirely unimportant, but rather to say that it is less an issue for the reliability and authority of Scripture than many naysayers would have you believe. More on this&amp;#8230; some other day.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:canon" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:gap"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not to say that this is the &lt;em&gt;only&lt;/em&gt; thing Esther is doing, but that it is &lt;em&gt;one&lt;/em&gt; of the significant things the book does.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:gap" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 2 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary><category term="devotions"></category></entry><entry><title>Nehemiah’s Exhortation</title><link href="http://chriskrycho.com/2014/nehemiahs-exhortation/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-01-25T22:30:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Chris Krycho</name></author><id>tag:chriskrycho.com,2014-01-25:2014/nehemiahs-exhortation/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;This week, I did most of my devotional reading early in the morning. Though I have gone back and forth on the time of day in which I am best able to spend time reading the Scriptures and praying, in &lt;em&gt;this&lt;/em&gt; season of life it is undeniably mornings. Our evenings are quite varied, for one thing. For another, these days I am for more awake at 6:15 in the morning than I am at 9:15 (or, as now, 10:15) at night. Thus, devotedly doing my devotions means doing them in the morning for the most part, lest I have a hard time keeping my eyes&amp;nbsp;open.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tonight&amp;#8217;s readings in Nehemiah covered passages with which I am quite familiar, having looked at them many times. A few of them are proof texts for certain views of preaching&amp;#8212;in particular, the way thtat the Levites gave the meaning of the text so that the people could understand it is often used to buttress support for expositional preaching. This, however, is a thoroughly ironic move hermeneutically speaking. The passage is actually indicating that the Levites were basically &lt;em&gt;translating&lt;/em&gt;, not offering explanatory commentary. Thus, it is a failure of exposition to derive proof for expository preaching from the&amp;nbsp;text.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of at least equal interest to me has always been the way Nehemiah responded to the people&amp;#8217;s repentant reaction to hearing the Law of God proclaimed by Ezra. Nehemiah encouraged the people not to focus on the sorrow of what they had done, but on the joy of who their God was and what he had done on their behealf. The same exhortation, it seems to me, is one that we should think about more often. To be sure, it is good to be reminded of our sin and our failings. It is even better, however, for us to turn from looking at ourselves and to look at the Messiah who has saved us &lt;em&gt;from&lt;/em&gt; those sins and failings. Too easily do many of us fixate on the magnitude of our sin&amp;#8212;either thinking it too big for God to really deal with, or too small for God to concern himself with, but in any case focusing on the sin&amp;#8212;instead of on the one who has conquered sin once and for&amp;nbsp;all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;May we instead learn, like Nehemiah exhorted the people, to &lt;em&gt;rejoice&lt;/em&gt; at what God has done on our behalf, and to celebrate the ways in which he has worked salvation in the midst of and through our sorrows and our&amp;nbsp;foibles.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="devotions"></category></entry><entry><title>What Was Their Sin?</title><link href="http://chriskrycho.com/2014/what-was-their-sin/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-01-25T08:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Chris Krycho</name></author><id>tag:chriskrycho.com,2014-01-25:2014/what-was-their-sin/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;As Christians, we all recognize that Adam and Eve&amp;#8217;s first sin in the garden of Eden prompted the catastropic Fall of all humanity, and that their eating of the fruit of the tree of the knowledge of good and evil was the &lt;em&gt;act&lt;/em&gt; of sin that produced such horrific results in human history. What is perhaps less clear is why that particular act was sinful. Was it disobedience? gaining knowledge? pride? idolatry? The most straightforward reading of Genesis 3 makes it clear that the act was sinful at the most basic level because it was disobedience, a direct rejection of the stated will of God. God tells Adam that the consequences he receives are because he ate of the tree from which he was commanded not to eat&amp;nbsp;(3:17).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perhaps the more interesting question, then, is why disobedience to God is a sin. As Christians, we acknowledge that the Bible teaches us this truth. Digging deeper is helpful in understanding many things about God and the nature of both humanity and the shape of the world we inhabit. To describe why disobedience is sinful, though, requires that we first define what sin &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt;. Sin is, at the most basic level, failure&amp;#8212;missing the mark, as the Greek word would have it. The next question, then, is: &lt;em&gt;Failure at&amp;nbsp;what?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sin is failure to be what humans were (and still are) meant to be&amp;#8212;a mystery of ages, to which we have the answer. Genesis tells us exactly who we humans are. We are made in the image of God. We are to be small icons of divine glory. The divinity we are meant to recapitulate in miniature exists in perfect harmony, is completely wise and wholly good, and exercises utter sovereignty. Women and men are meant likewise to exist in true harmony, to be wise in right measure and truly good, and to exercise sovereignty in our appointed spheres. This is what it &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; to be human: to do as God does in the ways he appoints in the world he&amp;nbsp;made.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thus, to &lt;em&gt;fail&lt;/em&gt; at that task is no small thing. It is to fail in the most significant way possible. Worse still, to fail as Adam and Eve did (and as we all have ever since) can only happen in a conscious act. Yes, our natures are now so corrupted that we all sin incidentally, too. But we all of us sin on purpose. Our first father and mother did not fail accidentally. They willfully rejected the very reason for their existence and spat in the face of the author of that existence. (Here is the source of the human struggle for existential meaning and the dread of meaningless that plagues us.) They rejected both the shape of reality and the one who made reality. They rebelled. They became traitors against the universe&amp;#8217;s&amp;nbsp;God.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Their sin, then, was not only disobedience. There are times when disobedience might be right: one &lt;em&gt;should&lt;/em&gt; reject unjust commands. This, however, was not such a command. Their act of disobedience included both mistrust of most trustworthy God and self-exaltation over and against the only exalted God. God does not only demand our allegiance, he &lt;em&gt;deserves&lt;/em&gt; it. He requires our worship not because he is vain, but because to worship anything else, however lovely, is to do injury to the object of that worship, to ourselves, and to the Triune Godhead. Adam and Eve&amp;#8217;s eating of the fruit of the tree of the knowledge of good represented precisely that offense. They rejected God&amp;#8217;s sovereignty, his wisdom and goodness, and even fellowship with him. They rejected their own sphere of sovereignty, chose quick knowledge over wisdom, deceit over goodness, and treachery over&amp;nbsp;communion.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="M.&amp;hairsp;Div."></category></entry><entry><title>From Creation to Consummation</title><link href="http://chriskrycho.com/2014/from-creation-to-consummation/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-01-24T22:05:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Chris Krycho</name></author><id>tag:chriskrycho.com,2014-01-24:2014/from-creation-to-consummation/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Some texts are a bit more mysterious than they might at first appear. One such is Psalm 24, at least for me. The poem has three basic&amp;nbsp;sections:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a declaration of Yahweh&amp;#8217;s possession of and sovereignty over the world he made (vv.&amp;nbsp;1&amp;#8211;2)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a reflection on the character of one who may approach Yahweh (vv.&amp;nbsp;3&amp;#8211;6)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a call to and an act of exultation in the glory of Yahweh (vv.&amp;nbsp;7&amp;#8211;10)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At first glance, there is no obvious connection between these three elements. The third might seem to follow from the first to some extent, but the emphases are all different. The first section addresses Yahweh&amp;#8217;s rule over creation; the last enjoins gates and doors&lt;sup id="fnref:gates-doors"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:gates-doors" rel="footnote"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; to worship him on the basis that he&amp;#8212;Yahweh of hosts&amp;#8212;is the king of glory. The middle section, on the character of those who can approach him, seems completely disconnected from&amp;nbsp;either.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yet David, the author of the Psalm, was not an idiot. When we find passages like this in Scripture and cannot at first see how to put them together, it behooves us to take a step back and consider them at further length.&lt;sup id="fnref:consider"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:consider" rel="footnote"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; David intended his poem to be understood, and not by God only. The pieces &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt; relate; the question is simply &lt;em&gt;how&lt;/em&gt; they fit. As is the way of all good poetry, there are holes here, and they require of the audience a bit more engagement than would a direct statement of David&amp;#8217;s&amp;nbsp;intent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sure enough, these pieces do relate. Each points us to a different aspect of Yahweh&amp;#8217;s nature. Indeed, the outline I wrote out above is actually a good summary of David&amp;#8217;s intent here. In verses 1&amp;#8211;2, we see that Yahweh owns the world he made. He is both creator and ruler. He is sovereign over creation, including the men and women who live in this world. Then, in verses 3&amp;#8211;6, we see his moral character. The requirements for anyone to approach Yahweh&amp;#8217;s holy place tell us just as much about Yahweh as about those who seek him: he is holy, he has clean hands (meaning he has not done nothing wrong), he is pure in heart, he rejects all idolatry, and he is utterly trustowrthy. Moreover, he blesses those who are like him; he makes them righteous and saves them. Finally in verses 7&amp;#8211;10, we see that he is glorious, strong and mighty, a king. He is not just &lt;em&gt;any&lt;/em&gt; king, but &lt;em&gt;the&lt;/em&gt; King of glory. He owns glory; it is his and no other&amp;#8217;s. He is stronger than any who would oppose him. He will triumph over his enemies. He will come into the city and take up his&amp;nbsp;reign.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In short, the Psalm moves us from creation to consummation. Yahweh made and rules over the world. He calls his people to be holy, as he is holy, and he makes them righteous and saves them. He will come into his glory as the King. And David gets us there without ever coming out and saying those bare facts; the poem moves our hearts the more thoroughly because he makes us work for us, and because he does so with such aching&amp;nbsp;beauty.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lift up your heads, O gates!
And lift them up, O ancienet doors,
that the King of glory may come in.
Who is this King of glory?
Yahweh of hosts,
he is the King of glory! Selah. (Psalm&amp;nbsp;24:9&amp;#8211;10)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hallelujah.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:gates-doors"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over-familiarity with the text has also perhaps dulled us to the curiosity of this exhortation. Perhaps there was something going on culturally we are missing today, but this is the only place in Scripture that anyone addresses gates and doors, to my knowledge.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:gates-doors" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:consider"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, that assumes we are paying enough attention to recognize that the poem is doing something unusual in the first place&amp;#8212;and, dare I say it, we too rarely are paying heed so closely.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:consider" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 2 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary><category term="devotions"></category></entry><entry><title>Foreign Wives and Real Devotion</title><link href="http://chriskrycho.com/2014/foreign-wives-and-real-devotion/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-01-23T07:28:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Chris Krycho</name></author><id>tag:chriskrycho.com,2014-01-23:2014/foreign-wives-and-real-devotion/</id><summary type="html">&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My son, give me your heart,
and let your eyes observe my ways.
For a prostitue is a deep pit;
a foreign woman&lt;sup id="fnref:fw"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:fw" rel="footnote"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; is a narrow well. (Proverbs 23:26&amp;#8211;27,&amp;nbsp;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;ESV&lt;/span&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The latter half of Ezra explains how it is that the people of Israel &lt;a href="/2014/justice-mercy-same-stroke/"&gt;turned away&lt;/a&gt; from their pattern of idolatry&amp;#8212;and it wasn&amp;#8217;t pretty or easy. After the people began building the temple again under the leadership of Haggai and Zechariah, after the favor shown to the Jews by the kings Darius and Artaxerxes, and after Ezra made his God-favored journey from Babylon to Jerusalem bearing more gifts and entrusted to teach the people the law, everything once again nearly went wrong because of an old pattern the Jews were embracing. Despite the clear instruction of the Law of Yahweh, they were intermarrying with the people around&amp;nbsp;them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The instruction not to intermarry was not racism, even if some abused it to that end. Those who did missed the point entirely, for Yahweh had always welcomed the outsider into his people. Indeed, the very existence of Israel was predicated on Yahweh&amp;#8217;s choosing for himself someone who was &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; following him. Likewise, the kingly line had in it multiple outsiders (most notably Rahab and Ruth). No, the point was not the superiority of the Jews over the people around them&amp;#8212;a notion that their history should have made clear was laughable in any case&amp;#8212;but the protection of their &lt;em&gt;worship&lt;/em&gt;. Every time that Israelites began intermarrying with the people around them, they also began following the worship practices of the people around them. They started worshipping idols, every single&amp;nbsp;time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thus, the prohibition on intermarriage was not a matter of racial distinction, but of religious distinction, and Israel&amp;#8217;s history bore out the necessity of the policy. Yet in Ezra 9, we find that once again they were slipping into the same old pattern. Ezra&amp;#8217;s response might be startling without that history. Even apart from a pattern of this same folly, though, his response is the right one from a shepherd when God&amp;#8217;s people disobey him. There is a lesson here for pastors and ministers: Ezra&amp;#8217;s first response was grief and a prayer of corporate repentance. Only after offering that prayer did he move to deal with the&amp;nbsp;sin.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The mundane&lt;sup id="fnref:mundane"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:mundane" rel="footnote"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; response Ezra made is interesting and has been much debated, given God&amp;#8217;s stated opposition to divorce. While we might speculate about the outcomes of the decision for the women and children affected by requiring these Israelite men to put them away, we have no grounds to do so. Certainly we can say that the right thing for these men to do would have been to provide for the families they had created, even while no longer having them as spouses. As to what they actually did, though, we simply have no basis for speaking one way or another. What we can say with confidence is that Ezra&amp;#8217;s actions here underscore the seriousness with which he took keeping the Law of God. Holiness mattered to him&amp;#8212;and not just his own personal holiness, but the holiness of the people of&amp;nbsp;God.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So it ought to be for us, especially those of us who seek to be teachers and leaders within the church. If we are to be the bride of Christ, we must seek to be &lt;em&gt;wholly&lt;/em&gt; pure. A bride does not care only that her face and one of her dress sleeves are white; she cares that her whole appearance is radiant and beautiful when she meets her groom. So let us diligently pursue both our own holiness and that of our brothers and sisters in&amp;nbsp;Christ.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:fw"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;ve chosen the Hebrew original rather than the usual translation of &amp;#8220;adulteress&amp;#8221;&amp;#8212;you&amp;#8217;ll see why momentarily.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:fw" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:mundane"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have chosen &amp;#8220;mundane&amp;#8221; rather than &amp;#8220;practical&amp;#8221; because the two are not the same, and the latter would imply that Ezra&amp;#8217;s prayer was not practical, when in fact prayer is often the most practical thing we can do.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:mundane" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 2 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary><category term="devotions"></category></entry><entry><title>Justice and Mercy in the Same Stroke</title><link href="http://chriskrycho.com/2014/justice-mercy-same-stroke/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-01-22T07:40:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Chris Krycho</name></author><id>tag:chriskrycho.com,2014-01-22:2014/justice-mercy-same-stroke/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The first four chapters of Ezra make for an interesting contrast with all the chapters of the Chronicles that immediately precede it. Though some of the pages are taken up with similar, &lt;a href="/2014/grappling-with-genealogies/"&gt;uninteresting(-at-least-to-us)&lt;/a&gt; details of the number of people who returned from the Exile to rebuild the temple of God under the command of Cyrus, other parts of this passage indicate the significant change that had taken place in the people of Judah and Benjamin and Levi during their sojourn far from their homes. In short: they had learned not to worship other gods. This becomes increasingly clear throughout Ezra-Nehemiah, and as one comes to the New Testament it is obvious that the lesson did indeed&amp;nbsp;stick.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is not to say that the Jews had no ongoing religious issues. They did, to be sure. But these issues were not the issue of idolatry, at least in the strict sense of the word. Tim Keller would likely argue that the issues they had were still matters of idolatry of a sort, and I would be inclined to agree with him; but in any case, they were no longer putting up Asherah poles or making sacrifices to Baal or Molech. There were many consequences of the Exile, including the end of the Davidic line of kings over Judah, the loss of the Ark of the Covenant, and the destruction of the First Temple. Most important of all, though, was this reality that the Jews never again engaged in large-scale worship of gods besides Yahweh. Their functional &lt;abbr title="the belief in and worship of a single God while accepting the existence or possible existence of other deities that may also be worshipped. (see Wikipedia: http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Henotheism)"&gt;henotheism&lt;/abbr&gt; gave way at last to true&amp;nbsp;monotheism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is amazing to me&amp;#8212;and wonderful&amp;#8212;that the result of God&amp;#8217;s judgment was not only the punishment of the judged but also their hearts being changed. He used a dreadful consequence to bring about real, lasting change in his people. It strikes me that sometimes we see exactly this, albeit on a smaller scale, in our own lives. There are times when we run far astray, and in his &lt;em&gt;mercy&lt;/em&gt; he judges us, so that we will return to him. Now, there is a final judgment beyond which there is no return, but in the interval, how great his grace! This is a double blessing to us who follow Christ: First, it reminds us that if we stray, he is faithful to send opportunity after opportunity (usually increasingly &lt;em&gt;painful&lt;/em&gt; opportunity) for our repentance. Second, it gives us reason not to go astray at all, realizing that the further we run, the more difficult will be our judgment. In both, we are reminded to worship our God: who judges justly and mercifully in the same&amp;nbsp;stroke.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="devotions"></category></entry><entry><title>Generation by Generation</title><link href="http://chriskrycho.com/2014/generation-by-generation/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-01-21T12:05:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Chris Krycho</name></author><id>tag:chriskrycho.com,2014-01-21:2014/generation-by-generation/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The concluding chapters of 2 Chronicles are just as mixed a bag as all the chapters that preceded them. Over and over again, kings rise and fall; generation to generation, the fortunes of the people rise and fall with their fidelity to Yahweh. From Hezekiah&amp;#8217;s reliance on Yahweh and God&amp;#8217;s corresponding triumph over the armies of Sennacherib of Assyria, to the final end of the Judaic kingdom&lt;sup id="fnref:judaic"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:judaic" rel="footnote"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; in the rebellions of Jehoiakim and Jehoiachin, the same themes that dominated the rest of the book are on full display here. Reliance on Yahweh leads to salvation and deliverance. Abandoning Yahweh leads to destruction. The narrative of human history, personal and corporate, played out time and again in the public history of&amp;nbsp;Israel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are many things that could be said of these chapters, but two points in particular caught my attention, both of which have been present throughout the book and so warrant some remarks here at the&amp;nbsp;end.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, the transition from generation to generation was rarely smooth. I do not mean merely the actual intrigues of the courts, of which there were clearly quite a few, what with multiple kings suffering assassination at the hands of their promptly-executed servants. Rather, I mean the spiritual succession. There are a few generations recorded here where multiple successive kings followed Yahweh wholeheartedly. Mostly, though, the kings bounced back and forth between fidelity and faithlessness (with no few examples of simple vacillation). Each father&amp;#8217;s son charted his own course. As a father myself, this is simultaneously a cause for hope and reason to pray the more faithfully for my own children. I must pray for them and seek earnestly to make disciples of them because there is no guarantee that they will follow Christ simply because I do. By the same token, there is hope that they will walk with God despite my own failings and follies. No child is doomed or blessed to walk her father&amp;#8217;s path; she makes her own&amp;nbsp;choices.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Second is the sheer efficacy of the Scriptures. Every time that the people were confronted with the word of God, they moved to repentance. They tore down idols, repaired the temple, and engaged once again in the practices outlined by the Law for purification and sacrifices. Time and again, it was the word of God that convicted people. It is tempting to try to stir people up to love and good works by our own efforts, but nothing we do will ever be as effective as the word of God, which is the Spirit&amp;#8217;s appointed means for sanctifying his people. For every minister in the world, and indeed for every believer in the world, this ought to be an enormous encouragement. We do not need to be people of unusual skill at public speaking, or especially effective debators. We simply need to know the word of God and lean hard on it, trusting that the Holy Spirit will use it. Yes, we should grow in our knowledge and understanding, and seek to become more skillful in the ways in which we interact with others. Ultimately, though, it is God&amp;#8217;s words that prove effective for turning people to him. That is good news&amp;nbsp;indeed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:judaic"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yes, there was a &amp;#8220;king&amp;#8221; in Judea later, but the domain of which Herod was a representative was not Judaic or Davidic but instituted by outsiders for their own ends.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:judaic" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary><category term="devotions"></category></entry><entry><title>Ending Badly</title><link href="http://chriskrycho.com/2014/ending-badly/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-01-20T23:30:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Chris Krycho</name></author><id>tag:chriskrycho.com,2014-01-20:2014/ending-badly/</id><summary type="html">&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Who can say, &amp;#8220;I have made my heart pure;&lt;br /&gt;
I am clean from my sin&amp;#8221;? (Proverbs 20:9,&amp;nbsp;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;ESV&lt;/span&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yet again, the annals of the kings of Judah point to the need for a different kind of king&amp;#8212;one who is faithful in the long run. Joash was a boy when he became king, rescued from the threat of death at the hands of his own power-mad grandmother by a faithful priest. For the days of that priest, he remained faithful, but after his death, he fell so far that he had that priest&amp;#8217;s son murdered for daring to &amp;#8220;speak truth to power&amp;#8221; in pointing out the folly of Joash&amp;#8217;s idolatry. How far must one fall to kill the son of the man who saved your life and put you on the throne? Yet this is how idolatry works. It corrupts and twists our senses, until we call evil good and good&amp;nbsp;evil.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But when he was strong, he grew proud, to his destruction. For he was unfaithful to the &lt;span style="font-variant: small-caps"&gt;Lord&lt;/span&gt; his God and entered the temple of the &lt;span style="font-variant: small-caps"&gt;Lord&lt;/span&gt; to burn incense on the altar of incense. (2 Chronicles 26:16,&amp;nbsp;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;ESV&lt;/span&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Uzziah follows the same pattern laid out by so many kings of Judah before him. He started well, but finished badly. Of the many themes of the book of Chronicles, one that comes home time and again is the risk of setting out to follow God and being turned aside in the course of life. Deadliest of all the lures for these kings was always the temptation to pride and confidence in their own strength. I see this, watching successful men and women today. How often do we choose people to lead us because we recognize their godliness and character, and then see them stumble into folly as pride consumes them? Too often. The example stands as a warning to all of us, but especially to any who wish to lead. If God grants us success&amp;#8212;especially the kind of success so prized by the world and by our flesh&amp;#8212;we must be doubly wary against the poisonous seeds of pride that so easily take root in our&amp;nbsp;hearts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perhaps most striking here is the particular way in which Uzziah fell. In this case, it was not as in so many others a matter of folly in battle. Rather, it was folly in worship. Uzziah seems to have come under the impression that his military victories indicated such a degree of God&amp;#8217;s favor&amp;#8212;such a degree of his own righteousness before God&amp;#8212;that he could disregard the ways God had commanded his people to approach him. He disregarded the supreme holiness of God, and took lightly the laws that Yahweh had laid out. It cost him everything on which he had prided himself; he spent the end of his life a leper alone. God&amp;#8217;s response to Uzziah&amp;#8217;s actions here serve as a stark reminder to me not to take worship lightly, and not to dishonor God by taking &lt;em&gt;him&lt;/em&gt; lightly. He is holy, and we ought never dare to trifle with&amp;nbsp;him.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Steadfast love and faithfulness preserve the king&lt;br /&gt;
and by steadfast love his throne is upheld. (Proverbs&amp;nbsp;20:28)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whose steadfast love and faithfulness preserve a king, and whose steadfast love upholds the throne of a king? It is Yahweh: a God merciful and gracious, abounding in steadfast love and faithfulness. It is the king who is above all the other kings. Proverbs points in unison with the Chronicles to the Messianic king. Praise be to God for his work in Christ Jesus. Hallelujah for a king who will  &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; turn his back on his God or on his people, who will not lead the people into idolatry or presumptuous worship, but who is himself &lt;em&gt;able&lt;/em&gt; to serve as priest, prophet, and&amp;nbsp;king.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="devotions"></category></entry><entry><title>Invest!—Memorizing Scripture</title><link href="http://chriskrycho.com/2014/invest-memorizing-scripture/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-01-19T23:05:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Chris Krycho</name></author><id>tag:chriskrycho.com,2014-01-19:2014/invest-memorizing-scripture/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Tonight, I am pausing from my normal discussion of the passages I&amp;#8217;ve been reading, to discuss instead how Jaimie and I have begun memorizing Scripture together this spring.&lt;sup id="fnref:memorization-confession"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:memorization-confession" rel="footnote"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Both of us have been persuaded of the value of memorizing Scripture for a long time (since before we met, and indeed since before we were in college).&lt;sup id="fnref:value"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:value" rel="footnote"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Jaimie&amp;#8217;s private Christian school included Scripture memorization as part of its curriculum, and the church at which I grew up likewise emphasized it as a useful discipline. Accordingly, both of us learned at relatively  young ages to practice memorizing verses from the Bible. We may not have been &lt;span class="caps"&gt;AWANA&lt;/span&gt; champions, but both of us have a good bit of the Bible stored in our&amp;nbsp;memories.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During college, as I studied the Bible and studied hermeneutics, I became increasingly convinced that the approach I had been taking to memorizing Scripture was, if not exactly &lt;em&gt;unhelpful&lt;/em&gt; (learning the Bible is a good move, full stop), nonetheless not nearly as helpful as it could be. Specifically, my emphasis on memorizing a verse here and a verse there&amp;#8212;even when I went so far as to memorize the whole sentence&amp;#8212;seemed to me to prevent me from really remembering the full meaning of the passage in question. Several times, I discovered that a verse I had memorized meant something other than what I had thought, as I studied its context carefully. It did not take but a few of these incidents for me to decide that I wanted to try something different. Accordingly, I decided to stoip memorizing individual verses or short passages, and to try instead to memorize a book of the Bible. That way, every single verse would automatically be in context for&amp;nbsp;me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You are probably thinking I was crazy, and/or (for those of you who know me well) that it is a typically over-the-top Chris Krycho thing to do. In some ways that might be true, at least in the details of my implementation: I jumped in with Hebrews, since it is one of my favorite books in the Bible. Things were actually going fairly well with that project; I had succesfully memorized up through chapter 7 and was working on verse 8&amp;#8230; and then I graduated from college. Suddenly, the 15&amp;#8211;20 minutes each day in which I had been accustomed to walking around on campus&amp;#8212;the time in which I had been practicing my Scripture memory&amp;#8212;was gone. I fell out of the habit, and never finished memorizing the&amp;nbsp;book.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fast forward three and a half years. Jaimie and I moved to North Carolina, and we started attending and soon joined &lt;a href="http://www.fbcdurham.org/"&gt;First Baptist Church of Durham&lt;/a&gt;. During our membership class, we received an interesting little booklet written by our senior pastor, Andy Davis, &lt;a href="http://www.fbcdurham.org/wp-content/uploads/2012/05/Scripture-Memory-Booklet-for-Publication-Website-Layout.pdf"&gt;&lt;em&gt;An Approach to Extended Memorization of Scripture&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Curious, I read through it that evening. Pastor Davis outlined there both the benefits of memorizing Scripture and&amp;#8212;to my surprise and interest&amp;#8212;basically the same concerns I had had about memorizing individual passages out of context. But then he did something profoundly helpful: he also provided a practical, straightforward system to help people learn to memorize extended sections of Scripture (i.e. &lt;em&gt;books&lt;/em&gt;). And not just crazy, over-the-top, intense people like Chris Krycho. Ordinary, not so strange&amp;nbsp;people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last fall, Jaimie and I started trying to memorize Philippians together. However, we did not have a system or a plan, and the attempt ended up going off the rails. We were moving at different paces, we were not helping each other review, and the whole thing eventually just sort of slid to a halt in the face of our busy lives and our lack of a plan. As part of our start to the new year, though, I suggested that we look at Pastor Davis&amp;#8217; materials and see if they would work for us. As it turns out, they do&amp;#8212;they work really, really&amp;nbsp;well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jaimie and I are 12 verses into Colossians 1, two weeks along. The system, simple as it is, has been easy to keep up each day, and has helped us stay in sync. We review together pretty much every day, and it has been a real joy. Picking a shorter book helps a lot, too: it feels more doable. By the time our next child is born in early June (Lord willing), we will have finished the book and be reviewing&amp;nbsp;it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The basic system itself is&amp;nbsp;simple:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pick a book. (Start short. Dr. Davis recommends Ephesians, and I certainly wouldn&amp;#8217;t go longer than&amp;nbsp;that.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Day 1: read 1:1 ten times out loud, then repeat it ten times from&amp;nbsp;memory.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Day 2: repeat 1:1 ten times from memory, checking the text if you need to. Once you finish that, read 1:2 ten times out loud, and then repeat it ten times from&amp;nbsp;meory.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Days 3 and following: repeat all previously memorized verses once from memory. Then repeat the previous day&amp;#8217;s verse 10 times from memory. Then read the next verse ten times out loud, and then repeat it ten times from&amp;nbsp;memory.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This way, one always reviews previous material in the book, but without it taking overly long. For example, on day 6, one would review 1:1&amp;#8211;5 from memory, say 1:5 another 9 times out loud from memory, read 1:6 out loud ten times, and then repeat 1:6 ten times from&amp;nbsp;memory.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To be honest, this system works &lt;em&gt;far&lt;/em&gt; better than the approach I had been taking on my own, both when I was memorizing Hebrews years ago and when I was working on Philippians last fall. The specific, active repetition helps solidify the verses in my head, which is important, especially because there are some verses that are just&amp;nbsp;hard.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pastor Davis outlines a good deal more in his &lt;a href="http://www.fbcdurham.org/wp-content/uploads/2012/05/Scripture-Memory-Booklet-for-Publication-Website-Layout.pdf"&gt;booklet&lt;/a&gt;, including arguing for the value of memorizing Scripture, why tackling longer stretches is helpful, and discussing both how to learn longer books and how to remember the books one has already learned. I commend this approach to you, even as I urge you strongly to consider making Scripture memory a regular spiritual&amp;nbsp;discipline.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:memorization-confession"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We actually tried starting this in the fall. It didn&amp;#8217;t work out so well. Keep reading.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:memorization-confession" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:value"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are not persuaded, I am not here going to make a full attempt to persuade you. Suffice it to say that I find it enormously helpful to have God&amp;#8217;s revelation stored up in my mind&amp;#8212;I find that the Holy Spirit often uses it to convict me or encourage me throughout the day, and that it is incredibly valuable in interacting with others, whether building up fellow believers or speaking with those who do not believe.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:value" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 2 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary><category term="devotions"></category></entry><entry><title>The Life and Death of Words</title><link href="http://chriskrycho.com/2014/life-and-death-of-words/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-01-18T22:55:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Chris Krycho</name></author><id>tag:chriskrycho.com,2014-01-18:2014/life-and-death-of-words/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;It is no exaggeration to say that I have spent more time thinking on the words Proverbs assigns to warning fools about the quantity of their speech than to almost any other part of the Proverbs.&lt;sup id="fnref:1"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:1" rel="footnote"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; I have many faults, but one of the most significant and ongoing is a tendency to be quick to speak and slow to hear (and yes, quick to become angry)&amp;#8212;to invert the order commended by James in the New Testament. This is no small&amp;nbsp;thing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Death and life are in the power of the tongue,&lt;br /&gt;
and those who love it will eat its fruits. (Proverbs&amp;nbsp;18:21)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Though I have sometimes heard this verse misused (as though to suggest a mystical power in our speech&amp;#8212;a view for which I think there is no warrant), the plain meaning alone is enough to give a person with my proclivities pause. If my one of my chief follies is the tendency to speak too freely and without sufficient consideration, what death have I wrought? Where might I have brought life instead? When I speak with Jaimie or with Ellie, when having long talks with friends, when offering my thoughts publicly, my words matter. &lt;em&gt;All&lt;/em&gt; words matter. Jesus warned the Pharisees (and warns us, lest we be like&amp;nbsp;them):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I tell you, on the day of judgment people will give account for every careless word they speak, for by your words you will be justified, and by your words you will be condemned. (Matthew 12:36&amp;#8211;37,&amp;nbsp;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;ESV&lt;/span&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The words one chooses to use&amp;#8212;the words &lt;em&gt;I&lt;/em&gt; choose to use&amp;#8212;can build others up or cut them down. They can encourage, or they can wound. They can bring life or&amp;nbsp;death.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A fool takes no pleasure in understanding,&lt;br /&gt;
but only in expressing his&amp;nbsp;opinion.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A fool&amp;#8217;s lips walk into a fight,&lt;br /&gt;
and his mouth invites a beating.&lt;br /&gt;
A fool&amp;#8217;s mouth is his ruin,&lt;br /&gt;
and his lips are a snare to his&amp;nbsp;soul.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If one gives an answer before he hears,&lt;br /&gt;
it is his folly and shame. (Proverbs 18:2, 6&amp;#8211;7,&amp;nbsp;13)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is a bit painful to think how often I have been a fool in these terms. It is a caution to me in writing these very posts. Yes, it is good to take time to reflect on the things I am learning from the Scriptures. It is, I think, profitable to post these particular reflections publicly.&lt;sup id="fnref:2"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:2" rel="footnote"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; There is, however, a serious danger that my writing could be an act of folly, and the more so the quicker I am to write before carefully considering the matter at&amp;nbsp;hand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I write on Scripture, I have one sort of responsibility: to honor the text, and in so doing to honor the one who authored the text. Few of us should seek to be teachers, because we will be held to a higher standard of judgment for our words. If I speak falsely of Scripture, there is a real chance that I will do harm to others&amp;#8217; spiritual health. When I write on other topics, I have a different sort of responsibility, but one no less weighty for that. If I publicly opine on politics, address personal situations in our lives, or discuss the contours of evangelical Christianity, my words will undoubtedly be read by people who stand either to benefit or to be injured by those words. Again: to write without careful consideration would be to risk bringing spiritual harm. In both cases, I would be in danger of dishonoring the God who gave us&amp;nbsp;words.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is particularly important for those of us who love words. I am obsessed with the beauty and power of human language, awed by the gift God bestowed on us in the creative potential of phonemes and clauses and sentences and paragraphs. I can (and, my friends can all wearily attest, &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt;) wax eloquent at the drop of a pin. This delight is a good thing; it is a part of the &lt;em&gt;imago dei&lt;/em&gt; in me. Yet my words are not to be their own ends. They, like I myself, exist for a cause greater than that. They are meant to serve God. If they do not, they will bring death. If they do, they will bring&amp;nbsp;life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The only other repeated warning I have considered as carefully is that on sexual immorality&amp;#8212;an area in which all young people are especially tempted.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:2"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It would not necessarily be profitable to post &lt;em&gt;every&lt;/em&gt; reflection publicly. Some of them would do the public no good, and posting them would be only a way of seeking attention in a way that would feed those selfsame sins. Confession is good. But confession is done with brothers and sisters in close fellowship&amp;#8212;not with the world at large.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:2" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 2 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary><category term="devotions"></category></entry><entry><title>Every King Broken</title><link href="http://chriskrycho.com/2014/every-king-broken/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-01-17T23:55:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Chris Krycho</name></author><id>tag:chriskrycho.com,2014-01-17:2014/every-king-broken/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;i class="editorial"&gt;The attentive reader will no doubt have noted that I missed a night last night, and am accordingly skipping over the relevant chapters. I fell asleep just after reading said chapters&amp;#8212;so the &lt;em&gt;most&lt;/em&gt; important aspect of this project, I still accomplished. Huzzah. As for why I got to it so late (and why I am again tonight)&amp;#8230; that will have to wait for next Tuesday to&amp;nbsp;explain.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A great deal of the latter parts of the Chronicles&amp;#8212;as in Kings&amp;#8212;are concerned with the deeds men who decided &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; to submit to Yahweh. Solomon&amp;#8217;s son, Rehoboam, set the tone for much of what followed. He began by obeying and worshiping God, but all too soon he went his own way. The Chronicler summarizes Rehoboam&amp;#8217;s turn  in a single sentence that I found strikingly&amp;nbsp;provocative:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When the rule of Rehoboam was established and he was strong, he abaondoned the law of the &lt;span style="font-variant: small-caps"&gt;Lord&lt;/span&gt;, and all Israel with him. (2 Chronicles&amp;nbsp;12:1)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;His deeds bore this out.  Whereas in the beginning of his reign Rehoboam was sensible enough to obey Yahweh when God spoke to the king through a prophet and warned him not to go to war with Jeroboam of Israel, his habits had&amp;nbsp;changed:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There were continual wars between Rehoboam and Jeroboam (2 Chronicles&amp;nbsp;12:15b)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Right there we have a perfect summary not only of the folly of so many kings of Judah in the years that followed Rehoboam, but of many of us as well. We turn to God in desperation in times of trouble, or when we are seeking security, but as soon as times are good and things seem to be going well with us, we are quick to abandon him. We begin to disobey, deciding our way is better and relying on our own wisdom. Never mind that we came to whatever point of success we have achieved only because God granted it to us in his&amp;nbsp;grace.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The next chapter records the reign of Rehoboam&amp;#8217;s son Ahijah&amp;#8212;a man who, it seems, recognized the power of Yahweh but did not fully submit to his rule. He happily relied on Yahweh when waging war, but (like his father, grandfather Solomon, and great-grandfather David before him) he rejected God&amp;#8217;s law when it came to taking multiple wives.&lt;sup id="fnref:wives"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:wives" rel="footnote"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; This sort of going halfway &lt;em&gt;also&lt;/em&gt; seems to characterize us all too frequently. We are happy to accept God&amp;#8217;s help, and may even be zealous for him in some ways, but too often are unwilling to submit to his&amp;nbsp;law.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ahijah&amp;#8217;s son Asa provides one more picture of a way that we often go wrong. He began exceedingly well. He relied on Yahweh for victory in war, and he also faithfully pursued his ways at home. He led Judah to break down their altars to other gods and pledge themselves to the worship of Yahweh, the one true God. He exiled even his own grandmother because of her devotion to idols. In short, if we had only chapter 15, we would think Asa a model king&amp;#8212;but the Chronicler adds an unhappy ending to the story. As Asa grew old, he turned away from the wisdom of his youth and decided to rely not on the strength of God for his country&amp;#8217;s defense but on his own political machinations and the strength in arms of neighboring nations.&lt;sup id="fnref:politics"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:politics" rel="footnote"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; That he was now going thoroughly off the rails becomes quite clear as one reads that he tortured the priest who told him that Yahweh disapproved of his treaty, and that he refused even in his illness to seek God&amp;#8217;s aid. There is a warning here: starting well does not guarantee one will finish&amp;nbsp;well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over and over again, as one reads through the Chronicles with Yahweh&amp;#8217;s resounding promise to David in mind&amp;#8212;that promise of a son whose throne would be established forever&amp;#8212;one is left disappointed. Beginning with Solomon, every single king misses the mark in some way. Either he flatly rejects Yahweh, or he simply finds an area in which he will not obey, or he falls away from wisdom as he ages. On and on go their follies&amp;#8212;the defects in character and failings in every virtue. But in this way, Rehoboam, Ahijah, and Asa all serve us still. They point us to the one king who did &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; fail, the man from the line of David, of the tribe of Judah, the great-grandson of Abraham, the offspring of the woman, born of a woman. That king never sinned. No matter how many years passed, he remained steadfast in the face of temptation to err (and remains steadfast in his prayers for us). He has but one bride, whom he awaits still. Jesus the Messiah is that&amp;nbsp;King.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:wives"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perhaps it is just me, but the idea of having multiple wives is somewhat terrifying. Jaimie is more than enough mystery for one lifetime. I think two women would leave me confounded without ceasing.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:wives" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:politics"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note that making alliances is not an inherently ungodly thing to do. The trick was that here it &lt;em&gt;clearly&lt;/em&gt; demonstrated Asa&amp;#8217;s lack of faith in Yahweh to save Judah, standing in rather stark contrast to his behavior in his youth.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:politics" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 2 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary><category term="devotions"></category></entry><entry><title>Who Can Dwell With God?</title><link href="http://chriskrycho.com/2014/who-can-dwell-with-god/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-01-15T23:55:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Chris Krycho</name></author><id>tag:chriskrycho.com,2014-01-15:2014/who-can-dwell-with-god/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Psalm 15, like many of the Psalms, has a double purpose. It points us simultaneously to whom we ought to aim to be as we strive to be holy as God is holy, and to Christ, the only one who has ever perfectly walked out these words. Walking through the passage tonight provided an opportunity both to pray for the Holy Spirit to make me more like these words, and to worship the Holy One of God who has actually fulfilled&amp;nbsp;them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;David opens with a provocative, challenging&amp;nbsp;question:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Oh &lt;span style="font-variant: small-caps"&gt;Lord&lt;/span&gt;, who shall sojourn in your tent?&lt;br /&gt;
Who shall dwell on your holy hill? (Psalm 15:1,&amp;nbsp;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;ESV&lt;/span&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Who indeed? The Psalms have already shown us&lt;sup id="fnref:1"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:1" rel="footnote"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; the image of a holy God who will brook no injustice and who hates sin passionately, but who is also the covenant-keeper and salvation of&amp;nbsp;Israel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He who walks blamelessly and does what is right&lt;br /&gt;
and speaks truth in his heart; &amp;#8230; (Psalm 15:2,&amp;nbsp;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;ESV&lt;/span&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is quite the target to hit already. Who &lt;em&gt;always&lt;/em&gt; walks blameless and does what is right? Not I. Who is &lt;em&gt;never&lt;/em&gt; self-deceived (still less never deceitful toward others)? Again, not&amp;nbsp;I.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;#8230;who does not slander with his tongue&lt;br /&gt;
and does no evil to his neighbor,&lt;br /&gt;
nor takes up a reproach against his friend; &amp;#8230; (Psalm 15:3,&amp;nbsp;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;ESV&lt;/span&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All of us have slandered our neighbors and taken up a reproach against friends. We have spoken cruelly of those we love, been harsh in our assessments of people over whom we have no such right to stand in judgment. We have been unkind to friends and held against them their sins. All of us have done evil to our neighbors&amp;#8212;there is no one among us who has escaped and managed to avoid ever harming anyone near&amp;nbsp;us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;#8230;in whose eyes a vile person is despised,&lt;br /&gt;
but who honors those who fear the Lord; &amp;#8230; (Psalm 15:4a,&amp;nbsp;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;ESV&lt;/span&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How many of us can truly say that we have this kind of heart&amp;#8212;that we always earnestly oppose those who rebel against God, and honor those who fear Him? Again: not I. Too often I make excuses for those who do not know God, rather than call their idolatrous and treacherous way of life as it is. Too often I am impatient and unkind and derogatory toward those who &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt; walk with&amp;nbsp;God.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;who swears to his own hurt and does not change;&lt;br /&gt;
who does not put out his money at interest&lt;br /&gt;
and does not take a bribe against the innocent.&lt;br /&gt;
He who does these things shall never be moved. (Psalm 15:4b&amp;#8211;5,&amp;nbsp;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;ESV&lt;/span&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How many of us have made a promise and then gone back on it because it became inconvenient? How many of us have, if not literally charged interest, then held it against people when it took them a long time to pay us back on money we lent them? To what extent are we &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; complicit in crimes against the innocent, even when we ourselves have kept our hands clean&amp;#8212;just by dint of our lives in a fallen world, as part of a fallen nation, where every year sees innocent lives lost at our&amp;nbsp;hands?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is not much hope for any of us to stand on God&amp;#8217;s holy hill even for a moment&amp;#8212;still less to dwell there forever. But Christ has measured up to every line that David raised, and gone beyond them. He stands in our stead, his righteousness granted to us, our failings taken on his own body. His Spirit empowers us to pursue this kind of life: fleeing sin and pursuing the holiness of God. May we seek to look more like Christ, who alone  has the right to sojourn in Yahweh&amp;#8217;s tent and who alone has the right to dwell on his holy hill&amp;#8212;but who has invited all of us in to the feast in that temple and to sit at his feet and eat the bread that satisfies on his&amp;nbsp;mountain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I take the view that the Psalms, in addition to being valuable in their own right individually, were organized by an editor who knew what he or she was about. That editor&amp;#8217;s decisions about where to put the Psalms is often illuminating&amp;#8212;much as it is with any other collection.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary><category term="devotions"></category></entry><entry><title>Practical Wisdom</title><link href="http://chriskrycho.com/2014/01-14-practical-wisdom/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-01-14T23:10:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Chris Krycho</name></author><id>tag:chriskrycho.com,2014-01-14:2014/01-14-practical-wisdom/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The Proverbs contain a striking mix of profound theological statements and practical, down-to-earth wisdom. Often the two come right next to each other,&lt;sup id="fnref:contrast?"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:contrast?" rel="footnote"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; and are both made all the more illuminating by way of the juxtaposition. The book&amp;#8217;s pages also include no few beautiful gems of insight into the human condition. Some of each caught my attention tonight as I read through Proverbs&amp;nbsp;14.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="on-the-human-condition"&gt;On the human&amp;nbsp;condition&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The heart knows its own bitterness,&lt;br /&gt;
and no stranger shares its joy. (Proverbs 14:10,&amp;nbsp;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;ESV&lt;/span&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And&amp;nbsp;again:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even in laughter the heart may ache,&lt;br /&gt;
and the end of joy may be grief. (Provebs 14:13,&amp;nbsp;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;ESV&lt;/span&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Both of these speak to realities we have all experienced. To be human in a fallen world is to be lonely at times&amp;#8212;to know that one&amp;#8217;s heart can never be shared perfectly with another. There are times when our hearts ache with this knowledge: because our grief is so deep that we wish another could partake of it with us and so ease the ache, and because our hearts are so full of gladness that we wish another could partake of it with us and so share the merriment. But we cannot. We are sundered from one another. But not finally so. We were made for better than this. Some day we will taste of it. In the long wait until that day, we may content ourselves with this: that very God of very God has drunk the bowl of our grief and supped with us in joy-making&amp;#8212;we are&amp;nbsp;known.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="practical-insights"&gt;Practical&amp;nbsp;insights&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A truthful witness saves lives,&lt;br /&gt;
but one who breathes out lies is deceitful. (Proverbs 14:25,&amp;nbsp;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;ESV&lt;/span&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This one seems both straightforward and obvious to me. It is interesting, though, that the author makes the point that the truthful witness &lt;em&gt;saves lives&lt;/em&gt;. It reminds me that our lenient age, with death a rare punishment for any crime, no matter how severe, is very different from almost every other. The word of a witness, in those days, meant the difference between a man being stoned to death and his going home to his family. Yet it is no less important today. I read recently of a case of wrongful conviction&amp;#8212;a man sentenced to prison for a crime he did not commit, which it is now &lt;em&gt;known&lt;/em&gt; he did not commit, and still he cannot get out of jail&amp;#8212;and all this because of a false testimony delivered on the stand many decades ago. &lt;sup id="fnref:justice"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:justice" rel="footnote"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Our words still have the power to make or ruin lives. Sometimes these are dramatic moments; other times they are the many little moments that add up to a larger shift in the course of one&amp;#8217;s life. Either way, telling the truth&amp;nbsp;matters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="theological-profundities"&gt;Theological&amp;nbsp;profundities&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the fear of the &lt;span style="font-variant: small-caps"&gt;Lord&lt;/span&gt; one has strong confidence,&lt;br /&gt;
and his children will have a refuge.&lt;br /&gt;
The fear of the &lt;span style="font-variant: small-caps"&gt;Lord&lt;/span&gt; is a fountain of life,&lt;br /&gt;
that one may turn away from the snares of death. (Proverbs 14:26&amp;#8211;27,&amp;nbsp;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;ESV&lt;/span&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These verses remind me in the sharpest terms that fearing Yahweh is essential to my own spiritual health and that of my family. Fearing him is confidence, refuge, life, escape from the snares of death. What would it mean, then, &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; to fear God? And make no mistake: fear here is more than mere reverence. God is holy, and his wrath burns hot against sin; we &lt;em&gt;should&lt;/em&gt; fear him. Not in contradistinction to loving him, though. Note that it is precisely in fearing Yahweh that one has confidence and refuge and life and&amp;nbsp;salvation!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The next one is of a rather different kind, but its anthropological theology is&amp;nbsp;striking:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whoever oppresses a poor man insults his Maker,&lt;br /&gt;
but he who is generous to the needy honors him. (Proverbs 14:31,&amp;nbsp;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;ESV&lt;/span&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;God so cares about the poor, that to oppress poor people is to insult him. He so loves the needy that being generous to them is to honor him. I think many Christians who are both theologically and politically conservative fail to take these kinds of words sufficiently seriously. Whatever the case may be for others, I know &lt;em&gt;I&lt;/em&gt; have failed to take them with all the gravity these words&amp;nbsp;carry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="striking-contrasts"&gt;Striking&amp;nbsp;contrasts&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The poor is disliked even by his neighbor,&lt;br /&gt;
but the rich has many friends.&lt;br /&gt;
Whoever despises his neighbor is a sinner,&lt;br /&gt;
but blessed is he who is generous to the poor. (Proverbs 14:20-21,&amp;nbsp;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;ESV&lt;/span&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first stanza is one of those straightforward, practical observations on the way things are in this broken world. It is simply &lt;em&gt;true&lt;/em&gt; that people look down on those who are poor, and that wealth earns friendship (of a sort). It is not &lt;em&gt;right&lt;/em&gt; that this is so. But still it is so. The second stanza shows up this reality for what it is, though: a reflection of a broken reality. The man who scorns his neighbor&amp;#8212;no matter the cause, but as we have seen perhaps &lt;em&gt;especially&lt;/em&gt; if for poverty&amp;#8212;sins in doing so. The man who gives generously to the poor is blessed. The contrast between the broken world in which we live and the holy ways of God to which we are called could not be&amp;nbsp;clearer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In summary, I am increasingly grateful for the Proverbs. I appreciate more and more Solomon&amp;#8217;s (and others&amp;#8217;) skill in composing them, and the editor&amp;#8217;s skill in arranging them so thoughtfully. Praise&amp;nbsp;God.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:contrast?"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It strikes me that we evangelicals&amp;#8212;ever jetting between the poles of abstruse dogmatics and applied pragmatics&amp;#8212;would do well to spend a bit more time on the way the Proverbs marry the two.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:contrast?" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:justice"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To be sure, this indicates flaws in our justice system, as well.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:justice" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 2 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary><category term="devotions"></category></entry><entry><title>When God Built David a House</title><link href="http://chriskrycho.com/2014/when-god-built-david-a-house/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-01-13T22:15:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Chris Krycho</name></author><id>tag:chriskrycho.com,2014-01-13:2014/when-god-built-david-a-house/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;First Chronicles 16&amp;#8211;17 marks one of the hinges in the progression of salvation history. Of all the great turns in the march of God&amp;#8217;s plan, this one is right up there with those that happened in the lives of Adam and Eve, Noah, Abraham, and Moses. David brought the ark of the covenant to Jerusalem and instituted the ritual&lt;sup id="fnref:ritual"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:ritual" rel="footnote"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; of worship that was to characterize the place where God&amp;#8217;s presence would dwell thenceforth&amp;#8212;a ritual that would produce many of the psalms and that would shape the best of the life of faithful Hebrews for generations to come. Then, Yahweh God blessed David with a covenant promise that far exceeded anything David did (or could have done) for his&amp;nbsp;creator.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is worth quoting Yahweh&amp;#8217;s promise to David at length, to see just how central this promise was to be in the history of God&amp;#8217;s plan for saving the&amp;nbsp;world:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="dquo"&gt;&amp;#8220;&lt;/span&gt;Moreover, I declare to you that the &lt;span style="font-variant: small-caps"&gt;Lord&lt;/span&gt; will build you a house.&lt;sup id="fnref:house"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:house" rel="footnote"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; When your days are fulfilled to walk with your fathers, I will raise up your offspring&lt;sup id="fnref:seed"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:seed" rel="footnote"&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; after you, one of your own sons, and I will establish his kingdom. He shall build a house for me, and I will establish his throne forever. I will be to him a father, and he shall be to me a son. I will not take my steadfast love from him, as I took it from him who was before you, but I will confirm him in my house and in my kingdom forever, and his throne shall be stablished forever.&amp;#8221; (1 Chronicles&amp;nbsp;17:10b&amp;#8211;14)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Much of this finds its first fulfillment in David&amp;#8217;s son Solomon, of course. Solomon built a temple for God, and Yahweh did fill it with his presence. Solomon, despite his wandering ways, continued to receive the blessings of God. However, even a casual reading of the rest of &lt;em&gt;this book&lt;/em&gt;&amp;#8212;the Chronicles&amp;#8212;immediately raises the question: How, exactly, will this promise be fulfilled if the Davidic line of kings ended when the Jews were exiled to&amp;nbsp;Babylon?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The New Testament makes it clear, of course: this promise finds its ultimately fulfillment in Jesus Christ. The Messiah &lt;em&gt;fills up&lt;/em&gt; a promise that had its first satisfaction in Solomon, but which was left unfinished in that king, great though he was. Jesus is the king whose throne is and will be established forever, from whom the Father&amp;#8217;s steadfast love with never be removed, and who indeed &lt;a href="/2014/temple-for-god.html" title="A Temple For God"&gt;built a house&lt;/a&gt; for God. Jesus is the one of whom the Father said, &amp;#8220;I will be to him a father, and he will be to me a son&amp;#8221; (see Hebrews&amp;nbsp;1:5).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But of course, just as the Hebrews were waiting with longing for a Messiah to come and fulfill this promise in the long years between the Exile and the coming of Christ, so we are awaiting the Messiah&amp;#8217;s coming in these long years between the Ascension and the Eschaton. The King is seated at the right hand of the Majesty on high (Hebrews 1:3), but he has not yet come to claim the whole of his kingdom. But in the interval, we follow David&amp;#8217;s&amp;nbsp;lead:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sing to the &lt;span style="font-variant: small-caps"&gt;Lord&lt;/span&gt;, all the earth!&lt;br /&gt;
Tell of his salvation from day to day.&lt;br /&gt;
Declare his glory among the nations,&lt;br /&gt;
his marvelous works among all the peoples!&lt;br /&gt;
For great is the &lt;span style="font-variant: small-caps"&gt;Lord&lt;/span&gt;, and greatly to be praised,&lt;br /&gt;
and he is to be held in awe above all gods.&lt;br /&gt;
For all the gods of the peoples are idols,&lt;br /&gt;
but the &lt;span style="font-variant: small-caps"&gt;Lord&lt;/span&gt; made the heavens,&lt;br /&gt;
Splendor and majesty are before him;&lt;br /&gt;
strength and joy are in his&amp;nbsp;place.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hallelujah. Maranatha.&lt;sup id="fnref:maranatha"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:maranatha" rel="footnote"&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:ritual"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Used here in the purely descriptive sense. Though we can all fall into &lt;em&gt;dead&lt;/em&gt; ritual, where we practice the mere outward forms of things with no motion of our will in line with the motions of our bodies, not all ritual is dead. Nor is all ritual bad. When our worship is &lt;em&gt;reduced&lt;/em&gt; to ritual, we have a problem, but ritual-less worship is anarchy and chaos at best.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:ritual" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:house"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;m skipping over this for the sake of brevity, but I find it really remarkable that when David plans to build God a house, God sends a prophet and tells David, &amp;#8220;No, &lt;em&gt;I&lt;/em&gt; am going to build &lt;em&gt;you&lt;/em&gt; a house.&amp;#8221; Here is a small picture of the gospel: God does for us what we are not worthy to do for him.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:house" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 2 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:seed"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="dquo"&gt;&amp;#8220;&lt;/span&gt;Offspring&amp;#8221; here is the same word (&amp;#8220;seed&amp;#8221;) used in the promise that the &amp;#8220;offspring&amp;#8221; of the woman would bruise the serpent&amp;#8217;s head and that the through &amp;#8220;offspring&amp;#8221; of Abraham the nations would be blessed.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:seed" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 3 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:maranatha"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="dquo"&gt;&amp;#8220;&lt;/span&gt;Come soon!&amp;#8221;&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:maranatha" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 4 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary><category term="devotions"></category></entry><entry><title>Scriptural Miscellanies</title><link href="http://chriskrycho.com/2014/scriptural-miscellanies-jan-12-2014/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-01-12T23:30:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Chris Krycho</name></author><id>tag:chriskrycho.com,2014-01-12:2014/scriptural-miscellanies-jan-12-2014/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;i class="editorial"&gt;Tonight, rather than doing a single, longer, extended piece, I am simply going to respond to a number of indidivual verses or passages, and more briefly than usual. Sleep is calling, but diligence in seeking God is a good I will not be quick to&amp;nbsp;overlook.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whoever loves discipline hates knowledge&lt;br /&gt;
but he who hates reproof is stupid. (Proverbs 12:1,&amp;nbsp;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;ESV&lt;/span&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It strikes me that this verse could serve as a heading for much of Proverbs, and unfortunately for much of many of our lives. It is easy to hate reproof, because it is easy to hate being wrong, because it is easy to be prideful and resistant to&amp;nbsp;correction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Deceit is in the heart of the wicked,&lt;br /&gt;
but those who plan peace have joy. (Proverbs 12:20,&amp;nbsp;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;ESV&lt;/span&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This verse&amp;#8212;and many like it throughout the Psalms&amp;#8212;makes it clear that the &lt;em&gt;many&lt;/em&gt; things may contrast with wickedness. Though wickedness has a relatively short list of characteristics in the Proverbs (murder and deception above all), the things contrasted with the behavior of the wicked is nearly infinite. The list includes wisdom, righteousness, peace, joy, and life, to name but a&amp;nbsp;few.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because the poor are plundered, because the needy groan,&lt;br /&gt;
&amp;#8220;I will now arise,&amp;#8221; says the &lt;span style="font-variant: small-caps"&gt;Lord&lt;/span&gt;;&lt;br /&gt;
&amp;#8220;I will place him in the saftey for which he&amp;nbsp;longs.&amp;#8221;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Though I do not buy into &amp;#8220;liberation theology&amp;#8221;, thinking as I do that its proponents tend to dramatically oversell their own case while ignoring entirely the Biblical witness toward the individual nature of redemption and the salvific work of Christ at Calvary, verses like this (and indeed: Psalms like this) remind us that the liberation position &lt;em&gt;does&lt;/em&gt; have something going for it. Namely, it takes seriously something that Scripture takes seriously: God&amp;#8217;s particular and especial concern for the poor and needy, not least those abused by people with more power than them. We would do well to integrate this thread more thoroughly into our evangelical conception of the world and our responsibilities thereto. We need not diminish our clear proclamation of the gospel nor mute our insistence on the centrality, supremacy, and sufficiency of Christ in order to set our hands to work diligently for the good of the poor and needy. We need not throw out penal substitutionary atonement to acknowledge that God &lt;em&gt;does&lt;/em&gt; show particular concern for the poor and&amp;nbsp;downtrodden.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="devotions"></category></entry><entry><title>Prayer of Thanksgiving</title><link href="http://chriskrycho.com/2014/prayer-thanksgiving-jan-12-2014/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-01-12T11:15:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Chris Krycho</name></author><id>tag:chriskrycho.com,2014-01-12:2014/prayer-thanksgiving-jan-12-2014/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Oh God&amp;#8212;our creator and father; our savior-king, lord, and friend; our helper, teacher, and comforter&amp;#8212;thank you for your unfailing love toward us. We marvel: you are the lord of light and of life, the maker of heaven and earth; you have set your glory above the heavens, and yet you are mindful of men and women like us. And not only mindful! You delight in us and love us in spite of our rebellion against you. You gave infinitely of yourself that we might be redeemed. Oh Lord, how majestic is your name in all the&amp;nbsp;earth!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As we have gathered here to worship, and as we bring you these gifts, we remember that everything we give to you is yours already. You do not &lt;em&gt;need&lt;/em&gt; anything of us; everything in all the world is yours already. All that we have we have from you&amp;#8212;not only our possessions, but even our lives&amp;#8212;so we pray that you be exalted in our giving, in our singing, and in the preached word. May we be those who in our giving gladly demonstrate that you are more precious to us than the things of this world. May Christ be exalted in our own hearts, in the work of this congregation, in the lives of the members of this church, in the community around us, and in the efforts of missionaries around the world as we give. Thank you so much for your steadfast love toward&amp;nbsp;us!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We pray all these things in the name of Jesus Christ our risen Lord.&amp;nbsp;Amen.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="prayers"></category></entry><entry><title>Saul and David/Righteousness and Folly</title><link href="http://chriskrycho.com/2014/saul-david-righteousness-folly/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-01-11T20:50:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Chris Krycho</name></author><id>tag:chriskrycho.com,2014-01-11:2014/saul-david-righteousness-folly/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The books of Chronicles serve as something of a parallel and supplementary account to the books of 1 and 2 Samuel and 1 and 2 Kings.&lt;sup id="fnref:kings"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:kings" rel="footnote"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; There are a few significant differences between the books, though. First, Samuel and Kings take considerable time to trace out Saul&amp;#8217;s history and then divided their attention fairly evenly between Judah and Israel, with a slight emphasis on Israel because of Elijah and Elisha&amp;#8217;s ministries there. The Chronicles skip almost entirely over Saul and focus predominantly on the Davidic line in&amp;nbsp;Judah.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Second, Samuel and Kings generally let events speak for themselves, with little commentary. Yahweh is always in control, but the author rarely provides explicit theological interpretation of the events recorded. The Chronicles, rather strikingly, &lt;em&gt;often&lt;/em&gt; make straightforward claims about divine action and provide moral commentary on the events they record. After its long list of &lt;a href="/theology/grappling-with-genealogies.html"&gt;genealogies&lt;/a&gt;, 1 Chronicles turns to a narrative of the history of the Hebrews in the kingdom era, picking up with Saul&amp;#8217;s death&amp;#8212;and immediately offers a theological interpretation of the events (2 Samuel and 1 Kings simply report the events and a few people&amp;#8217;s&amp;nbsp;responses):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So Saul died for his breach of faith. he broke faith with the &lt;span style="font-variant: small-caps"&gt;Lord&lt;/span&gt; in that he did not keep the command of the &lt;span style="font-variant: small-caps"&gt;Lord&lt;/span&gt;, and also consulted a medium, seeking guidance. He did not seek guidance from the &lt;span style="font-variant: small-caps"&gt;Lord&lt;/span&gt;. Therefore the &lt;span style="font-variant: small-caps"&gt;Lord&lt;/span&gt; put him to death and turned the kingdom over to David the son of Jesse. (1 Chronicles 10:13&amp;#8211;14,&amp;nbsp;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;ESV&lt;/span&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No ambiguity, no reason to misunderstand what happened. Kings made it clear by literary structure. The Chronicles just come out and say it: Yahweh took the kingdom away from Saul because he was unfaithful to him, and he gave it to a man who&amp;#8212;whatever his faults, and they were indeed many&amp;#8212;would follow&amp;nbsp;Yahweh.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Psalm 11, David evinces the very trust in Yahweh Saul lacked. He proclaims his confidence that Yahweh will save him. To the warning that &amp;#8220;the wicked bend the bow; / they have fitted their arrow to the string / to shoot in the dark at the upright in heart&amp;#8221; (Psalm 11:2, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;ESV&lt;/span&gt;), David has a simple reply: &amp;#8220;The &lt;span style="font-variant: small-caps"&gt;Lord&lt;/span&gt; is in his holy temple; / the &lt;span style="font-variant: small-caps"&gt;Lord&lt;/span&gt;&amp;#8216;s throne is in heaven; his eyes see, his eyelids test the children of man&amp;#8221; (Psalm 11:4, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;ESV&lt;/span&gt;). David&amp;#8217;s confidence was not in his own strength. His hope was not in being free and clear of anyone who would oppose him, but in the one whose throne is in heaven. Saul spent his days troubled and afraid because he was never secure in&amp;nbsp;Yahweh.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Proverbs 11:28 (&lt;span class="caps"&gt;ESV&lt;/span&gt;)&amp;nbsp;comments:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whoever trusts in his riches will fall,&lt;br /&gt;
but the righteous will flourish like a green&amp;nbsp;leaf.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The whole chapter resounds with the contrast between trust in riches or power or mortal plans and righteousness. Righteousness, it seems, is in trusting and obeying Yahweh. There is no righteousness that trusts in one&amp;#8217;s own strength. There is only the righteousness &amp;#8220;which comes through faith in Christ, the righteousness from God that depends on faith&amp;#8221; (Philippians 3:9, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;ESV&lt;/span&gt;). I am reminded tonight not to trust in my own abilities, nor in the provision God has given us,&lt;sup id="fnref:provision"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:provision" rel="footnote"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; but in God&amp;nbsp;himself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:kings"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Originally these four books were a single book, just as 1 and 2 Chronicles were a single book; it is rather unfortunate the modern divisions obscure this.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:kings" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:provision"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What folly to put our trust in the material things we have, when they are not ours save by the generous gift of God!&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:provision" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 2 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary><category term="devotions"></category></entry><entry><title>Grappling With Genealogies</title><link href="http://chriskrycho.com/2014/grappling-with-genealogies/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-01-10T22:17:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Chris Krycho</name></author><id>tag:chriskrycho.com,2014-01-10:2014/grappling-with-genealogies/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;i class="editorial"&gt;A brief note ahead of the rest of the post: this month, &lt;a href="http://christianaudio.com"&gt;ChristianAudio.com&lt;/a&gt; is giving away the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;ESV&lt;/span&gt; &amp;#8220;Hear the Word&amp;#8221; Audio Bible. Really, &lt;a href="http://christianaudio.com/free"&gt;for free&lt;/a&gt;. You give them an email address, you get the whole Bible, read &lt;em&gt;extremely&lt;/em&gt; well. I highly recommend that you follow up on this, because it is normally not inexpensive, though even so a good audio Bible is a very good investment. Now, back to the regularly scheduled&amp;nbsp;post.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As &lt;a href="/2014/temple-for-god/"&gt;challenging&lt;/a&gt; as it can be to apply 2 Chronicles 1&amp;#8212;5 correctly, finding the substance in a passage like 1 Chronicles 1&amp;#8212;5 is even harder, I think. The entire sequence is a list of names: fathers, sons, occasional wives and daughters in the mix. Genealogies are one of the most challenging sections in the Bible for Western readers, because they seem enormously dry and pointless. (I saw a non-Christian comment on finding the Bible incredibly boring the other day; I have no doubt that passaages like this one contributed substantially to that assessment.) Truth be told, though I am making a game effort at it, I still find these chapters difficult, too.&lt;sup id="fnref:sped-up"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:sped-up" rel="footnote"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are two things I hold onto as I consider these challenging chapters, though. The first is Paul&amp;#8217;s affirmation that &amp;#8220;All Scripture is breathed out by God and profitable for teaching, for reproof, for correction, and for training in righteousness, that the man of God may be complete, equipped for every good work&amp;#8221; (2 Timothy 3:16&amp;#8212;17, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;ESV&lt;/span&gt;). That &amp;#8220;all&amp;#8221; is important, because Paul included 1 Chronicles 1&amp;#8212;5 and Numbers 1 and Zechariah 4, challenging though they are in their different ways. He did not exclude them because they might not make as much sense to a future generation in another part of the world. Indeed, I would go so far as to say that under the inspiration of the Holy Spirit, Paul explicitly affirmed the value of these books in part &lt;em&gt;because&lt;/em&gt; they would be foreign to&amp;nbsp;us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Too often, we privilege our own cultural views as inherently correct in some way. We assume that because genealogies do not matter &lt;em&gt;to us&lt;/em&gt;, they do not matter &lt;em&gt;at all&lt;/em&gt;. Few of us, it is true, would be so bold as to say this out loud, but deep down, that is what we really believe. (For what we really believe to be true is what drives our actions.) The presence of these lengthy genealogies in the very word of God stands as a clear rebuke to our cultural snobbery&amp;#8211;and to our chronological snobbery, too. These genealogies remind us that we are not the first people in God&amp;#8217;s story, and that we will not be the last. We are not the main characters in this narrative: even of those named in these chapters, how many are familiar to us now?&lt;sup id="fnref:learned"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:learned" rel="footnote"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; How many men and women, faithful followers of God, simply go unnamed in these passages? Likewise, who will know our names a thousand years hence, should the Lord&amp;nbsp;tarry?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This genealogy stands as a rebuke to our self-adulation and our emphasis on our own value. It stands as a record of God&amp;#8217;s dealings with people who went long before us, and thus as a testament to the historical character of God&amp;#8217;s salvific work. It functions as a reminder that God&amp;#8217;s plan involves many a flawed hero, and not a few villains. It points us back to the need for a king who would &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; fit the pattern of all the kings named in this line. It highlights God&amp;#8217;s faithfulness to keep his promises to Abraham and Isaac and Jacob, and to David, even in the face of Israel&amp;#8217;s and Judah&amp;#8217;s rebellious ways. It ultimately points us to God himself, the one constant in all these names and relationships. He oversaw their history, as he oversees ours. We ought to reflect more often on those who have gone before us in the faith, and to thank God for them and for his work in history. We ought to be ever more dedicated to worshiping the God in whose hands history flows like a&amp;nbsp;watercourse.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:sped-up"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Confession time: I put the &lt;a href="http://christianaudio.com/free"&gt;audio&lt;/a&gt; in 2&amp;times; mode while I was listening to the latter parts of this section. It helped.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:sped-up" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:learned"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even having read through these chapters a number of times, it had escaped me until tonight that David&amp;#8217;s generals, Joab, Asahel, and Abishai, were his nephews&amp;#8211;the sons of his sister Zeruiah (see 1 Chronicles 2:16). This detail sheds interesting light on many of their interactions, especially on David&amp;#8217;s reticence to remove them from authority even when they were unruly. Yet it had previously been lost on me entirely.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:learned" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 2 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary><category term="devotions"></category></entry><entry><title>A Temple for God</title><link href="http://chriskrycho.com/2014/temple-for-god/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-01-09T07:45:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Chris Krycho</name></author><id>tag:chriskrycho.com,2014-01-09:2014/temple-for-god/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;i class=editorial&gt;Note: today&amp;#8217;s comments are a bit out of order on the sequence I&amp;#8217;ve been reading. I accidentally started &lt;em&gt;Second&lt;/em&gt; Chronicles rather than &lt;em&gt;First&lt;/em&gt;. I&amp;#8217;ll go back and start with First Chronicles&amp;nbsp;tomorrow.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At first blush, the first five chapters of 1 Chronicles do not seem to be particularly scintillating material on the whole. Solomon&amp;#8217;s request for wisdom, and God&amp;#8217;s answer, are notable, but otherwise the entire section is taken up by details of the construction of the temple. It is at points like this that read-the-Bible-in-a-year plans tend to get bogged down, and it is because of points like this that most read-the-Bible-in-a-year plans include readings from the New Testament as well as the Old. We struggle&amp;#8211;or at least, &lt;em&gt;I&lt;/em&gt; have historically struggled&amp;#8211;to make much of these passages. Why does it matter that there were &amp;#8220;four hundred pomegranates for the two latticeworks, two rows of pomegranates for each latticework, to cover the bowls of the capitals that were on top of the&amp;nbsp;pillars&amp;#8221;?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I read the parallel passage in 1 Kings a little while back, it struck me that what we have there&amp;#8212;and thus, also what we have here&amp;#8212;is enough information to get a sense of the beauty and majesty of this building. The enormous quantitites of precious metals that went into its construction, the attention paid to such fine details of every single aspect of the building and its adornments, the specially chosen timber brought in from a neighboring land: they all show us that this temple was&amp;nbsp;magnificent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are not a temple-building people, and our monuments tend to be austere and formal. Think of the Lincoln or Washington memorials in Washington, D. C.: they are not exactly &lt;em&gt;lively&lt;/em&gt; places. Though celebratory and laudatory, they seek to impress rather than to delight, focusing on clean, simple lines and shapes with little ornamentation. The Solomonic temple, and before it the tabernacle, were &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; like that. They were full of color and decoration, even as they were built at striking physical scales. They were designed to engage every sense, sight and smell especially. They were &lt;em&gt;beautiful&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So: beautiful the temple may have been. We are still left asking why the beauty of a temple built in ancient Jerusalem almost three millennia ago matters to Christians today. The answer, I think, lies in two passages in the New Testament.&amp;nbsp;First:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So then you are no longer strangers and aliens, but you are fellow citizens with the saints and members of the household of God, built on the foundation of the apostles and prophets, Christ Jesus himself being the cornerstone, in whom the whole structure, being joined together, grows into a holy temple in the Lord. In him you also are being built together into a dwelling place for God by the Spirit. (Ephesians 2:19-22,&amp;nbsp;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;ESV&lt;/span&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And&amp;nbsp;again:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then I saw a new heaven and a new earth, for the first heaven and the first earth had passed away, and the sea was no more. And I saw the holy city, new Jerusalem, coming down out of heaven from God, prepared as a bride adorned for her husband. And I heard a loud voice from the throne saying, &amp;#8220;Behold, the dwelling place of God is with man. He will dwell with them, and they will be his people, and God himself will be with them as their God. He will wipe away every tear from their eyes, and death shall be no more, neither shall there be mourning, nor crying, nor pain anymore, for the former things have passed&amp;nbsp;away.&amp;#8221;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And he who was seated on the throne said, &amp;#8220;Behold, I am making all things&amp;nbsp;new&amp;#8230;.&amp;#8221;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And I saw no temple in the city, for its temple is the Lord God the Almighty and the Lamb. And the city has no need of sun or moon to shine on it, for the glory of God gives it light, and its lamp is the Lamb. (Revelation 20:1&amp;#8212;5,&amp;nbsp;22&amp;#8212;23)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Do you see? As magnificent and beautiful as that old temple was, it has been supplanted. The &lt;em&gt;church&lt;/em&gt; is the temple, a dwelling place for God that is yet more beautiful. People are more stunning than the loveliest stones. And there will come a day when the dwelling place of God is with man, not only in spirit but in physical, at th econsummation of all things. That temple, filled as it was with the awesome presence of God, was but the tiniest taste of &lt;em&gt;this&lt;/em&gt; age, when God indwells every believer. And this age is but the tiniest taste of &lt;em&gt;that&lt;/em&gt; age, when the Lord God the Almighty and the Lamb come down from heaven and make their dwelling place with&amp;nbsp;man.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hallelujah. Our Lord,&amp;nbsp;come!&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="devotions"></category></entry><entry><title>Out of the Mouths of Poets</title><link href="http://chriskrycho.com/2014/mouths-of-poets/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-01-08T22:37:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Chris Krycho</name></author><id>tag:chriskrycho.com,2014-01-08:2014/mouths-of-poets/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Sometimes, the core idea of a passage&amp;#8211;especially when in poetic forms like in the Psalms&amp;#8211;cannot be understood apart from the structure of the passage itself. Tonight I was reading Psalm 8, and thinking about the aims of reading the Bible. Specifically, my aim is to know God and worship him more as I read Scripture. Thus, my goal is that each time I read through a section I would come away both more aware of who God is and more set in both my will and my affections&lt;sup id="fnref:affections"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:affections" rel="footnote"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; to honor&amp;nbsp;him.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I read Psalm 8, I was wondering, &amp;#8220;Okay, how does this lead me to worship?&amp;#8221; Echoing the psalm is a good start, of course, as it opens and&amp;nbsp;closes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Oh Yahweh, our Lord,&lt;br /&gt;
how majestic is your name in all the&amp;nbsp;earth!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the rest of the psalm is a meditation not only on Yahweh&amp;#8217;s majesty, but on the people he made. This is an interesting turn, and it caught me off guard as I started thinking more carefully about it. The key, I soon realized, is in the fact that this is a Psalm, not a letter or a sermon or a treatise. David felt free to get at his point sideways, as it were, and as is the fashion of&amp;nbsp;poetry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The whole poem turns back and forth between the God who made the heavens, who set his glory above them, and the people he made. The contrast is striking, and the more so because of the wonderful turns of&amp;nbsp;phrase.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I look at your heavens, the work of your fingers,&lt;br /&gt;
the moon and the stars, which you have set in place,&lt;br /&gt;
what is man that you are mindful of him,&lt;br /&gt;
and the son of man that you care for&amp;nbsp;him?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, I can sum up the point David is making here. One could say simply, &amp;#8220;Humans are small compared to the universe, so it is surprising that God would pay attention to them.&amp;#8221;  But to do so without further reflection is to miss some of the beauty of what David does in the &lt;em&gt;poetry&lt;/em&gt;, and therefore to miss the force of the passage. It is to miss an opportunity to have my emotions interact with this truth, and not only my mind. We have all felt the awe of staring at a night sky full of lights, a billion miles away and burning brighter than our own sun so that we can see them here across the aeons. We have all felt small against that&amp;nbsp;vastness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And if we stop for a moment and feel that here with David, and then are caught by the sudden turn&amp;#8212;&amp;#8221;what is man?&amp;#8221;&amp;#8212;we can feel with him the wonder that the God who set his glory above the heavens is the God who gave man dominion over creation. We can feel with him the surprise that God would not only establish his strength before the nations and before those who rebel against him, but that he would do it through babies and infants. We can feel with him the greatness of a God who is not limited by our feeble strength and our mortality, whose majesty goes beyond the tinyness of humanity and yet is somehow the greater for the ways he uses us, little beings that we&amp;nbsp;are.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How majestic is the name of Yahweh in all the earth,&amp;nbsp;indeed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:affections"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My desires, ambitions, emotions&amp;#8211;all the pieces of me that include but are not limited to my thoughts and feelings, and which are distinct from though closely interacting with my will&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:affections" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary><category term="devotions"></category></entry><entry><title>A Study in Contrasts: 2 Kings 16–20</title><link href="http://chriskrycho.com/2014/study-in-contrasts-2-kings-16-20/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-01-07T23:40:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Chris Krycho</name></author><id>tag:chriskrycho.com,2014-01-07:2014/study-in-contrasts-2-kings-16-20/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;One of the recurring themes of the books of Kings (1 and 2 Samuel, 1 and 2 Kings) is the distinction between those who &amp;#8220;did what was right in the eyes of Yahweh&amp;#8221; and those who &amp;#8220;did what was evil in the sight of Yahweh&amp;#8221;, e.g. 15:34, 17:2 respectively&amp;#8211;to name just two of the &lt;em&gt;many&lt;/em&gt; passages echoing this refrain in these books. Whereas 1 and 2 Samuel zoomed in on the contrast between Saul and David, 1 and 2 Kings take nearly all their successors at a very high level, often sparing them few more words than necessary to note their parentage, whether they did what was right or what was evil in the eyes of Yahweh, and a reference to other records of their&amp;nbsp;deeds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the dominant themes of these books, then, is that doing what is right in Yahweh&amp;#8217;s eyes has an enormous reward, while doing what is evil in his eyes eventually brings a great judgment. 2 Kings 17&amp;#8212;19 brings this message home, and hard. Centuries of rebellion on Israel&amp;#8217;s part culminated in the Assyrian capture of Samaria and the forcible exile of the Jews of Israel from their homeland. The author pauses from his otherwise quick-moving narrative to explain this point in detail for the better part of a chapter. Israel&amp;#8217;s fall was not the mere ordinary turn of regional political events it might have seemed. It was, instead, God&amp;#8217;s final judgment on a people who had continuously rebelled against him generation after generation, worshiping in a way they &lt;em&gt;knew&lt;/em&gt; was abhorrent to&amp;nbsp;him.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By contrast, when the same mighty king with his mighty army came to take Jerusalem, the city stood. Judah had its share of wicked kings, to be sure&amp;#8211;but unlike Israel, it also had many kings who &amp;#8220;did what was right in the eyes of Yahweh&amp;#8221; and in particular it had Hezekiah, who &amp;#8220;trusted in Yahweh, the God of Israel, so that there was none like him among all the kings of Judah after him, nor among those who were before him&amp;#8221;&amp;nbsp;(18:5).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The armies of the greatest power in the region&amp;#8211;unstoppable Assyria&amp;#8211;surrounded the capital city en masse. Their leaders boasted in their victories, tried to bully Hezekiah and the people into surrendering without a fight, and insulted the name of Yahweh. Attacking the people of God is always a bad idea; attacking him directly is an even &lt;em&gt;worse&lt;/em&gt; idea. The Scriptures are a long record of the lengths to which God will go to defend his name: he will quite literally die to defend the glorious reality that he is most righteous and most powerful being there is, most worthy of worship. When Sennacherib boasted, &amp;#8220;Who among all the gods of the lands have delivered their lands out of my hand, that Yahweh should deliver Jerusalem out of my hand?&amp;#8221; (18:35), he missed something. Hezekiah points it out in his prayer: &amp;#8220;[They] were not gods, but the work of men&amp;#8217;s hands, wood and stone. Therefore they were destroyed. So now, O Yahweh our God, save us, please, from his hand, that all the kingdoms of the earth may know that you, O Yahweh, are God alone&amp;#8221;&amp;nbsp;(19:18b&amp;#8212;29).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;God has &lt;em&gt;always&lt;/em&gt; been about the business of making his name known to the ends of the earth. Not because he is a braggart, but because he is the end for which all things exist&amp;#8211;the end for which &lt;em&gt;we&lt;/em&gt; exist. In setting ourselves against that, we are setting ourselves against reality. We are trying to fly by pushing away from the ground with the hairs on our head&amp;#8211;and for some reason, gravity comes out victorious. So when God brings judgment on blasphemers, that is a &lt;em&gt;mercy&lt;/em&gt; to the nations who have a chance to repent and kneel before the king of&amp;nbsp;all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What is amazing to me is just how profoundly longsuffering God is. Were I so often insulted, ignored, and injuriously assaulted in character, I would not wait hundreds of years, sending prophet after prophet to give people opportunity after opportunity to respond. I sometimes have a hard time restraining my impatience for a few minutes with my wife or my child. And yet the God who ultimately struck down 185,000 Assyrians waited generation upon generation to bring his judgment on Israel&amp;#8211;and he likewise gave the Assyrians the opportunity to repent (c.f. Jonah). This God is shockingly merciful, even as he brings&amp;nbsp;judgment.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="devotions"></category></entry><entry><title>Five Things Proverbs 6 Teaches</title><link href="http://chriskrycho.com/2014/five-things-proverbs-six/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-01-06T20:30:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Chris Krycho</name></author><id>tag:chriskrycho.com,2014-01-06:2014/five-things-proverbs-six/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Proverbs 6 makes 5 points, rather distinctly and sharply. First a summary and then a few thoughts on&amp;nbsp;each.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Verses 1&amp;#8211;5:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;Being security for your neighbor&amp;#8212;still less for a stranger&amp;#8212;is a bad&amp;nbsp;idea.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This first point is perhaps the least obviously applicable to me today. I don&amp;#8217;t make a habit of pledging money or possessions for a friend&amp;#8217;s (still less a stranger&amp;#8217;s) poor money decisions. I might &lt;em&gt;give&lt;/em&gt; a friend (or even a stranger) money, but I can&amp;#8217;t imagine putting myself in the position of guaranteeing a loan for someone else. That just seems like a terrible idea. Of course, that&amp;#8217;s the point of these verses: it &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; a terrible idea. The counsel here is to get out of that kind of situation as fast as possible (and, by implication, to avoid getting into such a situation in the first&amp;nbsp;place).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Verses 6&amp;#8211;11:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;Laziness will prove ruinous. Industriousness will produce good&amp;nbsp;results.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have seen this proven true time and again in the lives of those around me. As a general rule, people who work hard do well for themselves, and people who are lazy do very poorly for themselves. As a rule, I say, because there are times when this is not true&amp;#8212;there really are times when systemic injustices undermine even people&amp;#8217;s best efforts. This proverb is a proverb, not an iron-clad guarantee, and we would all do well to remember as much. That said: we would &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; do well to remember as much: if the political conservative&amp;#8217;s typical response is to simply point to this verse as a promise (which it is not), the political liberal&amp;#8217;s typical response is to act as though this verse has no bearing whatsoever. Sometimes, poverty has complex, structural, societal roots&amp;#8212;but sometimes, people are just lazy. God calls us &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; to be lazy; work is a good thing that was instituted before the&amp;nbsp;Fall.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Verses 12&amp;#8211;15:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;The ultimate fate of a wicked person is&amp;nbsp;calamity.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is nothing terribly complicated here. There is, however, a great deal of hope here for those of us who have watched wicked people go around behaving wickedly and seemingly coming off no worse for wear every time. There will come a day of recompense for every wicked deed. Lord willing, for some of those people, that day came when Christ came, and they will join us in the company of saints as they abandon their wickedness and turn to God. But for those who don&amp;#8217;t, justice will come, and it will come&amp;nbsp;swiftly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Verses 16&amp;#8211;19:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;There are some things God truly&amp;nbsp;hates.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is almost &lt;em&gt;passe&lt;/em&gt; to note how distasteful this idea is in our culture today, but the words on the page could not be clearer. There are things that Yahweh hates, things that are an abomination to him. He hates pride. He abominates deceit. He hates the shedding of innocent blood. He abominates the plotting of wickedness. He hates the doing of evil. He abominates false witness to be borne. He hates dissension between&amp;nbsp;brothers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But more than this: he hates those who &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt; these things. This is dreadful&amp;#8212;apart from the grace he shows us in&amp;nbsp;Christ.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Verses 20&amp;#8211;35:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;Adultery is folly. Wisdom runs the other&amp;nbsp;way.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="/2014/01/folly-of-sin"&gt;Once again&lt;/a&gt;, the proverbs hammer home the folly of adultery. It is not only that it does not give what it promises and brings spiritual ruin. It is that it also produces, at a purely practical level, destruction. A spouse&amp;#8217;s jealousy is (rightly) a fearful thing. Who in his right mind would sleep with another man&amp;#8217;s wife, knowing what the response would be? What woman would sleep with another woman&amp;#8217;s husband, knowing how her own rage would be? The implications just for one&amp;#8217;s own health&amp;#8212;still less any other part of one&amp;#8217;s life&amp;#8212;ought to be enough to warn us&amp;nbsp;away.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Proverbs remind me again and again that God cares about my life at every level. He is not distant or unengaged with these details; he cares about every aspect of human flourishing, and takes pains to make clear to us what that flourishing looks like&amp;#8212;and what it&amp;nbsp;doesn&amp;#8217;t.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="devotions"></category></entry><entry><title>The Folly of Sin</title><link href="http://chriskrycho.com/2014/folly-of-sin/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-01-05T23:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Chris Krycho</name></author><id>tag:chriskrycho.com,2014-01-05:2014/folly-of-sin/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Adultery. It has torn countless families and destroyed innumerable ministries over the years. Over and over again, the refrain is the same: &amp;#8220;I never thought it would happen to me!&amp;#8221; and &amp;#8220;I never meant for it to go this far!&amp;#8221;&lt;sup id="fnref:adultery-1"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:adultery-1" rel="footnote"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Given the evidence of the years, though, no one should ever cavalierly say, &amp;#8220;I&amp;#8217;ll never do that.&amp;#8221; Say it, yes. But back it up by making concrete choices every day not to break vows to your&amp;nbsp;spouse.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Proverbs 5 couldn&amp;#8217;t be clearer: adultery &lt;em&gt;looks&lt;/em&gt; good from the outside and feels good at the&amp;nbsp;outset:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;For the lips of a forbidden woman drip honey,
    and her speech is smoother than oil,
but in the end she is bitter as wormwood,
    sharp as a two-edged sword.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No one commits adultery because it looks so dreadful. People commit this sin&amp;#8212;like every other&amp;#8212;because it looks good. The trick, of course, is that it is &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt;. The Proverb highlights the contradiction of sin powerfully: sin looks sweet, but proves bitter. It seems smooth, but only proves smoothly destructive as it slices away at everything you value. Sin always produces the opposite of what it promises. Adultery promises intimacy, but adultery &lt;em&gt;destroys&lt;/em&gt; intimacy. Drugs promise liberated minds; instead they produce addiction. Covetousness promises satisfaction; instead it produces only an ever-gnawing emptiness. Sin is like a sweet-tasting infection that rots us from the inside&amp;nbsp;out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But it is more than that. Sin is not bad only because it proves so ruinous to us&amp;#8212;though certainly it is bad for that reason. Sin is bad because it is high treason, because it is at its core a rejection of the good, the true, the beautiful in that it is a rejection of God in the exaltation of self. Sin is ruinous to us in part because it is the undoing of everything of what we are: beings made to worship the Triune God, instead kneeling to our own reflection in the mirror instead of the one we were meant to&amp;nbsp;reflect.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But God is a righteous judge. He is holy. He does not tolerate sin. Psalm 5 puts it in sharp&amp;nbsp;relief:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;For you are not a God who delights in wickedness;
    evil may not dwell with you.
The boastful shall not stand before your eyes;
    you hate all evildoers.
You destroy those who speak lies;
    Yahweh abhors the bloodthirsty and deceitful man.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;God detests sin.&lt;sup id="fnref:sin-sermon"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:sin-sermon" rel="footnote"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Not just the hot-button sin issues of our day (though those are not excluded), but our pettiness and jealousy, our deceptions great and small, our boasting and pride. We are &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; evildoers. And yet, wonder of wonders, we live still. Though God who made us and at whom we have all shaken our fists in rebellion would be perfectly within his rights to end us without a thought; he does not. He shows mercy. He forbears long. He waits to bring&amp;nbsp;judgment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He provides a way of escape. We, like David, can enter his house &amp;#8220;through the abundance of [his] steadfast love.&amp;#8221; That steadfast love, that covenant love, that almight love, has reached down and partaken of frail humanity and death and even of divine wrath, so that God might be glorified in his holiness. We are saved not because God is sentimental or sappy, but because he is righteous, and has already paid the price for our&amp;nbsp;sins.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hallelujah.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:adultery-1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And yes, sometimes also (even more sadly), &amp;#8220;I don&amp;#8217;t care; why shouldn&amp;#8217;t I be happy?&amp;#8221;&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:adultery-1" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:sin-sermon"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For more on all of this, I commend to you the &lt;a href="http://www.sermonaudio.com/sermoninfo.asp?sermonID=15141146471"&gt;sermon&lt;/a&gt; our primary preaching pastor delivered today.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:sin-sermon" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 2 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary><category term="devotions"></category></entry><entry><title>Elijah and Elisha</title><link href="http://chriskrycho.com/2014/elijah-elisha/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-01-04T23:45:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Chris Krycho</name></author><id>tag:chriskrycho.com,2014-01-04:2014/elijah-elisha/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;One cannot help but notice, reading through 1 and 2 Kings, how much Elijah and Elisha echo Moses and foreshadow the Messiah. They perform miracles that show up the limitations of other so-called deities, part the Jordan, make clean what was impure, give miraculous children, raise the dead, multiply food for a meal for the hungry.&lt;sup id="fnref:bears"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:bears" rel="footnote"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; These men were prophets like Moses, but Israel knew that they were not &lt;em&gt;the&lt;/em&gt; prophet like Moses that the first savior of Israel had&amp;nbsp;promised.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reading through these books, it is interesting that Israel was eagerly awaiting another prophet like Elijah when Jesus came. Indeed, it is interesting that a later prophet would speak of Elijah coming again. Reading through this material&amp;#8212;which was originally all a single book covering all of 1 Samuel through 2 Kings&amp;#8212;one would not necessarily be inclined to call Elijah the greater of the pair. Indeed, Elisha both asked for and apparently received a double portion of the miraculous gift that Yahweh had given to Elijah. The text records far more miracles performed by Elisha than by Elijah. (Indeed, most of that list above belongs to Elisha and not to&amp;nbsp;Elijah.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Clearly, though, there was something special about&amp;nbsp;Elijah.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think it was his passion for the name of Yahweh, and I think the text makes this abundantly clear. It is not that Elisha was &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; passionate for the glory of Yahweh; it is that this is the main (and nearly the only) thing in view in Elijah&amp;#8217;s ministry. Elijah&amp;#8217;s responsibility was to point the people to repentance for their sins and to show up false religion for what it was. This he did. He stood for the name of Yahweh under the threat of death and all alone. Other faithful Yahweh-worshippers though there were in Israel at the time, it was Elijah alone on the mountain confronting the four hundred priests of Baal, and he alone who saw the mighty hand of Yahweh raised in triumph against Baalism. He, like John the Baptizer, was the lone voice in the wilderness, calling the people of Israel back to&amp;nbsp;God.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Elisha&amp;#8217;s role was different: he was the man of miracles and the fierce judge. He did the greatest miracles recorded in the Bible prior to the coming of the Messiah; only in Jesus himself was there a greater provider, healer, or resurrector. He pointed to the greatness of Yahweh through these miracles; unlike Elijah, he did so in a time when many others worshipped Yahweh. He stood on Elijah&amp;#8217;s shoulders, as it&amp;nbsp;were.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have often pondered over the last year or so that often it is the case that younger leaders can seem (and perhaps are) more effective than their elders&amp;#8212;but that even when this is so, there is a foundation present &lt;em&gt;because&lt;/em&gt; of the elders that is too easily overlooked. Many young men&amp;#8217;s pastoral ministries are successful not only because of their own faithfulness, but because of the work of the pastors who preceded them. Many young men can be more doctrinally sound than or more effective preachers than their predecessors &lt;em&gt;because&lt;/em&gt; of their predecessors. Elisha did his miracles in a land that had already seen Baalism humbled under fire from Yahweh. I do my writing, ministry (such as it is), and even thinking in the context set for me by faithful Christians who have gone before, women and men who have diligently sought Christ and laid a foundation on which I might&amp;nbsp;build.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:bears"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To say nothing of cursing mockers to be attacked by bears, in one of the stranger passages in the old Testament.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:bears" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary><category term="devotions"></category></entry><entry><title>Finding God in Proverbs</title><link href="http://chriskrycho.com/2014/finding-god-proverbs/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-01-03T23:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Chris Krycho</name></author><id>tag:chriskrycho.com,2014-01-03:2014/finding-god-proverbs/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;One of the most helpful patterns I have developed in the last few years of Scripture reading is asking one simple question as I read: &lt;em&gt;What does this passage reveal about God?&lt;/em&gt; There are many other questions&amp;#8212;good, important questions&amp;#8212;to ask of the text. But this one, I find, yields the most fruit. The Bible is not just a book of moral teachings, nor a mere practical guide for our lives. It is the revelation of the living God to his people.&lt;sup id="fnref:1"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:1" rel="footnote"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So what do we do when we get to, say, Proverbs? At first blush, the question seems a good deal less tractable here than in many other places. However hairy, most narratives &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt; show us the character of God. Propositional content, whether in letters or sermons or parables or prophecies, likewise tends to make clear, succinct statements about the person and nature of God. The Proverbs, though? Well, sometimes they do, and sometimes they say things like, &amp;#8220;Do not contend with a man for no reason, when he has done you no harm.&amp;#8221; That&amp;#8217;s helpful, to be sure, but when you first read it, it&amp;#8217;s not obvious how that gets us back to God. We could try to hammer the Proverbs into some framework for understanding God, try to reduce their presence in the canon to a role in some theme or another.&lt;sup id="fnref:2"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:2" rel="footnote"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; In the end, though, any such reductive effort is going to run aground on the shoals of misunderstanding&amp;#8212;quite the opposite of the intent of the&amp;nbsp;author.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Proverbs often show us God&amp;#8217;s character sideways. If we believe that the counsel offered by the Proverbs really is wise&amp;#8212;that the glowing promises here in Proverbs 3 of blessing, gain, and profit from wisdom are true, that there really is nothing better than to have understanding&amp;#8212;then we believe that they are insights into reality. And reality was made &lt;em&gt;by God&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;Yahweh by wisdom founded the earth;
    by understanding he established the heavens;
by his knowledge the deeps broke open,
    and the clouds drop down the dew.
(Proverbs 3:19--20)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If we then start asking good questions of the text we find very quickly that we do have a path back to the person and nature of God. For example: &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt; should we not contend with a man when he has done us no harm? Well, we ought not do so because it will certainly stir up trouble, and we know God does not delight in strife. Moreover, picking a fight with someone without cause is unjust, and this same author has told us that wisdom comports with justice and righteousness, and that &lt;em&gt;God&lt;/em&gt; is&amp;nbsp;just.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Taking a further step back, we can ask why this proverb is included in the inspired Scriptures. Then we see even more: God cares about the way people interact with one another. He values human flourishing, and so has provided enormous guidance for us in the form of hundreds upon hundreds of practical insights into the way the world is. He delights in people so greatly that he crosses the boundary between transcendence and immanence to give us his very&amp;nbsp;words.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It turns out there is an awful lot to learn about God in the Proverbs&amp;#8212;even the ones that do no mention&amp;nbsp;him.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That final phrase, &amp;#8220;to his people,&amp;#8221; is an important one for all hermeneutics; reading the Scriptures with faith makes a difference. &lt;a href="http://mereorthodoxy.com/"&gt;Matthew Lee Anderson&lt;/a&gt; makes this point helpfully and at some length in his excellent &lt;a href="http://www.amazon.com/End-Our-Exploring-Questioning-Confidence-ebook/dp/B00BUP1BQQ/?tag=krycho-20"&gt;&lt;em&gt;The End of Our Exploring&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:2"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is right here that many Biblical theologies&amp;#8212;that&amp;#8217;s a specific discipline in theology, though admittedly poorly named&amp;#8212;go amiss.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:2" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 2 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary><category term="devotions"></category></entry><entry><title>Kings in Contrast</title><link href="http://chriskrycho.com/2014/kings-contrast/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-01-02T21:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Chris Krycho</name></author><id>tag:chriskrycho.com,2014-01-02:2014/kings-contrast/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Tonight&amp;#8217;s reading in 1 Kings, Psalms, and Proverbs had some surprising overlaps. The material in 1 Kings covered a series of kings whose courses were largely &lt;em&gt;away&lt;/em&gt; from worshipping Yahweh and toward worshipping other gods. With only one exception, in fact, every single king listed in these five chapters rejected the God of Israel in favor of the gods of the nations which the Hebrews had driven out of Canaan. That exception, Asa, stands in sharp contrast to the litany of rebellious kings who preceded and followed him as being a man who followed God with his whole heart. Others, it seems, included Yahweh in their list of gods to worship, but never reverenced him as supreme and only. This list of wicked kings of both Israel and Judah climaxes with the appearance of Elijah, the righteous prophet who confronts the &lt;em&gt;most&lt;/em&gt; wicked king in the list, and who ultimately demonstrates Yahweh&amp;#8217;s superiority over the other gods the Hebrews&amp;nbsp;worshipped.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Proverbs 2 continues Solomon&amp;#8217;s exhortation to seek wisdom wholeheartedly, and his corresponding encouragement that Yahweh gives wisdom to those who seek it. But Solomon did not stop with the idea that knowledge and understanding are good&amp;#8212;though this he certainly affirms. Rather, he continued on to emphasize that God&amp;#8217;s knowledge and discernment go hand in hand with his integrity and justice. Those who seek this wisdom walk in righteousness and justice and equity. A person of wisdom is kept safe from both evildoers and from doing evil him- or herself. That Solomon&amp;#8217;s own line, beginning with his own son and continuing on down through every king but Asa in these chapters in 1 Kings, went so far astray indicates how little these words were&amp;nbsp;heeded.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The picture painted by Psalm 2 stands in impossibly sharp contrast to these depraved kings. The Anointed One of the psalm is a messianic figure: those who take refuge in him find shelter, but those who rebel against him are broken under his rule. There is a king in view here who laughs at the rebellion of the rulers of every nation (Israel included), who scorns the folly of plotting against the Most High God. The king that Yahweh calls his Son will receive those same nations as his inheritance. He will be the king above all other kings. He will be both wrathful against rebellion and merciful to those who &amp;#8220;take refuge in him&amp;#8221; (v.&amp;nbsp;11&amp;#8211;12).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So we have set before us the history of wicked men rebelling against the very God who gave them their thrones, and a call to that same line of the kings to humbly seek wisdom from that God, and a poetic picture of the true king against whom any rebellion is folly. And running through all of these are both the wrath of God against the folly and sin of those rebelling against him, and his mercy. Yahweh saves his people from following other gods in that magnificent confrontation on the mountain, Elijah on one side and the priests of Baal on the other. He is the source of wisdom, and the one who keeps his people from walking in folly or wickedness. And he is the righteous king who gives his people peace and security. Not because he does not do justice or cares little about sin, but precisely &lt;em&gt;because&lt;/em&gt; he does justice and cares about sin. That Anointed One, that Son of the Most High, is Jesus Christ, who died in order that everything would be put under his feet. Every wicked king in 1 Kings points to the need for Jesus. He is the fulfillment of the wisdom promised in Proverbs 2. He is the Anointed One, the Son of Yahweh, who reigns the nations in righteousness.&amp;nbsp;Hallelujah.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="devotions"></category></entry><entry><title>A New Year of Devotions</title><link href="http://chriskrycho.com/2014/new-year-devotions/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-01-01T23:25:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Chris Krycho</name></author><id>tag:chriskrycho.com,2014-01-01:2014/new-year-devotions/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I have found, over the years, that writing is a remarkably helpful tool for thinking through the things I am learning. I have also found that I am often better able to remain consistent in my study of Scripture if I am writing regularly about it. That could be in a journal, or on a blog, or just about anywhere. In 2014, I am going to experiment with posting this writing on my blog&amp;#8212;something I have done &lt;a href="http://2012-2013.chriskrycho.com/theology/topics/devotions/index.html"&gt;before&lt;/a&gt; to good effect for myself, and which a number of acquaintances seemed to like. After talking it through with my wonderful wife, I have set myself a limit of half an hour &lt;em&gt;total&lt;/em&gt; devoted to writing these posts. Hopefully it will prove&amp;nbsp;profitable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If it seems like 1 Kings 9&amp;#8211;13 is a funny place to start this sort of thing, that&amp;#8217;s because it is. But 1 Kings is where I am, and thus it is the place from which I will continue&amp;#8212;I do not see a good reason to start over at the beginning &lt;em&gt;again&lt;/em&gt; just a few months after having done so&amp;nbsp;before.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A number of points stuck out at me as I worked through this passage. First, and most important, is one of the recurring themes of the whole book: the question of obedience to Yahweh,&lt;sup id="fnref:yahweh"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:yahweh" rel="footnote"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; and the consequences of rejecting him. From the promise God offers Solomon  in chapter 9 through the death of a prophet in chapter 13, the issue is clear. Obedience to God brings everlasting favor, and disobedience brings&amp;nbsp;death.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is not exactly a new theme for the Bible as a whole: it shows up all the way back in Genesis 3. Nor does it stop here (nor even under the New Covenant with Christ): submission to God is characteristic of all who believe. Why? Not because God is some cruel dictator, but because he is both omniscient and omnibenevolent. He knows what is best for us. Defying his ways is like defying gravity: it might make for a &lt;a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=FlMBcTGJ4YM&amp;amp;name=DefyingGravity"&gt;catchy tune&lt;/a&gt;, but the net result is always crashing hard to the&amp;nbsp;ground.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So: Yahweh promised Solomon great things if he would simply follow him alone and not worship other gods. Solomon did exactly the opposite of what God had commanded the kings of Israel, though: he married multiple foreign women who themselves worshiped other gods,&lt;sup id="fnref:1"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:1" rel="footnote"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; and ultimately he built altars to and sacrificed to those other gods himself. We see the same thing in Jeroboam&amp;#8217;s life: God made him promises of really marvelous import, if he would simply walk with Yahweh. Instead, as soon as he became king he led the people &lt;em&gt;away&lt;/em&gt; from Yahweh, reasoning that Yahweh-worship was a threat to his own power, even though it was a prophet of Yahweh who had first told him all that would happen and that it was Yahweh who would do it. A righteous prophet ends up dead because he disobeyed God&amp;#8217;s clear&amp;nbsp;instructions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In short: God means business, and we ought to pay attention when he commands us in a certain area. Again, not because he is a tyrant, but because he loves us and he is righteous. When we defy him, we are simultaneously wronging ourselves and committing cosmic treason. It&amp;#8217;s a bad move, and he rightly responds in judgment. That, in turn, though, takes me back to his &lt;em&gt;decisive&lt;/em&gt; act of judgment: the one the Godhead executed on itself, in the sacrificial, atoning death of Christ on my behalf. My motivation for obedience, then, is not only fear, but joyful&amp;nbsp;gratitude.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#8217;s a good start to the&amp;nbsp;year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:yahweh"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I know it is a bit unusual to spell out the name of God used in the Old Testament like this, but it is my preference. I think it makes many passages much clearer to read Yahweh instead of &lt;span style="font-variant: small-caps"&gt;Lord&lt;/span&gt;, and it&amp;#8217;s simply what&amp;#8217;s there in the original (even if the Jews historically have chosen not to say it&amp;#8212;there&amp;#8217;s something interesting here, but I shall pass over it today).&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:yahweh" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note that the reason for the prohibition on marrying foreigners was always religious, not ethnic. Solomon&amp;#8217;s own lineage (and thus, Jesus&amp;#8217; too) includes several foreign women&amp;#8212;each of whom worshiped Yahweh.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 2 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary><category term="devotions"></category></entry></feed>