<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>chriskrycho.com</title><link href="http://chriskrycho.com/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://chriskrycho.com/feeds/theology.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://chriskrycho.com/</id><updated>2014-01-10T22:17:00-05:00</updated><entry><title>Grappling With Genealogies</title><link href="http://chriskrycho.com/2014/grappling-with-genealogies.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-01-10T22:17:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Chris Krycho</name></author><id>tag:chriskrycho.com,2014-01-10:2014/grappling-with-genealogies.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;!--Template: devotions--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i class="editorial"&gt;A brief note ahead of the rest of the post: this month, &lt;a href="http://christianaudio.com"&gt;ChristianAudio.com&lt;/a&gt; is giving away the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;ESV&lt;/span&gt; &amp;#8220;Hear the Word&amp;#8221; Audio Bible. Really, &lt;a href="http://christianaudio.com/free"&gt;for free&lt;/a&gt;. You give them an email address, you get the whole Bible, read &lt;em&gt;extremely&lt;/em&gt; well. I highly recommend that you follow up on this, because it is normally not inexpensive, though even so a good audio Bible is a very good investment. Now, back to the regularly scheduled&amp;nbsp;post.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As &lt;a href="/2014/temple-for-god/"&gt;challenging&lt;/a&gt; as it can be to apply 2 Chronicles 1&amp;#8211;5 correctly, finding the substance in a passage like 1 Chronicles 1&amp;#8211;5 is even harder, I think. The entire sequence is a list of names: fathers, sons, occasional wives and daughters in the mix. Genealogies are one of the most challenging sections in the Bible for Western readers, because they seem enormously dry and pointless. (I saw a non-Christian comment on finding the Bible incredibly boring the other day; I have no doubt that passaages like this one contributed substantially to that assessment.) Truth be told, though I am making a game effort at it, I still find these chapters difficult, too.&lt;sup id="fnref:sped-up"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:sped-up" rel="footnote"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are two things I hold onto as I consider these challenging chapters, though. The first is Paul&amp;#8217;s affirmation that &amp;#8220;All Scripture is breathed out by God and profitable for teaching, for reproof, for correction, and for training in righteousness, that the man of God may be complete, equipped for every good work&amp;#8221; (2 Timothy 3:16&amp;#8211;17, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;ESV&lt;/span&gt;). That &amp;#8220;all&amp;#8221; is important, because Paul included 1 Chronicles 1&amp;#8211;5 and Numbers 1 and Zechariah 4, challenging though they are in their different ways. He did not exclude them because they might not make as much sense to a future generation in another part of the world. Indeed, I would go so far as to say that under the inspiration of the Holy Spirit, Paul explicitly affirmed the value of these books in part &lt;em&gt;because&lt;/em&gt; they would be foreign to&amp;nbsp;us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Too often, we privilege our own cultural views as inherently correct in some way. We assume that because genealogies do not matter &lt;em&gt;to us&lt;/em&gt;, they do not matter &lt;em&gt;at all&lt;/em&gt;. Few of us, it is true, would be so bold as to say this out loud, but deep down, that is what we really believe. (For what we really believe to be true is what drives our actions.) The presence of these lengthy genealogies in the very word of God stands as a clear rebuke to our cultural snobbery&amp;#8212;and to our chronological snobbery, too. These genealogies remind us that we are not the first people in God&amp;#8217;s story, and that we will not be the last. We are not the main characters in this narrative: even of those named in these chapters, how many are familiar to us now?&lt;sup id="fnref:learned"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:learned" rel="footnote"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; How many men and women, faithful followers of God, simply go unnamed in these passages? Likewise, who will know our names a thousand years hence, should the Lord&amp;nbsp;tarry?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This genealogy stands as a rebuke to our self-adulation and our emphasis on our own value. It stands as a record of God&amp;#8217;s dealings with people who went long before us, and thus as a testament to the historical character of God&amp;#8217;s salvific work. It functions as a reminder that God&amp;#8217;s plan involves many a flawed hero, and not a few villains. It points us back to the need for a king who would &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; fit the pattern of all the kings named in this line. It highlights God&amp;#8217;s faithfulness to keep his promises to Abraham and Isaac and Jacob, and to David, even in the face of Israel&amp;#8217;s and Judah&amp;#8217;s rebellious ways. It ultimately points us to God himself, the one constant in all these names and relationships. He oversaw their history, as he oversees ours. We ought to reflect more often on those who have gone before us in the faith, and to thank God for them and for his work in history. We ought to be ever more dedicated to worshiping the God in whose hands history flows like a&amp;nbsp;watercourse.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:sped-up"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Confession time: I put the &lt;a href="http://christianaudio.com/free"&gt;audio&lt;/a&gt; in 2&amp;times; mode while I was listening to the latter parts of this section. It helped.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:sped-up" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:learned"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even having read through these chapters a number of times, it had escaped me until tonight that David&amp;#8217;s generals, Joab, Asahel, and Abishai, were his nephews&amp;#8212;the sons of his sister Zeruiah (see 1 Chronicles 2:16). This detail sheds interesting light on many of their interactions, especially on David&amp;#8217;s reticence to remove them from authority even when they were unruly. Yet it had previously been lost on me entirely.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:learned" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 2 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary><category term="devotions"></category></entry><entry><title>A Temple for God</title><link href="http://chriskrycho.com/2014/temple-for-god.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-01-09T07:45:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Chris Krycho</name></author><id>tag:chriskrycho.com,2014-01-09:2014/temple-for-god.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;!--Template: devotions--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i class=editorial&gt;Note: today&amp;#8217;s comments are a bit out of order on the sequence I&amp;#8217;ve been reading. I accidentally started &lt;em&gt;Second&lt;/em&gt; Chronicles rather than &lt;em&gt;First&lt;/em&gt;. I&amp;#8217;ll go back and start with First Chronicles&amp;nbsp;tomorrow.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At first blush, the first five chapters of 1 Chronicles do not seem to be particularly scintillating material on the whole. Solomon&amp;#8217;s request for wisdom, and God&amp;#8217;s answer, are notable, but otherwise the entire section is taken up by details of the construction of the temple. It is at points like this that read-the-Bible-in-a-year plans tend to get bogged down, and it is because of points like this that most read-the-Bible-in-a-year plans include readings from the New Testament as well as the Old. We struggle&amp;#8212;or at least, &lt;em&gt;I&lt;/em&gt; have historically struggled&amp;#8212;to make much of these passages. Why does it matter that there were &amp;#8220;four hundred pomegranates for the two latticeworks, two rows of pomegranates for each latticework, to cover the bowls of the capitals that were on top of the&amp;nbsp;pillars&amp;#8221;?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I read the parallel passage in 1 Kings a little while back, it struck me that what we have there&amp;#8211;and thus, also what we have here&amp;#8211;is enough information to get a sense of the beauty and majesty of this building. The enormous quantitites of precious metals that went into its construction, the attention paid to such fine details of every single aspect of the building and its adornments, the specially chosen timber brought in from a neighboring land: they all show us that this temple was&amp;nbsp;magnificent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are not a temple-building people, and our monuments tend to be austere and formal. Think of the Lincoln or Washington memorials in Washington, D. C.: they are not exactly &lt;em&gt;lively&lt;/em&gt; places. Though celebratory and laudatory, they seek to impress rather than to delight, focusing on clean, simple lines and shapes with little ornamentation. The Solomonic temple, and before it the tabernacle, were &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; like that. They were full of color and decoration, even as they were built at striking physical scales. They were designed to engage every sense, sight and smell especially. They were &lt;em&gt;beautiful&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So: beautiful the temple may have been. We are still left asking why the beauty of a temple built in ancient Jerusalem almost three millennia ago matters to Christians today. The answer, I think, lies in two passages in the New Testament.&amp;nbsp;First:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So then you are no longer strangers and aliens, but you are fellow citizens with the saints and members of the household of God, built on the foundation of the apostles and prophets, Christ Jesus himself being the cornerstone, in whom the whole structure, being joined together, grows into a holy temple in the Lord. In him you also are being built together into a dwelling place for God by the Spirit. (Ephesians 2:19-22,&amp;nbsp;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;ESV&lt;/span&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And&amp;nbsp;again:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then I saw a new heaven and a new earth, for the first heaven and the first earth had passed away, and the sea was no more. And I saw the holy city, new Jerusalem, coming down out of heaven from God, prepared as a bride adorned for her husband. And I heard a loud voice from the throne saying, &amp;#8220;Behold, the dwelling place of God is with man. He will dwell with them, and they will be his people, and God himself will be with them as their God. He will wipe away every tear from their eyes, and death shall be no more, neither shall there be mourning, nor crying, nor pain anymore, for the former things have passed&amp;nbsp;away.&amp;#8221;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And he who was seated on the throne said, &amp;#8220;Behold, I am making all things&amp;nbsp;new&amp;#8230;.&amp;#8221;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And I saw no temple in the city, for its temple is the Lord God the Almighty and the Lamb. And the city has no need of sun or moon to shine on it, for the glory of God gives it light, and its lamp is the Lamb. (Revelation 20:1&amp;#8211;5,&amp;nbsp;22&amp;#8211;23)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Do you see? As magnificent and beautiful as that old temple was, it has been supplanted. The &lt;em&gt;church&lt;/em&gt; is the temple, a dwelling place for God that is yet more beautiful. People are more stunning than the loveliest stones. And there will come a day when the dwelling place of God is with man, not only in spirit but in physical, at th econsummation of all things. That temple, filled as it was with the awesome presence of God, was but the tiniest taste of &lt;em&gt;this&lt;/em&gt; age, when God indwells every believer. And this age is but the tiniest taste of &lt;em&gt;that&lt;/em&gt; age, when the Lord God the Almighty and the Lamb come down from heaven and make their dwelling place with&amp;nbsp;man.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hallelujah. Our Lord,&amp;nbsp;come!&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="devotions"></category></entry><entry><title>Out of the Mouths of Poets</title><link href="http://chriskrycho.com/2014/mouths-of-poets.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-01-08T22:37:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Chris Krycho</name></author><id>tag:chriskrycho.com,2014-01-08:2014/mouths-of-poets.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;!--Template: devotions--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes, the core idea of a passage&amp;#8212;especially when in poetic forms like in the Psalms&amp;#8212;cannot be understood apart from the structure of the passage itself. Tonight I was reading Psalm 8, and thinking about the aims of reading the Bible. Specifically, my aim is to know God and worship him more as I read Scripture. Thus, my goal is that each time I read through a section I would come away both more aware of who God is and more set in both my will and my affections&lt;sup id="fnref:affections"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:affections" rel="footnote"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; to honor&amp;nbsp;him.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I read Psalm 8, I was wondering, &amp;#8220;Okay, how does this lead me to worship?&amp;#8221; Echoing the psalm is a good start, of course, as it opens and&amp;nbsp;closes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Oh Yahweh, our Lord,&lt;br /&gt;
how majestic is your name in all the&amp;nbsp;earth!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the rest of the psalm is a meditation not only on Yahweh&amp;#8217;s majesty, but on the people he made. This is an interesting turn, and it caught me off guard as I started thinking more carefully about it. The key, I soon realized, is in the fact that this is a Psalm, not a letter or a sermon or a treatise. David felt free to get at his point sideways, as it were, and as is the fashion of&amp;nbsp;poetry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The whole poem turns back and forth between the God who made the heavens, who set his glory above them, and the people he made. The contrast is striking, and the more so because of the wonderful turns of&amp;nbsp;phrase.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I look at your heavens, the work of your fingers,&lt;br /&gt;
the moon and the stars, which you have set in place,&lt;br /&gt;
what is man that you are mindful of him,&lt;br /&gt;
and the son of man that you care for&amp;nbsp;him?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, I can sum up the point David is making here. One could say simply, &amp;#8220;Humans are small compared to the universe, so it is surprising that God would pay attention to them.&amp;#8221;  But to do so without further reflection is to miss some of the beauty of what David does in the &lt;em&gt;poetry&lt;/em&gt;, and therefore to miss the force of the passage. It is to miss an opportunity to have my emotions interact with this truth, and not only my mind. We have all felt the awe of staring at a night sky full of lights, a billion miles away and burning brighter than our own sun so that we can see them here across the aeons. We have all felt small against that&amp;nbsp;vastness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And if we stop for a moment and feel that here with David, and then are caught by the sudden turn&amp;#8211;&amp;#8221;what is man?&amp;#8221;&amp;#8211;we can feel with him the wonder that the God who set his glory above the heavens is the God who gave man dominion over creation. We can feel with him the surprise that God would not only establish his strength before the nations and before those who rebel against him, but that he would do it through babies and infants. We can feel with him the greatness of a God who is not limited by our feeble strength and our mortality, whose majesty goes beyond the tinyness of humanity and yet is somehow the greater for the ways he uses us, little beings that we&amp;nbsp;are.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How majestic is the name of Yahweh in all the earth,&amp;nbsp;indeed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:affections"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My desires, ambitions, emotions&amp;#8212;all the pieces of me that include but are not limited to my thoughts and feelings, and which are distinct from though closely interacting with my will&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:affections" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary><category term="devotions"></category></entry><entry><title>A Study in Contrasts: 2 Kings 16–20</title><link href="http://chriskrycho.com/2014/study-in-contrasts-2-kings-16-20.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-01-07T23:40:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Chris Krycho</name></author><id>tag:chriskrycho.com,2014-01-07:2014/study-in-contrasts-2-kings-16-20.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;!--Template: devotions--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the recurring themes of the books of Kings (1 and 2 Samuel, 1 and 2 Kings) is the distinction between those who &amp;#8220;did what was right in the eyes of Yahweh&amp;#8221; and those who &amp;#8220;did what was evil in the sight of Yahweh&amp;#8221;, e.g. 15:34, 17:2 respectively&amp;#8212;to name just two of the &lt;em&gt;many&lt;/em&gt; passages echoing this refrain in these books. Whereas 1 and 2 Samuel zoomed in on the contrast between Saul and David, 1 and 2 Kings take nearly all their successors at a very high level, often sparing them few more words than necessary to note their parentage, whether they did what was right or what was evil in the eyes of Yahweh, and a reference to other records of their&amp;nbsp;deeds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the dominant themes of these books, then, is that doing what is right in Yahweh&amp;#8217;s eyes has an enormous reward, while doing what is evil in his eyes eventually brings a great judgment. 2 Kings 17&amp;#8211;19 brings this message home, and hard. Centuries of rebellion on Israel&amp;#8217;s part culminated in the Assyrian capture of Samaria and the forcible exile of the Jews of Israel from their homeland. The author pauses from his otherwise quick-moving narrative to explain this point in detail for the better part of a chapter. Israel&amp;#8217;s fall was not the mere ordinary turn of regional political events it might have seemed. It was, instead, God&amp;#8217;s final judgment on a people who had continuously rebelled against him generation after generation, worshiping in a way they &lt;em&gt;knew&lt;/em&gt; was abhorrent to&amp;nbsp;him.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By contrast, when the same mighty king with his mighty army came to take Jerusalem, the city stood. Judah had its share of wicked kings, to be sure&amp;#8212;but unlike Israel, it also had many kings who &amp;#8220;did what was right in the eyes of Yahweh&amp;#8221; and in particular it had Hezekiah, who &amp;#8220;trusted in Yahweh, the God of Israel, so that there was none like him among all the kings of Judah after him, nor among those who were before him&amp;#8221;&amp;nbsp;(18:5).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The armies of the greatest power in the region&amp;#8212;unstoppable Assyria&amp;#8212;surrounded the capital city en masse. Their leaders boasted in their victories, tried to bully Hezekiah and the people into surrendering without a fight, and insulted the name of Yahweh. Attacking the people of God is always a bad idea; attacking him directly is an even &lt;em&gt;worse&lt;/em&gt; idea. The Scriptures are a long record of the lengths to which God will go to defend his name: he will quite literally die to defend the glorious reality that he is most righteous and most powerful being there is, most worthy of worship. When Sennacherib boasted, &amp;#8220;Who among all the gods of the lands have delivered their lands out of my hand, that Yahweh should deliver Jerusalem out of my hand?&amp;#8221; (18:35), he missed something. Hezekiah points it out in his prayer: &amp;#8220;[They] were not gods, but the work of men&amp;#8217;s hands, wood and stone. Therefore they were destroyed. So now, O Yahweh our God, save us, please, from his hand, that all the kingdoms of the earth may know that you, O Yahweh, are God alone&amp;#8221;&amp;nbsp;(19:18b&amp;#8211;29).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;God has &lt;em&gt;always&lt;/em&gt; been about the business of making his name known to the ends of the earth. Not because he is a braggart, but because he is the end for which all things exist&amp;#8212;the end for which &lt;em&gt;we&lt;/em&gt; exist. In setting ourselves against that, we are setting ourselves against reality. We are trying to fly by pushing away from the ground with the hairs on our head&amp;#8212;and for some reason, gravity comes out victorious. So when God brings judgment on blasphemers, that is a &lt;em&gt;mercy&lt;/em&gt; to the nations who have a chance to repent and kneel before the king of&amp;nbsp;all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What is amazing to me is just how profoundly longsuffering God is. Were I so often insulted, ignored, and injuriously assaulted in character, I would not wait hundreds of years, sending prophet after prophet to give people opportunity after opportunity to respond. I sometimes have a hard time restraining my impatience for a few minutes with my wife or my child. And yet the God who ultimately struck down 185,000 Assyrians waited generation upon generation to bring his judgment on Israel&amp;#8212;and he likewise gave the Assyrians the opportunity to repent (c.f. Jonah). This God is shockingly merciful, even as he brings&amp;nbsp;judgment.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="devotions"></category></entry><entry><title>Five Things Proverbs 6 Teaches</title><link href="http://chriskrycho.com/2014/five-things-proverbs-six.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-01-06T20:30:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Chris Krycho</name></author><id>tag:chriskrycho.com,2014-01-06:2014/five-things-proverbs-six.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;!--Template: devotions--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Proverbs 6 makes 5 points, rather distinctly and sharply. First a summary and then a few thoughts on&amp;nbsp;each.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Verses 1&amp;#8212;5:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;Being security for your neighbor&amp;#8211;still less for a stranger&amp;#8211;is a bad&amp;nbsp;idea.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This first point is perhaps the least obviously applicable to me today. I don&amp;#8217;t make a habit of pledging money or possessions for a friend&amp;#8217;s (still less a stranger&amp;#8217;s) poor money decisions. I might &lt;em&gt;give&lt;/em&gt; a friend (or even a stranger) money, but I can&amp;#8217;t imagine putting myself in the position of guaranteeing a loan for someone else. That just seems like a terrible idea. Of course, that&amp;#8217;s the point of these verses: it &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; a terrible idea. The counsel here is to get out of that kind of situation as fast as possible (and, by implication, to avoid getting into such a situation in the first&amp;nbsp;place).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Verses 6&amp;#8212;11:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;Laziness will prove ruinous. Industriousness will produce good&amp;nbsp;results.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have seen this proven true time and again in the lives of those around me. As a general rule, people who work hard do well for themselves, and people who are lazy do very poorly for themselves. As a rule, I say, because there are times when this is not true&amp;#8211;there really are times when systemic injustices undermine even people&amp;#8217;s best efforts. This proverb is a proverb, not an iron-clad guarantee, and we would all do well to remember as much. That said: we would &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; do well to remember as much: if the political conservative&amp;#8217;s typical response is to simply point to this verse as a promise (which it is not), the political liberal&amp;#8217;s typical response is to act as though this verse has no bearing whatsoever. Sometimes, poverty has complex, structural, societal roots&amp;#8211;but sometimes, people are just lazy. God calls us &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; to be lazy; work is a good thing that was instituted before the&amp;nbsp;Fall.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Verses 12&amp;#8212;15:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;The ultimate fate of a wicked person is&amp;nbsp;calamity.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is nothing terribly complicated here. There is, however, a great deal of hope here for those of us who have watched wicked people go around behaving wickedly and seemingly coming off no worse for wear every time. There will come a day of recompense for every wicked deed. Lord willing, for some of those people, that day came when Christ came, and they will join us in the company of saints as they abandon their wickedness and turn to God. But for those who don&amp;#8217;t, justice will come, and it will come&amp;nbsp;swiftly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Verses 16&amp;#8212;19:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;There are some things God truly&amp;nbsp;hates.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is almost &lt;em&gt;passe&lt;/em&gt; to note how distasteful this idea is in our culture today, but the words on the page could not be clearer. There are things that Yahweh hates, things that are an abomination to him. He hates pride. He abominates deceit. He hates the shedding of innocent blood. He abominates the plotting of wickedness. He hates the doing of evil. He abominates false witness to be borne. He hates dissension between&amp;nbsp;brothers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But more than this: he hates those who &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt; these things. This is dreadful&amp;#8211;apart from the grace he shows us in&amp;nbsp;Christ.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Verses 20&amp;#8212;35:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;Adultery is folly. Wisdom runs the other&amp;nbsp;way.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="/2014/01/folly-of-sin"&gt;Once again&lt;/a&gt;, the proverbs hammer home the folly of adultery. It is not only that it does not give what it promises and brings spiritual ruin. It is that it also produces, at a purely practical level, destruction. A spouse&amp;#8217;s jealousy is (rightly) a fearful thing. Who in his right mind would sleep with another man&amp;#8217;s wife, knowing what the response would be? What woman would sleep with another woman&amp;#8217;s husband, knowing how her own rage would be? The implications just for one&amp;#8217;s own health&amp;#8211;still less any other part of one&amp;#8217;s life&amp;#8211;ought to be enough to warn us&amp;nbsp;away.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Proverbs remind me again and again that God cares about my life at every level. He is not distant or unengaged with these details; he cares about every aspect of human flourishing, and takes pains to make clear to us what that flourishing looks like&amp;#8211;and what it&amp;nbsp;doesn&amp;#8217;t.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="devotions"></category></entry><entry><title>The Folly of Sin</title><link href="http://chriskrycho.com/2014/folly-of-sin.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-01-05T23:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Chris Krycho</name></author><id>tag:chriskrycho.com,2014-01-05:2014/folly-of-sin.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;!--Template: devotions--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Adultery. It has torn countless families and destroyed innumerable ministries over the years. Over and over again, the refrain is the same: &amp;#8220;I never thought it would happen to me!&amp;#8221; and &amp;#8220;I never meant for it to go this far!&amp;#8221;&lt;sup id="fnref:adultery-1"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:adultery-1" rel="footnote"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Given the evidence of the years, though, no one should ever cavalierly say, &amp;#8220;I&amp;#8217;ll never do that.&amp;#8221; Say it, yes. But back it up by making concrete choices every day not to break vows to your&amp;nbsp;spouse.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Proverbs 5 couldn&amp;#8217;t be clearer: adultery &lt;em&gt;looks&lt;/em&gt; good from the outside and feels good at the&amp;nbsp;outset:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;For&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;the&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;lips&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;of&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;a&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;forbidden&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;woman&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;drip&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;honey&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;and&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;her&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;speech&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;is&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;smoother&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;than&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;oil&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="n"&gt;but&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;in&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;the&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;end&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;she&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;is&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;bitter&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;as&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;wormwood&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;sharp&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;as&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;a&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;two&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;edged&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;sword&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No one commits adultery because it looks so dreadful. People commit this sin&amp;#8211;like every other&amp;#8211;because it looks good. The trick, of course, is that it is &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt;. The Proverb highlights the contradiction of sin powerfully: sin looks sweet, but proves bitter. It seems smooth, but only proves smoothly destructive as it slices away at everything you value. Sin always produces the opposite of what it promises. Adultery promises intimacy, but adultery &lt;em&gt;destroys&lt;/em&gt; intimacy. Drugs promise liberated minds; instead they produce addiction. Covetousness promises satisfaction; instead it produces only an ever-gnawing emptiness. Sin is like a sweet-tasting infection that rots us from the inside&amp;nbsp;out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But it is more than that. Sin is not bad only because it proves so ruinous to us&amp;#8211;though certainly it is bad for that reason. Sin is bad because it is high treason, because it is at its core a rejection of the good, the true, the beautiful in that it is a rejection of God in the exaltation of self. Sin is ruinous to us in part because it is the undoing of everything of what we are: beings made to worship the Triune God, instead kneeling to our own reflection in the mirror instead of the one we were meant to&amp;nbsp;reflect.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But God is a righteous judge. He is holy. He does not tolerate sin. Psalm 5 puts it in sharp&amp;nbsp;relief:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;For&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;you&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;are&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;not&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;a&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;God&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;who&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;delights&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;in&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;wickedness&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;evil&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;may&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;not&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;dwell&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;with&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;you&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="n"&gt;The&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;boastful&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;shall&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;not&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;stand&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;before&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;your&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;eyes&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;you&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;hate&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;all&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;evildoers&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="n"&gt;You&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;destroy&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;those&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;who&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;speak&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;lies&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;Yahweh&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;abhors&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;the&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;bloodthirsty&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;and&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;deceitful&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;man&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;God detests sin.&lt;sup id="fnref:sin-sermon"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:sin-sermon" rel="footnote"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Not just the hot-button sin issues of our day (though those are not excluded), but our pettiness and jealousy, our deceptions great and small, our boasting and pride. We are &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; evildoers. And yet, wonder of wonders, we live still. Though God who made us and at whom we have all shaken our fists in rebellion would be perfectly within his rights to end us without a thought; he does not. He shows mercy. He forbears long. He waits to bring&amp;nbsp;judgment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He provides a way of escape. We, like David, can enter his house &amp;#8220;through the abundance of [his] steadfast love.&amp;#8221; That steadfast love, that covenant love, that almight love, has reached down and partaken of frail humanity and death and even of divine wrath, so that God might be glorified in his holiness. We are saved not because God is sentimental or sappy, but because he is righteous, and has already paid the price for our&amp;nbsp;sins.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hallelujah.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:adultery-1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And yes, sometimes also (even more sadly), &amp;#8220;I don&amp;#8217;t care; why shouldn&amp;#8217;t I be happy?&amp;#8221;&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:adultery-1" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:sin-sermon"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For more on all of this, I commend to you the &lt;a href="http://www.sermonaudio.com/sermoninfo.asp?sermonID=15141146471"&gt;sermon&lt;/a&gt; our primary preaching pastor delivered today.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:sin-sermon" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 2 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary><category term="devotions"></category></entry><entry><title>Elijah and Elisha</title><link href="http://chriskrycho.com/2014/elijah-elisha.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-01-04T23:45:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Chris Krycho</name></author><id>tag:chriskrycho.com,2014-01-04:2014/elijah-elisha.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;!--Template: devotions--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One cannot help but notice, reading through 1 and 2 Kings, how much Elijah and Elisha echo Moses and foreshadow the Messiah. They perform miracles that show up the limitations of other so-called deities, part the Jordan, make clean what was impure, give miraculous children, raise the dead, multiply food for a meal for the hungry.&lt;sup id="fnref:bears"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:bears" rel="footnote"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; These men were prophets like Moses, but Israel knew that they were not &lt;em&gt;the&lt;/em&gt; prophet like Moses that the first savior of Israel had&amp;nbsp;promised.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reading through these books, it is interesting that Israel was eagerly awaiting another prophet like Elijah when Jesus came. Indeed, it is interesting that a later prophet would speak of Elijah coming again. Reading through this material&amp;#8211;which was originally all a single book covering all of 1 Samuel through 2 Kings&amp;#8211;one would not necessarily be inclined to call Elijah the greater of the pair. Indeed, Elisha both asked for and apparently received a double portion of the miraculous gift that Yahweh had given to Elijah. The text records far more miracles performed by Elisha than by Elijah. (Indeed, most of that list above belongs to Elisha and not to&amp;nbsp;Elijah.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Clearly, though, there was something special about&amp;nbsp;Elijah.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think it was his passion for the name of Yahweh, and I think the text makes this abundantly clear. It is not that Elisha was &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; passionate for the glory of Yahweh; it is that this is the main (and nearly the only) thing in view in Elijah&amp;#8217;s ministry. Elijah&amp;#8217;s responsibility was to point the people to repentance for their sins and to show up false religion for what it was. This he did. He stood for the name of Yahweh under the threat of death and all alone. Other faithful Yahweh-worshippers though there were in Israel at the time, it was Elijah alone on the mountain confronting the four hundred priests of Baal, and he alone who saw the mighty hand of Yahweh raised in triumph against Baalism. He, like John the Baptizer, was the lone voice in the wilderness, calling the people of Israel back to&amp;nbsp;God.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Elisha&amp;#8217;s role was different: he was the man of miracles and the fierce judge. He did the greatest miracles recorded in the Bible prior to the coming of the Messiah; only in Jesus himself was there a greater provider, healer, or resurrector. He pointed to the greatness of Yahweh through these miracles; unlike Elijah, he did so in a time when many others worshipped Yahweh. He stood on Elijah&amp;#8217;s shoulders, as it&amp;nbsp;were.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have often pondered over the last year or so that often it is the case that younger leaders can seem (and perhaps are) more effective than their elders&amp;#8211;but that even when this is so, there is a foundation present &lt;em&gt;because&lt;/em&gt; of the elders that is too easily overlooked. Many young men&amp;#8217;s pastoral ministries are successful not only because of their own faithfulness, but because of the work of the pastors who preceded them. Many young men can be more doctrinally sound than or more effective preachers than their predecessors &lt;em&gt;because&lt;/em&gt; of their predecessors. Elisha did his miracles in a land that had already seen Baalism humbled under fire from Yahweh. I do my writing, ministry (such as it is), and even thinking in the context set for me by faithful Christians who have gone before, women and men who have diligently sought Christ and laid a foundation on which I might&amp;nbsp;build.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:bears"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To say nothing of cursing mockers to be attacked by bears, in one of the stranger passages in the old Testament.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:bears" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary><category term="devotions"></category></entry><entry><title>Finding God in Proverbs</title><link href="http://chriskrycho.com/2014/finding-god-proverbs.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-01-03T23:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Chris Krycho</name></author><id>tag:chriskrycho.com,2014-01-03:2014/finding-god-proverbs.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;!--Template: devotions--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the most helpful patterns I have developed in the last few years of Scripture reading is asking one simple question as I read: &lt;em&gt;What does this passage reveal about God?&lt;/em&gt; There are many other questions&amp;#8211;good, important questions&amp;#8211;to ask of the text. But this one, I find, yields the most fruit. The Bible is not just a book of moral teachings, nor a mere practical guide for our lives. It is the revelation of the living God to his people.&lt;sup id="fnref:1"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:1" rel="footnote"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So what do we do when we get to, say, Proverbs? At first blush, the question seems a good deal less tractable here than in many other places. However hairy, most narratives &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt; show us the character of God. Propositional content, whether in letters or sermons or parables or prophecies, likewise tends to make clear, succinct statements about the person and nature of God. The Proverbs, though? Well, sometimes they do, and sometimes they say things like, &amp;#8220;Do not contend with a man for no reason, when he has done you no harm.&amp;#8221; That&amp;#8217;s helpful, to be sure, but when you first read it, it&amp;#8217;s not obvious how that gets us back to God. We could try to hammer the Proverbs into some framework for understanding God, try to reduce their presence in the canon to a role in some theme or another.&lt;sup id="fnref:2"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:2" rel="footnote"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; In the end, though, any such reductive effort is going to run aground on the shoals of misunderstanding&amp;#8211;quite the opposite of the intent of the&amp;nbsp;author.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Proverbs often show us God&amp;#8217;s character sideways. If we believe that the counsel offered by the Proverbs really is wise&amp;#8211;that the glowing promises here in Proverbs 3 of blessing, gain, and profit from wisdom are true, that there really is nothing better than to have understanding&amp;#8211;then we believe that they are insights into reality. And reality was made &lt;em&gt;by God&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;Yahweh&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;by&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;wisdom&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;founded&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;the&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;earth&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;by&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;understanding&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;he&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;established&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;the&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;heavens&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="n"&gt;by&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;his&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;knowledge&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;the&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;deeps&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;broke&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;open&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;and&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;the&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;clouds&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;drop&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;down&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;the&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;dew&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;Proverbs&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;3&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;19&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;--&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;20&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If we then start asking good questions of the text we find very quickly that we do have a path back to the person and nature of God. For example: &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt; should we not contend with a man when he has done us no harm? Well, we ought not do so because it will certainly stir up trouble, and we know God does not delight in strife. Moreover, picking a fight with someone without cause is unjust, and this same author has told us that wisdom comports with justice and righteousness, and that &lt;em&gt;God&lt;/em&gt; is&amp;nbsp;just.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Taking a further step back, we can ask why this proverb is included in the inspired Scriptures. Then we see even more: God cares about the way people interact with one another. He values human flourishing, and so has provided enormous guidance for us in the form of hundreds upon hundreds of practical insights into the way the world is. He delights in people so greatly that he crosses the boundary between transcendence and immanence to give us his very&amp;nbsp;words.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It turns out there is an awful lot to learn about God in the Proverbs&amp;#8211;even the ones that do no mention&amp;nbsp;him.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That final phrase, &amp;#8220;to his people,&amp;#8221; is an important one for all hermeneutics; reading the Scriptures with faith makes a difference. &lt;a href="http://mereorthodoxy.com/"&gt;Matthew Lee Anderson&lt;/a&gt; makes this point helpfully and at some length in his excellent &lt;a href="http://www.amazon.com/End-Our-Exploring-Questioning-Confidence-ebook/dp/B00BUP1BQQ/?tag=krycho-20"&gt;&lt;em&gt;The End of Our Exploring&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:2"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is right here that many Biblical theologies&amp;#8211;that&amp;#8217;s a specific discipline in theology, though admittedly poorly named&amp;#8211;go amiss.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:2" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 2 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary><category term="devotions"></category></entry><entry><title>Kings in Contrast</title><link href="http://chriskrycho.com/2014/kings-contrast.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-01-02T21:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Chris Krycho</name></author><id>tag:chriskrycho.com,2014-01-02:2014/kings-contrast.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;!--Template: devotions--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tonight&amp;#8217;s reading in 1 Kings, Psalms, and Proverbs had some surprising overlaps. The material in 1 Kings covered a series of kings whose courses were largely &lt;em&gt;away&lt;/em&gt; from worshipping Yahweh and toward worshipping other gods. With only one exception, in fact, every single king listed in these five chapters rejected the God of Israel in favor of the gods of the nations which the Hebrews had driven out of Canaan. That exception, Asa, stands in sharp contrast to the litany of rebellious kings who preceded and followed him as being a man who followed God with his whole heart. Others, it seems, included Yahweh in their list of gods to worship, but never reverenced him as supreme and only. This list of wicked kings of both Israel and Judah climaxes with the appearance of Elijah, the righteous prophet who confronts the &lt;em&gt;most&lt;/em&gt; wicked king in the list, and who ultimately demonstrates Yahweh&amp;#8217;s superiority over the other gods the Hebrews&amp;nbsp;worshipped.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Proverbs 2 continues Solomon&amp;#8217;s exhortation to seek wisdom wholeheartedly, and his corresponding encouragement that Yahweh gives wisdom to those who seek it. But Solomon did not stop with the idea that knowledge and understanding are good&amp;#8211;though this he certainly affirms. Rather, he continued on to emphasize that God&amp;#8217;s knowledge and discernment go hand in hand with his integrity and justice. Those who seek this wisdom walk in righteousness and justice and equity. A person of wisdom is kept safe from both evildoers and from doing evil him- or herself. That Solomon&amp;#8217;s own line, beginning with his own son and continuing on down through every king but Asa in these chapters in 1 Kings, went so far astray indicates how little these words were&amp;nbsp;heeded.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The picture painted by Psalm 2 stands in impossibly sharp contrast to these depraved kings. The Anointed One of the psalm is a messianic figure: those who take refuge in him find shelter, but those who rebel against him are broken under his rule. There is a king in view here who laughs at the rebellion of the rulers of every nation (Israel included), who scorns the folly of plotting against the Most High God. The king that Yahweh calls his Son will receive those same nations as his inheritance. He will be the king above all other kings. He will be both wrathful against rebellion and merciful to those who &amp;#8220;take refuge in him&amp;#8221; (v.&amp;nbsp;11&amp;#8212;12).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So we have set before us the history of wicked men rebelling against the very God who gave them their thrones, and a call to that same line of the kings to humbly seek wisdom from that God, and a poetic picture of the true king against whom any rebellion is folly. And running through all of these are both the wrath of God against the folly and sin of those rebelling against him, and his mercy. Yahweh saves his people from following other gods in that magnificent confrontation on the mountain, Elijah on one side and the priests of Baal on the other. He is the source of wisdom, and the one who keeps his people from walking in folly or wickedness. And he is the righteous king who gives his people peace and security. Not because he does not do justice or cares little about sin, but precisely &lt;em&gt;because&lt;/em&gt; he does justice and cares about sin. That Anointed One, that Son of the Most High, is Jesus Christ, who died in order that everything would be put under his feet. Every wicked king in 1 Kings points to the need for Jesus. He is the fulfillment of the wisdom promised in Proverbs 2. He is the Anointed One, the Son of Yahweh, who reigns the nations in righteousness.&amp;nbsp;Hallelujah.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="devotions"></category></entry><entry><title>A New Year of Devotions</title><link href="http://chriskrycho.com/2014/new-year-devotions.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-01-01T23:25:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Chris Krycho</name></author><id>tag:chriskrycho.com,2014-01-01:2014/new-year-devotions.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;!--Template: devotions--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have found, over the years, that writing is a remarkably helpful tool for thinking through the things I am learning. I have also found that I am often better able to remain consistent in my study of Scripture if I am writing regularly about it. That could be in a journal, or on a blog, or just about anywhere. In 2014, I am going to experiment with posting this writing on my blog&amp;#8211;something I have done &lt;a href="http://2012-2013.chriskrycho.com/theology/topics/devotions/index.html"&gt;before&lt;/a&gt; to good effect for myself, and which a number of acquaintances seemed to like. After talking it through with my wonderful wife, I have set myself a limit of half an hour &lt;em&gt;total&lt;/em&gt; devoted to writing these posts. Hopefully it will prove&amp;nbsp;profitable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If it seems like 1 Kings 9&amp;#8212;13 is a funny place to start this sort of thing, that&amp;#8217;s because it is. But 1 Kings is where I am, and thus it is the place from which I will continue&amp;#8211;I do not see a good reason to start over at the beginning &lt;em&gt;again&lt;/em&gt; just a few months after having done so&amp;nbsp;before.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A number of points stuck out at me as I worked through this passage. First, and most important, is one of the recurring themes of the whole book: the question of obedience to Yahweh,&lt;sup id="fnref:yahweh"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:yahweh" rel="footnote"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; and the consequences of rejecting him. From the promise God offers Solomon  in chapter 9 through the death of a prophet in chapter 13, the issue is clear. Obedience to God brings everlasting favor, and disobedience brings&amp;nbsp;death.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is not exactly a new theme for the Bible as a whole: it shows up all the way back in Genesis 3. Nor does it stop here (nor even under the New Covenant with Christ): submission to God is characteristic of all who believe. Why? Not because God is some cruel dictator, but because he is both omniscient and omnibenevolent. He knows what is best for us. Defying his ways is like defying gravity: it might make for a &lt;a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=FlMBcTGJ4YM&amp;amp;name=DefyingGravity"&gt;catchy tune&lt;/a&gt;, but the net result is always crashing hard to the&amp;nbsp;ground.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So: Yahweh promised Solomon great things if he would simply follow him alone and not worship other gods. Solomon did exactly the opposite of what God had commanded the kings of Israel, though: he married multiple foreign women who themselves worshiped other gods,&lt;sup id="fnref:1"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:1" rel="footnote"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; and ultimately he built altars to and sacrificed to those other gods himself. We see the same thing in Jeroboam&amp;#8217;s life: God made him promises of really marvelous import, if he would simply walk with Yahweh. Instead, as soon as he became king he led the people &lt;em&gt;away&lt;/em&gt; from Yahweh, reasoning that Yahweh-worship was a threat to his own power, even though it was a prophet of Yahweh who had first told him all that would happen and that it was Yahweh who would do it. A righteous prophet ends up dead because he disobeyed God&amp;#8217;s clear&amp;nbsp;instructions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In short: God means business, and we ought to pay attention when he commands us in a certain area. Again, not because he is a tyrant, but because he loves us and he is righteous. When we defy him, we are simultaneously wronging ourselves and committing cosmic treason. It&amp;#8217;s a bad move, and he rightly responds in judgment. That, in turn, though, takes me back to his &lt;em&gt;decisive&lt;/em&gt; act of judgment: the one the Godhead executed on itself, in the sacrificial, atoning death of Christ on my behalf. My motivation for obedience, then, is not only fear, but joyful&amp;nbsp;gratitude.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#8217;s a good start to the&amp;nbsp;year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:yahweh"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I know it is a bit unusual to spell out the name of God used in the Old Testament like this, but it is my preference. I think it makes many passages much clearer to read Yahweh instead of &lt;span style="font-variant: small-caps"&gt;Lord&lt;/span&gt;, and it&amp;#8217;s simply what&amp;#8217;s there in the original (even if the Jews historically have chosen not to say it&amp;#8211;there&amp;#8217;s something interesting here, but I shall pass over it today).&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:yahweh" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note that the reason for the prohibition on marrying foreigners was always religious, not ethnic. Solomon&amp;#8217;s own lineage (and thus, Jesus&amp;#8217; too) includes several foreign women&amp;#8211;each of whom worshiped Yahweh.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 2 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary><category term="devotions"></category></entry></feed>