<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Chris Krycho - typing-your-ember</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/</link><description></description><lastBuildDate>Mon, 08 May 2017 22:00:00 -0400</lastBuildDate><item><title>Typing Your Ember, Part 2</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2017/typing-your-ember-part-2.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;i class='series-overview'&gt;You write &lt;a href="https://emberjs.com"&gt;Ember.js&lt;/a&gt; apps. You think &lt;a href="http://www.typescriptlang.org"&gt;TypeScript&lt;/a&gt; would be helpful in building a more robust app as it increases in size or has more people working on it. But you have questions about how to make it work.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;i class='series-overview'&gt;This is the series for you! I’ll talk through everything: from the very basics of how to set up your Ember.js app to use TypeScript to how you can get the most out of TypeScript today—and I’ll be pretty clear about the current tradeoffs and limitations, too.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;i class='series-overview'&gt;&lt;a href="/typing-your-ember.html"&gt;(See the rest of the series. →)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the [first part] of this series, I described how to set up a brand new Ember.js app to use TypeScript. In this part, I’m going to talk about starting to use TypeScript in the context of an existing Ember.js app.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is, in many ways, even simpler than setting up an app for the first time, because you already have almost everything you need. The steps here are exactly what you’re used to if you’re used to using the Ember CLI ecosystem:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol type="1"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Install &lt;code&gt;ember-cli-typescript&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="sh"&gt;&lt;code&gt;ember install ember-cli-typescript&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Start using TypeScript wherever you want in your app.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It really is that simple, for the most part. There are a couple qualifications, and a couple tips, though.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s start with &lt;strong&gt;qualifications&lt;/strong&gt;. There are open, unresolved &lt;a href="https://github.com/emberwatch/ember-cli-typescript/issues/"&gt;issues&lt;/a&gt; about using &lt;code&gt;ember-cli-typescript&lt;/code&gt; in your app in certain contexts. For example: &lt;a href="https://github.com/emberwatch/ember-cli-typescript/issues/8"&gt;using it with &lt;code&gt;ember-browserify&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. While everything will &lt;em&gt;build&lt;/em&gt; correctly in that case (even if the TypeScript compiler complains about being unable to resolve some things, the Ember CLI build pipeline will still work as expected), your editor integration won’t. There are a bunch of corners like this we’re still hammering out; those are the main things we need to get resolved before we can call this a “1.0.” We have the &lt;em&gt;main&lt;/em&gt; stuff working, but, well… there’s more to do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Along those same lines, you should take a close look at the &lt;a href="https://github.com/emberwatch/ember-cli-typescript#not-yet-supported"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Not yet supported&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; section of the README. There are parts of Ember’s programming model which TypeScript certainly &lt;em&gt;can&lt;/em&gt; support, but which we haven’t done the lifting to get the type declaration file to help with yet. (Looking for a place to pitch in and already comfortable doing some heavy lifting with some of TypeScript’s &lt;a href="http://www.typescriptlang.org/docs/handbook/mixins.html"&gt;most advanced type features&lt;/a&gt;? We could use the help.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One other thing to be aware of is that your &lt;code&gt;tsconfig.json&lt;/code&gt; settings will affect what kind of resolution your editor gives you. If you have &lt;code&gt;allowJs&lt;/code&gt; set to &lt;code&gt;true&lt;/code&gt; in your &lt;code&gt;tsconfig.json&lt;/code&gt;, your editors will resolve JS modules. Otherwise, they’ll &lt;em&gt;only&lt;/em&gt; resolve TS modules. This can be incredibly annoying at times. However, this isn’t something we’ve nailed down in terms of what the default should be yet. (You can &lt;a href="https://github.com/emberwatch/ember-cli-typescript/issues/"&gt;come tell us&lt;/a&gt; on GitHub if you have thoughts or insights there!) And the fact that Microsoft has left this configurable is suggestive: different projects may have different preferences here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, for the &lt;strong&gt;tips&lt;/strong&gt;. Note that these are just a couple quick pointers; I’ll come back and talk about structuring your project and more sophisticated uses of TypeScript in the future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Don’t turn on &lt;code&gt;--strict&lt;/code&gt; or the corresponding individual flags on day 1. Unless you have an extremely unusual and disciplined Ember.js codebase, you’ll have an incredible set of errors to deal with.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Don’t set the the &lt;code&gt;noEmitOnError&lt;/code&gt; flag to &lt;code&gt;true&lt;/code&gt; in your &lt;code&gt;tsconfig.json&lt;/code&gt;, for much the same reason. Since the state of type declaration files for Ember is best described as &lt;em&gt;nascent&lt;/em&gt; at present, many of your files will have errors in them just from failed imports!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Don’t try to convert everything at once. Just pick the next feature or bug you’re working on, and start with the files you’re touching for that bug. Rename it to &lt;code&gt;.ts&lt;/code&gt;, fix any major issues it flags up that you can—but stick as locally as possible. You’re apt to find a &lt;em&gt;lot&lt;/em&gt; of small bugs as you start migrating, and some of them are things which are apt to affect your whole system because they touch central data types. It’s okay. You can come back to those later. For today, you can just be explicit about the weirdnesses.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;As part of that: get comfortable—really, really comfortable—with &lt;a href="http://www.typescriptlang.org/docs/handbook/advanced-types.html#union-types"&gt;union types&lt;/a&gt;. They’ll make it much easier to express the kind of code you’ve &lt;em&gt;actually&lt;/em&gt; written.&lt;a href="#fn1" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref1"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Don’t worry about adding explicit types to &lt;em&gt;everything.&lt;/em&gt; In fact, depending on how comfortable you are already with typed languages, you should probably take a pretty different tack with this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;If you’re just stepping into the world of typed programming languages, you might start adding types where they’re the &lt;em&gt;lowest risk&lt;/em&gt;: some place like your automated tests. That’ll help you start to see how to take advantage of them, while not impacting the way you write your app code until you have a better idea how best to employ the types.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;If you’re already really comfortable with typed programming languages, you might employ types where they’re &lt;em&gt;most helpful:&lt;/em&gt; start with some types in the hairiest or trickiest spots of your app.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is plenty more I could say, but I think that’s a good start for now. I’ll have lots more to add in later posts about the details of how specifically to get the most mileage out of types within an Ember.js app today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="/2017/typing-your-ember-part-1"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Previous:&lt;/strong&gt; Part 1 – Set your Ember.js project up to use TypeScript.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;section class="footnotes"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn1"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Also, I &lt;em&gt;strongly&lt;/em&gt; encourage you to write types in terms of unions of types rather than in terms of &lt;a href="http://www.typescriptlang.org/docs/handbook/interfaces.html#optional-properties"&gt;optional properties on types&lt;/a&gt;. That might be surprising; I’ll explain it in more detail in a future post.&lt;a href="#fnref1"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 08 May 2017 22:00:00 -0400</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2017-05-08:/2017/typing-your-ember-part-2.html</guid><category>typescript</category><category>emberjs</category><category>typing-your-ember</category></item><item><title>Typing Your Ember, Part 1</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2017/typing-your-ember-part-1.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;i class='series-overview'&gt;You write &lt;a href="https://emberjs.com"&gt;Ember.js&lt;/a&gt; apps. You think &lt;a href="http://www.typescriptlang.org"&gt;TypeScript&lt;/a&gt; would be helpful in building a more robust app as it increases in size or has more people working on it. But you have questions about how to make it work.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;i class='series-overview'&gt;This is the series for you! I’ll talk through everything: from the very basics of how to set up your Ember.js app to use TypeScript to how you can get the most out of TypeScript today—and I’ll be pretty clear about the current tradeoffs and limitations, too.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;i class='series-overview'&gt;&lt;a href="/typing-your-ember.html"&gt;(See the rest of the series. →)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this first post in the series, we’re going to keep things simple and easy: we’re going to get an Ember.js app configured to use TypeScript. Later posts will cover some of the other details.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because of the lovely &lt;a href="https://ember-cli.com"&gt;Ember CLI&lt;/a&gt; ecosystem, this is a pretty straightforward process. I’m going to start from &lt;em&gt;zero&lt;/em&gt; so that even if you’ve never written an Ember app before, you can get this up and running by following these instructions. These instructions have also been tested and confirmed to work across platforms—you can do this equally on Windows, macOS, or Linux.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol type="1"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Make sure you have Ember’s prerequisites installed. Get &lt;a href="https://nodejs.org/en/"&gt;Node&lt;/a&gt; for your platform. Optionally (but highly recommended) install &lt;a href="https://yarnpkg.com"&gt;Yarn&lt;/a&gt; to manage your Node packages.&lt;a href="#fn1" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref1"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Install the Ember command lines tools globally:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="sh"&gt;&lt;code&gt;yarn global add ember-cli&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;or&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="sh"&gt;&lt;code&gt;npm install --global ember-cli&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Create an Ember app.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="sh"&gt;&lt;code&gt;ember new my-ts-app --yarn&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(Using the &lt;code&gt;--yarn&lt;/code&gt; flag will make it so your app uses &lt;a href="https://yarnpkg.com"&gt;&lt;code&gt;yarn&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and creates a &lt;code&gt;yarn.lock&lt;/code&gt; file instead of using &lt;code&gt;npm&lt;/code&gt; when it installs its dependencies.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Now move to the root of the newly created app: this is where we’ll do everything else in the post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="sh"&gt;&lt;code&gt;cd my-ts-app&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Add the &lt;a href="https://emberobserver.com/addons/ember-cli-typescript"&gt;&lt;em&gt;ember-cli-typescript&lt;/em&gt; add-on&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="sh"&gt;&lt;code&gt;ember install ember-cli-typescript&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Generate your first UI component.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="sh"&gt;&lt;code&gt;ember generate component some-input&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Rename the files it generated from &lt;code&gt;.js&lt;/code&gt; to &lt;code&gt;.ts&lt;/code&gt;:
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;app/components/some-input.js&lt;/code&gt; → &lt;code&gt;app/components/some-input.ts&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;tests/integration/components/some-input-test.js&lt;/code&gt; → &lt;code&gt;tests/integration/components/some-input-test.ts&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(Eventually, we’ll make it so that you get TypeScript for all newly generated components when using &lt;em&gt;ember-cli-typescript&lt;/em&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Add some content to the files:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="handlebars"&gt;&lt;code&gt;{{!-- some-input.hbs --}}
{{input value=theValue change=(mut theValue)}}
{{theValue}}&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre class="typescript"&gt;&lt;code&gt;// some-input.ts
import Ember from &amp;#39;ember&amp;#39;;

export default Ember.Component.extend({
  theValue: &amp;#39;&amp;#39;,
});&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Update your &lt;code&gt;application.hbs&lt;/code&gt; file to remove the default &lt;code&gt;{{welcome}}&lt;/code&gt; template and replace it with &lt;code&gt;{{some-input}}&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Spin up the Ember application with Ember CLI’s development server:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="sh"&gt;&lt;code&gt;ember serve&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You’ll likely note some warnings: the TypeScript compiler won’t be able to find some of the modules imported in your files. I’ll have more to say about this in a future post. For now, suffice it to say: don’t worry, Ember CLI is still resolving and compiling your modules just fine.&lt;a href="#fn2" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref2"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Load the application by going to &lt;code&gt;localhost:4200&lt;/code&gt; in your browser. You should see a blank white screen with an input in it. Type in it, and see the input rendered to the page. Simple enough, but it’s using a TypeScript file compiled along the way!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And that’s it: we’re done setting up an Ember.js app to use TypeScript! In the next post, I’ll talk a bit about strategies for migrating an existing app to TypeScript—not just the mechanics of it, but also where and how to start actually integrating types into your code.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="/2017/typing-your-ember-part-2"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Next:&lt;/strong&gt; Part 2 – Adding TypeScript to an existing Ember.js project.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;section class="footnotes"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn1"&gt;&lt;p&gt;I strongly prefer to use &lt;code&gt;yarn&lt;/code&gt; over &lt;code&gt;npm&lt;/code&gt; because &lt;code&gt;yarn&lt;/code&gt; installs are predictable and repeatable, and if there’s one thing I don’t need to spend time on when developing our Ember.js app at Olo, it’s chasing problems with transitive dependencies that are different in the build server than in my local development environment. Yarn’s lockfiles mean what ends up built on the server is &lt;em&gt;exactly&lt;/em&gt; what ended up built on my machine.&lt;a href="#fnref1"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn2"&gt;&lt;p&gt;But if you’re curious, here’s a preview: we really need more &lt;a href="http://www.typescriptlang.org/docs/handbook/declaration-files/introduction.html"&gt;type definitions&lt;/a&gt; for the Ember ecosystem. I’ll be covering &lt;em&gt;how&lt;/em&gt; we build those in much more detail in a future installment.&lt;a href="#fnref2"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 05 May 2017 00:10:00 -0400</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2017-05-05:/2017/typing-your-ember-part-1.html</guid><category>typescript</category><category>emberjs</category><category>typing-your-ember</category></item></channel></rss>