<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Chris Krycho - wisdom</title><link>http://v4.chriskrycho.com/</link><description></description><lastBuildDate>Mon, 04 Nov 2019 22:00:00 -0500</lastBuildDate><item><title>A Note on Attention</title><link>http://v4.chriskrycho.com/2019/a-note-on-attention.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;a href="https://v4.chriskrycho.com/2018/assumed-audiences.html"&gt;Assumed Audience&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/b&gt; written with an eye to folks willing to think a little bit harder about &lt;em&gt;attention&lt;/em&gt;—something we &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; need to get better at.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Walking through the airport this morning, I found that my attention itself had caught my attention. I have had &lt;a href="https://thefrailestthing.com/2018/08/03/spectrum-of-attention/"&gt;this bit&lt;/a&gt; from L. M. Sacasas bouncing around in my head for the last month or so:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The ability to take photographs expands (and limits) the hiker’s perceptive repertoire—it creates new possibilities, the landscape now appears differently to our hiker. Smartphone in hand, the hiker might now perceive the world as field of possible images. This may, for example, direct attention up from the path toward the horizon, causing even our experienced hiker to stumble. We may be tempted to say, consequently, that the hiker is no longer paying attention, that the device has distracted him. But this is, at best, only partly true. The hiker is still paying attention. In fact, he may be paying very close, directed attention, hunting for that perfect image. But his attention is of a very different sort than the “in the flow” attention of a hiker on the move. They are now missing some aspects of the surroundings, but picking up on others. Without the smartphone in hand, the hiker may not stumble, but they may not notice a particularly striking vista either.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://v4.chriskrycho.com/2019/photography-ing-again.html"&gt;Yesterday’s bit of history&lt;/a&gt; might give you to how I ended up walking through Denver International Airport with my camera in hand today, taking in the architecture with a rather different eye than I usually do. My normal path through the airport is &lt;em&gt;merely&lt;/em&gt; utilitarian: get to the gate, fill my water bottle, hit the bathroom, grab a seat and knock out some work while I wait to board. Today, though, I found myself considering the structures of the facility, its décor, the little touches architects and designers had put in place to (or at least, to attempt to) humanize what might otherwise be a terribly forbidding structure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(Airports are among the chief edifices of our modern, technological regime. They are not merely travel hubs, but miniature shopping malls. They require not only the massive infrastructure that supports aircraft themselves, but also the perhaps even greater infrastructure to support the cars we park there, the workers who cycle through, the food to be eaten, and so on. They are, I think, under-appreciated as signifiers of our default approach of technological mastery over the world. More on this, perhaps, another day.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The very act of carrying a camera with me changed my perceptual relationship to the airport. And why? Because the device around my neck prompted (that is: my choice to carry it with me prompted) a shift in my attention. I left Sacasas’ words above just as he wrote them, focused on the way a smartphone shifts the attention of his hypothetical hiker. The smartphone, by dint of its ubiquity and its versatility, does indeed (and &lt;em&gt;more especially&lt;/em&gt; than other devices) shift our attention. Not least, I think, because for most of us, there is no conscious choice to bring it with us, as there was for me with my camera this morning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The phone both draws our attention and diffuses it. For all that having the smartphone in my pocket may increase my attentiveness to the beautiful vista on a hike, it may also tempt me to disengage entirely from the hike: not only to consider the environment in a different light, but to send my mind across the world to other places, other activities entirely. The contrast with a dedicated device like the camera I brought with me is illuminating. Certainly a camera shifts my relationship to a hike, just as it does to a stroll through the airport. But it does so by way of &lt;em&gt;focusing&lt;/em&gt; my attention, and drawing it into aspects of the hike that I might otherwise miss. That focusing is a tradeoff: as Sacasas notes, it means there are things I notice which I might not have had I not had a camera in hand; but also that there are aspects of a hike that I do not enjoy as I would had I no camera to hand—precisely because my attention is focused by the device. But the difference between the way a single-purpose technology affects our attention and the way a device with greater versatility affects our attention is rather stark.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have an increasing degree of affection for an interest in devices dedicated to a single job. Some of this is simply that, as good as smartphones are at many tasks, a purpose-built piece can often serve better than a jack-of-all-trades production. As my friend &lt;a href="https://www.stephencarradini.com"&gt;Stephen&lt;/a&gt; has often lamented: the iPod was a better portable music player—in the sense of doing that one specific job—than any iPhone! I could say the same of my &lt;a href="https://us.kobobooks.com/collections/ereaders/products/kobo-aura-one-limited-edition"&gt;Kobo&lt;/a&gt;… and far more for a paper book! I find the experience of using those task-tailored technologies much more &lt;em&gt;enjoyable&lt;/em&gt; than our ubiquitous and flexible—and therefore ultimately &lt;em&gt;distracting&lt;/em&gt;—smartphones. They shape my attention very differently, and (I think), &lt;em&gt;better&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 04 Nov 2019 22:00:00 -0500</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:v4.chriskrycho.com,2019-11-04:/2019/a-note-on-attention.html</guid><category>attention</category><category>photography</category><category>social media</category><category>wisdom</category></item><item><title>From My Sent Folder: On Social Media Tradeoffs</title><link>http://v4.chriskrycho.com/2019/from-my-sent-folder-on-social-media-tradeoffs.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;a href="https://v4.chriskrycho.com/2018/assumed-audiences.html"&gt;Assumed Audience&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/b&gt; anyone &lt;em&gt;willing&lt;/em&gt; to think hard about social media and its place in our lives.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;I got a particularly thoughtful email from a friend about his family’s use of Facebook in response to &lt;a href="https://v4.chriskrycho.com/2019/breaking-up-with-social-media.html"&gt;yesterday’s essay&lt;/a&gt;. I’ve reproduced most of my response here because I think it’s a helpful extension on that essay.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I (a) totally hear where you’re coming from, and deeply sympathize; and (b) deeply disagree about the notion that they’re “just tools – not good or evil in themselves.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I agree in the strictest sense that the tools are not evil in and of themselves. But I think that particular framing is actually extremely misleading. Tools have &lt;em&gt;shapes&lt;/em&gt;, and those shapes form us in ways that may prove out to be particular bad. The usual example is: use a hammer for hours a day every day, and you’ll end up with calluses and quite possibly some hilariously out-of-proportion forearms if you don’t figure out how to be ambidextrous at least for hammering. That tools are not inherently moral does not mean they’re &lt;em&gt;neutral&lt;/em&gt;. (I also am not persuaded that tools are themselves always &lt;em&gt;morally&lt;/em&gt; neutral, but that’s another discussion and a subtler one.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the case of the social media tools, I &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt; think there are differences in both degree (the extent to which they shape us) and kind (the particular shapes they press us into as we use them). Thus my willingness to work for LinkedIn and my &lt;em&gt;un&lt;/em&gt;willingness to work for Twitter or Facebook! And with that in mind, I do agree that the tradeoffs around Facebook can look very different than those around Twitter today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What’s more, I’d go so far as to say that a service much like Facebook but retooled in certain very important ways could be a much-less-alloyed good in the world! (There are no unalloyed goods in our fallen reality, of course.) A service that was less interested in &lt;em&gt;driving user attention&lt;/em&gt; and therefore constantly working in ways that actively undermine people’s self-control and ability to disengage could have most (probably all!) the upsides Facebook offers you and your family today, with few of the horrid downsides we’re seeing with it at the macro scale and few (if any) of the downsides I have felt with it personally at the micro scale. It’s those vicious little loops driving me to check obsessively that I want out of—not the ability to have geographically distributed people able to stay in touch and indeed even to connect, of the sort you and I have benefited from so much.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;None of that is an argument for everyone to get off of Facebook. I certainly think you and your family have very &lt;em&gt;good&lt;/em&gt; reasons to be there. Rather, it’s more that the more of us who make the kinds of moves I’m making, the more it opens back up the &lt;em&gt;possibility&lt;/em&gt; that those communities could form in other spaces, and creates the &lt;em&gt;reminder&lt;/em&gt; for others that in fact many people are &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; in those spaces. It’s a very long play, for sure, but, you know: &lt;a href="https://winningslowly.org"&gt;winning slowly&lt;/a&gt; and all that jazz.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In that regard it’s not so different from my rejection of Amazon: I’m under no misapprehension that I’m going to have any meaningful effect on the company itself, and in fact I have friends who I think are &lt;em&gt;very wise&lt;/em&gt; to continue using it because e.g. Prime eliminates needless frictions from their very challenging lives. It’s that my opting out allows me to support &lt;em&gt;other&lt;/em&gt;—healthier!—businesses and hopefully keep them going.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All of which is kind of a long way of saying: these are &lt;em&gt;wisdom&lt;/em&gt; questions, and I think that wisdom not only allows but indeed &lt;em&gt;dictates&lt;/em&gt; different courses for different people.&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 14 Jun 2019 08:30:00 -0400</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:v4.chriskrycho.com,2019-06-14:/2019/from-my-sent-folder-on-social-media-tradeoffs.html</guid><category>social media</category><category>from my sent folder</category><category>ethics</category><category>wisdom</category></item><item><title>“Zuckerberg’s Blindness and Ours” (L. M. Sacasas)</title><link>http://v4.chriskrycho.com/2018/zuckerbergs-blindness-and-ours-l-m-sacasas.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Yesterday while talking with my wife as we drove to spend some time with extended family, I caught myself: tempted to describe a given &lt;em&gt;response&lt;/em&gt; to a particular cultural ill as a &lt;em&gt;solution&lt;/em&gt;. This is a turn of thinking that’s especially tempting for engineers—and perhaps the more so engineers with a physics background (like me!). In two of the fields to which I have applied myself (physics and software), knowledge often genuinely appears in the form of &lt;em&gt;solutions to problems&lt;/em&gt;. But the extent to which science (and scientism) on the one hand and engineering disciplines (especially software) on the other have come to the fore in our culture—the degree to which they have achieved nearly unassailable authority for us—means that we now too often take solutions as coextant with knowledge more generally.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is &lt;em&gt;solutionism&lt;/em&gt;, and it is bad. I noted above that two of the fields to which I have applied myself share this feature of having solutions to problems as their predominant form of knowledge. But this is not so in two of the other fields I have studied in some depth: for neither theology nor music is a &lt;em&gt;solution&lt;/em&gt; very often in demand. Very different modes of thought and of reasoning are in play in each of those, and appropriately so.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So it was with some particular appreciation that I read &lt;a href="https://thefrailestthing.com/2018/09/16/zuckerbergs-blindness-and-ours/"&gt;this piece by L. M. Sacasas&lt;/a&gt;, reflecting on the recent New Yorker profile of Mark Zuckerberg. Sacasas rightly highlights how mistaken this solutionist frame of knowledge is. From his conclusion (emphasis mine):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reducing knowledge to know-how and doing away with thought leaves us trapped by an impulse to see the world merely as a field of problems to be solved by the application of the proper tool or technique, and this impulse is also compulsive because it cannot abide inaction. We can call this an ideology or we can simply call it a frame of mind, but either way it seems that this is closer to the truth about the mindset of Silicon Valley.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is not a matter of stupidity or education, formally understood, or any kind of personal turpitude. Indeed, by most accounts, Zuckerberg is both earnest and, in his own way, thoughtful. Rather it is the case that one’s intelligence and one’s education, even if it were deeply humanistic, and one’s moral outlook, otherwise exemplary and decent, are framed by something more fundamental: a distinctive way of perceiving the world. This way of seeing the world, including the human being, as a field of problems to be solved by the application of tools and techniques, bends all of our faculties to its own ends. &lt;em&gt;The solution is the truth, the solution is the good, the solution the beautiful. Nothing that is given is valued.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The trouble with this way of seeing the world is that it cannot quite imagine the possibility that some problems are not susceptible to merely technical solutions or, much less, that some problems are best abided.&lt;/em&gt; It is also plagued by hubris—often of the worst sort, the hubris of the powerful and well-intentioned—and, consequently, it is incapable of perceiving its own limits. As in the Greek tragedies, hubris generates blindness, a blindness born precisely out of one’s distinctive way of seeing. And that’s not the worst of it. That worst of it is that we are all, to some degree, now tempted and prone to see the world in just this way too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 17 Sep 2018 08:20:00 -0400</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:v4.chriskrycho.com,2018-09-17:/2018/zuckerbergs-blindness-and-ours-l-m-sacasas.html</guid><category>links</category><category>ethics</category><category>wisdom</category></item><item><title>“Life Hacks” Are Dumb</title><link>http://v4.chriskrycho.com/2018/life-hacks-are-dumb.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;I don’t know where the idea of “life hacking” first appeared, or who first coined the term, and frankly I don’t much care about the details. The phrase itself says enough. It is the stereotypical and often self-caricaturing ethos of Silicon Valley: the rejection of what has come before, only to discover/invent/disrupt it as if it were wholly new, and proclaim the glories of tech startup culture.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We did once have a word for the idea of being attentive to your own strengths and weaknesses, and disciplining yourself in response to this so you could accomplish the things that are truly important. We called it &lt;em&gt;wisdom&lt;/em&gt;, and the pursuit of it was considered—in some circles, anyway—one of the great aims of human existence. All the great philosophical and religious traditions have had something to say about it. Many of them even find considerable concord on the sorts of practical wisdom for accomplishing goals that is an essential part of human flourishing, even as they disagree sharply about what constitutes that human flourishing!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But look to the tech startup scene and “wisdom” is not a word to be found in that vernacular. Instead we have “life hacks.” The anthropology here may be implicit, but it’s also obvious, and very dumb. We are not machines to be hacked. We are people, who ought to seek the good—wisely.&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 30 May 2018 07:00:00 -0400</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:v4.chriskrycho.com,2018-05-30:/2018/life-hacks-are-dumb.html</guid><category>wisdom</category><category>culture</category><category>life hacks</category></item></channel></rss>