<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Chris Krycho - workflow</title><link>http://v4.chriskrycho.com/</link><description></description><lastBuildDate>Thu, 06 Jul 2017 21:00:00 -0400</lastBuildDate><item><title>Farewell, Dropbox</title><link>http://v4.chriskrycho.com/2017/farewell-dropbox.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Over the last few years, I’ve grown increasingly annoyed with Dropbox. There have been a number of fairly high-profile misbehaviors on their part—most notably, &lt;a href="http://applehelpwriter.com/2016/07/28/revealing-dropboxs-dirty-little-security-hack/"&gt;this one&lt;/a&gt;—and then this past week, they started sending me notifications advertising Dropbox for Business.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src="https://f001.backblazeb2.com/file/chriskrycho-com/images/bad-dropbox.png" alt="Notification ads are the worst." /&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Notification ads are the worst.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, as I was with Google a few years ago &lt;a href="http://v4.chriskrycho.com/2014/goodbye-chrome.html" title="Goodbye, Chrome: You&amp;#39;re just too creepy now."&gt;when they pushed me over the edge&lt;/a&gt;—&lt;em&gt;also&lt;/em&gt; with notifications!—I’m out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don’t mind Dropbox’s wanting to have a sustainable business. To the contrary: as I often note, I’m quite willing to pay for software I use, and I currently use a number of paid services where free alternatives exist because I’d rather do that than pay for ads.&lt;a href="#fn1" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref1" role="doc-noteref"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; I &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt; mind when a company—&lt;em&gt;any&lt;/em&gt; company—decides that building their business means mistreating their users and customers. And harassing me with notifications about a variant of their product I don’t care about certainly crosses that line. Combine that with the misbehavior &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; the fact that Dropbox has a tendency to hammer my system for no apparent reason, and, well, I’m out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section id="transition-plans" class="level2"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Transition Plans&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;section id="file-syncing" class="level3"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;File syncing&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For basic storage and access to files across my devices, the shift will be pretty easy: I already have paid iCloud storage for backing up Photos (it’s far easier and comparably priced to all the other options, so that’s what we use). So everything I’ve &lt;em&gt;been&lt;/em&gt; doing with Dropbox I’ll be doing with iCloud Drive instead. And I have &lt;em&gt;way&lt;/em&gt; more overhead there with a 250GB plan that I do in my current 9GB of Dropbox storage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="file-sharing" class="level3"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;File sharing&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For things where I need to share files with other people, I’ll be using &lt;a href="https://droplr.com"&gt;Droplr&lt;/a&gt;. If or when I find a need to share something for a longer period of time, more often, or with more people, I’ll think about the Pro plan, but for right now the free plan will &lt;em&gt;more&lt;/em&gt; than suffice for, say, sending an audio file to &lt;a href="http://independentclauses.com"&gt;Stephen&lt;/a&gt; for editing &lt;a href="http://www.winningslowly.org"&gt;Winning Slowly&lt;/a&gt; episodes. (Also, iOS 11’s Files app &lt;a href="https://www.imore.com/files-app" title="iOS 11&amp;#39;s Files app FAQ"&gt;will support&lt;/a&gt; this sharing workflow natively.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="my-writing-setup" class="level3"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;My writing setup&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Probably the &lt;em&gt;most&lt;/em&gt; vexing (or at least: vexing-seeming) change here will be to my writing workflow. For a long time, I’ve made an alias pointing from a folder in Dropbox on my main machine into the clone of the &lt;a href="https://github.com/chriskrycho/chriskrycho.com"&gt;Git repository&lt;/a&gt; on that machine where I manage my website.&lt;a href="#fn2" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref2" role="doc-noteref"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; That has meant that I can edit the source version of a given post anywhere at any time, with any editor that has Dropbox integration. That was a winning combo for a long time, and it’s one thing I actually &lt;em&gt;can’t&lt;/em&gt; do with iCloud Drive. (I tried, and it sort of works, for a little while; but iCloud Drive doesn’t seem to expect this scenario. In its defense, it’s a weird setup.) I realized in thinking it through this evening, though: it doesn’t actually matter to me with the ways my workflow has shifted—and, perhaps just as importantly, with the way that the iOS ecosystem has shifted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For one thing, there are a &lt;em&gt;lot&lt;/em&gt; of options for directly editing files from Git repositories on iOS now. I don’t need to have it in Dropbox to be able to open it in any one of several &lt;em&gt;great&lt;/em&gt; iOS writing environments, whether to make a quick edit or to create a post from scratch. Both &lt;a href="https://workingcopyapp.com/"&gt;Working Copy&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://git2go.com"&gt;Git2Go&lt;/a&gt; work &lt;em&gt;very&lt;/em&gt; well. But for another thing, I currently can’t &lt;em&gt;generate&lt;/em&gt; the site without logging into my home machine anyway.&lt;a href="#fn3" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref3" role="doc-noteref"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; So if I need to make a tweak, well… &lt;a href="http://www.blink.sh"&gt;Blink.sh&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href="https://www.panic.com/prompt/"&gt;Prompt&lt;/a&gt; will let me log in remotely and do what I need to. And a little bit of Vim or Emacs will let me make any quick edits that way if I really feel I must.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And one side effect of realizing &lt;em&gt;that&lt;/em&gt; is that I can easily enough just copy a file from iCloud storage to my site’s working directory after writing it in a writing folder in iCloud if I so desire. Sure, that’s a &lt;em&gt;little&lt;/em&gt; finicky, but for the most part I won’t really need to mess with it: I can just &lt;code&gt;git push&lt;/code&gt; from my iPad, &lt;code&gt;git pull&lt;/code&gt; on my iMac and be ready to do whatever I need.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="other-apps" class="level3"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Other apps&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The last piece of the puzzle is the other “apps” that have made a home in my Dropbox. The reality, though, is that almost none of those actually matter to me. I don’t even look at the majority of that data, and other pieces of it —backups of GPS and heart-rate data from workouts, or copies of all my tweets from when I wanted to maintain a microblog on this site, for example—are really just needless at this point, as I have all of that data stored in &lt;em&gt;several&lt;/em&gt; cloud platforms (in the case of workout data) and/or don’t care about being able to retrieve it (in the case of tweets). I can happily just shut those things down and call it a day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="in-conclusion" class="level2"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;In Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So that’s it: goodbye Dropbox; hello other tools. (This post written from an iPad, and stored in iCloud Drive before publishing.) It’s been a long, and mostly just-fine ride, but I’m getting off here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn1" role="doc-endnote"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Full disclosure here: I am &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; a Dropbox paying customer—though that is the fault of their perhaps overly aggressive early customer acquisition strategy. I have never &lt;em&gt;needed&lt;/em&gt; to pay for Dropbox, even though I have many gigabytes stored in it, because I earned so much free storage for inviting other users early on.&lt;a href="#fnref1" class="footnote-back" role="doc-backlink"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn2" role="doc-endnote"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://stackoverflow.com/questions/19305033/why-is-putting-git-repositories-inside-of-a-dropbox-folder-not-recommended"&gt;You don’t want a Git repo sitting inside your Dropbox folder&lt;/a&gt;, but a symlink like this works just fine: you don’t end up with the conflicts that can happen with a full repo in Dropbox.&lt;a href="#fnref2" class="footnote-back" role="doc-backlink"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn3" role="doc-endnote"&gt;&lt;p&gt;I’m hoping to change that a bit in two ways in the future, by having the generator live on a not-my-home-machine server and by making Lighting much easier to just drop in and use than my finicky Pelican setup currently is. But that depends on actually making Lightning, you know, &lt;em&gt;work&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;a href="#fnref3" class="footnote-back" role="doc-backlink"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 06 Jul 2017 21:00:00 -0400</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:v4.chriskrycho.com,2017-07-06:/2017/farewell-dropbox.html</guid><category>writing</category><category>workflow</category></item><item><title>Academic Markdown and Citations</title><link>http://v4.chriskrycho.com/2015/academic-markdown-and-citations.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Much of my past few weeks were taken up with study for and writing and editing &lt;a href="http://v4.chriskrycho.com/2015/not-exactly-a-millennium.html"&gt;a paper&lt;/a&gt; for one of my classes at Southeastern. I’ve been writing all of my papers in Markdown ever since I got here, and haven’t regretted any part of that… except that managing references and footnotes has been painful at times.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Footnotes in Markdown look like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="markdown"&gt;&lt;code&gt;Here is some text.[^fn]

[^fn]: And the footnote!&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This poses no problems at all for normal footnotes. Academic writing introduces a few wrinkles, though, which means that this has always been the main pain point of my use of Markdown for writing papers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many academic citation styles (including the Chicago Manual of Style, on which our seminary’s &lt;a href="http://www.press.uchicago.edu/books/turabian/turabian_citationguide.html"&gt;style guide&lt;/a&gt; is based) tend to have a long version of the footnote appear first, followed by short versions later. Nearly &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; academic citations styles make free use of the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ibid."&gt;“ibid.”&lt;/a&gt; abbreviation for repeated references to save space, time, and energy. Here is how that might look in manually-written footnotes, citing the very paper in which I sorted this all out:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="markdown"&gt;&lt;code&gt;Some text in which I cite an author.[^fn1]

More text. Another citation.[^fn2]

What is this? Yet _another_ citation?[^fn3]

[^fn1]: So Chris Krycho, &amp;quot;Not Exactly a Millennium,&amp;quot; chriskrycho.com, July 22,

2015, http://v4.chriskrycho.com/2015/not-exactly-a-millennium.html
(accessed July 25, 2015), ¶6.
[^fn2]: Contra Krycho, ¶15, who has everything _quite_ wrong.
[^fn3]: ibid.&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This seems straightforward enough, though it is a bit of work to get the format right for each different kind of citation (articles, books, ebooks, electronic references to articles…). Things &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; get complicated in the editing process, though. For example, what if I needed to flip the order of some of these notes because it became clear that the paragraphs needed to move around? This happens &lt;em&gt;frequently&lt;/em&gt; during the editorial process. It becomes particularly painful when dealing with the “ibid.”-type references, because if I insert a new reference between two existing references, I have to go back in and manually add all that the reference content again myself.&lt;a href="#fn1" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref1" role="doc-noteref"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Enter Pandoc and &lt;span class="tex"&gt;BibT&lt;span class="texE"&gt;E&lt;/span&gt;X&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section id="managing-citations" class="level2"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Managing Citations&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The idea of plain-text solutions to academic writing is not especially new; only the application of Markdown to it is—and that, only relatively. People have been doing this, and &lt;a href="http://kieranhealy.org/blog/archives/2014/01/23/plain-text/"&gt;documenting their approaches&lt;/a&gt;, for quite a while. Moreover, tools for managing references and citations have existed for quite some time as well; the entire &lt;a href="http://www.latex-project.org"&gt;L&lt;span class="texA"&gt;A&lt;/span&gt;T&lt;span class="texE"&gt;E&lt;/span&gt;X&lt;/a&gt; toolchain is largely driven by the concerns of academic publishing, and as such there are tools in the &lt;span class="tex"&gt;L&lt;span class="texA"&gt;A&lt;/span&gt;T&lt;span class="texE"&gt;E&lt;/span&gt;X&lt;/span&gt; ecosystem which address many of these problems.&lt;a href="#fn2" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref2" role="doc-noteref"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One such is &lt;span class="tex"&gt;BibT&lt;span class="texE"&gt;E&lt;/span&gt;X&lt;/span&gt;, and the later (more capable) &lt;span class="tex"&gt;BibL&lt;span class="texA"&gt;A&lt;/span&gt;T&lt;span class="texE"&gt;E&lt;/span&gt;X&lt;/span&gt;: tools for managing bibliographies in &lt;span class="tex"&gt;L&lt;span class="texA"&gt;A&lt;/span&gt;T&lt;span class="texE"&gt;E&lt;/span&gt;X&lt;/span&gt; documents. The &lt;span class="tex"&gt;BibT&lt;span class="texE"&gt;E&lt;/span&gt;X&lt;/span&gt;/&lt;span class="tex"&gt;BibL&lt;span class="texA"&gt;A&lt;/span&gt;T&lt;span class="texE"&gt;E&lt;/span&gt;X&lt;/span&gt; approach to managing citations in a document is the use of the &lt;code&gt;\cite&lt;/code&gt; command, with the use of “keys” which map to specific documents: &lt;code&gt;\cite{krycho:2015aa}&lt;/code&gt;, for example.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is not Markdown, of course. But other folks who have an interest in Markdown and academic writing have put their minds to the problem already. Folks such as Jon MacFarlane, the originator and lead developer of &lt;a href="http://pandoc.org"&gt;Pandoc&lt;/a&gt;, perhaps the single most capable text-conversion tool in existence. As it turns out, Pandoc Markdown supports a &lt;a href="http://pandoc.org/README.html#citations"&gt;citation extension&lt;/a&gt; to the basic markup. It’s just a variant on the &lt;span class="tex"&gt;BibT&lt;span class="texE"&gt;E&lt;/span&gt;X&lt;/span&gt; citation style that feels more at home in Markdown: a pair of braces and an &lt;code&gt;@&lt;/code&gt;, plus the citation key, like &lt;code&gt;[@krycho]&lt;/code&gt;. Moreover, Pandoc knows how to use &lt;span class="tex"&gt;BibT&lt;span class="texE"&gt;E&lt;/span&gt;X&lt;/span&gt; libraries, as well as many others, and &lt;a href="http://citationstyles.org"&gt;Citation Style Languages&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;abbr&gt;CSL&lt;/abbr&gt;s) to generate markup in &lt;em&gt;exactly&lt;/em&gt; the format needed for any given citation style.&lt;a href="#fn3" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref3" role="doc-noteref"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instead of writing out all those citations details by hand, then, I can just format my footnotes like this (assuming the citekey I had set up for the article was &lt;code&gt;krycho:revelation:2015&lt;/code&gt;):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="markdown"&gt;&lt;code&gt;Some text in which I cite an author.[^fn1]

More text. Another citation.[^fn2]

What is this? Yet _another_ citation?[^fn3]

[^fn1]: [@krycho:revelation:2015], ¶6.
[^fn2]: Contra [@krycho:revelation:2015], ¶15, who has everything _quite_ wrong.
[^fn3]: [@krycho:revelation:2015].&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is much simpler and, importantly, has the exact same form for each citation. Pandoc will take care of making sure that the first reference is in the long form, later references are in the short form, and repeated references are in the “ibid.” form as appropriate. It even renders a properly sorted and structured Works Cited section.&lt;a href="#fn4" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref4" role="doc-noteref"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;4&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The slightly complex command I used to generate a Word document from a Markdown file with citations (using my own &lt;span class="tex"&gt;BibT&lt;span class="texE"&gt;E&lt;/span&gt;X&lt;/span&gt; library and the Chicago Manual of Style &lt;abbr&gt;CSL&lt;/abbr&gt;) on the command line is:&lt;a href="#fn5" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref5" role="doc-noteref"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;5&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="bash"&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ pandoc revelation.md --smart --standalone \
--bibliography /Users/chris/Documents/writing/library.bib \
--csl=/Users/chris/Documents/writing/chicago.csl -o revelation.docx&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To see an extended sample of this kind of usage in practice, take a look at the &lt;a href="http://v4.chriskrycho.com/2015/not-exactly-a-millennium.txt"&gt;Markdown source&lt;/a&gt; for the paper I wrote last week, using exactly this approach. Every footnote that references a specific source simply has a cite key of this variety. The header metadata includes a path to the bibliography file and a &lt;abbr&gt;CSL&lt;/abbr&gt;. (These could be configured globally, as well, but I chose to specify them on a per-file basis so that if I want or need to use &lt;em&gt;different&lt;/em&gt; styles or a separate library for another file at a later time, I can do so with a minimum of fuss. More on this below.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="/downloads/revelation.docx"&gt;Here&lt;/a&gt; is the rendered result. You can see that it automatically generated everything right down to the “ibid.”-style footnotes. I made a few, fairly minimal tweaks (replacing the search &lt;abbr&gt;URL&lt;/abbr&gt; with an &lt;abbr&gt;ATLA&lt;/abbr&gt; database catalog reference and inserting a section break before the Works Cited list), and turned the paper in—confident, for the first time since I started seminary, that all of the references were in the right order and the right format. With carefully formatted reference documents (with their own style sets),&lt;a href="#fn6" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref6" role="doc-noteref"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;6&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; I was able to generate an actually &lt;em&gt;nice&lt;/em&gt; &lt;abbr&gt;&lt;a href="/downloads/revelation-pretty.pdf"&gt;PDF&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/abbr&gt; version of the paper from another Word document, as well.&lt;a href="#fn7" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref7" role="doc-noteref"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;7&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And, better yet, you don’t even have to put citations in footnotes. As &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/anjdunning"&gt;@anjdunning&lt;/a&gt; pointed out in a &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/anjdunning/status/625415216575197184"&gt;tweet&lt;/a&gt; response to the original version of this post:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.twitter.com/chriskrycho"&gt;@chriskrycho&lt;/a&gt; Don’t put citekeys in a footnote: write everything as inline citations and it will also generate notes when asked by CSL def. &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/anjdunning/status/625415216575197184"&gt;∞&lt;/a&gt; July 26, 2015 17:19&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my standard example from above, then, you could simply do this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="markdown"&gt;&lt;code&gt;Some text in which I cite an author.[@krycho:revelation:2015, ¶6]

More text. Another citation.[Contra @krycho:revelation:2015, ¶15, who has
everything *quite* wrong.]

What is this? Yet _another_ citation?[@krycho:revelation:2015]&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This will generate the same markup for my purposes here; and as &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/anjdunning"&gt;@anjdunning&lt;/a&gt; noted, it goes one step further and does what’s appropriate for the &lt;abbr&gt;CSL&lt;/abbr&gt;. This might be handy if, for example, you wanted to use the Chicago notes-bibliography style in one format, but switch to a simpler parenthetical citation style for a different medium—or even if you had a paper to submit to different journals with different standards. Having the citations inline thus has many advantages.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, there are still times when you might want to split those out into distinct footnotes, of course. That second one is a good candidate, at least for the way I tend to structure my plain-text source. I find it useful in the case of &lt;em&gt;actual&lt;/em&gt; footnote content—i.e. text that I’m intentionally leaving aside from the main text, even with reference to other authors—to split it out from the main flow of the paragraph, so that someone reading the plain text source gets a similar effect to someone reading the web or Word or &lt;abbr&gt;PDF&lt;/abbr&gt; versions, with the text removed from the flow of thought. In any case, it’s quite nice that Pandoc has the power and flexibility such that you don’t &lt;em&gt;have&lt;/em&gt; to.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, you don’t actually &lt;em&gt;need&lt;/em&gt; the brackets around the citekey, depending on how you’re using the reference. If you wanted to cite the relevant author inline, you can—and it will properly display both the inline name and a reference (footnote, parenthetical, etc.) in line with the &lt;abbr&gt;CSL&lt;/abbr&gt; you’ve chosen. If I were going to quote myself in a paper, I would do something like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="markdown"&gt;&lt;code&gt;As @krycho:revelation:2015 comments:

&amp;gt; This was a hard paper to write.&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is &lt;em&gt;extremely&lt;/em&gt; powerful, and while I didn’t take advantage of it in my first paper using these tools, you can bet I will be in every future paper I write.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section id="all-those-references" class="level3"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;All those references&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, as is probably apparent, managing a &lt;span class="tex"&gt;BibT&lt;span class="texE"&gt;E&lt;/span&gt;X&lt;/span&gt; library by hand is no joke. Entries tend to look like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="tex"&gt;&lt;code&gt;@book{beale:revelation:2015,
        Date-Added = {2015-07-20 21:16:02 +0000},
        Date-Modified = {2015-07-20 21:21:05 +0000},
        Editor = {G. K. Beale and David H. Campbell},
        Publisher = {William B. Eerdmans Publishing Company},
        Title = {Revelation: A Shorter Commentary},
        Year = {2015}}&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While there is a lot of utility in having that data available in text, on disk, no one wants to &lt;em&gt;edit&lt;/em&gt; that by hand.&lt;a href="#fn8" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref8" role="doc-noteref"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;8&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; Gladly, editing it by hand is not necessary. For this project, I used the freely available &lt;a href="http://bibdesk.sourceforge.net"&gt;BibDesk&lt;/a&gt; tool, which is a workable (albeit not very pretty and not &lt;em&gt;very&lt;/em&gt; capable) manager for &lt;span class="tex"&gt;BibT&lt;span class="texE"&gt;E&lt;/span&gt;X&lt;/span&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src="//cdn.chriskrycho.com/images/bibdesk.png" title="Not very pretty, but it does work" alt="BibDesk – open to the library for my Revelation paper" /&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;BibDesk – open to the library for my Revelation paper&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once I filled in the details for each item and set a citekey for it, I was ready to go: BibDesk just stores the files in a standard &lt;code&gt;.bib&lt;/code&gt; file on the disk, which I specified per the Pandoc command above.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;BibDesk gets the job done alright, but only alright. Using a citation and reference management tool was a big win, though, and I fully intend to use one for every remaining project while in seminary—and, quite possibly, for other projects as well. Whether that tool is BibDesk or something else is a different matter entirely. (More on this below.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="to-the-web" class="level2"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;To the web!&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wanted something more out of this process, if I could get it. One of the reasons I use plain text as a source is because from it, I can generate Word documents, &lt;abbr&gt;PDF&lt;/abbr&gt;s, and &lt;em&gt;this website&lt;/em&gt; with equal ease. However, Python Markdown knows nothing of &lt;span class="tex"&gt;BibT&lt;span class="texE"&gt;E&lt;/span&gt;X&lt;/span&gt; or citekeys, to my knowledge—and since I render everything for school with Pandoc, I have long wanted to configure &lt;a href="http://docs.getpelican.com/en/3.6.0/"&gt;Pelican&lt;/a&gt; to use Pandoc as its Markdown engine instead of Python Markdown anyway.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As it happens, I actually set this up about a month ago. The process was pretty simple:&lt;a href="#fn9" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref9" role="doc-noteref"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;9&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol type="1"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I installed the &lt;a href="https://github.com/jstvz/pelican-pandoc-reader"&gt;pandoc-reader&lt;/a&gt; Pelican extension.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I set the plugin path in my Pelican configuration file.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I specified the arguments to Pelican I wanted to use.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The only additional tweaks necessary to get citation support were calling it with the &lt;code&gt;'--filter pandoc-citeproc'&lt;/code&gt; arguments, which lets it process any bibliography data supplied in the header metadata for the files. Calling Pandoc with &lt;code&gt;--bibliography &amp;lt;path to bibliography&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; (as in my example above) is a &lt;a href="http://pandoc.org/README.html#citation-rendering"&gt;shortcut&lt;/a&gt; for calling it with &lt;code&gt;--metadata &amp;lt;path to bibliography&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; the &lt;code&gt;--filter pandoc-citeproc&lt;/code&gt; arguments. I could just supply the bibliography directly in the call from Pelican, but this would limit me to using a single bibliography file for &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; of my posts—something I’d rather not limit myself to, since it might make sense to build up bibliographies around specific subjects, or even to have smaller bibliographies associated with each project (exported from the main bibliography), which could then be freely available along with the contents of the paper itself.&lt;a href="#fn10" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref10" role="doc-noteref"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;10&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (On this idea, see a bit more below under &lt;strong&gt;The Future&lt;/strong&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One word of warning: Pandoc is much slower to generate &lt;abbr&gt;HTML&lt;/abbr&gt; with &lt;code&gt;--filter pandoc-citeproc&lt;/code&gt; than &lt;em&gt;without&lt;/em&gt; the filter, and the larger your site, the more you will feel this. (The time to generate the site from scratch jumped from about 10s to about 30s for me, with 270 articles, 17 drafts, 2 pages, and 1 hidden page, according to Pelican.) Pandoc has to process &lt;em&gt;every&lt;/em&gt; article to check for citations, and that’s no small task. However, if you have Pelican’s content caching turned on, this is a one-time event. After that, it will only be processing any new content with it; total generation time is back down where it was before for me: the effort is all in generating the large indexes I use to display the content for the landing pages and for category and tag archives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And the result: that same paper, rendered to &lt;abbr&gt;HTML&lt;/abbr&gt; &lt;a href="http://v4.chriskrycho.com/2015/not-exactly-a-millennium.html"&gt;on my website&lt;/a&gt;, with citations and works cited, generated automatically and beautifully.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section id="other-site-generators" class="level3"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Other site generators&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don’t know the situation around using Pandoc itself in other generators, including Jekyll—I simply haven’t looked. I do know, however, that there &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; some tooling for Jekyll specifically to allow a similar workflow. If you’re using Jekyll, it looks like your best bet is to check out &lt;a href="https://github.com/inukshuk/jekyll-scholar"&gt;jekyll-scholar&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a href="https://github.com/inukshuk/citeproc-ruby"&gt;citeproc-ruby&lt;/a&gt; project, which (like pandoc-citeproc) enables you to embed citations and filter them through &lt;abbr&gt;CSL&lt;/abbr&gt;s to generate references automatically. As a note: you should definitely be able to get those working on your own deployment sites, but I have no idea whether it’s possible to do them with the GitHub Pages variant of Jekyll. (If anyone who reads this knows the answer to that, let me know on Twitter or App.net, and I’ll update the post accordingly.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="the-future" class="level2"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The future&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition to continuing to use &lt;span class="tex"&gt;BibT&lt;span class="texE"&gt;E&lt;/span&gt;X&lt;/span&gt; with BibDesk as a way of managing my citations in the short term, I’m thinking about other ways to improve this workflow. One possibility is integrating with &lt;a href="http://scholdoc.scholarlymarkdown.com"&gt;Scholdoc&lt;/a&gt; as it matures, instead of &lt;a href="http://pandoc.org"&gt;pandoc&lt;/a&gt;, and maybe (hopefully, albeit unlikely) even contributing to it somewhat. I’m also open to using other citation library tools, though my early explorations with Mendeley and Zotero did not particularly impress me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are substantial advantages for the applications (and thus for most users) to maintaining the data in an application-specific format (e.g. an SQLite database) rather than on the file system—but the latter has the advantage of making it much easier to integrate with other tools. However, Zotero and Mendeley both natively export to &lt;span class="tex"&gt;BibT&lt;span class="texE"&gt;E&lt;/span&gt;X&lt;/span&gt; format, and Mendeley natively supports &lt;a href="http://blog.mendeley.com/tipstricks/howto-use-mendeley-to-create-citations-using-latex-and-bibtex/"&gt;sync&lt;/a&gt; to a &lt;span class="tex"&gt;BibT&lt;span class="texE"&gt;E&lt;/span&gt;X&lt;/span&gt; library (Zotero can do the same, but via third-party &lt;a href="https://zoteromusings.wordpress.com/tag/bibtex/"&gt;plugins&lt;/a&gt;), so those remain viable options, which I may use for future projects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also want to look at making my library of resources available publicly, perhaps (a) as a standalone library associated with each project, so that anyone who wants to can download it along with the Markdown source to play with as an example and (b) as a general library covering my various reading and research interests, which will certainly be irrelevant to most people but might nonetheless provide some value to someone along the way. I’m a big fan of making this kind of data open wherever possible, because people come up with neat things to do with it that the original creators never expect. Not &lt;em&gt;everything&lt;/em&gt; should be open—but lots of things should, and this might be among them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="summary" class="level2"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m pretty happy with the current state of affairs, the aforementioned interest in other reference managers notwithstanding:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I can set up the citations &lt;em&gt;once&lt;/em&gt;, in a tool designed to manage references, instead of multiple times in multiple places.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I can use Pandoc and a &lt;abbr&gt;CSL&lt;/abbr&gt; to get the citations formatted correctly throughout a paper, including generating the bibliography automatically.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I can use the same tooling, integrated into my static site generator, to build a web version of the content—with no extra effort, once I configured it properly the first time.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perhaps most importantly, this helps me meet one of my major goals for all my writing: to have a single canonical &lt;em&gt;source&lt;/em&gt; for the content, which I will be able to access in the future regardless of what operating system I am using or what publishing systems come and go. Simple plain text files—Markdown—get me there. Now I’ve put good tools around that process, and I love it even more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn1" role="doc-endnote"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Coming up with names for footnotes in Markdown can be painful in general for long documents. If you try to name them manually, like I do for posts on my website, you will very quickly end up wasting time on the names. If you try to number them, they will end up out of order in a hurry. My own &lt;a href="http://2012-2013.chriskrycho.com/web/markdown-and-academic-writing/"&gt;previous solution&lt;/a&gt; to this problem quickly became unwieldy for larger papers, and required a &lt;em&gt;lot&lt;/em&gt; of hand-editing. Gladly, I no longer deal with that manually. Instead, I do all my drafting in &lt;a href="http://www.ulyssesapp.com"&gt;Ulysses&lt;/a&gt;, where you just type &lt;code&gt;(fn)&lt;/code&gt; and it creates a footnote automatically, and will move that footnote &lt;em&gt;object&lt;/em&gt; around transparently as you edit, handling all the number-setting, etc. on its own.&lt;a href="#fnref1" class="footnote-back" role="doc-backlink"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn2" role="doc-endnote"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The irony of site for software which boasts that it is “a high-quality typesetting system” and looks like &lt;a href="http://www.latex-project.org"&gt;&lt;em&gt;this&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; is not lost on me…&lt;a href="#fnref2" class="footnote-back" role="doc-backlink"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn3" role="doc-endnote"&gt;&lt;p&gt;If you used the installers on Pandoc’s website, &lt;code&gt;pandoc-citeproc&lt;/code&gt; comes with it. If you installed it via a package manager (e.g. by running &lt;code&gt;brew install pandoc&lt;/code&gt;), it may not have, so you’ll need to install it manually yourself (e.g. &lt;code&gt;brew install pandoc-citeproc&lt;/code&gt;).&lt;a href="#fnref3" class="footnote-back" role="doc-backlink"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn4" role="doc-endnote"&gt;&lt;p&gt;All of the content, including the rendered footnotes and the bibliography, has sensible content types set on it: headers are headers, body text is body text, etc. You can then customize to match the specifications of your style guide. I have a Chicago/Turabian style set set up with the formatting rules to match.&lt;a href="#fnref4" class="footnote-back" role="doc-backlink"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn5" role="doc-endnote"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Actually, it was even hairier than this, because I also had a &lt;code&gt;--reference-docx path/to/template.docx&lt;/code&gt; specified. If you think it’s perhaps a bit too complex, well, I agree. I plan to turn that into a command line alias in pretty short order, because remembering it every time is just not going to happen.&lt;a href="#fnref5" class="footnote-back" role="doc-backlink"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn6" role="doc-endnote"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Using the &lt;code&gt;--reference-docx&lt;/code&gt; argument to Pandoc, you can hand it a document that already uses your desired style set, so you don’t have to go in and apply it manually.&lt;a href="#fnref6" class="footnote-back" role="doc-backlink"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn7" role="doc-endnote"&gt;&lt;p&gt;I could have done that with Pandoc’s &lt;span class="tex"&gt;L&lt;span class="texA"&gt;A&lt;/span&gt;T&lt;span class="texE"&gt;E&lt;/span&gt;X&lt;/span&gt; &lt;abbr&gt;PDF&lt;/abbr&gt; tools, as well, but didn’t really feel like taking the time to tweak the &lt;span class="tex"&gt;L&lt;span class="texA"&gt;A&lt;/span&gt;T&lt;span class="texE"&gt;E&lt;/span&gt;X&lt;/span&gt; template for it.&lt;a href="#fnref7" class="footnote-back" role="doc-backlink"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn8" role="doc-endnote"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Probably someone does, but not me, and not most people!&lt;a href="#fnref8" class="footnote-back" role="doc-backlink"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn9" role="doc-endnote"&gt;&lt;p&gt;If you’re using Pelican, you can take a look at my Pelican configuration file &lt;a href="https://github.com/chriskrycho/chriskrycho.com/blob/ef3ecbca1765750392086355aeae026c1159d4b9/pelicanconf.py#L109"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the full configuration for using Pandoc this way.&lt;a href="#fnref9" class="footnote-back" role="doc-backlink"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn10" role="doc-endnote"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Optimally, I’d really just prefer to be able to set &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; of these arguments at a per-file level—i.e., not use &lt;code&gt;--filter pandoc cite-proc&lt;/code&gt; unless the file actually specifies a bibliography. And I could hack Pelican to do that; I’ve actually already &lt;a href="https://github.com/liob/pandoc_reader/pull/5"&gt;messed around&lt;/a&gt; with other, semi-related bits regarding Pelican and Pandoc’s shared handling of &lt;abbr&gt;YAML&lt;/abbr&gt; metadata. But I’d prefer to keep my installation as “vanilla” as possible to minimize the cost of setting things up again on a new machine or after a crash, etc.&lt;a href="#fnref10" class="footnote-back" role="doc-backlink"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 26 Jul 2015 13:50:00 -0400</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:v4.chriskrycho.com,2015-07-26:/2015/academic-markdown-and-citations.html</guid><category>workflow</category><category>writing</category></item></channel></rss>