<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Chris Krycho - work</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/</link><description></description><lastBuildDate>Sun, 15 Jul 2018 17:15:00 -0400</lastBuildDate><item><title>Some Mild Burnout</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2018/some-mild-burnout.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;I came to terms with reality a bit last week. It wasn’t fun. I concluded something attentive folks around me have likely known for a bit: I am dealing with low-level &lt;a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/healthy-lifestyle/adult-health/in-depth/burnout/art-20046642" title="The Mayo Clinic’s summary of burnout"&gt;burnout&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Have you become cynical or critical at work?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do you drag yourself to work and have trouble getting started once you arrive?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Have you become irritable or impatient with co-workers, customers or clients?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do you lack the energy to be consistently productive?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do you lack satisfaction from your achievements?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do you feel disillusioned about your job?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Are you using food, drugs or alcohol to feel better or to simply not feel?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Have your sleep habits or appetite changed?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Are you troubled by unexplained headaches, backaches or other physical complaints?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Mayo Clinic (the source for that list) notes that if you’re suffering from any &lt;em&gt;one&lt;/em&gt; of those, you may be experiencing burnout. By my count, I am experiencing &lt;em&gt;six&lt;/em&gt;. If you’re looking at the list and wondering: the first six. No changes to sleep, no abuse of food or drugs or alcohol, and I haven’t started having physical problems yet, which is why I classify what I’m experiencing as low-level or mild. But burnout is tricky. I’ve know a number of people who’ve had more serious cases—cases which led into significant physical problems that took them years to recover from.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my experience, when people think about burnout, they tend to think of the kind that comes from &lt;em&gt;overwork&lt;/em&gt; or from a lack of rest. You certainly can (indeed: certainly will) burn out by pulling 80-hour weeks for years on end. But those are not the only way you can burn out. You can also do it by ending up in a spot where you have too much responsibility, or deep and lasting conflict within your working environment, or sharp ethical disagreements with your leadership, or even just—“just” being the wrong word here—lasting mismatches between your tasks and the things you care about.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The particular reasons for my mild case of burnout aren’t the stereotypical kind. I get plenty of sleep, I enjoy my hobbies, I exercise and eat well, and I very carefully maintain a limit on the hours I work every week. I’m not &lt;em&gt;overworked&lt;/em&gt;. It’s a mix of other factors I won’t go into. The details aren’t actually that important here, and in any case my (genuinely excellent) manager knows them well and we are working on them together.&lt;a href="#fn1" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref1"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What is important is trying to figure out how to keep the burnout from getting worse. And acknowledging that it can happen to anyone. And that you may not see it coming, may deny you’re experiencing till something finally makes it click for you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What made this all finally click for me? It was &lt;a href="http://www.alliancenet.org/mos/postcards-from-palookaville/six-years-on#.W0vQM4pMFvI" title="Six Years On"&gt;this post by Carl Trueman&lt;/a&gt;, reflecting on his own &lt;em&gt;very&lt;/em&gt; different vocation—specifically, his bivocational work as both a pastor and a professor:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A few months into my pastorate, an academic friend who had done the same thing for nine years wrote me a letter and urged me to be careful – as soon as I ceased to enjoy the hobbies and casual pleasures of life, he warned, I would be close to burn-out and would need to step down. I was glad of the warning – every minister I have ever know who has burned out has told me that there was no obvious warning: one day everything seemed fine, the next they were barely able to get out of bed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That started me thinking on my own experience, and if I’m not quite there, I can see warning signs. The biggest danger sign, for me, is an utter lack of motivation around some of my hobbies. I generally relax, as my wife can attest, in &lt;em&gt;weird&lt;/em&gt; ways—by writing, by building an open-source library, by reading hard-and-interesting books. For the last several months, I have had almost no interest in doing any of that. So I’ve a mild case at the moment, and I’m doing everything I can to keep it from getting worse.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Burnout like I have right now is not the end of the world, to be clear. It &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; manageable. Many people—including people in my own family—carry much more significant burdens in terms of physical and mental health. But it is real, and it’s dangerous in no small part because it can cascade into really serious mental and physical health problems if you let it spiral out of control.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, two things:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol type="1"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;If I’m a bit slower on open-source projects for a while, you know why.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I’d like to be that blog post for someone else. If you’re experiencing the things on that list, figure out how to change &lt;em&gt;something&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;section class="footnotes"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn1"&gt;&lt;p&gt;You can assume that it’s not sharp conflict over ethical issues, because nothing in the world would make me jet from a job faster than that would&lt;a href="#fnref1" class="footnote-back"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 15 Jul 2018 17:15:00 -0400</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2018-07-15:/2018/some-mild-burnout.html</guid><category>burnout</category><category>work</category><category>productivity</category></item><item><title>Strategies for Maintaining Motivation</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2018/strategies-for-maintaining-motivation.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;A thing I’ve been thinking about a bit over the last few weeks is how to sustain motivation as you come into the “this no longer holds any intrinsic interest for me” phase of a project. I have a couple of these on my plate right now, but I also want to &lt;a href="http://esv.to/col3.23" title="Colossians 3:23"&gt;do my work well&lt;/a&gt;. Here I’m jotting down a couple of the strategies I’ve been taking so far; I’ll probably have another post like this in roughly six months when these particular projects are wrapped up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section id="section" class="level2"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;– 1. –&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Find related problems you can solve that support the effort or the team, which &lt;em&gt;are&lt;/em&gt; intrinsically interesting.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you keep your eyes open, you can sometimes find problems which don’t &lt;em&gt;directly&lt;/em&gt; advance the project you’re working on, but which both &lt;em&gt;indirectly&lt;/em&gt; advance the project and also give you something to work on when you need a break. In my context, this looks like small but broadly-useful pieces of developer tooling.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example: we’re in a spot where we’re spinning up a number of new applications in a given framework and stack. After getting through everything else on my plate this last Friday, I took a couple hours and started putting together a little tool that will make the major part of that process a single command-line invocation. This doesn’t directly advance the project I’m working on. But it &lt;em&gt;will&lt;/em&gt; be useful for our whole team over the next six months.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another example here for me is identifying technical initiatives we need, and taking the time to think through how we can accomplish them. These are real problems that we really need to solve, and even if we don’t need them solved &lt;em&gt;today&lt;/em&gt; (because we’re prioritizing other things), there is a lot of value in figuring out we’ll solve them when we &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt; get to them in a few months.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Both of those kinds of things can help by giving a sense of accomplishment while simultaneously doing something &lt;em&gt;besides&lt;/em&gt; the main task, but they don’t require huge blocks of time or keep you from getting the main project done. And they &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt; advance your team or your project in some sense.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="section-1" class="level2"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;– 2. –&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Find tasks which are &lt;em&gt;totally unrelated&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;instrincically interesting&lt;/em&gt;, but which do not keep you from getting your main job done.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is kind of like the previous task except that it may or may not even be related to what you’re working on. I have a couple pieces of technology work that I variously have started and will be starting that are totally unrelated to my main projects. But they’re things that I can go after a bit here and a bit there – the last half hour of a day when my brain is shot, or over lunch, or for a few hours when I’ve finished everything else on my plate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These kinds of things help me by serving as a &lt;em&gt;reward&lt;/em&gt; for getting through the stuff I need to get through. They thus provide a kind of extrinsic motivation where my intrinsic motivation has flagged. They also have enough intrinsic interest of their own that I can feel some of that very helpful sense of accomplishing something I care about when I make progress on them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s important that these things fit the profile I described, though: easy to move forward in small chunks of time, and okay to take a long while to finish. The danger with these–even more than with the first kind of small tasks I suggested–is that they &lt;em&gt;are&lt;/em&gt; so interesting, and you have to make sure you &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt; still get your regular work done.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="section-2" class="level2"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;– 3. –&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Find ways to gain a sense of &lt;em&gt;momentum.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This one is in some ways the hardest of these, because it’s just digging in deeper on the slog of the project in question–but it’s also the one that most directly gets you closer to the end of the project. The trick is to find a rhythm where you actually move meaningfully closer to the goal of &lt;em&gt;finishing the project&lt;/em&gt; all the time, while not ending up bogged down in nothing but slogs along the way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A big part of this is figuring out how to break up the project into smaller and more tractable pieces, and then alternating the various elements of it in such a way that you can continually feel the satisfaction of finishing things. Over the last two weeks at work, despite some pretty significant frustrations which made it really hard to do this, I came out with more of a sense of momentum than I had even before those frustrations came up–precisely because I actually knocked out the things we aimed to get done in that specific span of time. And we’re in a spot where we’re actually about to go live with the first meaningful chunk of what we’ve been building.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Keeping that sense of momentum is really important. Even when you’re looking at a 6-month stretch of not-that-interesting a set of work ahead of you, it helps to see yourself chipping away at it and making real progress.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="section-3" class="level2"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;– 4. –&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Just watch &lt;a href="https://m.youtube.com/watch?v=sl9pTDK8PAk"&gt;this sequence from Doctor Who Series 9&lt;/a&gt; over and over again.&lt;/strong&gt; Or better yet, the whole episode.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe title="Breaking the Wall (Doctor Who Series 9 Episode 11)" width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/sl9pTDK8PAk?rel=0" frameborder="0" allow="autoplay; encrypted-media" allowfullscreen&gt;
&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Personally, I think that’s a hell of a bird.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 03 Jun 2018 11:00:00 -0400</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2018-06-03:/2018/strategies-for-maintaining-motivation.html</guid><category>productivity</category><category>work</category></item><item><title>Vacation as Helpful Reminder</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2018/vacation-as-helpful-reminder.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;One very helpful reminder provided by taking time off: I am not &lt;em&gt;indispensable&lt;/em&gt; to my team; I am &lt;em&gt;valuable&lt;/em&gt; to my team. Those are not the same thing.&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 09 May 2018 21:00:00 -0400</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2018-05-09:/2018/vacation-as-helpful-reminder.html</guid><category>work</category></item><item><title>Career Trajectory</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2018/career-trajectory.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;I’ve been thinking a bit, for the last year or so, about my &lt;em&gt;career trajectory&lt;/em&gt;. Where do I want to go, and what do I want to do, over the next 5–10 years?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the first seven years or so of my working life, I was just learning everything I could in software, following my interests but without much of a conscious plan, and making sure I put food on the table for my family. And I think that was absolutely the right tack to take! I &lt;em&gt;did&lt;/em&gt; learn a ton, across a relatively wide swath of the industry. I have worked:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;as a cog in megacorporation with over 100,000 employees, writing C targeting a real-time operating system;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;as the sole dedicated software developer in a company where I was the 12th employee, maintaining decades-old Fortran and C and C++ and writing a fair bit of Python in a scientific computing and physics modeling context;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;as a subcontractor for a small consultancy doing PHP and jQuery and (both My- and Postgre)SQL;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;as a solo consultant on projects ranging from WordPress setups to building a small but non-trivial application front-to-back in JavaScript;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;and, most lately, at a VC-funded startup in the very-tricky scale-up phase, writing JavaScript, TypeScript, and a smidge of C&lt;sup&gt;♯&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a result, I’ve seen nearly every part of the stack to some degree—from writing a lex/yacc parser spike for a one-off assembly language to building rich browser client applications—and I’ve seen a lot of the kinds of companies that exist in our industry. I’ve also seen (and created!) a pretty remarkable amount of tech debt.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All of which means that, at 30 (almost 31!) and about a year from the end of my first decade in this industry, I’m starting to have a pretty good sense of the things I like, the things I don’t, and some of the directions I might like to go in the future.&lt;a href="#fn1" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref1"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; It actually feels a little odd, precisely &lt;em&gt;because&lt;/em&gt; I just went where my interests and reasonably good opportunities appeared.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But it’s also important. I know better now than I did a decade ago the things that bring me joy and the places where I’m best equipped to contribute effectively to a team. (I am of course also far better equipped to contribute effectively to a team than I was when I started!) I find that I care enormously about what to build as well as how to build it—my instincts and interests seem to be roughly 25% product person, 25% mentor and teacher, and 50% individual contributor, with a particular interest in building enabling tools for others.&lt;a href="#fn2" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref2"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; I have no idea where that will take me in the future, and I’m working closely with my (really excellent) manager at Olo to find ways to both use and develop those effectively where I am.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are two upshots to all of this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol type="1"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;If you’re a young developer (or, &lt;em&gt;probably&lt;/em&gt;, early on in almost any field), getting as varied—but not shallow!—experience you can in the early years is incredibly valuable. That goes double if you’re coming in from a “non-traditional” background as I did, because it’s a great way to get exposed practically to a lot of the different parts of software and to computer science ideas you won’t if you stay in just one spot. That’s obviously a hard luxury to come by in some ways, but if you &lt;em&gt;can&lt;/em&gt; manage it, it pays huge dividends.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I’m happy to be starting to have a sense of &lt;em&gt;direction&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;trajectory&lt;/em&gt;. I’m in the early stages of that, though; I’m curious to see what I sort out in conversation with Jaimie and my church community and others I trust, as well as my leadership at Olo, over the next year.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;section class="footnotes"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn1"&gt;&lt;p&gt;To be clear to any fellow &lt;a href="https://www.olo.com"&gt;Olo&lt;/a&gt;-ers who might read this: I’m not planning to go anywhere soon. This isn’t &lt;em&gt;that&lt;/em&gt; kind of post.&lt;a href="#fnref1" class="footnote-back"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn2"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Hello, &lt;a href="https://newrustacean.com"&gt;New Rustacean&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://github.com/typed-ember/ember-cli-typescript"&gt;ember-cli-typescript&lt;/a&gt;…&lt;a href="#fnref2" class="footnote-back"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 02 May 2018 07:00:00 -0400</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2018-05-02:/2018/career-trajectory.html</guid><category>work</category><category>software development</category><category>career</category></item></channel></rss>