<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Chris Krycho</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/</link><description></description><atom:link href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/feeds/writing.xml" rel="self"></atom:link><lastBuildDate>Sun, 26 Jul 2015 13:50:00 -0400</lastBuildDate><item><title>Academic Markdown and Citations</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2015/academic-markdown-and-citations.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Much of my past few weeks were taken up with study for and writing and editing &lt;a href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2015/not-exactly-a-millennium.html"&gt;a paper&lt;/a&gt; for one of my classes at Southeastern. I’ve been writing all of my papers in Markdown ever since I got here, and haven’t regretted any part of that… except that managing references and footnotes has been painful at times.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Footnotes in Markdown look like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="markdown"&gt;&lt;code&gt;Here is some text.[^fn]

[^fn]: And the footnote!&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This poses no problems at all for normal footnotes. Academic writing introduces a few wrinkles, though, which means that this has always been the main pain point of my use of Markdown for writing papers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many academic citation styles (including the Chicago Manual of Style, on which our seminary’s &lt;a href="http://www.press.uchicago.edu/books/turabian/turabian_citationguide.html"&gt;style guide&lt;/a&gt; is based) tend to have a long version of the footnote appear first, followed by short versions later. Nearly &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; academic citations styles make free use of the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ibid."&gt;“ibid.”&lt;/a&gt; abbreviation for repeated references to save space, time, and energy. Here is how that might look in manually-written footnotes, citing the very paper in which I sorted this all out:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="markdown"&gt;&lt;code&gt;Some text in which I cite an author.[^fn1]

More text. Another citation.[^fn2]

What is this? Yet *another* citation?[^fn3]

[^fn1]: So Chris Krycho, &amp;quot;Not Exactly a Millennium,&amp;quot; chriskrycho.com, July 22,
    2015, http://www.chriskrycho.com/2015/not-exactly-a-millennium.html
    (accessed July 25, 2015), ¶6.

[^fn2]: Contra Krycho, ¶15, who has everything *quite* wrong.

[^fn3]: ibid.&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This seems straightforward enough, though it is a bit of work to get the format right for each different kind of citation (articles, books, ebooks, electronic references to articles…). Things &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; get complicated in the editing process, though. For example, what if I needed to flip the order of some of these notes because it became clear that the paragraphs needed to move around? This happens &lt;em&gt;frequently&lt;/em&gt; during the editorial process. It becomes particularly painful when dealing with the “ibid.”-type references, because if I insert a new reference between two existing references, I have to go back in and manually add all that the reference content again myself.&lt;a href="#fn1" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref1"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Enter Pandoc and &lt;span class="tex"&gt;BibT&lt;span class="texE"&gt;E&lt;/span&gt;X&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section id="managing-citations" class="level2"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Managing Citations&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The idea of plain-text solutions to academic writing is not especially new; only the application of Markdown to it is—and that, only relatively. People have been doing this, and &lt;a href="http://kieranhealy.org/blog/archives/2014/01/23/plain-text/"&gt;documenting their approaches&lt;/a&gt;, for quite a while. Moreover, tools for managing references and citations have existed for quite some time as well; the entire &lt;a href="http://www.latex-project.org"&gt;L&lt;span class="texA"&gt;A&lt;/span&gt;T&lt;span class="texE"&gt;E&lt;/span&gt;X&lt;/a&gt; toolchain is largely driven by the concerns of academic publishing, and as such there are tools in the &lt;span class="tex"&gt;L&lt;span class="texA"&gt;A&lt;/span&gt;T&lt;span class="texE"&gt;E&lt;/span&gt;X&lt;/span&gt; ecosystem which address many of these problems.&lt;a href="#fn2" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref2"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One such is &lt;span class="tex"&gt;BibT&lt;span class="texE"&gt;E&lt;/span&gt;X&lt;/span&gt;, and the later (more capable) &lt;span class="tex"&gt;BibL&lt;span class="texA"&gt;A&lt;/span&gt;T&lt;span class="texE"&gt;E&lt;/span&gt;X&lt;/span&gt;: tools for managing bibliographies in &lt;span class="tex"&gt;L&lt;span class="texA"&gt;A&lt;/span&gt;T&lt;span class="texE"&gt;E&lt;/span&gt;X&lt;/span&gt; documents. The &lt;span class="tex"&gt;BibT&lt;span class="texE"&gt;E&lt;/span&gt;X&lt;/span&gt;/&lt;span class="tex"&gt;BibL&lt;span class="texA"&gt;A&lt;/span&gt;T&lt;span class="texE"&gt;E&lt;/span&gt;X&lt;/span&gt; approach to managing citations in a document is the use of the &lt;code&gt;\cite&lt;/code&gt; command, with the use of “keys” which map to specific documents: &lt;code&gt;\cite{krycho:2015aa}&lt;/code&gt;, for example.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is not Markdown, of course. But other folks who have an interest in Markdown and academic writing have put their minds to the problem already. Folks such as Jon MacFarlane, the originator and lead developer of &lt;a href="http://pandoc.org"&gt;Pandoc&lt;/a&gt;, perhaps the single most capable text-conversion tool in existence. As it turns out, Pandoc Markdown supports a &lt;a href="http://pandoc.org/README.html#citations"&gt;citation extension&lt;/a&gt; to the basic markup. It’s just a variant on the &lt;span class="tex"&gt;BibT&lt;span class="texE"&gt;E&lt;/span&gt;X&lt;/span&gt; citation style that feels more at home in Markdown: a pair of braces and an &lt;code&gt;@&lt;/code&gt;, plus the citation key, like &lt;code&gt;[@krycho]&lt;/code&gt;. Moreover, Pandoc knows how to use &lt;span class="tex"&gt;BibT&lt;span class="texE"&gt;E&lt;/span&gt;X&lt;/span&gt; libraries, as well as many others, and &lt;a href="http://citationstyles.org"&gt;Citation Style Languages&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;abbr&gt;CSL&lt;/abbr&gt;s) to generate markup in &lt;em&gt;exactly&lt;/em&gt; the format needed for any given citation style.&lt;a href="#fn3" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref3"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instead of writing out all those citations details by hand, then, I can just format my footnotes like this (assuming the citekey I had set up for the article was &lt;code&gt;krycho:revelation:2015&lt;/code&gt;):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="markdown"&gt;&lt;code&gt;Some text in which I cite an author.[^fn1]

More text. Another citation.[^fn2]

What is this? Yet *another* citation?[^fn3]

[^fn1]: [@krycho:revelation:2015], ¶6.

[^fn2]: Contra [@krycho:revelation:2015], ¶15, who has everything *quite* wrong.

[^fn3]: [@krycho:revelation:2015].&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is much simpler and, importantly, has the exact same form for each citation. Pandoc will take care of making sure that the first reference is in the long form, later references are in the short form, and repeated references are in the “ibid.” form as appropriate. It even renders a properly sorted and structured Works Cited section.&lt;a href="#fn4" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref4"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;4&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The slightly complex command I used to generate a Word document from a Markdown file with citations (using my own &lt;span class="tex"&gt;BibT&lt;span class="texE"&gt;E&lt;/span&gt;X&lt;/span&gt; library and the Chicago Manual of Style &lt;abbr&gt;CSL&lt;/abbr&gt;) on the command line is:&lt;a href="#fn5" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref5"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;5&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="bash"&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ pandoc revelation.md --smart --standalone \
--bibliography /Users/chris/Dropbox/writing/library.bib \
--csl=/Users/chris/Dropbox/writing/chicago.csl -o revelation.docx&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To see an extended sample of this kind of usage in practice, take a look at the &lt;a href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2015/not-exactly-a-millennium.txt"&gt;Markdown source&lt;/a&gt; for the paper I wrote last week, using exactly this approach. Every footnote that references a specific source simply has a cite key of this variety. The header metadata includes a path to the bibliography file and a &lt;abbr&gt;CSL&lt;/abbr&gt;. (These could be configured globally, as well, but I chose to specify them on a per-file basis so that if I want or need to use &lt;em&gt;different&lt;/em&gt; styles or a separate library for another file at a later time, I can do so with a minimum of fuss. More on this below.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="/downloads/revelation.docx"&gt;Here&lt;/a&gt; is the rendered result. You can see that it automatically generated everything right down to the “ibid.”-style footnotes. I made a few, fairly minimal tweaks (replacing the search &lt;abbr&gt;URL&lt;/abbr&gt; with an &lt;abbr&gt;ATLA&lt;/abbr&gt; database catalog reference and inserting a section break before the Works Cited list), and turned the paper in—confident, for the first time since I started seminary, that all of the references were in the right order and the right format. With carefully formatted reference documents (with their own style sets),&lt;a href="#fn6" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref6"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;6&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; I was able to generate an actually &lt;em&gt;nice&lt;/em&gt; &lt;abbr&gt;&lt;a href="/downloads/revelation-pretty.pdf"&gt;PDF&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/abbr&gt; version of the paper from another Word document, as well.&lt;a href="#fn7" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref7"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;7&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section id="all-those-references" class="level3"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;All those references&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, as is probably apparent, managing a &lt;span class="tex"&gt;BibT&lt;span class="texE"&gt;E&lt;/span&gt;X&lt;/span&gt; library by hand is no joke. Entries tend to look like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="tex"&gt;&lt;code&gt;@book{beale:revelation:2015,
        Date-Added = {2015-07-20 21:16:02 +0000},
        Date-Modified = {2015-07-20 21:21:05 +0000},
        Editor = {G. K. Beale and David H. Campbell},
        Publisher = {William B. Eerdmans Publishing Company},
        Title = {Revelation: A Shorter Commentary},
        Year = {2015}}&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While there is a lot of utility in having that data available in text, on disk, no one wants to &lt;em&gt;edit&lt;/em&gt; that by hand.&lt;a href="#fn8" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref8"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;8&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; Gladly, editing it by hand is not necessary. For this project, I used the freely available &lt;a href="http://bibdesk.sourceforge.net"&gt;BibDesk&lt;/a&gt; tool, which is a workable (albeit not very pretty and not &lt;em&gt;very&lt;/em&gt; capable) manager for &lt;span class="tex"&gt;BibT&lt;span class="texE"&gt;E&lt;/span&gt;X&lt;/span&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src="http://www.chriskrycho.com/images/bibdesk.png" title="Not very pretty, but it does work" alt="BibDesk – open to the library for my Revelation paper" /&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;BibDesk – open to the library for my Revelation paper&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once I filled in the details for each item and set a citekey for it, I was ready to go: BibDesk just stores the files in a standard &lt;code&gt;.bib&lt;/code&gt; file on the disk, which I specified per the Pandoc command above.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;BibDesk gets the job done alright, but only alright. Using a citation and reference management tool was a big win, though, and I fully intend to use one for every remaining project while in seminary—and, quite possibly, for other projects as well. Whether that tool is BibDesk or something else is a different matter entirely. (More on this below.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="to-the-web" class="level2"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;To the web!&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wanted something more out of this process, if I could get it. One of the reasons I use plain text as a source is because from it, I can generate Word documents, &lt;abbr&gt;PDF&lt;/abbr&gt;s, and &lt;em&gt;this website&lt;/em&gt; with equal ease. However, Python Markdown knows nothing of &lt;span class="tex"&gt;BibT&lt;span class="texE"&gt;E&lt;/span&gt;X&lt;/span&gt; or citekeys, to my knowledge—and since I render everything for school with Pandoc, I have long wanted to configure &lt;a href="http://docs.getpelican.com/en/3.6.0/"&gt;Pelican&lt;/a&gt; to use Pandoc as its Markdown engine instead of Python Markdown anyway.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As it happens, I actually set this up about a month ago. The process was pretty simple:&lt;a href="#fn9" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref9"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;9&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol type="1"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I installed the &lt;a href="https://github.com/jstvz/pelican-pandoc-reader"&gt;pandoc-reader&lt;/a&gt; Pelican extension.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I set the plugin path in my Pelican configuration file.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I specified the arguments to Pelican I wanted to use.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The only additional tweaks necessary to get citation support were calling it with the &lt;code&gt;'--filter pandoc-citeproc'&lt;/code&gt; arguments, which lets it process any bibliography data supplied in the header metadata for the files. Calling Pandoc with &lt;code&gt;--bibliography &amp;lt;path to bibliography&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; (as in my example above) is a &lt;a href="http://pandoc.org/README.html#citation-rendering"&gt;shortcut&lt;/a&gt; for calling it with &lt;code&gt;--metadata &amp;lt;path to bibliography&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; the &lt;code&gt;--filter pandoc-citeproc&lt;/code&gt; arguments. I could just supply the bibliography directly in the call from Pelican, but this would limit me to using a single bibliography file for &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; of my posts—something I’d rather not limit myself to, since it might make sense to build up bibliographies around specific subjects, or even to have smaller bibliographies associated with each project (exported from the main bibliography), which could then be freely available along with the contents of the paper itself.&lt;a href="#fn10" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref10"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;10&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (On this idea, see a bit more below under &lt;strong&gt;The Future&lt;/strong&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One word of warning: Pandoc is much slower to generate &lt;abbr&gt;HTML&lt;/abbr&gt; with &lt;code&gt;--filter pandoc-citeproc&lt;/code&gt; than &lt;em&gt;without&lt;/em&gt; the filter, and the larger your site, the more you will feel this. (The time to generate the site from scratch jumped from about 2.5s to about 30s for me, with 270 articles, 17 drafts, 2 pages, and 1 hidden page, according to Pelican.) Pandoc has to process &lt;em&gt;every&lt;/em&gt; article to check for citations, and that’s no small task. However, if you have Pelican’s content caching turned on, this is a one-time event. After that, it will only be processing any new content with it; total generation time is back down where it was before for me: the effort is all in generating the large indexes I use to display the content for the landing pages and for category and tag archives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section id="other-site-generators" class="level3"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Other site generators&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don’t know the situation around using Pandoc itself in other generators, including Jekyll—I simply haven’t looked. I do know, however, that there &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; some tooling for Jekyll specifically to allow a similar workflow. If you’re using Jekyll, it looks like your best bet is to check out &lt;a href="https://github.com/inukshuk/jekyll-scholar"&gt;jekyll-scholar&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a href="https://github.com/inukshuk/citeproc-ruby"&gt;citeproc-ruby&lt;/a&gt; project, which (like pandoc-citeproc) enables you to embed citations and filter them through &lt;abbr&gt;CSL&lt;/abbr&gt;s to generate references automatically. As a note: you should definitely be able to get those working on your own deployment sites, but I have no idea whether it’s possible to do them with the GitHub Pages variant of Jekyll. (If anyone who reads this knows the answer to that, let me know on Twitter or App.net, and I’ll update the post accordingly.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="the-future" class="level2"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The future&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition to continuing to use &lt;span class="tex"&gt;BibT&lt;span class="texE"&gt;E&lt;/span&gt;X&lt;/span&gt; with BibDesk as a way of managing my citations in the short term, I’m thinking about other ways to improve this workflow. One possibility is integrating with &lt;a href="http://scholdoc.scholarlymarkdown.com"&gt;Scholdoc&lt;/a&gt; as it matures, instead of &lt;a href="http://pandoc.org"&gt;pandoc&lt;/a&gt;, and maybe (hopefully, albeit unlikely) even contributing to it somewhat. I’m also open to using other citation library tools, though my early explorations with Mendeley and Zotero did not particularly impress me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are substantial advantages for the applications (and thus for most users) to maintaining the data in an application-specific format (e.g. an SQLite database) rather than on the file system—but the latter has the advantage of making it much easier to integrate with other tools. However, Zotero and Mendeley both natively export to &lt;span class="tex"&gt;BibT&lt;span class="texE"&gt;E&lt;/span&gt;X&lt;/span&gt; format, and Mendeley natively supports &lt;a href="http://blog.mendeley.com/tipstricks/howto-use-mendeley-to-create-citations-using-latex-and-bibtex/"&gt;sync&lt;/a&gt; to a &lt;span class="tex"&gt;BibT&lt;span class="texE"&gt;E&lt;/span&gt;X&lt;/span&gt; library (Zotero can do the same, but via third-party &lt;a href="https://zoteromusings.wordpress.com/tag/bibtex/"&gt;plugins&lt;/a&gt;), so those remain viable options, which I may use for future projects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also want to look at making my library of resources available publicly, perhaps (a) as a standalone library associated with each project, so that anyone who wants to can download it along with the Markdown source to play with as an example and (b) as a general library covering my various reading and research interests, which will certainly be irrelevant to most people but might nonetheless provide some value to someone along the way. I’m a big fan of making this kind of data open wherever possible, because people come up with neat things to do with it that the original creators never expect. Not &lt;em&gt;everything&lt;/em&gt; should be open—but lots of things should, and this might be among them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="summary" class="level2"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m pretty happy with the current state of affairs, the aforementioned interest in other reference managers notwithstanding:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I can set up the citations &lt;em&gt;once&lt;/em&gt;, in a tool designed to manage references, instead of multiple times in multiple places.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I can use Pandoc and a &lt;abbr&gt;CSL&lt;/abbr&gt; to get the citations formatted correctly throughout a paper, including generating the bibliography automatically.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I can use the same tooling, integrated into my static site generator, to build a web version of the content—with no extra effort, once I configured it properly the first time.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perhaps most importantly, this helps me meet one of my major goals for all my writing: to have a single canonical &lt;em&gt;source&lt;/em&gt; for the content, which I will be able to access in the future regardless of what operating system I am using or what publishing systems come and go. Simple plain text files—Markdown—get me there. Now I’ve put good tools around that process, and I love it even more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="references"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section class="footnotes"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn1"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Coming up with names for footnotes in Markdown can be painful in general for long documents. If you try to name them manually, like I do for posts on my website, you will very quickly end up wasting time on the names. If you try to number them, they will end up out of order in a hurry. My own &lt;a href="http://2012-2013.chriskrycho.com/web/markdown-and-academic-writing/"&gt;previous solution&lt;/a&gt; to this problem quickly became unwieldy for larger papers, and required a &lt;em&gt;lot&lt;/em&gt; of hand-editing. Gladly, I no longer deal with that manually. Instead, I do all my drafting in &lt;a href="http://www.ulyssesapp.com"&gt;Ulysses&lt;/a&gt;, where you just type &lt;code&gt;(fn)&lt;/code&gt; and it creates a footnote automatically, and will move that footnote &lt;em&gt;object&lt;/em&gt; around transparently as you edit, handling all the number-setting, etc. on its own.&lt;a href="#fnref1"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn2"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The irony of site for software which boasts that it is “a high-quality typesetting system” and looks like &lt;a href="http://www.latex-project.org"&gt;&lt;em&gt;this&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; is not lost on me…&lt;a href="#fnref2"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn3"&gt;&lt;p&gt;If you used the installers on Pandoc’s website, &lt;code&gt;pandoc-citeproc&lt;/code&gt; comes with it. If you installed it via a package manager (e.g. by running &lt;code&gt;brew install pandoc&lt;/code&gt;), it may not have, so you’ll need to install it manually yourself (e.g. &lt;code&gt;brew install pandoc-citeproc&lt;/code&gt;).&lt;a href="#fnref3"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn4"&gt;&lt;p&gt;All of the content, including the rendered footnotes and the bibliography, has sensible content types set on it: headers are headers, body text is body text, etc. You can then customize to match the specifications of your style guide. I have a Chicago/Turabian style set set up with the formatting rules to match.&lt;a href="#fnref4"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn5"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Actually, it was even hairier than this, because I also had a &lt;code&gt;--reference-docx path/to/template.docx&lt;/code&gt; specified. If you think it’s perhaps a bit too complex, well, I agree. I plan to turn that into a command line alias in pretty short order, because remembering it every time is just not going to happen.&lt;a href="#fnref5"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn6"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Using the &lt;code&gt;--reference-docx&lt;/code&gt; argument to Pandoc, you can hand it a document that already uses your desired style set, so you don’t have to go in and apply it manually.&lt;a href="#fnref6"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn7"&gt;&lt;p&gt;I could have done that with Pandoc’s &lt;span class="tex"&gt;L&lt;span class="texA"&gt;A&lt;/span&gt;T&lt;span class="texE"&gt;E&lt;/span&gt;X&lt;/span&gt; &lt;abbr&gt;PDF&lt;/abbr&gt; tools, as well, but didn’t really feel like taking the time to tweak the &lt;span class="tex"&gt;L&lt;span class="texA"&gt;A&lt;/span&gt;T&lt;span class="texE"&gt;E&lt;/span&gt;X&lt;/span&gt; template for it.&lt;a href="#fnref7"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn8"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Probably someone does, but not me, and not most people!&lt;a href="#fnref8"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;If you’re using Pelican, you can take a look at my Pelican configuration file &lt;a href="https://github.com/chriskrycho/chriskrycho.com/blob/ef3ecbca1765750392086355aeae026c1159d4b9/pelicanconf.py#L109"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the full configuration for using Pandoc this way.&lt;a href="#fnref9"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn10"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Optimally, I’d really just prefer to be able to set &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; of these arguments at a per-file level—i.e., not use &lt;code&gt;--filter pandoc cite-proc&lt;/code&gt; unless the file actually specifies a bibliography. And I could hack Pelican to do that; I’ve actually already &lt;a href="https://github.com/liob/pandoc_reader/pull/5"&gt;messed around&lt;/a&gt; with other, semi-related bits regarding Pelican and Pandoc’s shared handling of &lt;abbr&gt;YAML&lt;/abbr&gt; metadata. But I’d prefer to keep my installation as “vanilla” as possible to minimize the cost of setting things up again on a new machine or after a crash, etc.&lt;a href="#fnref10"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 26 Jul 2015 13:50:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2015-07-26:2015/academic-markdown-and-citations.html</guid><category>workflow</category><category>writing</category></item><item><title>Faithfulness</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2015/faithfulness.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;It’s been a lot more than a month since the promised monthly update. I’ll blame it on a lack of self-discipline… or perhaps on the presence thereof.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Every day, we face choices about where to spend our time. In this particular season of life, that has often meant not writing, even things I &lt;em&gt;want&lt;/em&gt; to write. I have a family to care for, a church to serve, work to do, and schoolwork to accomplish. Family is a daily endeavor, work and school nearly so, and church regular if not quite daily. In the midst of that, I have to decide: &lt;em&gt;What will I do today?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our culture tends to put the question in terms of balance; my friend and pastor Ashok Nachnani suggested to me a while back that it is better to think in terms of &lt;em&gt;faithfulness&lt;/em&gt;. “Balance” suggests holding all these things in equal proportion, juggling them against each other. “Faithfulness” suggests fulfilling the responsibilities as best we can, with the time we are given. The actual day-to-day outcome may not look particularly different, but it is an important shift in the way we think nonetheless. To be faithful may mean letting some desireable things go, and it may mean doing some things in a different way or to a lesser degree than we might like.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Writing, for example.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I &lt;em&gt;love&lt;/em&gt; writing. I like keeping a public record for my friends and family to see how my life is. I enjoy stretching my mental muscles in the way that writing requires. I enjoy thinking through pen or keyboard. But faithfulness to the responsibilities God has given me right now means &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; trying to balance those desires against each other, and instead doing what is best for my family and my church. For the most part, right now that means not writing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I put it to Jaimie a while back, at this point in life I have time for one hobby—and only one. That hobby, at this point, is fitness. I run half marathons, and now I do triathlons (first one coming up in 10 days!). That takes up a non-trivial amount of time every week. It helps me in the other areas of my life, to be sure: it helps me be less physically tired, improves my focus in school and work, and serves to maintain my health. Nonetheless, it is hobby-like and it takes a substantial amount of time every day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So right now, I write a great deal less than I want, and a great deal less than I did in college or early in our marriage. I miss the days when I had time to work on poetry for hours at a stretch, or simply to muse for a few thousand words. But it is far more important for me to spend time with Ellie and Kate than it is to write poetry, or to compose music, right now. Lord willing, I have 55–60 years ahead of me. Of those years, they will be close only another 15–20, and they will be the age they are today &lt;em&gt;only for today&lt;/em&gt;. As much as writing and composing and hobby programming all look appealing to me, and as much as those really are good expressions of the ways God has gifted me, focusing on them would not be the most &lt;em&gt;faithful&lt;/em&gt; use of my time—not today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is not to say that writing and composing and developing interesting software are not important. Rather: they &lt;em&gt;are&lt;/em&gt; good and valuable things. But they are things to focus on at other times in life. As fast as this life goes, and I am increasingly aware that it goes quickly indeed, I can expect in the ordinary course of things to have &lt;em&gt;many&lt;/em&gt; years available for those things. I can exercise my gifts faithfully in the right time and season. Today, I can learn to love my little girls well, invest deeply in their lives, and savor moments that will never come back.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most of all, I must remind myself that teaching and shaping them is easily the most significant thing I will ever do. Should I write an essay that persuaded a thousand people to change their views on the arts, or to adopt a better view of the church, still my impact on two little lives would be more important. If I can point them faithfully to Christ and help them learn to walk faithfully with him as healthy members of his body, that will be a good life to have lived. Everything else is icing on the cake.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Icing is good, for the record. Sometimes, in these sorts of posts, we can mistake &lt;em&gt;relative importance&lt;/em&gt; for &lt;em&gt;absolute importance&lt;/em&gt;. I should, at various times in my life, make sure to exercise the good gifts God has given me in ways appropriate to that time and context. Right now, that means continuing to write, but less frequently. In the future, it will mean something else.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And all of this must stand in the context of resurrection hope. Too often, I live—too often, we &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; live—as though the next 60 years are all we may expect, the only time for writing and composing and so on. But it is not. I look forward to endless ages of creativity, exercising those gifts &lt;em&gt;more&lt;/em&gt; fully than I am able now. So: Lord Jesus, come soon. And in the meantime, may I be faithful in each season to do as well as I can.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="references"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 18 Jun 2015 17:00:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2015-06-18:2015/faithfulness.html</guid><category>family</category><category>writing</category></item></channel></rss>