<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Chris Krycho - writing</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/</link><description></description><lastBuildDate>Wed, 28 Dec 2016 07:00:00 -0500</lastBuildDate><item><title>2016 in Review, Part 2 of 6</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2016/2016-review-2.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;i class='editorial'&gt;I originally drafted a single, mammoth post reflecting on this whole year—but at more than 6,000 words, that seemed like a bit much. As such, I’ve broken it into a series of posts, to be published daily through the start of the new year. Hopefully they’re a bit more digestible that way!&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2016/2016-review-intro.html"&gt;Introduction, or: a ridiculous year summarized&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2016/2016-review-1.html"&gt;Part 1: Running headfirst into a wall of pneumonia.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Part 2: So. many. words. I had no idea how many words.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Part 3: Podcasting: Winning Slowly, New Rustacean, and more!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Part 4: Writing software for Olo and for open source.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Part 5: Getting things done in 2016 and beyond.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Part 6: Plans for 2017!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of my goals for 2016 was to continue writing not only on this blog but in other outlets. I did a &lt;em&gt;lot&lt;/em&gt; of writing this year, but relatively little of it is published. But here’s a look at some of the numbers! Note that “This site” excludes republication of school papers, and that I don’t have an exact count for the school papers because I’ve already discarded a few of the shorter pieces, but their average length is well-known to me. More on the unpublished &lt;em&gt;Rust vs. Swift&lt;/em&gt; project below.&lt;a href="#fn1" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref1"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr class="header"&gt;
&lt;th style="text-align: center;"&gt;Category&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th style="text-align: center;"&gt;Words&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr class="odd"&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/m-div/"&gt;School&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: center;"&gt;~130,500&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class="even"&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;a href="https://mereorthodoxy.com/author/chris-krycho/"&gt;Mere Orthodoxy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: center;"&gt;~6000&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class="odd"&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: center;"&gt;This site&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: center;"&gt;~63,000&lt;a href="#fn2" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref2"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class="even"&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Rust vs. Swift&lt;/em&gt; project&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: center;"&gt;~9350&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class="odd"&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Total&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;~207,850&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of the writing for school, only a small fraction of it is &lt;a href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/m-div/"&gt;published here&lt;/a&gt;, unlike previous years. Roughly 75,000 words of that content is research notes I put together for an independent study I did—which was deeply profitable for me in terms of thinking through hermeneutical and theological systems, and which will hopefully be helpful for the professor for whom I prepared them, but which are not at all publishable. Another 10,000 of those words fit in a category charitably describable as “busy-work” and publishing them is &lt;em&gt;possible&lt;/em&gt; but would have no &lt;em&gt;value&lt;/em&gt;. The school-writing also includes the notes and manuscripts for my sermon-delivery class. You can find those sermons &lt;a href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/sermons/"&gt;on this site&lt;/a&gt; as well well, with audio, video, and the manuscripts available—but the notes are not worth publishing, as they’re entirely internal. Still: they’re words, I wrote them, and there are a lot of them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the plus side, I wrote one of the papers I’m proudest of from my entire seminary career in the spring: &lt;a href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2016/realism-and-antirealism.html"&gt;Realism and Antirealism—A key debate in the philosophy of science (with interesting implications for young-earth creationism)&lt;/a&gt;. I’m happy with it not least because I wrote it in a very compressed fashion because of some family health issues that hit at the end of that semester, and it still turned out extremely well because I had &lt;em&gt;planned&lt;/em&gt; it meticulously. Despite having only a single draft with one typo-level revision pass, it’s easily the best paper I’ve ever written. It turns out that doing a really careful outline helps when you’re working at this scale. I’ve not normally been a fan of outlining (and I’ve not normally found it helpful when I’ve tried it), but for any longer, more sustained argument, it’s absolutely necessary.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of the content on this site (excluding republication of school papers), an astounding ~14,000 of those words are in my “microblog” content. It’s amazing how much those little posts add up. That said, I’m surprised to see that I’ve put out as many &lt;em&gt;other&lt;/em&gt; words as I have this year on this site, and the total there is rather staggering. Writing on this site includes everything from &lt;a href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2016/ask.html" title="Ask: a short story"&gt;fiction&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2016/to-paint-god-as-a-man.html" title="To paint God as a man: an Advent poem"&gt;poetry&lt;/a&gt; to &lt;a href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2016/a-simple-childrens-catechism.html"&gt;a simple children’s catechism&lt;/a&gt; to &lt;a href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2016/what-is-functional-programming.html"&gt;an introduction to functional programming&lt;/a&gt;. I’m exceptionally pleased in retrospect to see how this came out, and I look forward to writing on equally varied terms in the year ahead.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some 13,000 of the words I wrote for this site were in my &lt;a href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/rust-and-swift.html"&gt;Rust and Swift&lt;/a&gt; series, a project I’ve enjoyed enormously since starting it in 2015 and would like to get back to in 2017. It went on hold because I was offered, and accepted, a contract to write a 30–40 page report for O’Reilly comparing the two languages, which was intended to come out this fall. Unfortunately, somewhere along the way some wires got crossed and my pitch and what they wanted didn’t end up being the same. Once that became clear (at the beginning of October), they opted to drop the project. This was a huge disappointment to me: it was a small hit financially, but a big one time-wise, as I sunk a &lt;em&gt;lot&lt;/em&gt; of hours into it in what was an already-very-busy fall; the project was over ¾ done when it was dropped.&lt;a href="#fn3" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref3"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A few big lessons I learned from this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol type="1"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Don’t overcommit. Even if the project had gone through without issue, it would have been more on my plate than I could reasonably handle. The fact that it was canceled after having done a lot of the work meant it was also &lt;em&gt;financially&lt;/em&gt; frustrating, but I had overcommitted regardless. Won’t do that again.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Be &lt;em&gt;even more&lt;/em&gt; clear up-front about the terms and goals of a project. I don’t know how we ended up with the crossed wires we did, but it was extremely frustrating.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;If you can get an advance, get an advance. Just saying.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In general, I’m quite pleased with the &lt;em&gt;volume&lt;/em&gt; of my output in 2016 (who wouldn’t be, right?). I’d definitely like a lot more of that to be public-facing in 2017, even if it’s lower in overall volume. I hope to take the material from that &lt;em&gt;Rust vs. Swift&lt;/em&gt; project, expand it slightly, and self-publish it. I also hope to put together at least one substantive essay for Mere Orthodoxy next year. And of course there will probably be thousands of words in this space, too—inevitably more than I even realize.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section class="footnotes"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn1"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Note as well that this excludes all the &lt;a href="https://github.com/chriskrycho/newrustacean.com/tree/589cd13225cde91f92bfca93f6679f2395d78886/docs"&gt;podcast scripts&lt;/a&gt; I wrote this year! Those would add well over 10,000 more words to this count.&lt;a href="#fnref1"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn2"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Yes, that number includes these posts!&lt;a href="#fnref2"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn3"&gt;&lt;p&gt;They wanted an analysis of when you’d choose each language; I pitched a comparison along similar lines to my blog series, looking at the language design choices as a view into software engineering tradeoffs. When the mismatch became clear, I pointed out that “when to choose Rust vs. Swift” is, generally speaking, a roughly two-sentence answer: “Choose Rust for cross-platform, high-performance/low-level code. Choose Swift if you’re writing apps on an Apple platform.” This was not, apparently, obvious to everyone else involved. In the words of the internet: &lt;span style="whitespace: nowrap"&gt;¯\_(ツ)_/¯&lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="#fnref3"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 28 Dec 2016 07:00:00 -0500</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2016-12-28:2016/2016-review-2.html</guid><category>writing</category><category>podcasting</category><category>software development</category><category>family</category><category>productivity</category><category>fitness</category><category>2016-in-review</category></item><item><title></title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2016/12-27-1730.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;I just ran the numbers for my end-of-year blog post, and it turns out I wrote over 200,000 words this year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That’s a &lt;em&gt;lot&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 27 Dec 2016 17:30:00 -0500</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2016-12-27:2016/12-27-1730.html</guid><category>writing</category></item><item><title>2016 in Review, Part 1 of 6</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2016/2016-review-1.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;i class='editorial'&gt;I originally drafted a single, mammoth post reflecting on this whole year—but at more than 6,000 words, that seemed like a bit much. As such, I’ve broken it into a series of posts, to be published daily through the start of the new year. Hopefully they’re a bit more digestible that way!&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2016/2016-review-intro.html"&gt;Introduction, or: a ridiculous year summarized&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2016/2016-review-1.html"&gt;Part 1: Running headfirst into a wall of pneumonia.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2016/2016-review-2.html"&gt;Part 2: So. many. words. I had no idea how many words.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Part 3: Podcasting: Winning Slowly, New Rustacean, and more!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Part 4: Writing software for Olo and for open source.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Part 5: Getting things done in 2016 and beyond.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Part 6: Plans for 2017!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Wait, hold on,&lt;/em&gt; you say. &lt;em&gt;Go back. How did you get walking pneumonia?&lt;/em&gt; This is a fun story, and it’s a huge part of what made the other parts of the latter half of 2016 go the way they did.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I went for what I expected to be a 15–16 mile long run as part of training for the half-marathon I signed up for this year. The previous week &lt;a href="http://runwith.chriskrycho.com/runs/12/" title="Run summary on runwith.chriskrycho.com"&gt;I’d done a 14-mile run&lt;/a&gt;, so 15–16 would have been no problem. I was feeling &lt;em&gt;awesome&lt;/em&gt; on the run, so decided to extend it to 17. This was right at the edge of what makes good sense for a week-over-week increase in mileage; you generally want to stick with ~10% increases and max out at 20%; but 17 is right at that limit relative to 14. So I turned right to cut through another nearby town instead of left to head directly home when I was at roughly the 11-mile mark.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then, where I &lt;em&gt;did&lt;/em&gt; cut back toward home, I took a wrong turn out of a five-way intersection. (You can see on the north end of the map, in Youngsville, &lt;a href="https://www.strava.com/activities/644619792" title="Run overview on Strava"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;). I realized this half a mile on, but figured there would be a spot to cut over. There is not. So I got back to where I had taken the wrong turn, filled up my water bottle and hit the bathroom, and made my way home. But at this point, I was already at ~15 miles, and ~4 miles from home. As I got back into our town, I decided: why not just go ahead and extend out to 20 miles?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And the truth is, that extra three quarters of a mile probably didn’t matter a bit. 19.25 vs. 20 miles? Same difference in its effect on my immune system, which is to say: it completely crashed it. A 42% week over week increase in mileage is no joke. The little cold I picked up from my 2-year-old daughter turned into borderline bronchitis. Yay.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What with a busy spring preceding—I had no idea how much busier I would be taking 2 classes and working 30 hours a week than I had been taking 3 classes and working 20 hours a week—I didn’t manage a triathlon. I had contented myself with the thought that I’d likely set another PR in my half marathon, but after weeks of recovery from walking pneumonia, that thought fell apart as well. I lost about a minute per mile in my pace, and my mileage was shot as well. I never got it back—not least because of a writing project which went south on me. I ended up being sick off and on all fall, and I’m only now getting my feet back under me. Sad to say, one of those times I got sick was the week of the half marathon I signed up for, and I’d been getting loud, clear signals from my body on previous runs that I was pushing too hard. So no race &lt;em&gt;at all&lt;/em&gt; this year. But better that than pushing and injuring myself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The year also saw a so-far unreversed weight gain that I find incredibly frustrating. In the first six months of 2016, I gained about ten pounds—despite keeping up the same basic activity level. I attribute this to a combination of factors: metabolic shifts in my late 20s, shifting back to doing almost purely running rather than a mix of running, swimming, and cycling, and the impact of acclimation to a workout load. I’m far from overweight, but I’m also slower and generally a bit flabbier as a result.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here’s hoping 2017 is &lt;em&gt;much&lt;/em&gt; better in all these regards! I plan to do a sprint-length triathlon and a full marathon. And I hope to lose those ten pounds again and get back to that healthier overall weight. That combo seems like the thing to do the year I turn thirty and graduate seminary.&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 27 Dec 2016 17:00:00 -0500</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2016-12-27:2016/2016-review-1.html</guid><category>writing</category><category>podcasting</category><category>software development</category><category>family</category><category>productivity</category><category>fitness</category><category>2016-in-review</category></item><item><title>2016 in Review, Introduction</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2016/2016-review-intro.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;i class='editorial'&gt;I originally drafted a single, mammoth post reflecting on this whole year—but at more than 6,000 words, that seemed like a bit much. As such, I’ve broken it into a series of posts, to be published daily through the start of the new year. Hopefully they’re a bit more digestible that way! This first day, you’re getting two posts; the rest of the year, one (at least: in this series!).&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2016/2016-review-intro.html"&gt;Introduction, or: a ridiculous year summarized&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2016/2016-review-1.html"&gt;Part 1: Running headfirst into a wall of pneumonia.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2016/2016-review-2.html"&gt;Part 2: So. many. words. I had no idea how many words.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Part 3: Podcasting: Winning Slowly, New Rustacean, and more!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Part 4: Writing software for Olo and for open source.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Part 5: Getting things done in 2016 and beyond.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Part 6: Plans for 2017!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;2016 was a long, difficult, strange, sometimes wonderful and sometimes dreadful year for me. It was one of the most professionally and scholastically enjoyable and rewarding years of my life, and also one of the most exhausting. As I often do at years-end, I am taking stock publicly of what went well, what went poorly, and what I might do different in a variety of categories—here, mostly in terms of my public-facing endeavors. This year’s summing-up post will also (for, I think, the first time) include some numbers! But first, a few comments on the big picture.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the end of 2015, I &lt;a href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2015/thoughts-on-2015-and-2016.html"&gt;offered a similar set of reflections&lt;/a&gt;. At the end of it, I laid out some plans for 2016:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am going to set a single goal in each of five major categories in my life:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;spiritual:&lt;/strong&gt; everything in my walk with God, including my own personal devotions, my involvement in the life of the church, and my “ministry” actions in general&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;family:&lt;/strong&gt; both quantity and quality time spent with my wife and my quickly-growing-up little girls&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;personal:&lt;/strong&gt; podcasting, blogging, and writing for &lt;a href="http://mereorthodoxy.com/author/chris-krycho/"&gt;other outlets&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;professional:&lt;/strong&gt; working in my new job and as a consultant, and carrying on toward the conclusion of my M. Div.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;health/fitness:&lt;/strong&gt; continuing to stay healthy, including eating well and continuing to stay fit by running and doing triathlon work&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Early in the year, I made the habit of writing these out formally on a day-by-day basis—and I did this off and on. If you were to look at my little (Moleskine-branded and delightful-to-me) daily planner, you’d see streaks of weeks where I noted specific tasks and whether I hit them or not, punctuated by weeks and months where I did nothing of the sort. I have always found it difficult to stick with these kinds of things, in part because I usually have a pretty good idea what I need to do on any given day without writing it down somewhere. (I use &lt;a href="https://www.omnigroup.com/omnifocus/" title="OmniFocus"&gt;other tools&lt;/a&gt; for tracking mid- and long-term deadlines for school.) In July, I started mashing this idea up with &lt;a href="http://bulletjournal.com" title="Bullet Journal site"&gt;bullet journaling&lt;/a&gt;, and I found that I (a) really like the system and (b) also didn’t stick with it consistently. A lot of that came down to the fact that I got thrown off—horribly—by getting a mild-but-still-utterly-debilitating case of walking pneumonia in July. (On which, more in a moment.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So much for last year’s ideas about &lt;em&gt;how&lt;/em&gt; I was going to hit those goals. How did I actually do at addressing them? The answer is: &lt;em&gt;okay&lt;/em&gt;. 2016 was not an amazing year. It was not a terrible year. But it had as many downs as ups.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My own walk with God remains &lt;em&gt;steady&lt;/em&gt;. Nothing amazing to report here, but I’m more than okay with that. I will perhaps say more on this in another post, but the older I get the more convinced I am that emotional highs are a trap. Sentiment and true religion are &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; the same thing; and Scripture calls us to &lt;em&gt;faithfulness&lt;/em&gt;, not &lt;em&gt;spiritual feelings&lt;/em&gt;. As such, in a year with this many bumps, I am glad to say that I had no horrible falls, and I read my Bible nearly every day and prayed every single day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our family learned some Bible verses, and started working on the Heidelberg Catechism. We shared the gospel with people as we were able, and met faithfully with our church. We were not extraordinary, and we were far from flawless, but I think we did &lt;em&gt;well&lt;/em&gt;. I hope and pray in God’s grace we are able to continue in faithfully doing well in the years to come. Certainly if there is one thing I hope to do more of in 2017 it is spend time with my girls. I am not a huge “kid person,” but these years are precious and go by quickly; far better to spend more time with them and have a podcast episode or a writing project go out later (or not at all) than to miss these little years.&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 27 Dec 2016 16:00:00 -0500</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2016-12-27:2016/2016-review-intro.html</guid><category>writing</category><category>podcasting</category><category>software development</category><category>family</category><category>productivity</category><category>fitness</category><category>2016-in-review</category></item><item><title></title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2016/12-10-1245.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Drinking &lt;a href="https://bluebottlecoffee.com/releases/guatemala-alta-verapaz-santa-sofia-oak"&gt;Guatemala Tactic Santa Sofia&lt;/a&gt; by [Blue Bottle] alongside some eggnog, with the Doctor Who Series 7 soundtrack playing in the background, as I finish up some work on an independent study at SEBTS. Mmmmmm.&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 10 Dec 2016 12:45:00 -0500</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2016-12-10:2016/12-10-1245.html</guid><category>coffee</category><category>sebts</category><category>writing</category><category>music</category></item><item><title></title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2016/10-08-1109.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;And, on evaluating &lt;a href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2016/10-08-1109.html"&gt;that table&lt;/a&gt;… I need to pull about half of it out: too much code.&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 08 Oct 2016 11:09:00 -0400</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2016-10-08:2016/10-08-1109.html</guid><category>writing</category><category>rust-and-swift</category><category>rust</category><category>swift</category></item><item><title></title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2016/10-08-1046.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;This morning I… carefully built a 3⨉16 table comparing Rust and Swift syntax. Exciting, right? 🤓&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 08 Oct 2016 10:46:00 -0400</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2016-10-08:2016/10-08-1046.html</guid><category>writing</category><category>rust-and-swift</category><category>rust</category><category>swift</category></item><item><title></title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2016/10-06-0832.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Wrote ~500 words and nailed down a chapter’s structure this morning. Good start to the day!&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 06 Oct 2016 08:32:00 -0400</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2016-10-06:2016/10-06-0832.html</guid><category>writing</category><category>rust-and-swift</category><category>rust</category><category>swift</category></item><item><title></title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2016/10-02-0856.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Playing Harmy’s &lt;em&gt;Unspecialized Star Wars&lt;/em&gt; for my girls while I write some more this morning. 💕&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 02 Oct 2016 08:56:00 -0400</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2016-10-02:2016/10-02-0856.html</guid><category>writing</category><category>rust</category><category>swift</category><category>rust-and-swift</category></item><item><title></title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2016/10-01-1758.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://atom.io"&gt;Atom&lt;/a&gt; + the &lt;a href="https://atom.io/themes/github-atom-light-syntax"&gt;GitHub theme&lt;/a&gt; + &lt;a href="https://atom.io/packages/Zen"&gt;Zen package&lt;/a&gt; = a pretty good technical writing environment.&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 01 Oct 2016 17:58:00 -0400</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2016-10-01:2016/10-01-1758.html</guid><category>writing</category><category>rust</category><category>swift</category><category>rust-and-swift</category></item><item><title></title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2016/09-10-1323.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;My writing setup as I’m working on my new Rust and Swift project (click/tap the image to see the full screenshot):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://cdn.chriskrycho.com/images/writing-setup.png"&gt;&lt;img src="http://cdn.chriskrycho.com/images/writing-setup-thumb.png" title="writing setup thumbnail" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 10 Sep 2016 13:23:00 -0400</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2016-09-10:2016/09-10-1323.html</guid><category>writing</category></item><item><title></title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2016/08-09-1257.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;i class=editorial&gt;I originally posted this as a &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/chriskrycho/status/763056742460755971"&gt;tweetstorm&lt;/a&gt;, but I’m treating &lt;em&gt;this&lt;/em&gt; as the canonical and adding a tweet to the end of that “topic” linking back here. &lt;a href="http://indiewebcamp.com"&gt;Indie web&lt;/a&gt; forever.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://asciidoc.org"&gt;AsciiDoc&lt;/a&gt;: a typical programmer-first, not writer-first, tool. Just try to find text formatting on &lt;a href="http://asciidoc.org"&gt;the site&lt;/a&gt;. It’s §10 in the user guide. §10!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The “user guide” is an &lt;em&gt;implementor’s&lt;/em&gt; guide, not a &lt;em&gt;user’s&lt;/em&gt; guide. &lt;i&gt;:sigh:&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Gladly, &lt;a href="http://asciidoctor.org"&gt;asciidoctor.org&lt;/a&gt; makes it easier: “What is AsciiDoc” and “Writer’s Guide” and “Syntax Reference” are all on the front page.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;But if you’ve ever wondered why Markdown caught on and AsciiDoc didn’t… well, there are many reasons, but this highlights the most basic: Markdown prioritizes the needs of the &lt;em&gt;writer&lt;/em&gt;, not the implementor. Plain and simple as that.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 09 Aug 2016 12:57:00 -0400</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2016-08-09:2016/08-09-1257.html</guid><category>writing</category></item><item><title></title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2016/08-04-2317.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;I signed a contract today for a neat little writing project broadly related to my ongoing &lt;a href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/rust-and-swift.html"&gt;Rust and Swift&lt;/a&gt; series. Probably means a bit of a hiatus on the series itself, but there’s a lot of fun ahead. More on that as it develops.&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 04 Aug 2016 23:17:00 -0400</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2016-08-04:2016/08-04-2317.html</guid><category>writing</category><category>programming languages</category><category>rust</category><category>swift</category><category>rust-and-swift</category></item><item><title></title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2016/07-24-1149.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Either &lt;a href="https://medium.com"&gt;Medium&lt;/a&gt; actually thinks this, or they’re willing to sell their product with it but &lt;em&gt;don’t&lt;/em&gt; think it. Either way, it’s nonsense. “Moving thinking forward”? Really?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src="http://cdn.chriskrycho.com/images/medium.jpg" alt="The hero image from medium.com on July 24, 2016" /&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;The hero image from medium.com on July 24, 2016&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 24 Jul 2016 11:49:00 -0400</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2016-07-24:2016/07-24-1149.html</guid><category>writing</category></item><item><title></title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2016/07-21-2225.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Well, I might have stayed up too late tonight writing what has ended up being a 1700-word post on Tolkien and typology for &lt;a href="//mereorthodoxy.com"&gt;Mere Orthodoxy&lt;/a&gt;. But it was fun!&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 21 Jul 2016 22:25:00 -0400</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2016-07-21:2016/07-21-2225.html</guid><category>writing</category></item><item><title></title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2016/07-19-0911.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;I may have spent over an hour this morning writing about allegorical interpretation and &lt;em&gt;The Lord of the Rings&lt;/em&gt; instead of finishing the book I was reading for an independent study. But I’ll blame that on the book, because its authors just got Tolkien very, &lt;em&gt;very&lt;/em&gt; wrong. 😜&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 19 Jul 2016 09:11:00 -0400</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2016-07-19:2016/07-19-0911.html</guid><category>hermeneutics</category><category>writing</category></item><item><title></title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2016/2016-05-18-2241.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Finally at a spot where I have both the time and the mental energy to pick back up my &lt;a href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/rust-and-swift.html"&gt;Rust and Swift&lt;/a&gt; series. Initializers, I’m coming for you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id="refs" class="references"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 18 May 2016 22:41:00 -0400</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2016-05-18:2016/2016-05-18-2241.html</guid><category>writing</category><category>programming languages</category><category>rust</category><category>swift</category></item><item><title></title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2016/2016-05-17-2226.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;I wrote just under 30,000 words this semester. Not too shabby. Glad to have wrapped up another one!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id="refs" class="references"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 17 May 2016 22:26:00 -0400</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2016-05-17:2016/2016-05-17-2226.html</guid><category>writing</category></item><item><title></title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2016/2016-05-17-1909.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;In a few hours, Lord willing, I’ll have written a few thousand more words for an essay final and finished this semester.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id="refs" class="references"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 17 May 2016 19:09:00 -0400</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2016-05-17:2016/2016-05-17-1909.html</guid><category>writing</category></item><item><title></title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2016/2016-05-16-1833.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Finished writing &lt;em&gt;enough words&lt;/em&gt;. Going to take a two hour break to go hack on a potential solution to a problem that has been vexing us at work for months and which I think I know how to solve. Then come back, edit, and submit this thing!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id="refs" class="references"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 16 May 2016 18:33:00 -0400</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2016-05-16:2016/2016-05-16-1833.html</guid><category>writing</category></item><item><title></title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2016/2016-05-16-1645.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;500 words and some editing and 75 minutes to go. Put on some Ellie Goulding. Head down. Let’s do this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id="refs" class="references"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 16 May 2016 16:45:00 -0400</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2016-05-16:2016/2016-05-16-1645.html</guid><category>music</category><category>writing</category></item><item><title></title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2016/2016-05-16-1025.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;750 words written today. My brain feels like mush. Time to listen to &lt;em&gt;Star Wars: The Force Awakens&lt;/em&gt;. And maybe also drink some more coffee.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id="refs" class="references"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 16 May 2016 10:25:00 -0400</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2016-05-16:2016/2016-05-16-1025.html</guid><category>writing</category><category>music</category><category>coffee</category></item><item><title></title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2016/2016-05-15-1641.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Also, I’m betting I’m not the only one who finds it frustrating that every single tool I use gives me a different word count for the same content.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id="refs" class="references"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 15 May 2016 16:41:00 -0400</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2016-05-15:2016/2016-05-15-1641.html</guid><category>writing</category></item><item><title></title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2016/2016-05-15-1636.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;~5600 words down. ~1800 to go. Yes, I underestimated yesterday by about 1500 words. &lt;em&gt;Whoops.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id="refs" class="references"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 15 May 2016 16:36:00 -0400</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2016-05-15:2016/2016-05-15-1636.html</guid><category>writing</category></item><item><title></title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2016/2016-05-14-1556.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;~3500 words down, ~2500 to go. Steady on!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id="refs" class="references"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 14 May 2016 15:56:00 -0400</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2016-05-14:2016/2016-05-14-1556.html</guid><category>writing</category></item><item><title></title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2016/2016-04-23-1525.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;I’m drafting the next episode of &lt;a href="//www.newrustacean.com"&gt;New Rustacean&lt;/a&gt; on a 3-year-old retina iPad Mini and I &lt;em&gt;love&lt;/em&gt; it. An iPad Pro looks awfully appealing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id="refs" class="references"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 23 Apr 2016 15:25:00 -0400</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2016-04-23:2016/2016-04-23-1525.html</guid><category>writing</category><category>podcasting</category></item><item><title></title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2016/2016-04-20-1452.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Finished putting together a 200-word outline for a 25-page paper for my Philosophy of Science and Religion class. Perhaps surprisingly, I don’t normally work with outlines like this, but at larger scales, I think it’s necessary.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id="refs" class="references"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 20 Apr 2016 14:52:00 -0400</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2016-04-20:2016/2016-04-20-1452.html</guid><category>writing</category></item><item><title></title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2016/2016-04-05-0800.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;One of the things that’s weird about writing sermons for a class is the requirement to turn in a summary of my preparation. Why, you ask? Because it tends to look like this…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src="//cdn.chriskrycho.com/images/sermon-notes.jpg" title="sermon notes with markup" /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;div id="refs" class="references"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 05 Apr 2016 08:00:00 -0400</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2016-04-05:2016/2016-04-05-0800.html</guid><category>writing</category><category>sermons</category><category>M. Div.</category><category>SEBTS</category></item><item><title></title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2016/2016-04-01-1330.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Whoa: Ulysses exposes its iCloud documents &lt;em&gt;quite&lt;/em&gt; elegantly to Spotlight (or Alfred or your launcher of choice). Quite impressed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id="refs" class="references"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 01 Apr 2016 13:30:00 -0400</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2016-04-01:2016/2016-04-01-1330.html</guid><category>writing</category></item><item><title>Ulysses, Byword, and “Just Right”</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2016/ulysses-byword-and-just-right.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;I’m trying out Ulysses again, as it’s been updated substantially since I last used it. I think the main thing to say about it is that it’s gorgeous and a really great editor, and that there is nonetheless something about it which makes it feel not quite as &lt;em&gt;fluid&lt;/em&gt; as Byword always has.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Neither of them quite &lt;em&gt;nails&lt;/em&gt; it for my purposes, though:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Neither is quite there for text that includes a lot of code samples. (Basically: neither supports the GitHub variations on Markdown, which are incredibly important for &lt;a href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/rust-and-swift.html"&gt;a lot of my writing&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Neither has the ability to do things like autocompletion of citations from something like BibLatex. (No standalone app does, to my knowledge.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ulysses’ most powerful features only work in its iCloud bucket. And they’re not standard: rather than embracing &lt;a href="http://criticmarkup.com"&gt;CriticMarkup&lt;/a&gt; for comments, they have their own. The same is true of e.g. their code blocks.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ulysses &lt;em&gt;converts&lt;/em&gt; any other Markdown documents to its own custom variant when you open them. Had those documents formatted a way you liked (e.g. with specific kinds of link or footnote formatting)? Don’t expect them to still be that way.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Byword really does one thing well: opening and writing single documents. It does this extremely well, but it also has none of the library management that is useful for larger projects.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Both of these apps are really wonderful in many ways, and I think it’s fair to say that they’re &lt;em&gt;perfect&lt;/em&gt; for many writers. &lt;a href="http://jaimiekrycho.com/"&gt;My wife&lt;/a&gt;, for example, does nearly all her fiction writing in Ulysses; it works wonderfully for her. But for the kinds of writing I do—usually technical in one way or another—it is limited in its utility. That’s not really a critique of the apps. It’s more the recognition that I have some pretty unusual requirements of my writing apps.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That said, I don’t think I’m the only person out there who has these particular needs. I am, for example, hardly the only person working with citations and academic text, or writing Markup with lots of code samples in it. And as much as you can bend general-purpose text editors like &lt;a href="https://atom.io"&gt;Atom&lt;/a&gt; to your will,&lt;a href="#fn1" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref1"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; it’s not the same as a dedicated writing app that focuses—in the ways that Ulysses and Byword both do—on just being a great tool for &lt;em&gt;writing&lt;/em&gt;. Writing and writing &lt;em&gt;code&lt;/em&gt; are not the same, after all. A tool that’s really well-optimized for the latter isn’t necessarily well-optimized for the former.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Keep your ears open. You might just be hearing more about this in the future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id="refs" class="references"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;section class="footnotes"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn1"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Trust me, I have: I have Zen mode installed, a custom Byword-like theme I use when I just want to write, and even a citation autocompletion package integrated with it. It’s not bad. But I still don’t love it as a first-choice &lt;em&gt;writing&lt;/em&gt; tool.&lt;a href="#fnref1"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 26 Mar 2016 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2016-03-26:2016/ulysses-byword-and-just-right.html</guid><category>design</category><category>software development</category><category>writing</category></item><item><title></title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2016/2016-03-12-1450.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;It is both &lt;em&gt;nice&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;odd&lt;/em&gt; to have no analytics for my website. On the one hand, it is liberating: if no one reads, I’m none the wiser. On the other hand, it’s strange: there are posts I know are getting read a fair bit… but &lt;em&gt;how&lt;/em&gt; much I have no idea.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id="refs" class="references"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 12 Mar 2016 14:50:00 -0500</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2016-03-12:2016/2016-03-12-1450.html</guid><category>writing</category></item><item><title>Academic Markdown and Citations</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2015/academic-markdown-and-citations.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Much of my past few weeks were taken up with study for and writing and editing &lt;a href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2015/not-exactly-a-millennium.html"&gt;a paper&lt;/a&gt; for one of my classes at Southeastern. I’ve been writing all of my papers in Markdown ever since I got here, and haven’t regretted any part of that… except that managing references and footnotes has been painful at times.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Footnotes in Markdown look like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="markdown"&gt;&lt;code&gt;Here is some text.[^fn]

[^fn]: And the footnote!&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This poses no problems at all for normal footnotes. Academic writing introduces a few wrinkles, though, which means that this has always been the main pain point of my use of Markdown for writing papers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many academic citation styles (including the Chicago Manual of Style, on which our seminary’s &lt;a href="http://www.press.uchicago.edu/books/turabian/turabian_citationguide.html"&gt;style guide&lt;/a&gt; is based) tend to have a long version of the footnote appear first, followed by short versions later. Nearly &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; academic citations styles make free use of the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ibid."&gt;“ibid.”&lt;/a&gt; abbreviation for repeated references to save space, time, and energy. Here is how that might look in manually-written footnotes, citing the very paper in which I sorted this all out:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="markdown"&gt;&lt;code&gt;Some text in which I cite an author.[^fn1]

More text. Another citation.[^fn2]

What is this? Yet *another* citation?[^fn3]

[^fn1]: So Chris Krycho, &amp;quot;Not Exactly a Millennium,&amp;quot; chriskrycho.com, July 22,
    2015, http://www.chriskrycho.com/2015/not-exactly-a-millennium.html
    (accessed July 25, 2015), ¶6.

[^fn2]: Contra Krycho, ¶15, who has everything *quite* wrong.

[^fn3]: ibid.&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This seems straightforward enough, though it is a bit of work to get the format right for each different kind of citation (articles, books, ebooks, electronic references to articles…). Things &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; get complicated in the editing process, though. For example, what if I needed to flip the order of some of these notes because it became clear that the paragraphs needed to move around? This happens &lt;em&gt;frequently&lt;/em&gt; during the editorial process. It becomes particularly painful when dealing with the “ibid.”-type references, because if I insert a new reference between two existing references, I have to go back in and manually add all that the reference content again myself.&lt;a href="#fn1" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref1"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Enter Pandoc and &lt;span class="tex"&gt;BibT&lt;span class="texE"&gt;E&lt;/span&gt;X&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section id="managing-citations" class="level2"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Managing Citations&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The idea of plain-text solutions to academic writing is not especially new; only the application of Markdown to it is—and that, only relatively. People have been doing this, and &lt;a href="http://kieranhealy.org/blog/archives/2014/01/23/plain-text/"&gt;documenting their approaches&lt;/a&gt;, for quite a while. Moreover, tools for managing references and citations have existed for quite some time as well; the entire &lt;a href="http://www.latex-project.org"&gt;L&lt;span class="texA"&gt;A&lt;/span&gt;T&lt;span class="texE"&gt;E&lt;/span&gt;X&lt;/a&gt; toolchain is largely driven by the concerns of academic publishing, and as such there are tools in the &lt;span class="tex"&gt;L&lt;span class="texA"&gt;A&lt;/span&gt;T&lt;span class="texE"&gt;E&lt;/span&gt;X&lt;/span&gt; ecosystem which address many of these problems.&lt;a href="#fn2" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref2"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One such is &lt;span class="tex"&gt;BibT&lt;span class="texE"&gt;E&lt;/span&gt;X&lt;/span&gt;, and the later (more capable) &lt;span class="tex"&gt;BibL&lt;span class="texA"&gt;A&lt;/span&gt;T&lt;span class="texE"&gt;E&lt;/span&gt;X&lt;/span&gt;: tools for managing bibliographies in &lt;span class="tex"&gt;L&lt;span class="texA"&gt;A&lt;/span&gt;T&lt;span class="texE"&gt;E&lt;/span&gt;X&lt;/span&gt; documents. The &lt;span class="tex"&gt;BibT&lt;span class="texE"&gt;E&lt;/span&gt;X&lt;/span&gt;/&lt;span class="tex"&gt;BibL&lt;span class="texA"&gt;A&lt;/span&gt;T&lt;span class="texE"&gt;E&lt;/span&gt;X&lt;/span&gt; approach to managing citations in a document is the use of the &lt;code&gt;\cite&lt;/code&gt; command, with the use of “keys” which map to specific documents: &lt;code&gt;\cite{krycho:2015aa}&lt;/code&gt;, for example.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is not Markdown, of course. But other folks who have an interest in Markdown and academic writing have put their minds to the problem already. Folks such as Jon MacFarlane, the originator and lead developer of &lt;a href="http://pandoc.org"&gt;Pandoc&lt;/a&gt;, perhaps the single most capable text-conversion tool in existence. As it turns out, Pandoc Markdown supports a &lt;a href="http://pandoc.org/README.html#citations"&gt;citation extension&lt;/a&gt; to the basic markup. It’s just a variant on the &lt;span class="tex"&gt;BibT&lt;span class="texE"&gt;E&lt;/span&gt;X&lt;/span&gt; citation style that feels more at home in Markdown: a pair of braces and an &lt;code&gt;@&lt;/code&gt;, plus the citation key, like &lt;code&gt;[@krycho]&lt;/code&gt;. Moreover, Pandoc knows how to use &lt;span class="tex"&gt;BibT&lt;span class="texE"&gt;E&lt;/span&gt;X&lt;/span&gt; libraries, as well as many others, and &lt;a href="http://citationstyles.org"&gt;Citation Style Languages&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;abbr&gt;CSL&lt;/abbr&gt;s) to generate markup in &lt;em&gt;exactly&lt;/em&gt; the format needed for any given citation style.&lt;a href="#fn3" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref3"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instead of writing out all those citations details by hand, then, I can just format my footnotes like this (assuming the citekey I had set up for the article was &lt;code&gt;krycho:revelation:2015&lt;/code&gt;):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="markdown"&gt;&lt;code&gt;Some text in which I cite an author.[^fn1]

More text. Another citation.[^fn2]

What is this? Yet *another* citation?[^fn3]

[^fn1]: [@krycho:revelation:2015], ¶6.

[^fn2]: Contra [@krycho:revelation:2015], ¶15, who has everything *quite* wrong.

[^fn3]: [@krycho:revelation:2015].&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is much simpler and, importantly, has the exact same form for each citation. Pandoc will take care of making sure that the first reference is in the long form, later references are in the short form, and repeated references are in the “ibid.” form as appropriate. It even renders a properly sorted and structured Works Cited section.&lt;a href="#fn4" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref4"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;4&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The slightly complex command I used to generate a Word document from a Markdown file with citations (using my own &lt;span class="tex"&gt;BibT&lt;span class="texE"&gt;E&lt;/span&gt;X&lt;/span&gt; library and the Chicago Manual of Style &lt;abbr&gt;CSL&lt;/abbr&gt;) on the command line is:&lt;a href="#fn5" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref5"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;5&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="bash"&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ pandoc revelation.md --smart --standalone \
--bibliography /Users/chris/Dropbox/writing/library.bib \
--csl=/Users/chris/Dropbox/writing/chicago.csl -o revelation.docx&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To see an extended sample of this kind of usage in practice, take a look at the &lt;a href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2015/not-exactly-a-millennium.txt"&gt;Markdown source&lt;/a&gt; for the paper I wrote last week, using exactly this approach. Every footnote that references a specific source simply has a cite key of this variety. The header metadata includes a path to the bibliography file and a &lt;abbr&gt;CSL&lt;/abbr&gt;. (These could be configured globally, as well, but I chose to specify them on a per-file basis so that if I want or need to use &lt;em&gt;different&lt;/em&gt; styles or a separate library for another file at a later time, I can do so with a minimum of fuss. More on this below.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="/downloads/revelation.docx"&gt;Here&lt;/a&gt; is the rendered result. You can see that it automatically generated everything right down to the “ibid.”-style footnotes. I made a few, fairly minimal tweaks (replacing the search &lt;abbr&gt;URL&lt;/abbr&gt; with an &lt;abbr&gt;ATLA&lt;/abbr&gt; database catalog reference and inserting a section break before the Works Cited list), and turned the paper in—confident, for the first time since I started seminary, that all of the references were in the right order and the right format. With carefully formatted reference documents (with their own style sets),&lt;a href="#fn6" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref6"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;6&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; I was able to generate an actually &lt;em&gt;nice&lt;/em&gt; &lt;abbr&gt;&lt;a href="/downloads/revelation-pretty.pdf"&gt;PDF&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/abbr&gt; version of the paper from another Word document, as well.&lt;a href="#fn7" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref7"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;7&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And, better yet, you don’t even have to put citations in footnotes. As &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/anjdunning"&gt;@anjdunning&lt;/a&gt; pointed out in a &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/anjdunning/status/625415216575197184"&gt;tweet&lt;/a&gt; response to the original version of this post:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.twitter.com/chriskrycho"&gt;@chriskrycho&lt;/a&gt; Don’t put citekeys in a footnote: write everything as inline citations and it will also generate notes when asked by CSL def.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/anjdunning/status/625415216575197184"&gt;∞&lt;/a&gt; July 26, 2015 17:19&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my standard example from above, then, you could simply do this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="markdown"&gt;&lt;code&gt;Some text in which I cite an author.[@krycho:revelation:2015, ¶6]

More text. Another citation.[Contra @krycho:revelation:2015, ¶15, who has
everything *quite* wrong.]

What is this? Yet *another* citation?[@krycho:revelation:2015]&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This will generate the same markup for my purposes here; and as &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/anjdunning"&gt;@anjdunning&lt;/a&gt; noted, it goes one step further and does what’s appropriate for the &lt;abbr&gt;CSL&lt;/abbr&gt;. This might be handy if, for example, you wanted to use the Chicago notes-bibliography style in one format, but switch to a simpler parenthetical citation style for a different medium—or even if you had a paper to submit to different journals with different standards. Having the citations inline thus has many advantages.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, there are still times when you might want to split those out into distinct footnotes, of course. That second one is a good candidate, at least for the way I tend to structure my plain-text source. I find it useful in the case of &lt;em&gt;actual&lt;/em&gt; footnote content—i.e. text that I’m intentionally leaving aside from the main text, even with reference to other authors—to split it out from the main flow of the paragraph, so that someone reading the plain text source gets a similar effect to someone reading the web or Word or &lt;abbr&gt;PDF&lt;/abbr&gt; versions, with the text removed from the flow of thought. In any case, it’s quite nice that Pandoc has the power and flexibility such that you don’t &lt;em&gt;have&lt;/em&gt; to.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, you don’t actually &lt;em&gt;need&lt;/em&gt; the brackets around the citekey, depending on how you’re using the reference. If you wanted to cite the relevant author inline, you can—and it will properly display both the inline name and a reference (footnote, parenthetical, etc.) in line with the &lt;abbr&gt;CSL&lt;/abbr&gt; you’ve chosen. If I were going to quote myself in a paper, I would do something like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="markdown"&gt;&lt;code&gt;As @krycho:revelation:2015 comments:

&amp;gt; This was a hard paper to write.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is &lt;em&gt;extremely&lt;/em&gt; powerful, and while I didn’t take advantage of it in my first paper using these tools, you can bet I will be in every future paper I write.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section id="all-those-references" class="level3"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;All those references&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, as is probably apparent, managing a &lt;span class="tex"&gt;BibT&lt;span class="texE"&gt;E&lt;/span&gt;X&lt;/span&gt; library by hand is no joke. Entries tend to look like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="tex"&gt;&lt;code&gt;@book{beale:revelation:2015,
        Date-Added = {2015-07-20 21:16:02 +0000},
        Date-Modified = {2015-07-20 21:21:05 +0000},
        Editor = {G. K. Beale and David H. Campbell},
        Publisher = {William B. Eerdmans Publishing Company},
        Title = {Revelation: A Shorter Commentary},
        Year = {2015}}&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While there is a lot of utility in having that data available in text, on disk, no one wants to &lt;em&gt;edit&lt;/em&gt; that by hand.&lt;a href="#fn8" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref8"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;8&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; Gladly, editing it by hand is not necessary. For this project, I used the freely available &lt;a href="http://bibdesk.sourceforge.net"&gt;BibDesk&lt;/a&gt; tool, which is a workable (albeit not very pretty and not &lt;em&gt;very&lt;/em&gt; capable) manager for &lt;span class="tex"&gt;BibT&lt;span class="texE"&gt;E&lt;/span&gt;X&lt;/span&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src="//cdn.chriskrycho.com/images/bibdesk.png" title="Not very pretty, but it does work" alt="BibDesk – open to the library for my Revelation paper" /&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;BibDesk – open to the library for my Revelation paper&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once I filled in the details for each item and set a citekey for it, I was ready to go: BibDesk just stores the files in a standard &lt;code&gt;.bib&lt;/code&gt; file on the disk, which I specified per the Pandoc command above.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;BibDesk gets the job done alright, but only alright. Using a citation and reference management tool was a big win, though, and I fully intend to use one for every remaining project while in seminary—and, quite possibly, for other projects as well. Whether that tool is BibDesk or something else is a different matter entirely. (More on this below.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="to-the-web" class="level2"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;To the web!&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wanted something more out of this process, if I could get it. One of the reasons I use plain text as a source is because from it, I can generate Word documents, &lt;abbr&gt;PDF&lt;/abbr&gt;s, and &lt;em&gt;this website&lt;/em&gt; with equal ease. However, Python Markdown knows nothing of &lt;span class="tex"&gt;BibT&lt;span class="texE"&gt;E&lt;/span&gt;X&lt;/span&gt; or citekeys, to my knowledge—and since I render everything for school with Pandoc, I have long wanted to configure &lt;a href="http://docs.getpelican.com/en/3.6.0/"&gt;Pelican&lt;/a&gt; to use Pandoc as its Markdown engine instead of Python Markdown anyway.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As it happens, I actually set this up about a month ago. The process was pretty simple:&lt;a href="#fn9" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref9"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;9&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol type="1"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I installed the &lt;a href="https://github.com/jstvz/pelican-pandoc-reader"&gt;pandoc-reader&lt;/a&gt; Pelican extension.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I set the plugin path in my Pelican configuration file.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I specified the arguments to Pelican I wanted to use.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The only additional tweaks necessary to get citation support were calling it with the &lt;code&gt;'--filter pandoc-citeproc'&lt;/code&gt; arguments, which lets it process any bibliography data supplied in the header metadata for the files. Calling Pandoc with &lt;code&gt;--bibliography &amp;lt;path to bibliography&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; (as in my example above) is a &lt;a href="http://pandoc.org/README.html#citation-rendering"&gt;shortcut&lt;/a&gt; for calling it with &lt;code&gt;--metadata &amp;lt;path to bibliography&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; the &lt;code&gt;--filter pandoc-citeproc&lt;/code&gt; arguments. I could just supply the bibliography directly in the call from Pelican, but this would limit me to using a single bibliography file for &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; of my posts—something I’d rather not limit myself to, since it might make sense to build up bibliographies around specific subjects, or even to have smaller bibliographies associated with each project (exported from the main bibliography), which could then be freely available along with the contents of the paper itself.&lt;a href="#fn10" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref10"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;10&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (On this idea, see a bit more below under &lt;strong&gt;The Future&lt;/strong&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One word of warning: Pandoc is much slower to generate &lt;abbr&gt;HTML&lt;/abbr&gt; with &lt;code&gt;--filter pandoc-citeproc&lt;/code&gt; than &lt;em&gt;without&lt;/em&gt; the filter, and the larger your site, the more you will feel this. (The time to generate the site from scratch jumped from about 10s to about 30s for me, with 270 articles, 17 drafts, 2 pages, and 1 hidden page, according to Pelican.) Pandoc has to process &lt;em&gt;every&lt;/em&gt; article to check for citations, and that’s no small task. However, if you have Pelican’s content caching turned on, this is a one-time event. After that, it will only be processing any new content with it; total generation time is back down where it was before for me: the effort is all in generating the large indexes I use to display the content for the landing pages and for category and tag archives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And the result: that same paper, rendered to &lt;abbr&gt;HTML&lt;/abbr&gt; &lt;a href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2015/not-exactly-a-millennium.html"&gt;on my website&lt;/a&gt;, with citations and works cited, generated automatically and beautifully.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section id="other-site-generators" class="level3"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Other site generators&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don’t know the situation around using Pandoc itself in other generators, including Jekyll—I simply haven’t looked. I do know, however, that there &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; some tooling for Jekyll specifically to allow a similar workflow. If you’re using Jekyll, it looks like your best bet is to check out &lt;a href="https://github.com/inukshuk/jekyll-scholar"&gt;jekyll-scholar&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a href="https://github.com/inukshuk/citeproc-ruby"&gt;citeproc-ruby&lt;/a&gt; project, which (like pandoc-citeproc) enables you to embed citations and filter them through &lt;abbr&gt;CSL&lt;/abbr&gt;s to generate references automatically. As a note: you should definitely be able to get those working on your own deployment sites, but I have no idea whether it’s possible to do them with the GitHub Pages variant of Jekyll. (If anyone who reads this knows the answer to that, let me know on Twitter or App.net, and I’ll update the post accordingly.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="the-future" class="level2"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The future&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition to continuing to use &lt;span class="tex"&gt;BibT&lt;span class="texE"&gt;E&lt;/span&gt;X&lt;/span&gt; with BibDesk as a way of managing my citations in the short term, I’m thinking about other ways to improve this workflow. One possibility is integrating with &lt;a href="http://scholdoc.scholarlymarkdown.com"&gt;Scholdoc&lt;/a&gt; as it matures, instead of &lt;a href="http://pandoc.org"&gt;pandoc&lt;/a&gt;, and maybe (hopefully, albeit unlikely) even contributing to it somewhat. I’m also open to using other citation library tools, though my early explorations with Mendeley and Zotero did not particularly impress me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are substantial advantages for the applications (and thus for most users) to maintaining the data in an application-specific format (e.g. an SQLite database) rather than on the file system—but the latter has the advantage of making it much easier to integrate with other tools. However, Zotero and Mendeley both natively export to &lt;span class="tex"&gt;BibT&lt;span class="texE"&gt;E&lt;/span&gt;X&lt;/span&gt; format, and Mendeley natively supports &lt;a href="http://blog.mendeley.com/tipstricks/howto-use-mendeley-to-create-citations-using-latex-and-bibtex/"&gt;sync&lt;/a&gt; to a &lt;span class="tex"&gt;BibT&lt;span class="texE"&gt;E&lt;/span&gt;X&lt;/span&gt; library (Zotero can do the same, but via third-party &lt;a href="https://zoteromusings.wordpress.com/tag/bibtex/"&gt;plugins&lt;/a&gt;), so those remain viable options, which I may use for future projects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also want to look at making my library of resources available publicly, perhaps (a) as a standalone library associated with each project, so that anyone who wants to can download it along with the Markdown source to play with as an example and (b) as a general library covering my various reading and research interests, which will certainly be irrelevant to most people but might nonetheless provide some value to someone along the way. I’m a big fan of making this kind of data open wherever possible, because people come up with neat things to do with it that the original creators never expect. Not &lt;em&gt;everything&lt;/em&gt; should be open—but lots of things should, and this might be among them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="summary" class="level2"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m pretty happy with the current state of affairs, the aforementioned interest in other reference managers notwithstanding:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I can set up the citations &lt;em&gt;once&lt;/em&gt;, in a tool designed to manage references, instead of multiple times in multiple places.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I can use Pandoc and a &lt;abbr&gt;CSL&lt;/abbr&gt; to get the citations formatted correctly throughout a paper, including generating the bibliography automatically.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I can use the same tooling, integrated into my static site generator, to build a web version of the content—with no extra effort, once I configured it properly the first time.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perhaps most importantly, this helps me meet one of my major goals for all my writing: to have a single canonical &lt;em&gt;source&lt;/em&gt; for the content, which I will be able to access in the future regardless of what operating system I am using or what publishing systems come and go. Simple plain text files—Markdown—get me there. Now I’ve put good tools around that process, and I love it even more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id="refs" class="references"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section class="footnotes"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn1"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Coming up with names for footnotes in Markdown can be painful in general for long documents. If you try to name them manually, like I do for posts on my website, you will very quickly end up wasting time on the names. If you try to number them, they will end up out of order in a hurry. My own &lt;a href="http://2012-2013.chriskrycho.com/web/markdown-and-academic-writing/"&gt;previous solution&lt;/a&gt; to this problem quickly became unwieldy for larger papers, and required a &lt;em&gt;lot&lt;/em&gt; of hand-editing. Gladly, I no longer deal with that manually. Instead, I do all my drafting in &lt;a href="http://www.ulyssesapp.com"&gt;Ulysses&lt;/a&gt;, where you just type &lt;code&gt;(fn)&lt;/code&gt; and it creates a footnote automatically, and will move that footnote &lt;em&gt;object&lt;/em&gt; around transparently as you edit, handling all the number-setting, etc. on its own.&lt;a href="#fnref1"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn2"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The irony of site for software which boasts that it is “a high-quality typesetting system” and looks like &lt;a href="http://www.latex-project.org"&gt;&lt;em&gt;this&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; is not lost on me…&lt;a href="#fnref2"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn3"&gt;&lt;p&gt;If you used the installers on Pandoc’s website, &lt;code&gt;pandoc-citeproc&lt;/code&gt; comes with it. If you installed it via a package manager (e.g. by running &lt;code&gt;brew install pandoc&lt;/code&gt;), it may not have, so you’ll need to install it manually yourself (e.g. &lt;code&gt;brew install pandoc-citeproc&lt;/code&gt;).&lt;a href="#fnref3"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn4"&gt;&lt;p&gt;All of the content, including the rendered footnotes and the bibliography, has sensible content types set on it: headers are headers, body text is body text, etc. You can then customize to match the specifications of your style guide. I have a Chicago/Turabian style set set up with the formatting rules to match.&lt;a href="#fnref4"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn5"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Actually, it was even hairier than this, because I also had a &lt;code&gt;--reference-docx path/to/template.docx&lt;/code&gt; specified. If you think it’s perhaps a bit too complex, well, I agree. I plan to turn that into a command line alias in pretty short order, because remembering it every time is just not going to happen.&lt;a href="#fnref5"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn6"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Using the &lt;code&gt;--reference-docx&lt;/code&gt; argument to Pandoc, you can hand it a document that already uses your desired style set, so you don’t have to go in and apply it manually.&lt;a href="#fnref6"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn7"&gt;&lt;p&gt;I could have done that with Pandoc’s &lt;span class="tex"&gt;L&lt;span class="texA"&gt;A&lt;/span&gt;T&lt;span class="texE"&gt;E&lt;/span&gt;X&lt;/span&gt; &lt;abbr&gt;PDF&lt;/abbr&gt; tools, as well, but didn’t really feel like taking the time to tweak the &lt;span class="tex"&gt;L&lt;span class="texA"&gt;A&lt;/span&gt;T&lt;span class="texE"&gt;E&lt;/span&gt;X&lt;/span&gt; template for it.&lt;a href="#fnref7"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn8"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Probably someone does, but not me, and not most people!&lt;a href="#fnref8"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn9"&gt;&lt;p&gt;If you’re using Pelican, you can take a look at my Pelican configuration file &lt;a href="https://github.com/chriskrycho/chriskrycho.com/blob/ef3ecbca1765750392086355aeae026c1159d4b9/pelicanconf.py#L109"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to see the full configuration for using Pandoc this way.&lt;a href="#fnref9"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn10"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Optimally, I’d really just prefer to be able to set &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; of these arguments at a per-file level—i.e., not use &lt;code&gt;--filter pandoc cite-proc&lt;/code&gt; unless the file actually specifies a bibliography. And I could hack Pelican to do that; I’ve actually already &lt;a href="https://github.com/liob/pandoc_reader/pull/5"&gt;messed around&lt;/a&gt; with other, semi-related bits regarding Pelican and Pandoc’s shared handling of &lt;abbr&gt;YAML&lt;/abbr&gt; metadata. But I’d prefer to keep my installation as “vanilla” as possible to minimize the cost of setting things up again on a new machine or after a crash, etc.&lt;a href="#fnref10"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 26 Jul 2015 13:50:00 -0400</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2015-07-26:2015/academic-markdown-and-citations.html</guid><category>workflow</category><category>writing</category></item><item><title>Faithfulness</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2015/faithfulness.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;It’s been a lot more than a month since the promised monthly update. I’ll blame it on a lack of self-discipline… or perhaps on the presence thereof.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Every day, we face choices about where to spend our time. In this particular season of life, that has often meant not writing, even things I &lt;em&gt;want&lt;/em&gt; to write. I have a family to care for, a church to serve, work to do, and schoolwork to accomplish. Family is a daily endeavor, work and school nearly so, and church regular if not quite daily. In the midst of that, I have to decide: &lt;em&gt;What will I do today?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our culture tends to put the question in terms of balance; my friend and pastor Ashok Nachnani suggested to me a while back that it is better to think in terms of &lt;em&gt;faithfulness&lt;/em&gt;. “Balance” suggests holding all these things in equal proportion, juggling them against each other. “Faithfulness” suggests fulfilling the responsibilities as best we can, with the time we are given. The actual day-to-day outcome may not look particularly different, but it is an important shift in the way we think nonetheless. To be faithful may mean letting some desireable things go, and it may mean doing some things in a different way or to a lesser degree than we might like.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Writing, for example.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I &lt;em&gt;love&lt;/em&gt; writing. I like keeping a public record for my friends and family to see how my life is. I enjoy stretching my mental muscles in the way that writing requires. I enjoy thinking through pen or keyboard. But faithfulness to the responsibilities God has given me right now means &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; trying to balance those desires against each other, and instead doing what is best for my family and my church. For the most part, right now that means not writing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I put it to Jaimie a while back, at this point in life I have time for one hobby—and only one. That hobby, at this point, is fitness. I run half marathons, and now I do triathlons (first one coming up in 10 days!). That takes up a non-trivial amount of time every week. It helps me in the other areas of my life, to be sure: it helps me be less physically tired, improves my focus in school and work, and serves to maintain my health. Nonetheless, it is hobby-like and it takes a substantial amount of time every day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So right now, I write a great deal less than I want, and a great deal less than I did in college or early in our marriage. I miss the days when I had time to work on poetry for hours at a stretch, or simply to muse for a few thousand words. But it is far more important for me to spend time with Ellie and Kate than it is to write poetry, or to compose music, right now. Lord willing, I have 55–60 years ahead of me. Of those years, they will be close only another 15–20, and they will be the age they are today &lt;em&gt;only for today&lt;/em&gt;. As much as writing and composing and hobby programming all look appealing to me, and as much as those really are good expressions of the ways God has gifted me, focusing on them would not be the most &lt;em&gt;faithful&lt;/em&gt; use of my time—not today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is not to say that writing and composing and developing interesting software are not important. Rather: they &lt;em&gt;are&lt;/em&gt; good and valuable things. But they are things to focus on at other times in life. As fast as this life goes, and I am increasingly aware that it goes quickly indeed, I can expect in the ordinary course of things to have &lt;em&gt;many&lt;/em&gt; years available for those things. I can exercise my gifts faithfully in the right time and season. Today, I can learn to love my little girls well, invest deeply in their lives, and savor moments that will never come back.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most of all, I must remind myself that teaching and shaping them is easily the most significant thing I will ever do. Should I write an essay that persuaded a thousand people to change their views on the arts, or to adopt a better view of the church, still my impact on two little lives would be more important. If I can point them faithfully to Christ and help them learn to walk faithfully with him as healthy members of his body, that will be a good life to have lived. Everything else is icing on the cake.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Icing is good, for the record. Sometimes, in these sorts of posts, we can mistake &lt;em&gt;relative importance&lt;/em&gt; for &lt;em&gt;absolute importance&lt;/em&gt;. I should, at various times in my life, make sure to exercise the good gifts God has given me in ways appropriate to that time and context. Right now, that means continuing to write, but less frequently. In the future, it will mean something else.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And all of this must stand in the context of resurrection hope. Too often, I live—too often, we &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; live—as though the next 60 years are all we may expect, the only time for writing and composing and so on. But it is not. I look forward to endless ages of creativity, exercising those gifts &lt;em&gt;more&lt;/em&gt; fully than I am able now. So: Lord Jesus, come soon. And in the meantime, may I be faithful in each season to do as well as I can.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id="refs" class="references"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 18 Jun 2015 17:00:00 -0400</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2015-06-18:2015/faithfulness.html</guid><category>family</category><category>writing</category></item></channel></rss>