<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Chris Krycho - Zettelkasten</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/</link><description></description><lastBuildDate>Thu, 03 Jan 2019 17:40:00 -0500</lastBuildDate><item><title>Don’t Forget Your Notebook</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2019/dont-forget-your-notebook.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.chriskrycho.com/2018/assumed-audiences.html"&gt;Assumed Audience&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/b&gt; people interested in research, note-taking, memory, and the like.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m sitting at a coffee shop enjoying a tasty drink and working on an app idea I’ve been slowly fleshing out over the last 3½ years… in a paper notebook.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ve been &lt;a href="https://www.chriskrycho.com/zettelkasten/" title="#zettelkasten on chriskrycho.com"&gt;writing a bit&lt;/a&gt; here over the last month or so about my experiment in building a &lt;a href="https://zettelkasten.de/posts/extend-your-mind-and-memory-with-a-zettelkasten/" title="Extend Your Mind and Memory With a Zettelkasten"&gt;Zettelkasten&lt;/a&gt;, and so far I’m quite pleased with it. It’s already proven helpful to me, and given my experiences so far I expect it to be much more so over the (hopefully many!) years ahead. I’ve &lt;a href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2018/starting-to-build-a-zettelkasten.html" title="Starting to Build a Zettelkasten"&gt;noted&lt;/a&gt; that &lt;a href="http://www.chriskrycho.com/2018/zettelkasten-update-all-in-on-bear.html" title="Zettelkasten Update: All in on Bear"&gt;I’m putting all of my notes&lt;/a&gt; in &lt;a href="https://bear.app"&gt;Bear&lt;/a&gt;, as it’s a handy tool that &lt;em&gt;mostly&lt;/em&gt; maps to the way I think about note-taking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I’m sitting working on this app design, though, it strikes me how valuable I find a physical notebook to be. Plain old pen and paper remain my favorite tool for &lt;em&gt;thinking&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m not alone in this, &lt;a href="https://zettelkasten.de/posts/use-real-notebook/" title="Use a Real Notebook"&gt;even among the proponents of a Zettelkasten approach&lt;/a&gt;. Nor does this surprise me. I’ve long observed that I write—and, more importantly—&lt;em&gt;think&lt;/em&gt; differently with pen and paper than I do with keyboard and computer.&lt;a href="#fn1" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref1"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; That is true &lt;em&gt;especially&lt;/em&gt; true of poetry, but it’s still a factor even for something like app design—and not only, but certainly, as a factor of the tactility of it and for the sheer analogicity (if you’ll pardon the neologism) of it. Pen scratching on paper, with &lt;em&gt;genuinely&lt;/em&gt; immediate feedback, is different even than the best experience of stylus and laptop.&lt;a href="#fn2" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref2"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; Even for something like sketching out a particular &lt;abbr title="user interface"&gt;UI&lt;/abbr&gt; flow, a notebook affords different things than a tablet does. Perhaps doubly so because of the very analog nature of pen and paper: I am not tempted to make sure my lines are &lt;i&gt;just so&lt;/i&gt; on paper as I am on an iPad, where “undo” is a constant temptation, the very expression of the perfect being the enemy of the good.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The net of this is simple: even if you’re adopting something like &lt;a href="https://bear.app"&gt;Bear&lt;/a&gt; for your way of storing and searching your notes, it’s valuable to have paper and pen-or-pencil near to hand. You may spend a little more time copying and elaborating notes as you transfer them from your notebook than you would if you simply did everything digitally from the start, but you will also think different—and, at least in my experience, &lt;em&gt;better&lt;/em&gt;—thoughts using pen and paper than not.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s a truism in software development that we ought to use the right tool fo the job. The same goes for &lt;em&gt;learning&lt;/em&gt;, and we ought not facilely dismiss the old tools simply because the newer ones have their own strengths.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section class="footnotes"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn1"&gt;&lt;p&gt;I include iPads here, because the difference &lt;em&gt;seems&lt;/em&gt; to be typing into a screen. There are also real differences I perceive between writing with an iPad and keyboard than with a traditional computer, but those pale in comparison to the difference between computer and analog.&lt;a href="#fnref1" class="footnote-back"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn2"&gt;&lt;p&gt;I have an iPad Pro with an Apple Pencil. The responsiveness is astounding and outstanding; but it is not paper and pen.&lt;a href="#fnref2" class="footnote-back"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 03 Jan 2019 17:40:00 -0500</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2019-01-03:/2019/dont-forget-your-notebook.html</guid><category>writing</category><category>Zettelkasten</category><category>note-taking</category><category>research</category></item><item><title>Trying a New Book-Reading Strategy</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2018/trying-a-new-book-reading-strategy.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.chriskrycho.com/2018/assumed-audiences.html"&gt;Assumed Audience:&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/b&gt; people broadly interested in reading, writing, learning, and research systems.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today I started trying a new(-to-me!) approach to deeply reading books, with some relatively light reading (so that I can get the practice).&lt;a href="#fn1" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref1"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; I’m hoping to be able to grow this skill and use it effectively for learning deeply in 2019. The strategy is pretty simple:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol type="1"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Use very quick, light marks in the margins: &lt;code&gt;✓&lt;/code&gt; for agreement, &lt;code&gt;x&lt;/code&gt; for disagreement, &lt;code&gt;~&lt;/code&gt; for something that’s worth noting as halfway right but worth clarifying, and &lt;code&gt;*&lt;/code&gt; for key arguments. This is basically the tack I’ve taken for a long time, but I’ve dropped all underlining or bracketing from the process: they’re slow, and I’m not really persuaded they’re more helpful than just adding a quick mark, as the really helpful bits come later in my experience.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;On finishing reading each chapter (or major section):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pull in the quotes I want to keep from it. Interact with them as makes sense.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Create a note with a short summary of the argument of the chapter. Link from it to the quotes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The goal here is to have a quick view into the contents of the chapter, including the various quotes that were particularly salient from it.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;On finishing the book, summarize the argument of the book by using the quotes and summaries of the chapters along the way to guide me in formulating my own interpretation of the author’s arguments. Add in some explicit interaction with the argument-in-sum.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Along the way, I’ll also write up other thoughts and interactions with the text, linking them to the other notes as makes sense.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once I have these kinds of notes, I will have a lot of material available to put to whatever use. Most importantly, I will have done a lot more active thinking about the ideas I encountered, and will have quick access to those thoughts to build on later. But I will also be able to use both those quick references to the book and to my own thoughts as prompted by the book to generate writing prompts for blog posts, book reviews, teaching notes, and so on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You’ll notice that this is quite similar in a number of ways to &lt;a href="https://www.chriskrycho.com/2018/just-write-down-what-you-do.html"&gt;my approach to logging my work&lt;/a&gt;; that’s intentional. I have found that an extremely fruitful way to be able to quickly grasp what I have &lt;em&gt;done&lt;/em&gt; over a given span. It seems likely that this variant on it will be equally useful for quickly grasping what I have &lt;em&gt;read&lt;/em&gt; over a given span.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One other note: I will definitely not be doing this for &lt;em&gt;everything&lt;/em&gt; I read. That would be laborious indeed! I plan to do this for books which I find to be of particularly high value this way. Many books simply do not warrant it, and indeed warrant little more than a quick skim (or to be put aside entirely). I wrote a couple days ago about my intent to use my time more carefully in 2019; one part of that is carefully distinguishing in &lt;em&gt;how&lt;/em&gt; I read as well as &lt;em&gt;what&lt;/em&gt; I read.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section class="footnotes"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn1"&gt;&lt;p&gt;I’m reading &lt;cite&gt;The Shepherd Leader: Achieving Effective Shepherding in Your Church&lt;/cite&gt;, by Timothy Z. Witmer, as part of the elder training work at my church, as I have been nominated to and expect to stand for the office of elder in mid-2019. That might not seem like light reading to you, but I’ve read an awful lot of academic theology over the last decade and no few books in this same vein during my M. Div. work.&lt;a href="#fnref1" class="footnote-back"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 26 Dec 2018 09:10:00 -0500</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2018-12-26:/2018/trying-a-new-book-reading-strategy.html</guid><category>Zettelkasten</category><category>note-taking</category><category>research</category><category>reading</category></item><item><title>Hey Siri, Record a Zettel</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2018/hey-siri-record-a-zettel.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.chriskrycho.com/2018/assumed-audiences.html"&gt;Assumed Audience:&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/b&gt; people interested in reading, writing, learning, and research systems—particularly on iOS, and particularly with automation in view.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A few evenings ago, I spent a little while building out some Siri Shortcuts to make the process of building out notes in &lt;a href="https://www.chriskrycho.com/zettelkasten"&gt;my Zettelkasten&lt;/a&gt; on the fly easier. Building them in Bear is easy &lt;em&gt;enough&lt;/em&gt;, but it’s even nicer to just be able to tap a button and have things like the date auto-generated for the note title in exactly the format I want: &lt;code&gt;YYYY.MM.DD.HHMM&lt;/code&gt;, like &lt;code&gt;2018.12.14.2205&lt;/code&gt; for a note created on December 14, 2018, at 10:05 pm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This timestamp format means I can always find notes by when they were written, and it’s easy to sort them by when I created them, which in turn seems the kind of thing that will prove helpful in the long-term, given how much our memories are &lt;em&gt;associative&lt;/em&gt;. (This insight is &lt;a href="https://zettelkasten.de/posts/no-categories/"&gt;not original&lt;/a&gt; by any means, but it’s something I’ve long valued in my &lt;a href="https://www.chriskrycho.com/2018/just-write-down-what-you-do.html"&gt;work&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So having a little tool that handles that part automatically is &lt;em&gt;great&lt;/em&gt;. The other thing that’s nice about using shortcuts is that I can use them in a hands-free context. I can now just say, “Hey Siri, record a new Zettel” and (since Shortcut configurations are shared across my iCloud account), I can do the whole process without typing a thing. Tagging is a bit harder here, but I can do well enough (it helps that I enunciate &lt;em&gt;extremely&lt;/em&gt; clearly).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One thing I wish is that iOS had support for doing these kinds of things when in do-not-disturb mode when driving. That’s the time when my “record a new Zettel” Siri Shortcut would be &lt;em&gt;most&lt;/em&gt; handy, and it’s not available. I’d be perfectly fine with having to come back and do a bit of cleanup later to get it &lt;em&gt;just right&lt;/em&gt;, as long as I could get the thought down somewhere I could come back to it later. You can do things like say “Hey Siri, in Bear, add a note,” and Siri will prompt you for its content—so clearly the functionality is there. SiriKit just needs to better support it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As for these particular shortcuts: I’m still working out the kinks, but for what it’s worth, here are the shortcuts I’ve built so far:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.icloud.com/shortcuts/c2406245de5846bebbda93d798034e25"&gt;Record a New Zettel&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.icloud.com/shortcuts/ae956fdd00454f0d824dd47ea69cecd2"&gt;Write a New Zettel&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.icloud.com/shortcuts/45a7c484309344c9a59e2f3e48a68083"&gt;Quote → Zettel&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m also thinking I’ll end up using the built-in hook Bear has to download a web page, but I haven’t worked that into my flow just yet.&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 14 Dec 2018 22:15:00 -0500</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2018-12-14:/2018/hey-siri-record-a-zettel.html</guid><category>Zettelkasten</category><category>automation</category><category>iOS</category><category>research</category><category>notes</category></item><item><title>Zettelkasten Update: All in on Bear</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2018/zettelkasten-update-all-in-on-bear.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.chriskrycho.com/2018/assumed-audiences.html"&gt;Assumed Audience:&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/b&gt; people broadly interested in reading, writing, learning, and research systems.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wrote &lt;a href="https://www.chriskrycho.com/2018/starting-to-build-a-zettelkasten.html"&gt;earlier this week&lt;/a&gt; about adopting a Zettelkasten approach for research, and moving writing prompts and ideas from &lt;a href="https://bear.app"&gt;Bear&lt;/a&gt; into &lt;a href="https://ulysses.app"&gt;Ulysses&lt;/a&gt; as part of that. I’m already reversing course, though, and pushing &lt;em&gt;ideas&lt;/em&gt; from Ulysses back over into Bear. (Don’t worry, this isn’t the typical “obsessing over tools &lt;em&gt;instead&lt;/em&gt; of doing work” problem. It’s a change that flows out of doing the work.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The reason is simple: Ulysses is fantastic for organizing writing projects. However, it has a pair of very important (for me) limitations for the ideation and research phase.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;It does &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; support the kind of easy cross-linking between notes that Bear does. But I find that super handy for saying “these two might belong together in a post.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;While Ulysses does have keywords (which could in principle work as a kind of tagging system), there is no easy way to navigate around between them. This is even handier than cross-linking for noting that two ideas might go together.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What’s more, I realized this week that I actually find it &lt;em&gt;quite&lt;/em&gt; useful to have my writing ideas in the same place as all my other notes, because it’s much easier to see the other things that might be useful for reference that way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the moment, then, my solution is: Ulysses for the actual content of writing projects (talks, essays, blog posts, etc.), but Bear for all the research (notes, quotes, links, etc.).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More on all of this as I work it out for myself!&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 08 Dec 2018 09:55:00 -0500</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2018-12-08:/2018/zettelkasten-update-all-in-on-bear.html</guid><category>research</category><category>writing</category><category>Zettelkasten</category><category>tools</category></item><item><title>Starting to Build a Zettelkasten</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2018/starting-to-build-a-zettelkasten.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.chriskrycho.com/2018/assumed-audiences.html"&gt;Assumed Audience:&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/b&gt; people broadly interested in reading, writing, learning, and research systems.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I’ve been slowly mulling on a number of things over the last few weeks, it became increasingly clear to me that I needed to invest a bit more in my research system. I’ve &lt;a href="https://www.chriskrycho.com/2017/how-do-you-manage-your-research-notes.html"&gt;asked before&lt;/a&gt; how people manage their own research, and I’ve noted how &lt;a href="https://www.chriskrycho.com/2018/blog-as-note-taking-tool.html"&gt;I use my blog as a note-taking tool of sorts&lt;/a&gt;. As I’ve started digging into a couple larger problems—one of which is likely going to take me a decade of work—I’ve come back to this question, and I find that I still don’t have great answers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Something like the &lt;a href="https://zettelkasten.de"&gt;Zettelkasten approach&lt;/a&gt; seems like it probably does what I need it to. So this week I’ve started organizing notes in &lt;a href="https://bear.app"&gt;Bear&lt;/a&gt; that way. I’m &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; taking the tack sometimes advocated of intentionally having no hierarchy whatsoever for my notes, though I’m eschewing any particularly deep hierarchies. I consistently find that I need some kind of project or “notebook” level of organization when I’m digging deep on something, and it’s always nice to hear that I’m not alone in that. &lt;a href="https://blog.ayjay.org/my-zettelkasten/"&gt;Alan Jacobs, on the same topic:&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, I thought, why not have a collection of Zettel that is based not on a lifetime of research but on a single project? So I tried that. And it worked wonderfully.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unlike Jacobs, the notecard system doesn’t work for me. I enjoy writing notes by hand, but in a lot of cases I’m writing down code snippets, which is very hard to do on notecards unless the code snippets are &lt;em&gt;very&lt;/em&gt; brief. Instead, I’m so far making heavy use of Bear’s ability to &lt;a href="https://bear.app/faq/Tags%20&amp;amp;%20Linking/How%20to%20link%20notes%20together/"&gt;link between notes&lt;/a&gt;, and even heavier use of Bear’s &lt;a href="https://bear.app/faq/Tags%20&amp;amp;%20Linking/Nested%20Tags/"&gt;tagging system&lt;/a&gt; for adding keywords to notes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In line with my comment about hierarchy, though, I’m only allowing myself one level of hierarchy: the “project” or “notebook.” Everything in that “notebook” is a single keyword/tag deep, structured like &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;notebook&amp;gt;/&amp;lt;keyword&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;—never &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;notebook&amp;gt;/&amp;lt;keyword&amp;gt;/&amp;lt;another keyword.&lt;/code&gt;. I am also freely including tags across these “notebooks”: something might be in &lt;code&gt;A/q&lt;/code&gt; and also &lt;code&gt;C/z&lt;/code&gt;. That gives me the best of both worlds: project-level organization, but also the ability to see associations that play out beyond an individual project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We’ll see how this plays out, but so far I’m liking it a lot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Amusingly, it’s forcing me to clean up my existing set of notes in Bear: things tagged “writing/ideas” are now getting pushed over into a corresponding bucket in &lt;a href="https://ulysses.app"&gt;Ulysses&lt;/a&gt;, which is my preferred application for actually &lt;em&gt;writing&lt;/em&gt;. Miscellaneous/non-project notes are currently going in a top level “notebook”—a top level tag in Bear—called &lt;code&gt;z&lt;/code&gt; (for Zettelkasten). Under it I have things like &lt;code&gt;z/pedagogy&lt;/code&gt;, but once again, I’m intentionally allowing myself only one level of nesting here. I am still &lt;a href="https://www.chriskrycho.com/2018/just-write-down-what-you-do.html"&gt;logging my work&lt;/a&gt; in a work tag. And I also have notebooks for things like food, gift ideas, etc., since Bear is currently my go-to notes app. (This is part of what forced me to the project/notebook mentality in the first place: having dozens of top-level tags in that sidebar was just going to break my brain.) But hopefully having all these notes around and in a just-structured-&lt;em&gt;enough&lt;/em&gt; form will be useful as I work on these larger projects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ll report more as I keep going with this!&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 05 Dec 2018 08:30:00 -0500</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2018-12-05:/2018/starting-to-build-a-zettelkasten.html</guid><category>writing</category><category>research</category><category>Zettelkasten</category><category>notes</category></item><item><title>Blog as Note-Taking Tool</title><link>http://www.chriskrycho.com/2018/blog-as-note-taking-tool.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;I have a habit that might not make sense to you. I reread my own blog posts fairly regularly. It’s not vanity—not some weird obsession with my own awesomeness in the form of my own writing or some such nonsense. It’s that in my blog posts over the last decade, I have a pretty serious backlog of &lt;em&gt;what I was thinking about at any given point in time.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s not exhaustive, by a long shot. It only includes things I actually decided to publish.&lt;a href="#fn1" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref1"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; There are, sadly, not many short thoughts in the mix. Nor is it well-tagged or organized in any internally-consistent way—even in any single version of the site, much less across versions. But nonetheless the history is still there, and I &lt;em&gt;can&lt;/em&gt; traverse the various lines through it, such as they are. (Sometimes, even, the changes in organization and structure are illuminating about how I was thinking about things at the time!) In any case, my habit of linking to previous references to ideas has proven invaluable for the times when I want to trawl back through old posts and consider those old thoughts again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reading old blog posts is a strange experience, of course. The person who wrote these things was recognizably myself; but I am not who I then I was, and I sometimes disagree with myself on the substance and often on the style. (I occasionally find an old gem and wonder how I ever managed to write so well.) That very strangeness, it turns out, is why I do this every so often, though. Thinking well is often a matter of forging connections between ideas that were previously not connected for us. We cannot consciously hold in our minds even a fraction of all the things we have thought about or even written something about over the years. We can, however, jog our memories, and let new connections form. And rereading one’s own blog post is a great way to do that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’d not heard specifically of the &lt;a href="https://zettelkasten.de"&gt;Zettelkasten method&lt;/a&gt; until Alan Jacobs linked it a while back, but it fits this model pretty perfectly, and maps as well to ways I’ve been &lt;em&gt;trying&lt;/em&gt; to structure my note-taking and thinking for the past few years. (I’m going to be consciously doing more of this in &lt;a href="http://www.bear-writer.com"&gt;Bear&lt;/a&gt;, my current notes app of choice. I’ll probably write up my experience that way once I’ve actually had some experience!) But this also ties into some of the things Jacobs has been &lt;a href="https://blog.ayjay.org/the-blog-garden/" title="The Blog Garden"&gt;musing out loud&lt;/a&gt; about in his own blog over the last week. It’s not just that a blog can serve as a place to do some of the fleshing-out of ideas. It’s not just that a blog can be a record of the development of ideas. It can also serve to jog new ideas if you read yourself again, displaced (both literally and temporally) from the original writing of the thing. A blog is kind of like a public notebook, and while it &lt;em&gt;may&lt;/em&gt; be useful for others to browse through it, is &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; useful for me to browse back through it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section class="footnotes"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn1"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Though: if you look at the archives, especially including those on my &lt;a href="http://blog.chriskrycho.com" title="Thoughts; A Flame"&gt;first real blog&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="http://2012-2013.chriskrycho.com"&gt;the previous iteration of this site&lt;/a&gt;, you’ll notice that I published a lot of posts about a lot of subjects, whether my thoughts were especially well-formed or not.&lt;a href="#fnref1" class="footnote-back"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Chris Krycho</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 16 Jul 2018 07:00:00 -0400</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.chriskrycho.com,2018-07-16:/2018/blog-as-note-taking-tool.html</guid><category>Zettelkasten</category><category>notes</category><category>memory</category><category>writing</category><category>blogging</category></item></channel></rss>